<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="crt_features">
  <title>Monasca Transform Features</title>
  <body>
    <section id="monasca_transform_features">
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li>Monasca Transform is a new component in Monasca which transforms and aggregates
            metrics using Apache Spark</li>
          <li>Aggregated metrics are published to Kafka and are available for other monasca
            components like monasca-threshold and are stored in monasca datastore</li>
          <li>Cloud operators can set thresholds and set alarms to receive notifications when
          thresholds are met.</li>
          
          <li>These aggregated metrics are made available to the cloud operators via Ops Console's
            new Capacity Summary (reporting) UI</li>
          <li>Capacity reporting is a new feature in <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> which will provides cloud operators an
            overall capacity (available, used and remaining) for Compute and Object Storage</li>
          <li>Cloud operators can look at Capacity reporting via Ops Console's Compute Capacity
            Summary and Object Storage Capacity Summary UI</li>
          <li>Capacity reporting allows the cloud operators the ability to ensure that cloud resource pools have
            sufficient capacity to meet demands of users. See table below for Service and Capacity Types.</li>
          <li>A list of aggregated metrics is provided <xref keyref="crt_aggregated_metrics">here</xref></li>
          <li>Capacity reporting aggregated metrics are aggregated and published every hour</li>
          <li>In addition to the overall capacity, there are graphs which show the capacity trends
            over time range (for 1 day, for 7 days, for 30 days or for 45 days)</li>
          <li>Graphs showing the capacity trends by a particular project or compute host are also
            provided.</li>
          <li>Monasca Transform is integrated with centralized monitoring (Monasca) and centralized
            logging</li>
          <li>Flexible Deployment</li>
          <li>Upgrade &amp; Patch Support</li>
        </ul>
        <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_el2_3gj_my">
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.1*"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="4.49*"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Service</entry>
                <entry>Type of Capacity</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Compute</entry>
                <entry>Host Capacity</entry>
                <entry>CPU/Disk/Memory: Used, Available and Remaining Capacity - for entire cloud
                  installation or by compute host</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry/>
                <entry>VM Capacity</entry>
                <entry>CPU/Disk/Memory: Allocated, Available and Remaining - for entire cloud
                  installation, by host or by project</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Object Storage</entry>
                <entry>Disk Capacity</entry>
                <entry>Used, Available and Remaining Disk Capacity - for entire cloud installation
                  or by project</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry/>
                <entry>Storage Capacity</entry>
                <entry>Utilized Storage Capacity - for entire cloud installation or by
                  project</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </p>
      
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
