<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="register_suse_already_installed">
  <title>Registering SUSE Linux from the Installed System</title>
  <body>
    
    <section id="installed_system">
      <title>Registering from the Installed System</title>
      <p> If you have skipped the registration during the installation or want to re-register your
        system, you can register the system at any time using the YaST module "Product Registration"
        or the command line tool "SUSEConnect". </p>
      <p><b>Registering with YaST</b></p>
      <p> To register the system start "YaST -> Software -> Product Registation". Provide the E-mail
        address associated with the SUSE account you or your organization uses to manage
        subscriptions. In case you do not have a SUSE account yet, go to the SUSE Customer Center
        home page (<xref href="https://scc.suse.com/" format="html" scope="external">https://scc.suse.com/</xref>) to create one. </p>
      <p> Enter the Registration Code you received with your copy of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server.
        Proceed with Next to start the registration process. </p>
      <p> By default the system is registered with the SUSE Customer Center. However, if your
        organization provides local regsitration servers you can either choose one form the list of
        auto-detected servers or provide the URl at "Register System via local SMT Server". Proceed
        with "Next". </p>
      <p><b>Registering with SUSEConnect</b></p>
      <p> To register from the command line, use the command
        <codeblock>sudo SUSEConnect -r &lt;REGISTRATION_CODE&gt; -e &lt;EMAIL_ADDRESS&gt;</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p> Replace &lt;REGISTRATION_CODE&gt; with the Registration Code you received with your copy
        of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. Replace &lt;EMAIL_ADDRESS&gt; with the E-mail address
        associated with the SUSE account you or your organization uses to manage subscriptions. To
        register with a local registration server, also provide the URL to the server:
        <codeblock>sudo SUSEConnect -r &lt;REGISTRATION_CODE&gt; -e &lt;EMAIL_ADDRESS&gt; --url "https://suse_register.example.com/"</codeblock>
      </p>
    </section>
    
  </body>
</topic>
