<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd" >
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="eulahos30">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Software License Terms</title>
  <body>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <xref type="section" href="#eulahos30/eula">Part 1: HPE End User License Agreement</xref>
      </li>
      <li>
        <xref type="section" href="#eulahos30/auth">Part 2: Additional License Authorizations for
          Software</xref>
      </li>
      <li>
        <xref type="section" href="#eulahos30/ancilliary">Part 3: Ancillary and Open Source Software
          for Software</xref>
      </li>
    </ul>
    <section id="eula">
      <title>Part 1: HPE End User License Agreement</title>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <b>Applicability.</b> This end user license agreement (the "Agreement") governs the use of
            <keyword keyref="kw-hos-tm"/> Software ("Software"), unless it is subject to a separate
          agreement between you and Hewlett Packard Enterprise Company and its subsidiaries ("HPE").
          By downloading, copying, or using the software you agree to this Agreement. </li>
        <li>
          <b>Terms.</b> This Agreement includes supporting material accompanying the Software or
          referenced by HPE which may be software license information, additional license
          authorizations, software specifications, published warranties, supplier terms, open source
          software licenses and similar content ("Supporting Material"). Additional license
          authorizations are below and at: <xref
            href="http://docs.hpcloud.com/pdf/static/HPE_HOS_3.0_OpenSource_and_3rd_Party_Licenses.pdf"
            scope="external" format="pdf"
            >http://docs.hpcloud.com/pdf/static/HPE_HOS_3.0_OpenSource_and_3rd_Party_Licenses.pdf</xref>.</li>
        <li>
          <b>Authorization</b>. If you agree to this Agreement on behalf of another person or
          entity, you warrant you have authority to do so.</li>
        <li>
          <b>Consumer Rights.</b> If you obtained Software as a consumer, nothing in this Agreement
          affects your statutory rights.</li>
        <li>
          <b>Electronic Delivery.</b> HPE may elect to deliver Software and related software product
          or license information by electronic transmission or download.</li>
        <li>
          <b>License Grant.</b> If you abide by this Agreement, HPE grants you a non-exclusive,
          non-transferable license to use one copy of the version or release of the accompanying
          Software for your Internal Use (as defined below) only, and is subject to any specific
          software licensing information that is in the Software product or its Supporting Material.
          Your use is subject to the following restrictions, unless specifically allowed in
          Supporting Material: <ul>
            <li>You may not use Software to provide products or services to third parties.</li>
            <li>You may not make copies and distribute, resell, sublicense or provide access to the
              Software to third parties.</li>
            <li>You may not download and use patches, enhancements, bug fixes, or similar updates
              unless you have a license to the underlying Software. However, such license doesn't
              automatically give you a right to receive such updates and HPE reserves the right to
              make such updates only available to customers with support contracts.</li>
            <li>You may not copy Software or make it available on a public or external distributed
              network.</li>
            <li>You may not allow access on an intranet unless it is restricted to authorized
              users.</li>
            <li>You may make one copy of the software for archival purposes or when it is an
              essential step in authorized use.</li>
            <li>You may not modify, reverse engineer, disassemble, decrypt, decompile, or make
              derivative works of Software except as permitted by law. </li>
          </ul></li>
        <li>
          <b>Remote Monitoring.</b> Some software may require keys or other technical protection
          measures and HPE may monitor your compliance with the Agreement, remotely or otherwise. If
          HPE makes a license management program for recording and reporting license usage
          information, you will use such program no later than 180 days from the date it's made
          available.</li>
        <li>
          <b>Ownership.</b> No transfer of ownership of any intellectual property will occur under
          this Agreement.</li>
        <li>
          <b>Copyright Notices.</b> You must reproduce copyright notices on software and
          documentation for authorized copies.</li>
        <li><b>90-day Limited Warranty for HPE Software.</b>
          <ul>
            <li>HPE-branded software is free of malware at the time of delivery; if you notify HPE
              within 90 days of delivery of non-conformance to this warranty, HPE will replace your
              copy. This Agreement states all remedies for warranty claims.</li>
            <li>HPE does not warrant that the operation of software will be uninterrupted or error
              free, or that software will operate in hardware and software combinations other than
              as authorized by HPE in Supporting Material. To the extent permitted by law, HPE
              disclaims all other warranties.</li>
          </ul></li>
        <li>
          <b>Intellectual Property Rights Infringement.</b> Subject to Section 14(e) of this Part 1,
          HPE will defend and/or settle any claims against you that allege that HPE-branded software
          as supplied under this Agreement infringes the intellectual property rights of a third
          party. HPE will rely on your prompt notification of the claim and cooperation with our
          defense. HPE may modify the software so as to be non-infringing and materially equivalent,
          or we may procure a license. If these options are not available, we will refund to you the
          amount paid for the affected product in the first year or the depreciated value
          thereafter. HPE is not responsible for claims resulting from any unauthorized use of the
          software.</li>
        <li>
          <b>Limitation of Liability.</b>HPE's liability to you under this Agreement is limited to
          the amount actually paid by you to HPE for the relevant software, except for amounts in
          Section 11 ("Intellectual Property Rights Infringement"). Neither you nor HPE will be
          liable for lost revenues or profits, downtime costs, loss or damage to data or indirect,
          special or consequential costs or damages. This provision does not limit either party's
          liability for: unauthorized use of intellectual property, death or bodily injury caused by
          their negligence; acts of fraud; willful repudiation of the Agreement; or any liability
          that may not be excluded or limited by applicable law.</li>
        <li>
          <b>Termination.</b> This Agreement is effective until terminated or in the case of a
          limited-term license, upon expiration; however, your rights under this Agreement terminate
          if you fail to comply with it. Immediately upon termination or expiration, you will
          destroy the software and documentation and any copies, or return them to HPE. You may keep
          one copy of software and documentation for archival purposes. We may ask you to certify in
          writing you have complied with this section. Warranty disclaimers, the limitation of
          liability, this section on termination, and Section 14 ("General") will survive
          termination.</li>
        <li>
          <b>General.</b>
          <ol>
            <li><b>Assignment</b>. You may not assign this Agreement without prior written consent
              of HPE, payment of transfer fees and compliance with HPE's software license transfer
              policies. Authorized assignments will terminate your license to the software and you
              must deliver software and documentation and copies thereof to the assignee. The
              assignee will agree in writing to this Agreement. You may only transfer firmware if
              you transfer associated hardware.</li>
            <li><b>U.S. Government</b>. If the software is licensed to you for use in the
              performance of a U.S. Government prime contract or subcontract, you agree that,
              consistent with FAR 12.211 and 12.212, commercial computer software, computer software
              documentation and technical data for commercial items are licensed under HPE's
              standard commercial license.</li>
            <li><b>Global Trade Compliance. </b>You agree to comply with the trade-related laws and
              regulations of the U.S. and other national governments. If you export, import or
              otherwise transfer products provided under this Agreement, you will be responsible for
              obtaining any required export or import authorizations. You confirm that you are not
              located in a country that is subject to trade control sanctions (currently Cuba, Iran,
              N. Korea, N. Sudan, and Syria) and further agree that you will not retransfer the
              products to any such country. HPE may suspend its performance under this Agreement to
              the extent required by laws applicable to either party.</li>
            <li><b>Audit</b>. HPE may audit you for compliance with the software license terms. Upon
              reasonable notice, HPE may conduct an audit during normal business hours (with the
              auditor's costs being at HPE's expense). If an audit reveals underpayments then you
              will pay to HPE such underpayments. If underpayments discovered exceed five (5)
              percent, you will reimburse HPE for the auditor costs.</li>
            <li><b>Third Party and Open Source Components</b>. To the extent any component of the
              software is subject to any third party license terms, including open source license
              terms, then those third party license terms or open source license terms shall govern
              with respect to the subject component; otherwise, the terms of this Agreement shall
              govern.</li>
            <li><b>Notices</b>. Written notices under this Agreement may be provided to HPE via the
              method provided in the Supporting Material or if none, via "contact HPE" site on <xref
                href="http://www.hpe.com" scope="external" format="html">www.hpe.com</xref>.</li>
            <li><b>Governing Law</b>. This Agreement will be governed by the laws of the state of
              California, U.S.A., excluding rules as to choice and conflict of law. You and HPE
              agree that the United Nations Convention on Contracts for the International Sale of
              Goods will not apply.</li>
            <li><b>Force Majeure</b>. Neither party will be liable for performance delays nor for
              non-performance due to causes beyond its reasonable control, except for payment
              obligations.</li>
            <li><b>Entire Agreement</b>. This Agreement represents our entire understanding with
              respect to its subject matter and supersedes any previous communication or agreements
              that may exist. Modifications to the Agreement will be made only through a written
              amendment signed by both parties. If HPE doesn't exercise its rights under this
              Agreement, such delay is not a waiver of its rights.</li>
          </ol></li>
        <li><b>Australian Consumers.</b> If you acquired the software as a consumer within the
          meaning of the 'Australian Consumer Law' under the Australian Competition and Consumer Act
          2010 (Cth) then despite any other provision of this Agreement, the terms at this URL
          apply: <xref href="http://www.hpe.com/software/SWlicensing" scope="external" format="html"
            >http://www.hpe.com/software/SWlicensing</xref>.</li>
      </ol></section>


    <section id="auth">
      <title>Part 2: Additional License Authorizations for <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>
        Software</title>
      <p>This Part 2 includes Additional License Authorizations (ALA) for the Software. You may use
        the Software in accordance with the terms of this ALA in addition to the terms of your
        agreement with HPE, or in the absence of such agreement, the HPE End User License Agreement
        (EULA) in Part 1 above as well as the Ancillary and Open Source Software license terms
        listed in Part 3. You may also be referred to as "Customer" below.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="definitions">
      <title>Definitions</title>
      <p>Capitalized terms not otherwise defined in this Additional License Authorizations document
        are defined in the governing Agreement.</p>
      <p>
        <b>Cloud Fabric</b> - means a collection of physical and virtual operating system
        environments that are configured and operated as a unit to provide virtualization,
        networking, website, storage and file services.</p>
      <p>
        <b>Internal Use</b> - means use of the Software for purposes of supporting Customer's
        internal business operations or functions.</p>
      <p>
        <b>Management Software</b> - means an <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> management software running
        on a Physical Server for the sole purpose of deploying or managing a Cloud Fabric.</p>
      <p>
        <b>Physical Server</b> - means a single, physical hardware server or other computer but is
        not a Virtual Machine.</p>
      <p><b>Term of Use</b> - means the period of time licensed for use of the Software.</p>
      <p>
        <b>Use</b> - means to use, install, store, load, execute and display the Software in
        accordance with the particular license(s) purchased by Customer.</p>
      <p>
        <b>Virtual Machine(s)</b> - means a computer that does not physically exist but is simulated
        by another computer.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="additional-license-terms">
      <title>Additional License Terms</title>
      <ol>
        <li><b> Software:</b> Subject to Customer's compliance with the terms and conditions of this
          Agreement, HPE grants to Customer a non-exclusive, limited, non-sublicenseable,
          non-transferable, revocable license to Use the Software to manage cloud services on a per
          Physical Server basis for the Term of Use as specified in the purchase agreement. <sl>
            <sli><b>Per Server License</b>: Following purchase, this per-server license is to be
              assigned to a Physical Server that will be used to run your Cloud Fabric. After the
              Physical Servers are licensed and those licenses are properly assigned, you may run
              any number of instances of the Management Software to deploy, configure, manage and
              operate your <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> based Cloud Fabric. The right to Use the
              Software may not be transferred from the initial licensed Physical Server to a new or
              replacement Physical Server, except according to Section 2(i) below. </sli>
            <sli>Subject to Customer’s continuing compliance with the terms and conditions of this
              Agreement, following the Term of Use, Customer may continue to Use the Software on the
              Physical Server that was licensed and in operation before the end of the Term of
              Use.</sli>
          </sl></li>
        <li><b>Other Terms:</b>
          <ol>
            <li>
              <b>Trademarks.</b> Notwithstanding anything to the contrary in this Section, you may
              not distribute the Software or components of the Software using HPE trademarks unless
              permitted to do so under a separate written agreement with HPE.</li>
            <li><b>Assigning Licenses:</b> Before you can install and use the Management Software to
              deploy your Cloud Fabric, you must assign to each Physical Server running the host
              fabric one per-Physical Server license. Each Physical Server to which you assign a
              license is a licensed host server.</li>
            <li>
              <b>Commercial Service Providers:</b> Customers must accept the terms contained in a
              supplemental agreement in order to provide commercial services to third parties using
              the Software, found at <xref
                href="https://h20392.www2.hpe.com/portal/swdepot/displayProductInfo.do?productNumber=CS_SRV_PRVD"
                format="html" scope="external"
                >https://h20392.www2.hpe.com/portal/swdepot/displayProductInfo.do?productNumber=CS_SRV_PRVD</xref>.</li>
            <li>
              <b>Compliance and Audit:</b> HPE shall have the right to audit the customer's use of
              the Software at HPE's expense and in accordance with any agreement between the parties
              related to confidentiality. </li>
            <li><b>Confidentiality:</b> The Software contains confidential and proprietary
              information of HPE ("Confidential Information"). Customer will hold in confidence and
              not use or disclose any Confidential Information, except as expressly permitted in the
              Agreement. To the extent this restriction is not prohibited under applicable law, and
              except as specifically authorized under in writing by HPE, Customer shall not disclose
              to any third party the results of (i) any performance benchmarks you run on the
              Software, or any portion thereof, or (ii) specific detailed comparisons you make
              between the Software, or any portion thereof, and any product owned by you or a
              third-party product.</li>
            <li>
              <b>Copyright Notices:</b> Customer must reproduce all copyright notices that appear in
              or on the Software (including documentation) on all permitted copies or adaptions.
              Copies of documentation are limited to internal use.</li>
            <li>
              <b>Delivery:</b> Customer agrees to accept the Software upon receipt. </li>
            <li>
              <b>Outsourcing Software Management:</b> You may install and run the Software on your
              Physical Servers that are under the day-to-day management and control of third
              parties, provided all such Physical Servers and other devices are and remain fully
              dedicated to your use. You are responsible for all of the obligations under this
              Agreement regardless of the physical location of the hardware upon which the Software
              is used.</li>
            <li>
              <b>Reassigning Licenses:</b> During the Term of Use, You may reassign the Software
              license to a substitute Physical Server, except that no reassignment is permitted
              within ninety (90) days of a previous reassignment unless such reassignment is made to
              a replacement Physical Server that has been replaced due to permanent hardware
              failure. Following the Term of Use, no license transfers or reassignments are
              permitted.</li>
            <li>
              <b>Rights to use other versions:</b> You may create, store, install, run or access a
              copy or instance of a prior version of the Software in place of the latest release of
              the Software. The permitted use of an earlier version does not extend the support
              lifecycle of the earlier version. The permitted use of a version of the Software does
              not extend to updated versions released after the Term of Use.</li>
            <li>
              <b>Third Party Licenses:</b> You are responsible for complying with all terms of use
              for any third party software, content, service or website you load, create or access
              when using the Software.</li>
            <li>
              <b>Updates and Supplements:</b> We may update or supplement the Software during the
              Term of Use. If so, you may use that update or supplement with the Software, subject
              to any additional terms that accompany the update or supplement.</li>
            <li> The OpenStack word mark and the Square O Design, together or apart, are trademarks
              or registered trademarks of OpenStack Foundation in the United States and other
              countries, and are used with the OpenStack Foundation's permission.</li>
          </ol></li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section id="ancilliary">
      <title>Part 3: Ancillary and Open Source Software for Software</title>
      <p>Additional license authorizations related to ancillary, third party and open source
        software components are available at: <xref
          href="http://docs.hpcloud.com/pdf/static/HPE_HOS_3.0_OpenSource_and_3rd_Party_Licenses.pdf"
          scope="external" format="pdf"
          >http://docs.hpcloud.com/pdf/static/HPE_HOS_3.0_OpenSource_and_3rd_Party_Licenses.pdf</xref>.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
