<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.1">
  <title>Tricircle</title>
  <para>The purpose of the Tricircle project is to provide networking automation
            across Neutron servers in multi-region OpenStack clouds deployment.</para>
  <para>Each OpenStack cloud includes its own Nova, Cinder and Neutron, the Neutron
            servers in these OpenStack clouds are called local Neuron servers, all these
            local Neutron servers will be configured with the Tricircle Local Neutron
            Plugin. A separate Neutron server will be installed and run standalone as
            the coordinator of networking automation across local Neutron servers, this
            Neutron server will be configured with the Tricircle Central Neutron Plugin,
            and is called central Neutron server.</para>
  <para>Leverage the Tricircle Central Neutron Plugin and the Tricircle Local Neutron
            Plugin configured in these Neutron servers, the Tricircle can ensure the
            IP address pool, IP/MAC address allocation and  network segment allocation
            being managed globally without conflict, and the Tricircle handles tenant
            oriented data link layer(Layer2) or network layer(Layer3) networking
            automation across local Neutron servers, resources like VMs, bare metal or
            containers of the tenant can communicate with each other via Layer2 or Layer3,
            no matter in which OpenStack cloud these resources are running on.</para>
  <para>Note: There are some our own definitions of Layer2/Layer3 networking
            across Neutron. To make sure what they are, please read our design
            documentation, especially “6.5 L2 Networking across Neutron”. The wiki and
            design documentation are linked below.</para>
  <para>The Tricircle and multi-region OpenStack clouds will use shared
            KeyStone(with centralized or distributed deployment) or federated KeyStones.</para>
  <para>The Tricircle source code is distributed under the terms of the Apache
            License, Version 2.0. The full terms and conditions of this license are
            detailed in the LICENSE file.</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Free software: Apache license</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Design documentation: <link xlink:href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zcxwl8xMEpxVCqLTce2-dUOtB-ObmzJTbV1uSQ6qTsY/">Tricircle Design Blueprint</link></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Wiki: <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/tricircle"/></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Installation guide: <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/tricircle/latest/install/index.html"/></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Admin guide: <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/tricircle/latest/admin/index.html"/></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Configuration guide: <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/tricircle/latest/configuration/index.html"/></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Networking guide: <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/tricircle/latest/networking/index.html"/></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Source: <link xlink:href="http://git.openstack.org/cgit/openstack/tricircle"/></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Bugs: <link xlink:href="http://bugs.launchpad.net/tricircle"/></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Blueprints: <link xlink:href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/tricircle"/></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Release notes: <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/releasenotes/tricircle"/></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Contributing: <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/tricircle/latest/contributor/index.html"/></para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>
