<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" >
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic4315">
  <title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> 1.0: Installation Overview</title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
      <othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
      <othermeta name="role" content="Storage Administrator"/>
      <othermeta name="role" content="Storage Architect"/>
      <othermeta name="role" content="Michael B,"/>
      <othermeta name="product-version1" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>
      <!--PUBLISHED-->
      <!--./commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-overview.md-->
      <!--permalink: /helion/openstack/install/overview/--></p>
    <p> </p>
    <p>The HPE Helion OpenStack installation follows the standard <xref
        href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO" scope="external" format="html">TripleO
        deployment model</xref>, creating a seed, an undercloud and an overcloud.</p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
          <b>Seed</b>: The seed VM is started as a VM from a specific seed VM image. It contains a
          number of self-contained OpenStack components that are used to deploy the undercloud. The
          seed deploys the undercloud by using Ironic baremetal driver to deploy a specific
          undercloud machine image.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
          <b>Undercloud</b>: In a typical HPE Helion OpenStack deployment, the undercloud is a
          baremetal server. The undercloud is a complete OpenStack installation, which is then used
          to deploy the overcloud.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
          <b>Overcloud</b>: The overcloud is the end-user OpenStack cloud. In a typical HPE Helion
          OpenStack deployment, the overcloud comprises several baremetal servers.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>For more details on the seed, an undercloud and an overcloud, see the <xref
        href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.technical-overview.ga.xml#topic25331/install-configure"
        type="section">Installation Planning section</xref> in the Technical Overview.</p>
    <section id="the-installation-process">
      <title>The Installation Process</title>
      <p>HPE Helion OpenStack is designed to deliver an open source OpenStack solution at the modest
        scale. A baremetal multi-node deployment consists of a minimum of 8 baremetal servers, to
        which you can add up to 100 Compute nodes:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>1 seed cloud host (installer system)</li>
        <li>1 undercloud server</li>
        <li>3 overcloud controllers</li>
        <li>2 overcloud Swift nodes</li>
        <li>At least 1 overcloud Compute node </li>
      </ul>
      <p>After the installation, you can add additional block storage nodes (not required if 3Par is
        being used for block storage) and <xref
          href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-security.xml">configure your network
          securely</xref>.</p>
      <p>The high-level process for installing HPE Helion OpenStack involves the following:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>Review the information in the <xref
              href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-supportmatrix.xml">Support
              Matrix</xref> and <xref
              href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.technical-overview.ga.xml">Technical
              Overview</xref> for details about hardware and software requirements.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Verify that the necessary <xref
              href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-prereqs.xml">Prerequisites</xref>
            have been performed.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Install with either KVM or ESX hypervisor support:</p>
          <ul>
            <li>
              <p>
                <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-kvm.xml">Install with KVM
                  hypervisor support</xref> and then <xref
                  href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-vsa.xml">configure HPE
                  StoreVirtual VSA for Block Storage</xref> or <xref
                  href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-3par.xml">configure HPE 3PAR
                  StoreServ Storage</xref>.</p>
            </li>
            <li>
              <p>
                <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-esx.xml">Install with ESX
                  hypervisor support</xref> and then <xref
                  href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-ESX-Proxy.xml">deploy the
                  compute proxy on the ESX hosts</xref> and <xref
                  href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-ovsvapp.xml">deploy OVSvApp
                  for HPE Virtual Cloud Networking</xref>.</p>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Optionally, <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-DNSaaS.xml"
              >install and configure DNSaaS support</xref>.</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <p>There are a few things you should be aware of before you begin your HPE Helion OpenStack
        baremetal installation.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <p>Loading images is slow, so be patient.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The seed VM must remain booted while the undercloud and overcloud are up.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The <codeph>stackrc</codeph> and <codeph>tripleo_*_passwords</codeph> files contain
            credentials for the undercloud and the overcloud; you should ensure that they are
            securely stored separately from the seed.</p>
          <p>
            <codeph>/root/stackrc</codeph>
          </p>
          <p>
            <codeph>/root/tripleo/tripleo_*_passwords</codeph>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>The installation will create two initial Object Storage nodes. If you need additional
            Object Storage nodes, you must create them manually after installation.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>All the Helion servers use UTC as a time zone.</p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        <b>Important:</b> When installing HPE Helion OpenStack it is your responsibility to track
        the physical location (slot number and rack) and associated identifiers (such as MAC
        addresses) for each physical server to aid in future hardware maintenance. This is necessary
        because when HPE Helion OpenStack is installed on physical servers, the TripleO automation
        tracks only the MAC network addresses of servers; the physical locations of servers are not
        tracked. This means there is no automated way to inform a service technician which slot or
        rack to go to when service is needed on a particular physical server.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="next-step">
      <title>Next Step</title>
      <p>Review the information in <xref
          href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-prereqs.xml">Installation
          Prerequisites</xref>.</p>
      <p>
        <xref href="#topic4315"> Return to Top </xref>
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="moreinfo">
      <title>For more information</title>
      <p>Before you start, if you want more information on HPE Helion OpenStack see the
        following:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.faq.xml">FAQ</xref>
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.release-notes.xml">Release notes</xref>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
