<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic9766">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> 1.0: Cinder Block Storage Using HPE StoreVirtual VSA</title>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.-vsa-overview.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/openstack/install/vsa/overview/--></p>
<p>

</p>
<p>HPE Helion OpenStack bundles and facilitates deployment of HPE StoreVirtual VSA which can be configured as backend for OpenStack Cinder Block Storage.</p>
<p>This page provides detailed information on using HPE StoreVirtual VSA for realizing cloud storage.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9766/StoreVirtual-overview">HPE StoreVirtual VSA overview</xref> </li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9766/cinder-architecture">Cinder Architecture</xref>

<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9766/cinder-api">Cinder API</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9766/scheduler">Scheduler</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9766/cinder-volume">Cinder volume and Lefthand driver</xref>  </li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9766/differentiated-storage-offerings">Differentiated storage offerings</xref>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9766/scale-out-vsa">Scale Out Cinder Block storage with StoreVirtual VSA</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9766/next-steps">Next Steps</xref>
</li>
</ul>
<section id="StoreVirtual-overview"> <title>HPE StoreVirtual VSA overview</title>
<p>HPE StoreVirtual VSA Software is a Virtual Storage Appliance that provides the complete array functionality on top of Linux KVM environment without an external 
array hardware. It transforms your server's internal or direct-attached storage into a fully featured shared storage array—without the cost and complexity 
associated with dedicated storage. HPE StoreVirtual VSA uses scale-out, distributed clustering to provide a pool of storage with enterprise storage features and simple management.</p>
<p>Multiple StoreVirtual systems running on different servers create a clustered pool of storage with the ability to make data highly available by 
protecting volumes with network RAID. A logical grouping of clusters is done in order to form a unit and is called a management group. Each cluster can be treated as storage node by hypervisor and is accessed using VIP (virtual IP).</p>
<p>With Network RAID, blocks of data are striped and mirrored across multiple StoreVirtual systems, allowing volumes and applications to stay online in the event of disk, storage subsystem or server failure. iSCSI connectivity on HPE StoreVirtual VSA, support the use of the storage pools by cloud instances.
A single management group can contain up to 32 StoreVirtual nodes - grouped into clusters. A single cluster comprises 1 to 16 StoreVirtual nodes. Each management group can optimally manage a maximum of 1500 volumes.</p>
<p>HPE Helion OpenStack supports multiple clusters. For minimal deployment, you can create a management group with one cluster and with a single StoreVirtual node on it.</p>
<p>HPE StoreVirtual VSA enables the following features in HPE Helion OpenStack</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>
<b>Storage clustering</b>: It allows you to consolidate multiple storage nodes into pools of storage. The available capacity and performance is aggregated and made available to every volume in the cluster. As storage needs increase, StoreVirtual can scale performance and capacity online.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>
<b>Data availability</b>: Network RAID strips and mirrors multiple copies of data across a cluster of storage nodes, eliminating any single point of failure in the StoreVirtual SAN. Applications have continuous data availability in the event of  power, network, disk, controller, or entire storage node failure.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>
<b>Thin provisioning</b>: It allocates space only as data is actually written without requiring pre-allocation of storage. This raises the overall utilization and efficiency and thus increases the Return on Investment(ROI).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>
<b>Simplified data protection</b>: Snapshots create thinly provisioned, instant point-in-time copies of data on a per-volume basis. As an administrator, you can access snapshots to recover individual files/folders from the volume, or rollback an entire volume to a prior state.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>
<b>Centralized Management Console (CMC)</b>: Multiple data centers and sites can be managed from an all inclusive "single pane-of-glass." All  StoreVirtual SAN features are managed from the Centralized Management Console (CMC) for simple, easy-to-manage storage.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="hp-storevirtual-dep-platform"> <title>HPE StoreVirtual Deployment Models supported in HPE Helion OpenStack</title>
<p>The following diagram displays the different development platforms supported in HPE Helion OpenStack</p>
<p>
  <image href="../../media/storevitual-development-platform.png" placement="break"/>
</p>
<p>There are three supported models for deploying StoreVirtual in HPE Helion OpenStack</p>
<ol>
<li>You can deploy and configure dedicated HPE StoreVirtual VSA Storage nodes using the HPE Helion OpenStack TripleO/Heat-based Installer. Licenses for these VSA nodes are included for use from HPE Helion OpenStack Compute Cloud Nodes only.</li>
<li>User deploys and configures StoreVirtual VSA in VMware ESX platform, and maps these to Cinder backends. Licenses for these must be separately procured and are not included with HPE Helion OpenStack</li>
<li>User installs StoreVirtual P4000 devices rather than using StoreVirtual VSA. These devices must be separately procured and are not included with HPE Helion OpenStack</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="cinder-architecture"> <title>Cinder architecture</title>
<p>Cinder is the block-based storage component of the HPE  Helion OpenStack platform for cloud computing. It facilitates the provisioning of storage in the form of block devices known as Cinder volumes. In the most common scenario, the Cinder volumes provide persistent storage to guest virtual machines (known as instances) that are managed by OpenStack Compute software. Cinder is based on the distributed architecture which can scale horizontally and serve concurrent volume management requests.</p>
<p>Cinder consists of three basic services:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>
<b>Cinder API</b>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>
<b>Cinder scheduler</b>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>
<b>Cinder volume</b> <i>along with an underlying dedicated database</i>
</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
  <image href="../../media/storevirtual-cinder-api.png" placement="break"/>
</p>
</section>
<section id="cinder-api"> <title>Cinder API</title>
<p>Cinder API is a REST based interface to perform volume operations. As an end-user, you can accomplish volume operations without worrying about the storage  backend device used to provide the actual storage. The following volume operations are supported:</p>
<ol>
<li>Create volumes</li>
<li>Delete volumes</li>
<li>Extend volumes</li>
<li>Attach volumes</li>
<li>Detach volumes</li>
<li>Create snapshots</li>
<li>Delete snapshots</li>
<li>Create volumes from snapshots</li>
<li>Create cloned volumes</li>
<li>Copy images to volumes</li>
<li>Copy volumes to images
<!--12. Volume Backup to Swift
13. Volume Restore from Swift-->
<!--12. Volume migration(backend assisted).--></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="scheduler"> <title>Scheduler</title>
<p>The Cinder Scheduler tracks various backend capabilities and chooses the backend to place a new volume on. There are various configurable plugins for the scheduler. Filter scheduler has filters and weighers which help in deciding the backend to be used for a new volume request. The selection criteria includes the filters like- volume type, available free space, QoS specs, Extra specs etc. Scheduler ensures that the volumes are uniformly spread across all available backend devices.</p>
</section>
<section id="cinder-volume"> <title>Cinder Volume and LeftHand driver</title>
<p>Once the Scheduler determines the backend to be used, the Cinder volume performs the actual operations against the backend.</p>
<p>The Cinder volume service hosts the LeftHand Driver to communicate with the backend representing the StoreVirtual cluster, using the LeftHand REST API.</p>
<p>
<b>Note:</b> The HPLeftHandISCSIDriver is based on the Block Storage service (Cinder) plug-in architecture. Volume operations are run by communicating with the HPE LeftHand/StoreVirtual system over HTTPS, or SSH connections. 
For more details on the Lefthand driver, refer to <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/config-reference/content/HP-LeftHand-StoreVirtual-driver.html"   format="html" >HPE LeftHand/StoreVirtual driver</xref>.</p>
<p>When you configure multiple StoreVirtual backends, one cinder-volume is launched for each back-end storage or back-end storage pool. Each backend instance maps to an instance of a StoreVirtual cluster. Each cluster listens at an assigned VIP that is configured in the Cinder backend entry in <i>cinder.conf</i>.</p>
</section>
<section id="differentiated-storage-offerings"> <title>Differentiated Storage Offerings</title>
<p>HPE Helion OpenStack uses StoreVirtual as a backend to Cinder to realize horizontally scalable block storage. StoreVirtual is unique in the sense that storage controller runs as a virtual appliance and helps realize Software Defined Block Storage.</p>
<p>Cinder provides the concept of volume types to represent differentiated storage offerings based on various performance outputs, quality of service and backend devices that are used to realize cloud storage. Essentially, a volume type is mapped to one or more backends of similar capabilities as illustrated in figure below:</p>
<p>
  <image href="../../media/storevirtual-volume-mapping-new.png" placement="break"/>
</p>
<p>As a cloud administrator, you can create volume types to specify the storage offerings of the cloud and  configure Cinder with backends which have the ability to serve storage characteristics represented by the volume types. For example, as a cloud admin, you have the following storage capabilities:</p>
<p>
<b>1. Low Cost, Low Performance, High Capacity Storage</b> (Bronze)</p>
<p>
<b>2. Medium Cost, Medium Performance, Medium Capacity Storage</b> (Silver)</p>
<p>
<b>3. High Cost, High Performance, Low Capacity Storage</b> (Gold)</p>
<p>Then, as the cloud administrator, you need to create three volume types - bronze, silver and gold - and configure Cinder with three different backends. Each backend needs to be mapped to bronze, silver and gold, respectively.</p>
<p>Differentiated storage offerings based on performance and quality can be realized in HPE Helion OpenStack by creating clusters of different capabilities, configuring clusters as backends and mapping these backends to different volume types as suggested above.</p>
</section>
<section id="scale-out-vsa"> <title>Scale Out Cinder Block Storage with StoreVirtual VSA</title>
<p>The following diagram displays a reference design that is used as a starting point for scale out Cinder Block Storage with HPE StoreVirtual VSA.</p>
<p>
  <image href="../../media/storevirtual-scale-out-vsa.png" placement="break"/>
</p>
<p>The sizing of the StoreVirtual VSA Management Groups, Clusters and Instances is an intricate exercise used in balancing various parameters and preferences and should be done to optimize configurations for your specific deployment.</p>
</section>
<section id="next-steps"> <title>Next Step</title>
<ul>
<li>
<xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-vsa.xml" >Deploy and Configure HPE StoreVirtual VSA</xref>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
  <xref href="#topic9766"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
<!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
</section>
</body>
</topic>
