<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic13582">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> 1.0: Installation: Deploy and Configure HPE StoreVirtual VSA</title>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.install-GA-vsa.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/openstack/install/vsa/--></p>
<p>

</p>
<p>This page provides detailed instructions on deployment of HPE StoreVirtual VSA Storage Nodes, and their configuration as Cinder backend.It covers the following topics:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic13582/high-level-view">Deployment and Configuration Procedure Overview</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic13582/install-hp-storevirtual-cmc">Installing HPE StoreVirtual VSA Centralized Management Console (CMC) on Linux</xref>

<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic13582/prerequisites">Prerequisites</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic13582/installation">Installation</xref>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic13582/deploy-vsa">Deploying HPE StoreVirtual VSA storage sytems</xref>

<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic13582/prerequisites-vsa">Prerequisites</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic13582/enroll-new-baremetal-server">Enrolling the new Baremetal server</xref>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic13582/verify-install">Verifying the StoreVirtual installation status</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic13582/create-cluster">Creating  and adding a StoreVirtual Cluster to a new Management Group</xref> </li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic13582/adding-a-node">Adding a StoreVirtual node to an existing Management Group</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic13582/next-steps">Next Steps</xref>
</li>
</ul>
<section id="high-level-view"> <title>Deployment and Configuration Procedure Overview</title>
<p>The following diagram gives an overview of the steps involved in deploying, configuring and integrating StoreVirtual nodes into your cloud. The subsequent sections provide the detailed instructions on integration workflow.</p>
<p>
  <image href="../../media/storevirtual-integration.png" placement="break"/>HPE StoreVirtual VSA Deployment and Configuration Procedure 
</p>
<!--1 - **Install CMC**
     
   [Install CMC](#install-hp-storevirtual-cmc) on the seed node where the seed cloud is running. The CMC binary comes along with the HPE Helion OpenStack installer and is present in the **Tripleo** directory. 

2 - **Add VSA Baremetal nodes to ironic database**
    
   * Identify the hardware for StoreVirtual deployment and enroll the Baremetal to the ironic database.

   * Log in to the undercloud and source the environment variables(source stackrc).

   * Execute ironic CLI commands from the undercloud to enroll the Baremetal into ironic database.
   
   * [Deploy StoreVirtual storage systems](#deployment-vsa).

3a - **Run update cloud script to provision VSA node**

   * After the [enrollment of the new Baremetal server](#deployment-vsa) in the undercloud, log in to the seed cloud.

   * Update the *overcloud.json* file for StoreVirtual deployment and apply the configuration.
    
   * Execute the update cloud script.

3b - **Discover StoreVirtual in CMC**

   * After updating the cloud, StoreVirtual system is deployed in the new Baremetal server that is enrolled.

   * Create StoreVirtual cluster.

   * The IP address of the StoreVirtual storage system can be retrieved from `/etc/vsa/vsa_network_config.json` file in StoreVirtual node.

   * Launch the CMC and discover the StoreVirtual systems that have been deployed.

3c - **Create VSA cluster**

   * After discovering the StoreVirtual storage systems in CMC, [create the StoreVirtual cluster and management group](#create-cluster) from CMC.

4a - **Launch the undercloud Horizon dashboard**

4b - **Register VSA cluster**

4c - **Create VSA backend**

4d- **Get Cinder configuration for VSA backend**

   * Launch the Horizon Dashboard to [register and create backend for StoreVirtual](/helion/openstack/ga/undercloud/oc/config/storevirtual/) system.
    
   * After creating the backend, generate the Cinder backend advisory for StoreVirtual.

5a - **Update `overcloud-config.json` file with cinder configuration**

   With the advise generated from the above steps, update the overcloud-config.json file in the seed cloud.

5b - **Run update cloud script to update cinder.conf**

   * The cinder.conf in the overcloud should be updated after updating the overcloud-config.json file in the seed cloud.

   * Execute [update cloud script](/helion/openstack/ga/undercloud/oc/config/storevirtual/) from seed cloud. -->
</section>
<section id="install-hp-storevirtual-cmc"> <title>Installing HPE StoreVirtual VSA Centralized Management Console (CMC) on Linux</title>
<p>In order to configure the HPE StoreVirtual VSA nodes, you must first install the CMC. You can manage all connected StoreVirtual VSA instances from single CMC connected to HPE Helion OpenStack management network.</p>
</section>
<section id="prerequisites"> <title>Prerequisites</title>
<ul>
<li>
<p>You must be running the X Windows System to install the CMC.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>We recommend that you install CMC on the same KVM host that is used to run the seed VM. This host has direct network connectivity to servers running HPE StoreVirtual VSA. However, you may select an alternate host as long as it is accessible from the HPE Helion OpenStack management network.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
<b>Note</b>: These changes are required for 64-bit operating system only.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Execute the following commands:</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># apt-get update
# dpkg --add-architecture i386

# apt-get install openjdk-7-jdk:i386
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="installation"> <title>Installation</title>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Verify if the CMC installer file inside <codeph>tripleo</codeph> directory (packaged along with the HPE Helion OpenStack installer) has the executable permission otherwise execute the following command:</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># chmod +x CMC_11.5.01.0079.0_Installer_Linux.bin
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
<li>
<p>Launch the installer</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># ./CMC_11.5.01.0079.0_Installer_Linux.bin
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
<li>
<p>Follow the steps in the console based installation wizard to complete the installation.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>To start the CMC:<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.-->
From the directory in which the files are installed, click the <b>HPE Store Virtual Centralized Management Console</b> to launch CMC.<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--></p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>
<b>Note</b>: To launch the CMC from command line (CLI), navigate to the location where it is installed and enter</p>
<codeblock>
  <codeph> # ./"HPE Store Virtual Centralized Management Console".
</codeph>
</codeblock>
<p>
  <xref href="#topic13582"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
</section>
<section id="deploy-vsa"> <title>Deploying HPE StoreVirtual VSA</title>
</section>
<section id="prerequisites-vsa"> <title>Prerequisites</title>
<p>Ensure the following prerequisites are fulfilled before HPE StoreVirtual Storage systems are deployed:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Before enrolling the new Baremetal server for StoreVirtual deployment, ensure that <codeph>#ironic node-list</codeph> in the undercloud server does not have any free nodes.This is required to register a new node which matches the disk requirements for StoreVirtual and is picked by the installer for StoreVirtual deployment.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ensure that you have created a minimum of two(2) RAID groups. You can create a maximum of eight(8) groups. The first RAID group where the OS image is deployed is not considered for StoreVirtual storage.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Each physical disk should be RAID protected and should not be RAID 0. You can use RAID 5 and above. <!--For more details, refer - [**Storevirtual documentation LINK**]--></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>For deploying StoreVirtual systems without Adaptive Optimization (AO) the setup must have a minimum two(2) disks(/dev/sda, /dev/sdb).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>For deploying StoreVirtual systems with Adaptive Optimization (AO) the setup must have at least three(3) disks(/dev/sda, /dev/sdb,/dev/sdc). The disk /dev/sdb should be a Solid State Drive(SSD).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ensure that you create the RAID group for SSD drives immediately after creating the RAID group for boot volume. For example: If three RAID groups are to be created. The following is recommended :</p>

<p>
<b>Step 1</b>: Create the first RAID group for HDD drives and mark this as boot volume(/dev/sda)</p>

<p>
<b>Step 2</b>: Create the second RAID group for SSD drives which should be used as Tier 0 for AO (/dev/sdb)</p>

<p>
<b>Step 3</b>: Create the third RAID group for HDD drives which will be used as Tier 1(/dev/sdc)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Seed Cloud is installed and is running.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The bundled license for the StoreVirtual VSA has a maximum limit of 50TB per node, and hence the total amount of the configured storage on the StoreVirtual system should not exceed 50 TB.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<!--<img src="/media/storevirtual-cluster-network-diagram1.png" placement="break"/>-->
</section>
<section id="enroll-new-baremetal-server"> <title>Enrolling the New Baremetal Server</title>
<p>To deploy HPE StoreVirtual VSA, perform the following:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>SSH to undercloud as heat-admin from seed.</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># ssh heat-admin@&lt;IP Address&gt;
# sudo -i
# source stackrc
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>
<b>Note:</b> Before enrolling the new Baremetal server for StoreVirtual deployment, ensure that <codeph>ironic node-list</codeph> in the undercloud server does not have any free nodes suitable for StoreVirtual installation. If a suitable node is available, skip the Baremetal registration steps and go to <b>step 5</b> below.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Register the new Baremetal server in the Ironic database. Replace the cpus, memory_mb,local_gb,ipmi_address, ipmi_password variable values with your Baremetal settings.</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># ironic node-create -d pxe_ipmitool -p cpus=&lt;value&gt; -p memory_mb=&lt;value&gt; -p local_gb=&lt;value&gt; -p cpu_arch=&lt;value&gt; -i ipmi_address=&lt;IP Address&gt; -i ipmi_username=&lt;username&gt; -i ipmi_password=&lt;password&gt;
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>Following is the example for reference:</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># ironic node-create -d pxe_ipmitool -p cpus=12 -p memory_mb=98304 -p local_gb=1800 -p cpu_arch=amd64 -i ipmi_address=10.12.22.70 -i ipmi_username=admin -i ipmi_password=password
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
<li>
<p>Create the ironic port for the ironic node that you created in the  previous step.</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># ironic port-create --address $MAC_ADDR --node_uuid $NODE_UUID
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>
<b>$MAC_ADDR</b> refers to the MAC Address of the Baremetal server.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>List the Baremetal nodes. This command also lists the newly added nodes.</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># ironic node-list
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
<li>
<p>Log out from the undercloud to go back to the seed.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Edit the <codeph>/root/baremetal.csv file</codeph> in seed cloud with the details of the newly added node. <!--7. Edit the `/root/tripleo/configs/kvm-custom-ips.json` and update the value for `vsa_scale` or `vsa_ao_scale` appropriately.--></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Edit the environment variables file used during initial installation and update the value for <codeph>vsa_scale</codeph> or <codeph>vsa_ao_scale</codeph> appropriately</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>vsa_scale: &lt;no of StoreVirtual systems&gt;

vsa_ao_scale: &lt;no of StoreVirtual systems with AO enabled&gt;
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>
<b>NOTE</b>: For HPE StoreVirtual VSA, a management group with two storage systems and a Failover Manager is the minimum configuration for automated fault tolerant operations. Configurations greater than two systems can be redundant and do not require a Failover Manager. The Failover Manager is a specialized version of the LeftHand OS software designed to operate as a manager and provide automated failover capability. It runs as a virtual appliance and must be installed on a separate system/VM  other than the storage systems in the SAN.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Execute the environment variables <!--`kvm-custom-ips.json`--> file using the source command</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># source tripleo/tripleo-incubator/scripts/hp_ced_load_config.sh tripleo/configs/&lt;environment variables file name&gt; 
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>for example</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># source tripleo/tripleo-incubator/scripts/hp_ced_load_config.sh tripleo/configs/kvm-custom-ips.json 
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<!--**Note**: Source the same file (`kvm-default.json` or `kvm-custom-ips.json`) that is used during the initial installation for specifying the environment IPs.9. Run the installer script to update the overcloud. During the installation, the number of StoreVirtual storage systems that you specified in the `overcloud-config.json`, are deployed.--></li>
<li>
<p>Run the installer script to update the overcloud. During the installation, the number of StoreVirtual storage systems that you specified in the environment variables file are deployed.</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># bash -x /root/tripleo/tripleo-incubator/scripts/hp_ced_installer.sh --update-overcloud |&amp; tee update.log
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
</ol>
<p>
  <xref href="#topic13582"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
</section>
<section id="verify-install"> <title>Verifying StoreVirtual installation status</title>
<p>To verify that the StoreVirtual storage system is deployed successfully, perform the following checks:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Log in to the undercloud from seed.</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># ssh heat-admin@&lt;undercloud IP address&gt;
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
<li>
<p>Source stackrc file and list the deployed StoreVirtual nodes.</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># source stackrc 
# heat stack-list
# nova list|grep vsa
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
<li>
<p>Log in to the StoreVirtual system from the seed using the IP address retrieved 
from the above steps.</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># ssh heat-admin@&lt;StoreVirtual system IP Address&gt;
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
<li>
<p>Check the log files.</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># tailf /installer.log
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>The message "<i>Started VM vsa-hostname</i>" indicates the successful installation of StoreVirtual on the machine.The IP Address of the StoreVirtual storage system can be retrieved from this log file.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>To display the status of all the StoreVirtual VMs.</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph># virsh list --all 
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>To get more details on the installer logs, check the <codeph>/var/log/storevirtual-installer.log</codeph> file.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>On successful installation of StoreVirtual VM on Baremetal, go to the Centralized Management Console(CMC) and discover the storage systems.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="create-cluster"> <title>Creating a StoreVirtual Cluster and adding it to a new Management Group</title>
<p>
  <b>Prerequisites</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>CMC is already installed</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>HPE StoreVirtual VSA (one or more) is deployed in the same management network where CMC is installed.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>To create a cluster, do the following:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Open CMC.</p>

<p>By default, the CMC is configured to discover the StoreVirtual nodes in the subnet in which it is installed. You can manually add the nodes also.</p>

<p>
<image href="../../media/storevirtual-cmc1.png" placement="break"/>CMC Main Page 
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In the CMC UI, click <b>Find</b> and then click <b>Find Systems</b> from the left panel.<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> Find Systems dialogue box is displayed.</p>

<p>
<image href="../../media/storevirtual-cmc2.png" placement="break"/>Find Systems option 
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You can choose <b>Add</b> or <b>Find</b> option to search the system. <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.-->Find option  starts searching for the nodes in the same subnet as that of CMC. Add option displays an <b>Enter IP</b> pop-up box to enter the IP of the StoreVirtual system.</p>

<p>
<b>Note:</b>To get the details of the HPE StoreVirtual VSA IP, log in to StoreVirtual system and check <codeph>/etc/vsa/vsa_network_config.json</codeph> file.</p>

<p>
<image href="../../media/storevirtual-cmc3.png" placement="break"/>Add option 
</p>

<p>
<image href="../../media/storevirtual-cmc4.png" placement="break"/>Find option 
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Click <b>OK</b> to proceed or click <b>Cancel</b> to cancel the process.<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.-->The node is discovered and the details are displayed in a tabular format in the Find Systems dialogue box.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>(Optional) Click <b>Add</b> in the Find Systems dialogue box to add more nodes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>(Optional) Click <b>Edit</b> in the Find Systems dialogue box to modify the details of the selected node.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>(Optional) Click <b>Remove</b> in the Find Systems box to delete a node.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Click <b>Close</b> to return to the Home page.<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> The discovered nodes are displayed under <b>Available Systems</b> option in the left panel.</p>

<p>
<image href="../../media/storevirtual-cmc5.png" placement="break"/>Discovered Nodes Under Available Systems 
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>To add the node to a management group, right-click the node to display a menu and select <b>Add to a New Management Group</b>.<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> Management Groups, Clusters, And Volumes wizard is displayed.</p>

<p>
<image href="../../media/storevirtual-cmc6.png" placement="break"/>Create Management Page 
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In the <b>Management Group Name</b> box, enter a name for the management group and click <b>Next</b> to display the Add Administrative User page.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Enter the required information for the Administrative user and click <b>Next</b> to display the Management Group Time page.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Synchronize the time using NTP server or manually and click <b>Next</b> to display the Domain Name Server Configuration page.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Define  DNS details and click <b>Next</b> to display the Email Notification Setup page and define SMTP details.</p>

<p>
<b>Note</b>: It is optional to enter the details in the above step.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Click <b>Next</b> to display a Wizard in the Create a Cluster page.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Select the cluster type as <i>Standard Cluster</i> from the displayed options and click <b>Next</b>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In the <b>Cluster Name</b> box, enter the name of the cluster and click <b>Next</b>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In the Add VIP and Subnet Mask pop-up box, enter the virtual IP and Subnet Mask of the cluster in the respective boxes and click <b>OK</b>.<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> The details are displayed in a tabular format in the page.</p>

<p>
<b>Note</b>: Ensure that the Virtual IP (VIP) is unique and is in the same subnet as the HPE StoreVirtual VSA system.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Click <b>Next</b> to go to the next page.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>(Optional) Click the checkbox displayed against <b>Skip Volume Creation</b>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Click <b>Next</b>.<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.-->The Management Group and Cluster is created and displays in the Home page of CMC.</p>

<p>
<image href="../../media/storevirtual-cmc7.png" placement="break"/>CMC Main Page with the Cluster 
</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>
  <xref href="#topic13582"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
</section>
<section id="adding-a-node"> <title>Adding HPE StoreVirtual VSA System to an existing Management Group</title>
<p>To add a StoreVirtual system to any existing Management Group, do the following:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Open CMC.</p>

<p>By default, the CMC is configured to discover the HPE StoreVirtual VSA systems in the subnet on which it is installed. You can manually add the nodes also.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In the CMC page, click <b>Find Systems</b> from the left panel.<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> Find Systems dialogue box is displayed with an Enter IP pop-up box.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You can choose <b>Add</b> or <b>Find</b> option to search the system. <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.-->Find option  starts searching for the nodes in the subnet. Add option displays an <b>Enter IP</b> pop-up box to enter the IP of the StoreVirtual node.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Click <b>OK</b> to proceed or click <b>Cancel</b> to cancel the process.<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.-->The node is discovered and the details are displayed in a tabular format in the Find Systems dialogue box.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>(Optional) Click <b>Add</b> in the Find Systems dialogue box to add more nodes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>(Optional) Click <b>Edit</b> in the Find Systems dialogue box to modify the details of the selected node.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>(Optional) Click <b>Remove</b> in the Find Systems box to delete a node.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Click <b>Close</b> to return to the Home page.<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> The discovered nodes are displayed under <b>Available Systems</b> option in the left panel.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Right-click the node to display a menu and select <b>Add to an Existing Management Group</b>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Enter the name of the management group.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Click <b>Add</b> to add the node to the group that you specified.<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> The node is added to the management group.</p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="next-steps"> <title>Next Steps</title>
<ul>
<li>
<p>
<xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.undercloud-resources-overview.xml" >Working with HPE Helion OpenStack Undercloud Horizon Dashboard</xref>-(Recommended)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>
<xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.0commercial.sirius-cli-workflow.xml" >Sirius CLI</xref>
</p>
</li>
</ul>
<!-- [Working with HPE StoreVirtual VSA](/helion/openstack/ga/undercloud/storage/storevirtual/)-  REQUIRED



     Configure HPE StoreVirtual **(REQUIRED)** HPE StoreVirtual VSA Software is a Virtual Storage Appliance that provides the complete array functionality on top of Linux KVM environment without an external array hardware. It eliminates the need for external shared storage required to implement block storage features. It uses scale-out, distributed clustering to provide a pool of storage with enterprise storage features and simple management.

    For detailed intructions, see the  document. 
- [Working With StoreVirtual Backends](/helion/openstack/ga/undercloud/oc/config/storevirtual/)-  REQUIRED

    Our managed DNS service, based on the OpenStack Designate project, is engineered to help you create, publish, and manage your DNS zones and records securely and efficiently to either a public or private DNS server network.

    For detailed installation intructions, see [DNSaaS Installation and Configuration](/helion/openstack/ga/install/dnsaas/).-->
<!--## Next step

Configure HPE 3PAR StoreServ, see [HPE Helion OpenStack Commercial: HPE StoreServ (3PAR) Support](/helion/openstack/install/3par/).-->
<p>
  <xref href="#topic13582"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
<!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
</section>
</body>
</topic>
