<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic18834">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> 1.1.1: Release Notes</title>
<titlealts>
<searchtitle>HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1: Related OpenStack Documentation</searchtitle>
</titlealts>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion OpenStack"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="All"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Geraldine K."/>
<othermeta name="product-version1" content="HPE Helion OpenStack"/>
<othermeta name="product-version2" content="HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./commercial/GA1/1.1.1commercial.release-notes.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/openstack/1.1.1/release-notes/11/--></p>
<p>
  <xref href="1.1commercial.release-notes.xml" >See the Release Notes for HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1.</xref>
</p>
<p>Thank you for your interest in HPE Helion OpenStack This document provides an overview of the features contained within HPE Helion OpenStack version 1.1.1, including known issues and workarounds, and where to find further information on the product release:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic18834/features">Features in HPE Helion OpenStack</xref> </li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic18834/known-issues">Known Issues in this Release</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic18834/For-Further-Information">For Further Information</xref> </li>
</ul>
<section id="features"> <title>Features in HPE Helion OpenStack</title>
<p>The following features have been added to HPE Helion OpenStack by release.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic18834/111">HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1.1</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic18834/110">HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic18834/101">HPE Helion OpenStack 1.01</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic18834/10">HPE Helion OpenStack 1.0</xref>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="111"> <title>Features in HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1.1</title>
<p>
<b>Integration with HPE ArcSight</b>
HPE Helion OpenStack through its centralized logging infrastructure (Logstash,) can be configured to send events and logs to an HPE ArcSight endpoint. The HPE ArcSight connector can, in turn, be configured to receive logs and events in real time from this Logstash configuration inside an HPE Helion OpenStack environment.</p>
<p>Integration with HPE ArcSight provides the ability to monitor, analyze, and correlate HPE Helion OpenStack logs through HPE ArcSight Logger and ESM and supports continuous security monitoring of the entire HPE Helion OpenStack infrastructure. Technical details of this integration along with a step-by-step tutorial are available in the whitepaper entitled <xref href="http://www8.hp.com/h20195/V2/GetDocument.aspx?docname=4AA5-8025ENW&amp;cc=us&amp;lc=en" scope="external" format="html" >Monitoring HPE Helion OpenStack with HPE ArcSight</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Enabled customer-provided certificates for all endpoints</b>
This release supports the use of a <xref href="1.1.1commerical.services-customer-provided-certificates.xml" >customer-provided certificate</xref> without requiring any changes to the service configurations other than a possible restart.</p>
</section>
<section id="110"> <title>Features in HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1</title>
<p>The following features have been added to HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1:</p>
<p>
<b>OpenStack Juno support</b> All of the <xref href="1.1commerical.services-overview.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack services</xref> have been updated to <xref href="http://www.openstack.org/software/juno/" scope="external" format="html" >OpenStack Juno</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>HPE Helion OpenStack Metering services</b> The <xref href="1.1commerical.services-reporting-overview.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack Telemetry and Reporting service</xref> leverages the OpenStack Ceilometer metering service. The Metering Operations service takes specified measurements of both physical and virtual resources, including physical servers and network devices such as switches and firewalls.</p>
<p>
<b>Additional Components in Centralized Logging</b> <xref href="1.1commerical.services-logging-overview.xml" >Centralized logging support</xref> has now been added for the following additional components: <!--HPM-28--></p>
<ul>
<li>HAProxy</li>
<li>Syslog</li>
<li>Keepalived </li>
</ul>
<p>
<b>AppArmor profiles enabled for Compute nodes</b> AppArmor proactively protects the operating system and applications from external or internal threats, even zero-day attacks, by enforcing good behavior and preventing even unknown application flaws from being exploited. <!--HPM27--></p>
<p>
<b>Windows Server validation as a guest O/S on KVM</b> - HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1 has achieved <xref href="http://www.windowsservercatalog.com/svvp/" scope="external" format="html" >Microsoft Server Virtualization Validation Program</xref> (SVVP) approval.  As such, HPE Helion OpenStack is a validated and supported virtual environment for Windows Server 2012 R2, 2012, 2008 R2, and 2008.  <!--HPM-29--></p>
<p>For information on creating and deploying a Microsoft Windows Server that is Microsoft SVVP compliant on HPE Helion OpenStack as a Nova compute VM, see <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.create-deploy-certified-microsoft-windows-guest-image.xml" >How to build a Microsoft Windows Server guest image for HPE Helion OpenStack</xref>.  <!--DOCS-917--></p>
<p>Microsoft can provide technical support to customers with licensed Windows Server Operating Systems that are deployed as Nova compute VMs.</p>
<p>
<b>Swift diagnostic checks</b> - New diagnostics checks have been implemented for <xref href="1.1commerical.services-object-overview.xml" >Swift cluster</xref>. Diagnostic messages are sent to the <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-swift-deployment-monitor-replica-swift-status.xml" >Icinga service</xref>. <!--HPM15--></p>
<p>
<b>Improved recovery time</b> - When a virtual IP is moved to another overcloud controller on the system, the controller will become available in approximately one minute. <!--HPM121--></p>
<p>
<b>New Horizon Dashboard functionality</b> - The <xref href="1.1commercial.install-GA-DNSaaS.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack DNSaaS service</xref> functionality is now accessible through the <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-horizon-overview.xml" >Horizon dashboard</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Transport Layer Security (TLS) support</b> - HPE Helion OpenStack now supports TLS protocols to protect internal traffic for Overcloud OpenStack API and endpoints. <!--HPM16--></p>
<p>
<b>HPE Helion OpenStack Identity service</b> - The Identity service, based on OpenStack Keystone V2 or V3 provides one-stop authentication, including Identity, Token, Catalog and Policy services. See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-overview.xml" >Identity Service Overview</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Fibre Channel Zone Manager support</b> - The OpenStack Fibre Channel Zone Manager creates the necessary Fibre Channel zones during an attach of a Block Storage (Cinder) volume. Brocade Fibre Channel Zone Driver performs zoning operations via SSH. See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.services-volume-fibre.xml" >Configuring Fibre Channel Zone Manager</xref>.<!--HMP32--></p>
<p>
<b>Enable Unified Extensible Firmware Interface (UEFI) support for Gen8 and Gen9 HPE Servers</b> - UEFI is industry standard set of interfaces between the system firmware, the operating system, and between various components of the system firmware delivers enhanced security benefits for the HPE ProLiant Gen8 and Gen9 Server family. UEFI is meant to replace the Basic Input/Output System (BIOS) firmware interface. For more information, see <xref href="http://www8.hp.com/us/en/products/server-software/product-detail.html?oid=6935826" scope="external" format="html" >HPE Unified Extensible Firmware Interface</xref>.<!--HPM12--></p>
<p>
  <b>Compute Service Configuration Drive</b> - The HPE Helion OpenStack compute service can be configured to <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide/cli_config_drive.html" scope="external" format="html"> write metadata to a special configuration drive</xref> that contains information normally available through the metadata service.</p>
<p>
<b>Ruby CLI No Longer Supported</b> - The Ruby CLI (unix_cli) is no longer supported. Users are advised to consider the Python CLIs as an alternative.</p>
</section>
<section id="101"> <title>Features in HPE Helion OpenStack 1.01</title>
<p>The following features have been added to HPE Helion OpenStack 1.01:</p>
<p>
<b>Defect fixes</b> - A number of defects were addressed and fixed in this release.</p>
<p>
<b>Security documentation</b> - A new document is included in this release that contains recommendations for securing your HPE Helion OpenStack network. <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.install-GA-security.xml" >Configuring your network securely</xref> details the firewall rules you can apply at the edge of the HPE Helion OpenStack deployment to protect against external abuse and defines router rules within the HPE Helion OpenStack deployment to protect against insider abuse or administrative errors.</p>
<p>
<b>HPE Helion OpenStack Flexible Control Plane</b> - The <xref href="1.1commerical.flexible-control-pane-overview.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack Flexible Control Plane</xref> introduces the capacity to deploy the control plane in a virtual environment in addition to the current baremetal physical deployment. This new configuration reduces the control plane footprint to just three servers from the current seven to ten servers.</p>
</section>
<section id="10"> <title>Features in HPE Helion OpenStack 1.0</title>
<p>The following features have been added to HPE Helion OpenStack 1.0:</p>
<p>
<b>OpenStack Services</b> - The full set of standard <xref href="1.1commerical.services-overview.xml#OpenStack" type="section">OpenStack services</xref> is in HPE Helion OpenStack Nova (Compute), Swift (Object Operations), Cinder (Volume Operations), Neutron (Networking Operations), Glance (Image OPerations), Keystone (Identity Management), Horizon (Helion dashboard), Heat (Orchestration), TripleO, and Ironic.</p>
<p>

<b>Other Services</b> - <xref href="1.1commerical.services-overview.xml#Other" type="section">Other services</xref> included in the release include: Sherpa, Sirius, EON, DNSaaS, and DVR.</p>
<p>
<b>LogStash/ElasticSearch</b> - This service provides enhanced security and supportability of your cloud by offering centralized logging.</p>
<p>
<b>Icinga</b> - This service provides infrastructure monitoring ensuring the health of the cloud.</p>
<p>
<b>HPE StoreVirtual VSA</b> -  <xref href="http://www8.hp.com/us/en/products/storage-software/product-detail.html?oid=5306917" scope="external" format="html" >HPE StoreVirtual VSA</xref> is storage virtualization software used as the default fault-tolerant, software-defined storage backend for the Volume Operations service, and provides easy deployment on KVM nodes meeting on-demand scale-out requirements of cloud storage without sacrificing performance.</p>
<p>
<b>Support for VMWare ESX</b> - VMWare ESX is a baremetal hypervisor. HPE Helion OpenStack makes ESX host onboarding and management easier and lets you setup the ESX proxy node during installation of the overcloud.</p>
<p>
<b>HPE Virtual Cloud Networking (VCN) Application</b> - Enables you to create networks, subnets and ports, as well as security groups and security group rules for your ESX clusters using OVSvApp.</p>
</section>
<section id="known-issues"> <title>Known Issues in this Release</title>
<p>The following are the known issues for HPE Helion OpenStack</p>
  
  
  <p>
    <b>Deployment Issues</b>
  </p>"Invalid Device Choice" error encountered while setting the persistent boot device.
  Deployment can fail on HPE Gen9 servers with iLO firmware version 2.2, with the following error
  in the conductor logs: "Invalid Device Choice" while setting the persistent boot device.
  <p>This error is caused by an issue in iLO firmware version 2.2 on HPE Gen9 servers. You have
    two options for working around this issue: <ol>
      <li> Manually install proliantutils version greater than or equal to 2.1.3 on the
        undercloud node. Run the following command on the undercloud node to install
        proliantutils: <codeblock>$ pip install "proliantutils>=2.1.3"</codeblock>
      </li>
      <li> Or switch to using iLO firmware version 2.1. </li>
    </ol>
  </p>

  
  
<p>
  <b>Operational Issues</b>
</p>
<p>When using HPE Helion OpenStack you might experience the following issues:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>When a significant update operation is performed, such as adding or removing nodes, connectivity to the VM will drop until the operation is completed. This may last for up to 15 minutes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If you use the Updates and Extensions tab of the Helion Dashboard for the overcloud (known as the <i>Sherpa UI</i>) to download two images that use the same name in two different projects, the second image will fail to upload to the Image Operations service (Glance). Avoid using images that use the same name. <!-- (CODN-24) --></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If, for some reason, the overcloud compute service is rebooted, the VMs might be in an ERROR state. Execute the following commands to restart the services and remove the error(s):</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>sudo service nova-compute restart
sudo service nova-scheduler restart
sudo service nova-conductor restart
sudo service neutron-openvswitch-agent restart
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
<li>
<p>In some instances, the centralized logging feature does not function after the product installation. If this occurs, perform the following steps on the overcloud controller and all compute nodes:</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>service beaver restart
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
<li>The nova compute node with IP 10.23.32.210 may have processing issues, causing the check_mk agent responses to pause or hang. Multiple check processes can interfere with each other, which can lead to more delays. Kill all running check processes to work around the issue.
<!-- CORE-3174 --></li>
</ul>
<p>
  <b>Networking Issues</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>After installation, VMs hosted on a particular compute host are not pingable. To resolve this issue, restart the Neutron-Open vSwitch-agent on that compute host.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Under heavy load, the neutron-openvswitch-agent can fail to properly clean-up old virtual network interfaces resulting in degraded performance.  Restarting the neutron-openvswitch-agent can correct this problem. <!-- VNETCORE-490 DOCS-1062 --></p>
</li>
</ul>
<!-- Removed per Jack McCann
* When Distributed Virtual Router (DVR) is enabled, private IP address communication between instances on the same Neutron network is slower than public IP address communication. DVR speeds-up public IP address communication between instances on the same Neutron network, making private IP address communucation appear slower than public IP address communication. VNETCORE-441 DOCS-1063 
 -->
<p>
<!-- Removing this for 1.1.1 because it's fixed as of VNETCORE-448
* With Distributed Virtual Router (DVR) enabled, the performance of the `neutron router-interface-delete` command is known to degrade significantly as the number of routers or compute nodes increases.--> <!-- VNETCORE-448 DOCS-1061 --></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>When creating very large numbers (thousands) of VM instances in a synchronous manner, sporadic instance creation failure may be experienced. To work around this behavior, lower the instance creation rate until consistent success is achieved. <!-- VNETEE-53 DOCS-1050 CORE-3042--></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If a Nova compute node becomes unreachable, many openSSL requests are made to it, spawning many processes. The requests are not timed out or killed, causing resource usage to continue to increase. <!-- CORE-3174 --></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Helion installer cannot handle spaces before or after IP addresses in kvm-custom-ips.json. As a result, the Helion installer cannot create the seed VM's networking.
<!-- DOCS-1317 and HLM-669 --></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>VMs scheduled on a particular host may not get their IP address in a timely manner. On that particular host, the neutron-openvswitch-agent process takes a large percentage of the CPU. Restarting the neutron services on that host will allow things to recover. <!-- Vnetcore-746 --></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
  <b>Helion Dashboard Issues</b>
</p>
<p>When using HPE Helion OpenStack you might experience the following issues:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>You cannot associate floating IP to a nova instance port in the Horizon dashboard for users other than the admin user. By default, Horizon does not provide a "network" for any new user/tenant combo. The only way to get a network is to make an existing network a shared network. However there will be no router, because Horizon does not provide a mechanism to share the router, and thus there are no available ports listed.
The workaround is to associate/disassociate the floating IP from the CLI, like so: <!-- docs 1160 --> <!-- HORI-3315 --></p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>neutron floatingip-associate &lt;FLOATINGIP_ID&gt; &lt;PORT&gt;
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>Alternatively, from Horizon, create a router for the shared network and set the gateway to ext-net/public.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Changing the user settings in a non-admin role affects all users across all projects. Changes to a user role should not affect other roles. There is no workaround. <!-- (HORI-2934) --></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
  <b>Update Issues</b>
</p>
<p>You may experience the following issues when performing updates in this release:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Depending on configuration, an overcloud update may take longer than was the case in earlier releases. 
<!--ANSUPDATE-276/DOCS-1070 --></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>After an update, the node removal procedure might not work.  This is a known issue.<!-- CORE-2940 / DOCS 1068  --></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Overcloud updates may fail because you cannot stop VSA VMs. Overcloud updates require that all VMs be stopped before an update can proceed. During an overcloud update, you may find that you are not able to stop the VSA VM (by issuing a <codeph>virsh stop</codeph> command). This causes the update to stop.</p>

<p>To fix this problem you can use the VSA command-line interface (CLIQ) to shut down VSA on the VM that cannot be shut down. You can access CLIQ by running ssh to port 16022 on the Virtual IP for the VSA server. If you do not know the IP address/username/password of the VSA system, you can find it in <b>/etc/cinder/cinder.conf</b> on controller0 on the overcloud.</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>ssh -l &lt;username&gt; &lt;IP&gt; -p 16022
ClIQ&gt; shutdownNsm action=Shutdown
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>Proceed with the update.
<!--CORE 2981 / DOCS 1067--></p>
</li>
</ul>
<!-- Cinder cannot create volumes after a system update.   A resolution is under development. per DOCS 1182  -->
<p>
<!-- Cinder fails to create Bootable Volumes after a system update. It appears that ISCSI authentication is failing on controller0. The workaround is to migrate the `cinder-volume` service to another node, for example, controller1, and to stop the `cinder-backup` service on controller0.
Performing backups and creating bootable volumes will then work.-->   <!--CORE-2987 / DOCS 1064--></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Cinder might fail after an update. To fix Cinder,  restart the <codeph>cinder-volume</codeph> service on controller0 by entering: <!-- DOCS-1047 --></p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>$ sudo service cinder-volume restart
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>Then restart the <codeph>cinder-backup</codeph> service on all three overcloud controller nodes by entering:</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>$ sudo service cinder-backup restart
</codeph>
</codeblock>

  <p>For more information on how to restart the singleton Cinder volume  service, see <xref href="1.0commerical.high-availability.xml#topic21283/cinder-volume" type="section">HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1: High Availability</xref>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>
<!--DOCS-1032--> Cinder backup and create bootable volume functions fail after an update. A workaround exists if this is an ISCSI error.  To determine if this is an ISCSI error, grep for the following string in in <codeph>/var/log/cinder/cinder-volume.log</codeph> on controller0:</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>grep 'Failed to copy image &lt;image-id&gt; to volume: &lt;volume-id&gt;, error: iscsiadm: No session found.' /var/log/cinder/cinder-volume.log
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>If this is an ISCSI error, you will see confirmation in the return, for example:</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph> 2015-02-23 13:46:01.415 21650 ERROR cinder.volume.flows.manager.create_volume [req-918f993f-5456-4eba-a266-67a638e9aa99 9f5ec59efa57483aad14b20378091195 c4b1111b613c4454a4cb3101ac420f54 - - -] Failed to copy image eeecc4aa-8a99-447d-848f-c40f4af0d606 to volume: 0260a9e1-2e4a-444f-81d7-867f63f23fe9, error: iscsiadm: No session found.
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>If you confirm that the error is present on Controller0, then the workaround is to:</p>

<ul>
<li>
<p>migrate the cinder-volume service to another node, for example, controller1 (refer to <xref href="1.0commerical.high-availability.xml#cinder-volume" type="section">HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1: High Availability</xref>)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>stop the cinder-backup service on controller0 using</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>sudo service cinder-backup stop
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Performing backups and creating bootable volumes will then work.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
  <b>Other Issues</b>
</p>
<p>Other issues you might experience when using HPE Helion OpenStack</p>
<!-- (DOCS-839) -->
<ul>
<li>
<p>When you resize an instance of Nova (in the Horizon portal under <i>Project &gt; Instances</i>
            and select <i>Resize Instance</i> from the drop-down list), the system produces the
            following error: ‘‘Error: Unable to resize instance [instance name]".
            <!--(NOV-6664) (NOV-6664) --></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A Kernel Panic error occurs on DL 360 G7 systems when a user employs SSH to log in to a virtual machine and attempts to connect to an IP address external to HPE Helion OpenStack If this occurs, update the kernel to the latest version. <!-- (EE-21) --></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When a controller node crashes, it must be rebooted to return to its operational state. <!-- (CORE-1387) --></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The installation process leaves behind it a running VM, and a shared internal network <codeph>default-net</codeph>.</p>

<p>This shared internal network can cause problems when running Tempest tests. If this is an issue, you can remove the <codeph>demo</codeph> VM and the <codeph>default-net</codeph> network. <!-- (CORE-586) --></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The Keepalived processes do not restart automatically when they are killed. Use the service <codeph>keepalived start</codeph> to restart Keepalived. <!-- (CORE-972) --></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The HAProxy does not automatically restart when it is killed. Restart haproxy manually using <codeph>service haproxy restart</codeph>. <!-- (CORE-943) --></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
<!--
- Heat templates and updating Helion: If you  are using a modified heat template, you should update the new templates that are provided with the installer to reflect what you had modified in your previous deployment. If you have not made any changes to the original template, then you can execute
 `./tripleo/tripleo-incubator/scripts/hp_ced_installer.sh -??-update-undercloud` 
and
 `./tripleo/tripleo-incubator/scripts/hp_ced_installer.sh -??-update-overcloud` 
to update the HEAT templates.
-->
<!-- above is for patch or update --></p>
</section>
<section id="For-Further-Information"> <title>For Further Information</title>
<p>For additional information about HPE Helion OpenStack OpenStack Cloud Software, and the HPE Helion Support Center:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<xref href="1.1commercial.index.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack Documentation web site</xref>: Provides information on topics such as installation and configuration, FAQs, and applications for all of the HPE Helion OpenStack product offerings.</li>
<li>
<xref href="http://www.openstack.org/" scope="external" format="html" >OpenStack web site</xref>: Provides information on computing, networking, and storage in OpenStack various programs such as TripleO, and the OpenStack community.</li>
<li>
<xref href="http://us-support.external.hp.com/portal/site/hpsc/public" scope="external" format="html" >HPE Support Center</xref>: Provides a way to report issues with HPE Helion OpenStack</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="legal-notices-disclaimer"> <title>Legal Notices and Disclaimer</title>
<!--See the [HPE Helion OpenStack Open Source and Third-Party Software License Agreements](/helion/openstack/1.1/commercial-3rd-party-license-agreements/).-->
  <p> <tm tmtype="reg">Linux</tm> is the registered trademark of Linus Torvalds in the U.S. and other countries.</p>
<p>The OpenStack Word Mark is either a registered trademark/service mark or trademark/service mark of the OpenStack Foundation, in the United States and other countries and is used with the OpenStack Foundation's permission. We are not affiliated with, endorsed or sponsored by the OpenStack Foundation, or the OpenStack community.</p>
<p>
<b>HPE Helion OpenStack Warranty</b>: 
The programs included with the Debian Host Linux system are free software. The exact license terms for each program are described in the individual files in /usr/share/doc/*/copyright. Debian Host Linux comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY, to the extent permitted by applicable law.</p>
<p>
  <xref type="section" href="#topic18834"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
<!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
</section>
</body>
</topic>
