<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic5798">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> 1.1: Network Administrator Notes</title>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Systems Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Cloud Architect"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Storage Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Network Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Service Developer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Cloud Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Application Developer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Network Engineer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Michael B"/>
<othermeta name="product-version1" content="HPE Helion Openstack"/>
<othermeta name="product-version2" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.network-administrator-notes.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/openstack/1.1/network/administrator/notes/--></p>
<p>The HPE Helion OpenStack cloud networking platform is based on the OpenStack standard. OpenStack defines an architecture and compliant vendors (of which HPE is one) create the implementations. HPE Helion is one of these OpenStack implementations.</p>
<p>The OpenStack Cloud Administrator Notes describe the common administrator tasks required to enable and maintain the primary OpenStack services. These primary services are shown below.</p>
<p>
  <image href="../../media/commercial_openstack-services.png" placement="break"/>
</p>
<p>As a Helion administrator, you should follow the OpenStack Cloud Administrator Guide (available at <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/"   format="html" >http://docs.openstack.org/</xref>) to enable and maintain each of these OpenStack services. Then refer to this guide for additional information to enable and maintain HPE Helion OpenStack This guide will explain what you have to do in addition to, or instead of, what is in the OpenStack guide.</p>
<p>To simplify the interaction between the <b>
<i>OpenStack Cloud Administrator Guide</i>
</b> and this guide, this Helion administrator guide mirrors the organization of the <b>
<i>OpenStack Cloud Administrator Guide</i>
</b>. To manage Neutron for example, refer to the OpenStack guide on Neutron (Chapter 7, Networking), then refer to Managing the Network service in this guide to determine if Helion OpenStack requires configuration steps.</p>
<p>Because OpenStack defines a platform with multiple services, administrators need to understand how these services interact and interdepend. The following illustration explains these relationships.</p>
<p>
  <image href="../../media/commercial.network-administrator.png" placement="break"/>
</p>
<p>The OpenStack Cloud Administrator Guide is available on the OpenStack website http://docs.openstack.org/admin-guide-cloud/content/index.html</p>
<p>To help you perform your administrative roles in these areas, this guide includes information on:</p>
<ul>
<li>
        <xref href="#topic5798/managing-the-identity-service-managing-the-identity-service"
          format="dita">Managing the Identity service</xref>
      </li>
<li><xref href="#topic5798/managing-the-dashboard-managing-the-dashboard" format="dita">Managing the
          Dashboard</xref>
      </li>
<li>
        <xref href="#topic5798/managing-the-compute-service-managing-the-compute-service"
          format="dita">Managing the Compute service</xref>
      </li>
<li><xref href="#topic5798/managing-object-storage-managing-object-storage" format="dita">Managing Object
          Storage</xref>
      </li>
<li>
        <xref href="#topic5798/managing-block-storage-managing-block-storage" format="dita">Managing Block Storage</xref>
      </li>
<li>
        <xref href="#topic5798/managing-the-network-service-managing-the-network-service"
          format="dita">Managing the Network service</xref>
      </li>
<li><xref href="#topic5798/managing-the-database" format="dita">Managing the Database</xref>
      </li>
</ul>
<section id="managing-the-identity-service-managing-the-identity-service"> <title>Managing the Identity service (#Managing-the-Identity-service)</title>
<p>OpenStack Identity, code-named keystone, is the default identity management system for OpenStack Configuring the OpenStack Identity service is sufficient for Helion administrators. No additional work is required to support HPE Helion OpenStack</p>
</section>
<section id="managing-the-dashboard-managing-the-dashboard"> <title>Managing the Dashboard (Managing-the-Dashboard)</title>
<p>The OpenStack dashboard, code named Horizon, is a Web-based interface that allows you to manage OpenStack resources and services. The dashboard allows you to interact with the OpenStack Compute cloud controller using the OpenStack APIs. 
In the Helion environment, HPE uses HPE Badge and the Helion undercloud dashboard in addition to Horizon.</p>
</section>
<section id="managing-the-compute-service-managing-the-compute-service"> <title>Managing the Compute service (Managing-the-Compute-service)</title>
<p>The OpenStack Compute service (code named Nova) allows you to control an Infrastructure-as-a-Service (IaaS) cloud computing platform. It gives you control over instances and networks, and allows you to manage access to the cloud through users and projects.
Configuring the OpenStack Compute service is sufficient for Helion administrators. No additional work is required.</p>
</section>
<section id="managing-object-storage-managing-object-storage"> <title>Managing Object Storage (Managing-Object-Storage</title>
<p>OpenStack Object Storage (code-named swift) is open source software for creating redundant, scalable data storage using clusters of standardized storage servers. Configuring the OpenStack Object Storage service is sufficient for Helion administrators. No additional work is required.</p>
</section>
<section id="managing-block-storage-managing-block-storage"> <title>Managing Block Storage (Managing-Block-Storage)</title>
<p>The OpenStack Block Storage service (code name Cinder) works through the interaction of a series of daemon processes named cinder-* that reside persistently on the host machine or machines.  For Helion, you have the option to configure backend support for:</p>
<ul>
<li>VSA</li>
<li>3PAR</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="managing-the-network-service-managing-the-network-service"> <title>Managing the Network service (Managing-the-Network-service)</title>
<p>The Networking service, code-named Neutron, provides an API that lets you define network connectivity and addressing in the cloud.  Configuring the OpenStack Network service is largely sufficient for Helion administrators.</p>
<p>For details on configuring Helion Neutron, see <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/neutron/1.1commercial_neutron-pre-installation.xml" >Neutron Prerequisites</xref>.</p>
</section>
<section id="managing-metering-managing-the-database"> <title>Managing Metering  (Managing-the-Database)</title>
<p>Metering (code named Ceilometer) supports billing systems for OpenStack cloud resources.  As the list of meters expands, metering data can be analyzed for different purposes other than billing.  Configuring the OpenStack Metering service is sufficient for Helion administrators. No additional work is required.</p>
</section>
<section id="managing-the-database"> <title>Managing the Database</title>
<p>The Database service provides scalable and reliable cloud provisioning functionality for both relational and non-relational database engines. Helion supports the OpenStack</p>
<p>
  <xref href="#topic5798"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
<!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
</section>
</body>
</topic>
