<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic7556">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> 1.1: Identity Service (Keystone) Overview</title>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Storage Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Storage Architect"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Michael B, Meera B,"/>
<othermeta name="product-version1" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
    <p><!--PUBLISHED--><!--./commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-overview.md--><!--permalink: /helion/openstack/1.1/services/identity/overview/--></p>
    <p> </p>
    <!-- modeled after HPE Cloud Networking Getting Started (network.getting.started.md) -->
    <p>Based on Openstack Keystone, the HPE Helion Openstack Identity service provides one-stop
      authentication using the Keystone V2 or V3 API.</p>
    <p>The Identity service enables you to create and configure users, specify user roles and
      credentials, and issue security tokens.</p>
    <p>The Identity service validates that incoming requests are being made by the user who claims
      to be making the call.</p>
    <p>Users have a login and may be assigned tokens to access resources. Users can scope their
      authentication to a project (or, tenant) which then limits where and how their tokens can be
      used to interact with services. User roles, which are sets of rights and privileges, can be
      assigned to control access to projects.</p>
    <note>Users can have different roles per project. Actual user role functionality is defined by
      each separate OpenStack service outside of the Identity service. Refer to the policy.json file
      for each service in the <codeph>/etc/&lt;SERVICENAME&gt;/policy.json</codeph> file.</note>
    <p>The Identity service confirms that incoming request are being made by the user who claims to
      be making the call by validating a set of claims that the user is making. These claims are
      initially in the form of a set of credentials (username and password, or user access keys).
      After initial confirmation, the Identity service will issue a token that the user can provide
      to demonstrate that their identity has been authenticated when making subsequent requests.</p>
    <p>
      <b>User Authentication</b> - The Identity service can be configured during initial
      installation to use either a local, user authentication system (users and passwords are all
      created and managed by Keystone) or via an external user management system like LDAP or
      Microsoft Active Directory. It is recommended that an external user management system be used
      for production deployments. The local user management system is intended to support only
      limited trials and proof of concept deployments and does not offer the advanced user
      management functions often required for production deployments.</p>
    <p>
      <b>User Management</b> - The HPE Helion OpenStack Identity Service tracks users and their
      permissions. The main components of user management include:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Users</li>
      <li>Projects</li>
      <li>Roles</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      <b>Service management</b> - The HPE Helion OpenStack Identity Service provides a catalog of
      available services with their API endpoints.</p>
    <p>
      <b>Group management</b> - The HPE Helion OpenStack Identity Service allows administrators to
      create groups and add users to groups. Then, rather than assign a role to each user
      individually, the admin can assign a role to the group. Every group is in a <xref
        type="section" href="#topic7556/domain">domain</xref>.</p>
    <p>
      <b>
        <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-domains.xml">Domain
          management</xref>
      </b> - The HPE Helion OpenStack Identity Service allows administrators to create tenants,
      users, and groups within a <xref type="section" href="#topic7556/domain">domain</xref> and
      assign roles to users and groups.</p>
    <p>Administrators can create multiple <xref type="section" href="#topic7556/domain"
        >domains</xref>, which allow for the isolation of projects and users. The admin can assign
      users, groups, and projects right to a specific domain, but restrict rights in other domains.
      Domain admins manage resources in their own domains.</p>
    <section id="key-components">
      <title>Key Components</title>
      <p>The Identity service primarily works on the following key concepts:</p>
    </section>
    <section id="domain">
      <title>Domain</title>
      <p>A domain is a high-level container for <xref type="section" href="#topic7556/project"
          >projects</xref>, <xref type="section" href="#topic7556/user">users</xref> and <xref
          type="section" href="#topic7556/group">groups</xref>.</p>
      <p>For detailed information, Getting Started, and API references, see <xref
          href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-domains.xml">Domain
          Management</xref>.</p>
      <note>Regardless of the backend used (LDAP or MySQL), <xref
          href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-domains.xml">domain
          management</xref> is not available using the Horizon dashboard. This initial
        implementation is targeted at sysadmins and developers interested in creating and deploying
        Domains for initial proof of concept deployments.</note>
    </section>
    <section id="admins">
      <title>Administrators</title>
      <p>The HPE Helion OpenStack Identity service features three types of administrator users:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Cloud Admins are super admins. This role needs a domain-scope token.</li>
        <li>Domain admins manage users, user groups, and projects in their own domain. This role
          needs a domain-scope token</li>
        <li>Project admin can assign roles to users in their project. Requires a project token.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="project">
      <title>Project</title>
      <p>A project is a collection of users, groups, and/or resources (such as Compute or Object
        Storage). Also known as a <codeph>tenant</codeph>. Each project name must be unique in an
        associated domain.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="user">
      <title>Users</title>
      <p>A user is a person, system, or service who requests access to HPE Helion OpenStack Users are
        associated with projects and are assigned roles a project.</p>
      <p>The Identity authentication service validates incoming requests made by users using the
        login information provided by the user either through a local Keystone login or an external
        authentication system. Users are provided tokens to access resources through a service
        catalog. Each user name must be unique in the associated domain.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="group">
      <title>Group</title>
      <p>A group is a collection of <xref type="section" href="#topic7556/user">users</xref> that is
        associated with one or more <xref type="section" href="#topic7556/project">projects</xref>
        or <xref type="section" href="#topic7556/domain">domains</xref>. Each group name must be
        unique in the associated domain.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="role">
      <title>Role</title>
      <p>A role defines set of rights and privileges that can be assigned to a user at the domain or
        project level. A user assuming that role inherits those rights and privileges. A role is
        also called a <i>personality</i>. Each user name must be unique across all of your
        domains.</p>
      <p>Roles are created and assigned by the Identity service to either specific UserIDs or
        Groups. The function of the role itself is defined by each separate OpenStack service. More
        information on Roles can be found in the <xref
          href="http://docs.openstack.org/admin-guide-cloud/content/keystone-user-management.html"
          scope="external" format="html">User management section</xref> of the OpenStack Cloud
        Administrator Guide.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="policy">
      <title>Policies</title>
      <p>A policy is a centralized repository for policy engine rule sets.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="creds">
      <title>Credentials</title>
      <p>Credentials are data that belongs to, are owned by, and are generally only known to a user.
        This data is used by the user to prove his/her identity. For example:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Username and password</li>
        <li>An authentication token provided by the Identity Service</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="auth">
      <title>Authentication</title>
      <p>Authentication is the act of confirming the identity of a user. The Identity service
        confirms that the incoming request is being made by the user by validating a set of claims
        that the user is making.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="token">
      <title>Token</title>
      <p>A token is a random string that is used to access resources. Each token has a scope that
        describes which resources are accessible with it.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="service">
      <title>Service</title>
      <p>An OpenStack service, such as Compute (Nova), Object Storage (Swift), or Image Service
        (Glance). Provides one or more endpoints through which users can access resources and
        perform operations.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="endpoint">
      <title>Endpoint</title>
      <p>A network-accessible address, usually described by a URL, where a service may be
        accessed.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="next">
      <title>Next Steps</title>
    </section>
    <section id="working-with-domain-management">
      <title>Working with Domain Management</title>
      <p>For detailed information, Getting Started, and API references, see <xref
          href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-domains.xml">Domain
          Management</xref>.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="configure-horizon-for-keystone-v3">
      <title>Configure Horizon for Keystone V3</title>
      <p>To enable Keystone v3 in the Horizon dashboard, manually change the settings. See <xref
          href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-configure-v3.xml">Configuring
          Horizon for Keystone v3</xref> for instructions and important restrictions.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="integrate-the-identity-service-keystone-with-ldapad">
      <title>Integrate the Identity Service (Keystone) with LDAP/AD</title>
      <p>You can optionally <xref
          href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-integrate-ldap.xml">integrate
          the Identity service with with an existing LDAP directory</xref> for authentication and
        authorization services.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="working-with-the-identity-service">
      <title>Working with the Identity Service</title>
      <p>To <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-using.xml">perform
          tasks using the Identity service</xref>, you can use the <xref
          href="http://api.openstack.org/api-ref-identity-v3.html" scope="external" format="html"
          >API</xref> or <xref
          href="http://docs.openstack.org/cli-reference/content/keystoneclient_commands.html"
          scope="external" format="html">CLI</xref>.</p>
      <p>
        <xref href="#topic7556"> Return to Top </xref>
      </p>
      <!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
