<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd"><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic8293">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> 1.1: Services Overview</title>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Systems Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Cloud Architect"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Storage Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Network Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Service Developer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Cloud Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Application Developer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Network Engineer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Paul F"/>
<othermeta name="product-version1" content="HPE Helion Openstack"/>
<othermeta name="product-version2" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-overview.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/openstack/1.1/services/overview/--></p>
<p>

</p>
<p>OpenStack is comprised of several integrated services. Each service works through an API (application programming interface) that allows services to work together and allows users to interact with the services.</p>
<p>HPE Helion OpenStack includes a number of additional services to work with your cloud.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic8293/service">Service User Accounts</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic8293/OpenStack">OpenStack Services</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic8293/hp">HPE Services</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic8293/install">Installation services</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic8293/Other">Other Services</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic8293/info">More information</xref>
</li>
</ul>
<p>In addition to the APIs, you can interact with the most services through a graphic user interface (dashboard or console) or a command line interface (CLI).</p>
<section id="service"> <title>Service User Accounts</title>
<p>The HPE Helion OpenStack installation process creates a <b>service</b> <b>user</b> account for each installed service. Service user accounts require elevated privileges to validate end user tokens. It is therefore strongly recommended that you do <b>
<i>not</i>
</b> add these service user accounts to any project because this could allow project users to access services they should not have permission to access.</p>
<p>The service user accounts include, but are not limited to, the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Object Storage (Swift)</li>
<li>Nova</li>
<li>Neutron</li>
<li>Sherpa</li>
<li>Glance</li>
<li>Cinder</li>
<li>Heat</li>
<li>Keystone</li>
<li>Ceilometer</li>
<li>Ceph</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="OpenStack"> <title>OpenStack Services</title>
<p>The following services are foundation technologies used by the HPE Helion OpenStack Based on OpenStack technology, HPE Helion OpenStack comprises of a set of services and architecture that defines a data-center-level operating system (DCOS).</p>
<p>For information on enabling and maintaining each of these OpenStack services, see <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.network-administrator-notes.xml">Network Administrator Notes</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Compute Operations</b>. The Compute service manages the hypervisors and virtual machines in your environment. Also known as <b>Nova</b>.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-compute-overview.xml">Overview of the Compute service</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Identity</b>. The Identity Management service enables you to create and administer users and security groups, and control access to your cloud environment. Also known as <b>Keystone</b>.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-overview.xml">Overview of the Identity Management service</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Image Operations</b>. The Image Operations service enables you to create and maintain server images, which you can use to launch virtual machines across the cloud. Also known as <b>Glance</b>.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-imaging-overview.xml">Overview of the Image service</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Networking Operations</b>. The Networking service enables you to create and manage virtual networks. Also known as <b>Neutron</b>.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-networking-overview.xml">Overview of the Networking service</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Object Operations</b>. The Object Operations service enables you to store and retrieve data. Object Storage is a distributed storage system for static data such as virtual machine images, photo storage, email storage, backups and archives. Also known as <b>Swift</b>.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-object-overview.xml">Overview of the Object Operations service</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Orchestration</b>. The Orchestration service provides a template-based orchestration for describing a cloud application. A Heat template is a <xref href="http://www.yaml.org/"   format="html">YAML</xref> file that describes the infrastructure for a cloud application. Templates contain vendor-independent specifications for launching a particular service or application.  Also known as <b>Heat</b>.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-orchestration-overview.xml">Overview of the Orchestration service</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Volume Operations</b>. The Volume Operations service enables you to attach storage volumes to the virtual instances in your cloud environment. The service provides persistent block level storage devices for use with your Compute instances. Also known as <b>Cinder</b>.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-volume-overview.xml">Overview of the Volume Operations Service</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Metering</b>. The Metering service enables a single infrastructure to collect measurements throughout your cloud environment. Also known as <b>Ceilometer</b>.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-reporting-overview.xml">Overview of the Metering Service</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Ceph</b>. Ceph is an Open Source, scalable, software defined storage running on HPE Servers which provides block and object storage with unified management.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/ceph/1.1commercial.ceph-overview.xml">Overview of the Ceph Service</xref>
</p>
<!-- Not in Commerical
**Loom**. The Loom service facilitates the comprehension and manipulation of complex systems using the Unity dashboard.

See [Overview of the Loom Service](/helion/openstack/1.1/services/loom/overview/).
-->
</section>
<section id="hp"> <title>HPE Services</title>
<p>The following services have been developed by HPE for use with the HPE Helion OpenStack</p>
<p>
<b>Sirius</b>. HPE Helion OpenStack Sirius service assists the Cloud Administrator in the configuration of storage services (like Cinder and Swift) which run in the Overcloud on various storage devices.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-sirius-overview.xml">Overview of Sirius Service</xref>
</p>
<p>
<b>EON</b>. ESX on border (EON) service is an inventory which interacts with the VMware vCenter server and collects the information available at the datacenters and clusters. These information is used for deployment and configuration of ESX Proxy Compute node. EON service is deployed in undercloud controller node.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-eon-overview.xml">Overview of EON Service</xref>
</p>
<p>
<b>Sherpa</b>. The Sherpa service provides a link to the remote web catalog. The catalog provides a repository of software that can be purchased and downloaded into the Cloud OS environment.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-sherpa-overview.xml">Overview of Sherpa Service</xref>.</p>
</section>
<section id="dash"> <title>Dashboard services</title>
<p>HPE Helion OpenStack uses the following services or software to present user interfaces to aspects of HPE Helion OpenStack</p>
<p>
<b>Horizon</b> The Horizon service is the basis of the <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.dashboard.how-works.xml">HPE Helion OpenStack dashboards</xref> for creating and managing HPE Helion OpenStack resources. The Horizon dashboard is developed by HPE for use with HPE Helion OpenStack</p>
<p>You can use the HPE Helion OpenStack dashboard to view, allocate, and manage all virtual resources within a cloud. 
See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-horizon-overview.xml">Overview of the Horizon Service</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Icinga</b> The Icinga service, which runs in the undercloud, helps cloud admins monitor the disk usage of Swift storage node(s). Icinga is an open-source software project.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.services-icinga.xml">Overview of the Icinga Service</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Kibana</b>. The Kibana service, which runs in the undercloud, is the user interface into the <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-logging-overview.xml">centralized logging service</xref> that helps view logging data across the HPE Helion OpenStack cloud. Kibana is an open-source software project.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.services-kibana.xml">Overview of the Icinga Service</xref>.</p>
</section>
<section id="install"> <title>Installation services</title>
<p>The following services are used only during the HPE Helion OpenStack installation:</p>
<p>
<b>TripleO</b>. TripleO (which stands for OpenStack-on-OpenStack is a program designed to facilitate the installation of an OpenStack cloud. The HPE Helion OpenStack installation process uses TripleO.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-tripleo-overview.xml">Overview of the TripleO Service</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Ironic</b>. The Ironic service runs during the installation for provisioning of the controller and KVM compute host in a baremetal deployment.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-ironic-overview.xml">Overview of the Ironic Service</xref>.</p>
</section>
<section id="Other"> <title>Other services and features</title>
<p>The following services and features can be used with HPE Helion OpenStack</p>
<p>
<b>Centralized Logging</b>. The HPE Helion OpenStack Centralized Logging uses a number of services and systems to collect logs throughout the cloud into a central system. The administrator can use a single graphic interface to view log information in charts, graphs, tables, histograms, and other forms.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-logging-overview.xml">Centralized Logging Overview</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>DNSaaS</b>. The HPE Helion OpenStack DNSaaS (Domain Name System as a Service) provides a way to display, create, modify, and delete DNS records on the assigned DNS server network.</p>
<p>See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.install-GA-DNSaaS.xml">Overview of the DNS as a Service</xref>.</p>
</section>
<section id="info"> <title>For more information</title>
<p>For information on how to operate your cloud we suggest you read the <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/ops/"   format="html">OpenStack Operations Guide</xref>. The <b>Architecture</b> section contains useful information about how an OpenStack Cloud is put together. However, HPE Helion OpenStack takes care of these details for you. The <b>Operations</b> section contains information on how to manage the system.</p>
<p>For more information on installing the command-line interface for interacting with services, see <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide/content/install_clients.html"   format="html">installing the OpenStack command-line clients</xref>.</p>
<p>
  <xref href="#topic8293"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
<!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
</section>
</body>
</topic>
