<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic2976">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> 1.1: Troubleshooting OVSvApp Installation and Operation</title>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Systems Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Cloud Architect"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Storage Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Network Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Service Developer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Cloud Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Application Developer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Network Engineer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Paul F"/>
<othermeta name="product-version1" content="HPE Helion Openstack"/>
<othermeta name="product-version2" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.troubleshooting.ovsvapp.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/openstack/1.1/services/troubleshooting/ovsvapp/--></p>
<p>
<xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.troubleshooting.dita" > ▲ Troubleshooting</xref> | <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.install-GA-ovsvapp.dita" > ▲ Deploying and Configuring OVSvApp on ESX hosts</xref> </p>
<p>If you are having issues with the installation or operation of the OVSvApp, review these tips:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Install prerequisite <xref href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/pyvmomi" scope="external" format="html" >python library pyvmomi</xref>. You can install the library using the following command:</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>pip install --upgrade pyvmomi
</codeph>
</codeblock>

<p>Even if pyvmomi is already installed, run the command again to update the library to get major fixes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>During installation of OVSvApp VMs on a large scale, OVSvApp VM can hang and installation might not proceed. If this happens, execute the <codeph>neutron agent list</codeph> command. If the output shows a OVSvApp VM in the <codeph>xxx</codeph> agent state, rerun the installation for that specific failed OVSvApp VM by specifying the ESX host name in the <codeph>new_hosts</codeph> field under the <codeph>new-host-addition</codeph> section of the <codeph>ovs_vapp.ini</codeph> file.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In a multiple vCenter environment, during tenant VMs spawn, if a VM fails to spawn on one vCenter server and successfully spawns on another vCenter server, check for stale portgroups, which causes stale OVS Flows. If an OVSvApp agent needs to be restarted, the OVS flows might be slow to be restored. If that happens, restart the agent to stabilize the flows.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If DRS and HA are enabled on the cluster, VMs except OVSvApp VM will migrate to other ESX hosts.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If the <codeph>neutron agent list</codeph> command shows a specific OVSvApp agent up and running, but you see an ESX host in maintenance mode, you can disable agent monitoring for the OVSvApp solution. To disable agent monitoring, add a flag <codeph>enable_agent_monitor</codeph> set to <codeph>false</codeph> as <codeph>enable_agent_monitor = false</codeph> to the <codeph>/etc/neuton/neutron.conf</codeph> file. Restart the server to activate the value.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Do not delete a tenant VM port via "neutron port-delete" command for a tenant VM.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>For any Operating System related issues:
<xref href="http://hlinux-home.usa.hp.com/bugzilla/" scope="external" format="html" >hLinux Bugzilla</xref>
</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In a scalable environment, portgroups might not get deleted when the <codeph>nova delete</codeph> command is run.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The VM port binding is with the host name of the OVSvApp VM on the ESX Compute host which provisioned the tenant VM.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When vCenter username &lt;"vCenter_username"&gt; has domain included, provide username details in username@domain format.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When <codeph>cert_check</codeph> is <b>False</b>, <codeph>cert_path</codeph> should be a blank field.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>For Helion ESX type install, do not attempt to revert the Overcloud nodes from 1.01 to 1.0 through the restore process. Restoring will power down the ESX hosts associated with the registered vCenter cluster. <!-- ALM 11335 --></p>
</li>
</ul>
<section id="sos"> <title>Contacting Customer Service</title>
<p>If you need further assistance, contact <xref href="http://www.hpcloud.com/about/contact" scope="external" format="html" >HPE Customer Support</xref>.</p>
<p>Before contacting HPE Customer Support, <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.troubleshooting.dita#sos" type="section">run the <codeph>run-sosreport</codeph> command</xref> on the affected system.</p>
<p>
  <xref href="#topic2976"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
</section>
</body>
</topic>
