<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic6925">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> 1.1: Flexible Control Plane Overview</title>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Systems Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Cloud Architect"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Storage Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Network Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Service Developer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Cloud Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Application Developer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Network Engineer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Geraldine K,"/>
<othermeta name="product-version1" content="HPE Helion Openstack"/>
<othermeta name="product-version2" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.flexible-control-pane-overview.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/openstack/1.1/flexiblecontrol/overview/--></p>
<p>

</p>
<p>The HPE Helion OpenStack Flexible Control Plane (FCP) architectural configuration enables you to deploy the control plane in a virtual environment. This new configuration reduces the control plane footprint to just three servers from the current seven servers.</p>
<p>This topic covers:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic6925/deploy">Deployment Architecture</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic6925/details">Environment Details</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic6925/prereq">Pre-requisites</xref>

<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic6925/kvmsetup">KVM Host Setup</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic6925/variables">Configurable Variables</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic6925/configfiles">Configuration Files</xref>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Due to length, the <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.flexible-control-pane-installation.xml" >step-by-step installation instructions</xref> are available separately.</p>
<section id="overview"> <title>Overview</title>
<p>The FCP addresses the issue of the relative size of the control plane being too large for smaller clouds. 
The FCP is supported for the following use cases:</p>
<ul>
<li>Evaluation</li>
<li>Demonstration</li>
<li>Proof of concept</li>
</ul>
<p>Current Known Limitations:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>As of HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1.1, FCP is in an experimental phase and we do not recommend you use FCP in your production environment. We recommend that you test FCP in your test environment, for small-scale clouds of up to eight compute nodes.</p>

<p>For additional information about FCP, contact the HPE Helion Support Center.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Virtual Storage Appliance Adaptive Optimization (VSA-AO) is not supported.</p>
</li>
<li>For an FCP system, upgrade from HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1 has not been tested.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="deploy"> <title>Deployment Architecture</title>
<p>Only one deployment architecture is possible, using three KVM hosts.
Figure 1 illustrates the deployment of overcloud compute nodes and VSA nodes to physical servers. In the diagram, the seed VM, undercloud controller node, overcloud controller nodes, and Swift nodes are in the virtualized environment. The StoreVirtual node and overcloud compute nodes remain baremetal servers.</p>
<p>
<image href="../../media/flexiblecontrolpane1.png" placement="break"/>
<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.-->
Figure 1</p>
<p>In the deployment scenario in Figure 2, the cloud control plane is distributed across three KVM hosts with the deployment of VSA storage nodes and overcloud Nova compute nodes on physical servers.</p>
<p>
<image href="../../media/FCP_Figure2_HOS1.1.png" placement="break"/>
<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.-->
Figure 2</p>
</section>
<section id="details"> <title>Environment Details</title>
<p>The above environment contains the following networks:</p>
<ul>
<li>Management Network</li>
<li>IPMI</li>
<li>Service</li>
<li>External</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="management-network"> <title>Management Network</title>
<p>This network is used for most cloud traffic including: PXE boot nodes, tenant access to service APIs, internal API traffic between services (one service to another), HA heartbeats, tenant access to services, VxLAN traffic for between tenant VMs, VM access to block and object storage, object storage replication and synchronization between StoreVirtual VSAs, Object Operations service nodes, MySQL clusters, RabbitMQ clusters, keepalived, <xref href="https://helion.hpwsportal.com" scope="external" format="html" >HDN</xref> access to the product catalog, monitoring checks to Icinga.</p>
<p>In this example, the Management Network CIDR is 192.168.124.0/24.</p>
</section>
<section id="ipmi-intelligent-platform-management-interface"> <title>IPMI (Intelligent Platform Management Interface)</title>
<p>This is the network for server hardware management. 
In this example the CIDR (Classless Inter-Domain Routing) address of the IPMI network is 192.168.1.0/24.</p>
</section>
<section id="service"> <title>Service</title>
<p>Connects trusted VMs in the overcloud to communicate with the cloud infrastructure component using this network. In this example, the Service Network CIDR is 192.168.125.0/24.</p>
</section>
<section id="external"> <title>External</title>
<p>This network is connected to the Internet or intranet and provides floating IPs. In this example the External Network CIDR is 172.32.100.0/24.</p>
</section>
<section id="hardware"> <title>Hardware Details</title>
</section>
<section id="kvmsetup"> <title>KVM Host</title>
<p>The minimum recommended configurations are as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li>RAM: 96GB</li>
<li>CPU Cores: 12</li>
<li>HDD: 2TB</li>
</ul>
<p>For nodes other than KVM Hosts, refer to the <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.install-GA-supportmatrix.xml" >Support Matrix</xref> documentation.</p>
</section>
<section id="prereq"> <title>Prerequisites</title>
<p>The FCP configuration has the same prerequisites as HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1. Please be sure the environment satisfies the prerequisites before beginning installation.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.install-GA-prereqs.xml" >Installation Prerequisites</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.technical-overview.ga.xml" >Network Topology Requirements</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.install-GA-supportmatrix.xml" >Hardware/Software Requirements</xref>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="options"> <title>Configurable Options for Flexible Control Plane</title>
<p>The following section describes the environment variables involved in configuring the FCP, which you set during the installation process outlined in the <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.flexible-control-pane-installation.xml" >installation instructions</xref>.</p>
</section>
<section id="variables"> <title>Configurable Variables</title>
<p>Below are descriptions of configuration variables that are specifically applicable to configuring the FCP, which you will set during the installation step-by-step process.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>
<b>HP_VM_MODE</b>
</p>

<p>Set this variable to specify the mode of deployment as single or hybrid. Currently, the options supported are: "y" and "hybrid". To enable FCP, set the value to "hybrid".</p>

<p>export HP_VM_MODE=hybrid</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>
<b>OVERCLOUD_HYPERVISOR_PUBLIC_INTERFACE</b>
</p>

<p>Set this to the value of the name of the interface that carries the neutron external traffic on your overcloud compute nodes.
The default value is eth2. If this is correct you do not need to set this variable. For example:</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>export OVERCLOUD_HYPERVISOR_PUBLIC_INTERFACE=eth1
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Refer to <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.install-GA-JSON.xml" >Editing the Installation Configuration JSON File</xref> for a full list of the environmental variables that control your installation.</p>
                        <note>For FCP, the following defaults apply to the variables below (tuned to
                                the FCP environment):</note>
<codeblock>
  <codeph>undercloud.neutron_public_interface eth0
overcloud.virtual_interface eth0
overcloud.hypervisor_public_interface eth2
overcloud.neutron_public_interface eth0
overcloud.neutron_public_interface_raw_device ''
&lt;validate these names against the 'envars' section&gt; 
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</section>
<section id="configfiles"> <title>Configuration Files</title>
</section>
<section id="create-a-vm-plan-file-create-vm-plan-file"> <title>Create a VM-plan file {#Create vm-plan file}</title>
<p>Create a VM-plan file (vm-plan) to represent the distribution of virtual machines over
   their hosts. This is an example vm-plan file and its format mirrors that of
   the baremetal.csv file:</p>
<codeblock>
  <codeph>,user,,192.168.11.112,2,32768,,Undercloud,
,user,,192.168.11.112,2,32768,,OvercloudControl,
,user,,192.168.11.113,2,32768,,OvercloudControl,
eth2,user,,192.168.11.114,2,32768,,OvercloudControl,
,user,,192.168.11.113,2,32768,,OvercloudSwift,
eth2,user,,192.168.11.114,2,32768,,OvercloudSwift,
</codeph>
</codeblock>
<p>Field 1 is the BRIDGE_INTERFACE nic on the remote host.</p>
<p>(If empty, this will default to the same value of BRIDGE_INTERFACE as
            used on the seed host)
            For example: "eth7".</p>
<p>Field 2 is the KVM user under which the VM will run.
        (This user does not have to be root.)</p>
<p>Field 3 is ignored.</p>
<p>Field 4 is the IP address of the remote KVM host.
        (If empty, this will be the local host do not use 'localhost'.)</p>
<p>Field 5 is the number of CPUs to give the virtual machine.
        (You must specify this value.)</p>
<p>Field 6 is the amount of memory in GiB the virtual machine will have.
        (You must specify this value.)</p>
<p>Field 7 is ignored.</p>
<p>Field 8 is the role the virtual machine will have.
        (You must specify this value.)</p>
                        <note>Physical baremetal nodes are added later; do NOT add them to this
                                file.</note>
<!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
<p>Continue to <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.flexible-control-pane-installation.xml" >step-by-step installation instructions and known issues</xref>.</p>
</section>
</body>
</topic>
