<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic5601">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> 1.1: Using the Identity Service (Keystone)</title>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Systems Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Cloud Architect"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Storage Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Network Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Service Developer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Cloud Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Application Developer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Network Engineer"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Paul F"/>
<othermeta name="product-version1" content="HPE Helion Openstack"/>
<othermeta name="product-version2" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-using.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/openstack/1.1/services/identity/using/--></p>
<p>Based on OpenStack Keystone, the HPE Helion OpenStack Identity service provides one-stop authentication.</p>
<p>The following lists of tasks can be performed by a user or administrator through the <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.dashboard.how-works.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack Dashboard</xref>, the <xref href="http://api.openstack.org/api-ref-identity-v3.html" scope="external" format="html" >API</xref> or <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/cli-reference/content/keystoneclient_commands.html" scope="external" format="html" >CLI</xref>.</p>
<section id="UI"> <title>Using the dashboards</title>
<p>You can use the <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.dashboard.how-works.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack Dashboard</xref> to work with the Identity service.</p>
      <note>
        <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-domains.xml">Domain
          management</xref> is not available using the HPE Helion OpenStack Dashboard. This initial
        implementation is targeted at sysadmins and developers interested in creating and deploying
        Domains for initial proof of concept deployments.</note>
<p>To use Keystone v3 in Horizon, manually change the settings. See <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-configure-v3.xml" >Configuring Horizon for Keystone v3</xref> for instructions and important restrictions.</p>
<p>Depending upon your user type, <xref type="section" href="#topic5601/user">user</xref> or <xref type="section" href="#topic5601/admin">administrator</xref>, you can perform the following tasks.</p>
</section>
<section id="user"> <title>Tasks performed by users</title>
<p>The following Identity service tasks are usually performed by someone with the <i>user</i> role.</p>
</section>
<section id="listing-domains"> <title>Listing Domains</title>
<ul>
<li>View information on all your domains, including names, enabled status, ID, and policy links.</li>
<li>View information on a specified domain, including the description, enabled status, ID, and policy links.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="listing-projects"> <title>Listing Projects</title>
<p>Use the Identity service to view a list of projects in your cloud environment.</p>
</section>
<section id="userprojects"> <title>Working with projects</title>
<p>All project-level tasks must be performed by an administrator.</p>
</section>
<section id="admin"> <title>Tasks performed by an Administrator<!--Removed anchor point admin--><!-- id="admin" --></title>
<p>The following Identity service tasks are usually performed by someone with the <i>administrator</i> role.</p>
</section>
<section id="admindomains"> <title>Working with domains</title>
<p>Use the Identity service to configure user access to your cloud domains. For detailed information, see <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1commerical.services-identity-domains.xml" >Domain Management</xref>.</p>
<ul>
<li>Add a domain to your cloud.</li>
<li>Update information for a specified domain, including the description, enabled status, ID, and policy links. </li>
<li>Delete a domain.</li>
<li>List the domain roles for a specified user.</li>
<li>List domain roles for a specified domain group.</li>
<li>Grant a specified role to a domain group.</li>
<li>Validate that a group has a specified role on a domain.</li>
<li>Revoke a role from a group on a domain.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adminprojects"> <title>Working with projects</title>
<ul>
<li>Add a project to a domain.</li>
<li>View information on all your projects, including names, enabled status, and ID.</li>
<li>View information on a specified project, including the name, enabled status, and ID.</li>
<li>Update a specified project, including the description, enabled status, ID, and policy links. </li>
<li>Delete a project.</li>
<li>List the project roles for a specified user or group.</li>
<li>Grant a specified role to a project user or group.</li>
<li>Validate that a project user or group has a specified role.</li>
<li>Revoke a role from a project user or group.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adminusers"> <title>Working with users</title>
<ul>
<li>Add a user to a project.</li>
<li>View information on all your users, including names and enabled status.</li>
<li>View information on a specified user, including the name and enabled status.</li>
<li>Update a specified user, including the description, enabled status, ID, and policy links. </li>
<li>Delete a user.</li>
<li>List the project, group, and roles associated with a specified user.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adminusers1"> <title>Working with groups</title>
<ul>
<li>Add a group to a domain.</li>
<li>View information on the groups associated with a domain, including names, descriptions, and policy links.</li>
<li>View information on a specific group, including the name, description, and policy links.</li>
<li>Update a specified group, including the description, enabled status, ID, and policy links. </li>
<li>Delete a group.</li>
<li>List the users in a group, including the name, description, and enabled status.</li>
<li>Add and remove users from a group.</li>
<li>Validate that a user is in a specific group.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="admincreds"> <title>Working with credentials</title>
<p>Use the Identity service to create and manage credentials for user per tenant.</p>
<ul>
<li>Add a credential to a domain.</li>
<li>View information on the credentials associated with a domain, including IDs, policy links, associated projects, type, and associated users.</li>
<li>View information on a specific credential.</li>
<li>Update a specified credential, including the description, enabled status, ID, and policy links. </li>
<li>Delete a credential.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adminroles"> <title>Working with roles</title>
<p>Use the Identity service to configure user roles within your cloud environment.</p>
<ul>
<li>Add a role to a domain.</li>
<li>View information on the roles associated with a domain, including names, IDs, and policy links.</li>
<li>Assign a role to a domain user.</li>
<li>Validate that a user has a specific role.</li>
<li>Revoke a role from a user.</li>
<li>List role assignments for a group or user.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="adminpolicy"> <title>Manage Policies</title>
<p>Use the Identity service to configure policies.</p>
<ul>
<li>Add a role to a project.</li>
<li>View information on the policies associated with a domain, including names, IDs, and the user that owns the policy.</li>
<li>Update a specified policy, including names, IDs, and the user that owns the policy. </li>
<li>Delete a policy.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="manage-endpoints"> <title>Manage Endpoints</title>
<p>Create and delete endpoints associated with a service.</p>
</section>
<section id="manage-endpoint-filtering"> <title>Manage Endpoint Filtering</title>
<p>Find endpoint filtered by a specific attribute or service type.</p>
</section>
<section id="issue-token"> <title>Issue Token</title>
<p>Issue a new UUID or PKI token for a user.</p>
</section>
<section id="signature-validation"> <title>Signature Validation</title>
<p>Manage S3 signature validation.</p>
</section>
<section id="manage-federated-access"> <title>Manage Federated Access</title>
<p>Configure federated access for use in HPE Helion OpenStack</p>
</section>
<section id="resetting-a-user-password"> <title>Resetting a user password</title>
<p>Use the Identity service to reset a password for a user.</p>
</section>
<section id="for-more-information"> <title>For more information</title>
<p>For information on how to operate your cloud we suggest you read the <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/ops/" scope="external" format="html" >OpenStack Operations Guide</xref>. <!-- The *Architecture* section contains useful information about how an OpenStack Cloud is put together. However, the HPE Helion OpenStack takes care of these details for you. The *Operations* section contains information on how to manage the system.--></p>
<p>
  <xref href="#topic5601"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
<!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
</section>
</body>
</topic>
