<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic2805">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> 1.1 and 1.1.1: AppArmor Overview</title>
<titlealts>
<searchtitle>HPE Helion Openstack 1.1: AppArmor Overview</searchtitle>
</titlealts>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
<othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Storage Administrator"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Storage Architect"/>
<othermeta name="role" content="Michael B,"/>
<othermeta name="product-version1" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.install-GA-apparmor.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/openstack/1.1/install/apparmor/--></p>
<p>
  <b>This document describes the installation process for HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1 and HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1.1.</b>
</p>
<p>(If you already have 1.1 installed, you can update Helion OpenStack from 1.1 to 1.1.1 by following the update procedures described in <xref href="../../commercial/GA1/1.1.1commercial.helion-update.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack 1.1.1 Update Guide</xref>.)</p>
<p>The HPE Helion OpenStack default installation includes AppArmor profiles as a tool for enhanced security for VMs running on KVM compute nodes.</p>
<p>AppArmor profiles can modified, as needed, for your organization. However, the default profiles, as installed, have been configured to provide optimal protection for HPE Helion OpenStack All profiles are configured for <i>enforce</i> mode (for more information, see <xref type="section" href="#topic2805/modes">AppArmor profile modes</xref> below) and designed to mitigate hostile VMs exploiting hypervisor breakout attacks.</p>
<p>HPE Helion OpenStack follows the <xref href="http://wiki.apparmor.net/index.php/Libvirt"   format="html" >svirt model</xref> to provide guest isolation. Every guest VM is locked down to be able to access only its own configuration files, disk files and volume devices.</p>
<p>You should not need to interact with these profiles. Modification instructions are beyond the scope of this document.</p>
<p>For more information on AppArmor and managing profiles, review the information in the <xref href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/AppArmor"   format="html" >Ubuntu AppArmor Documentation</xref> and the other links <xref type="section" href="#topic2805/info">below</xref>.</p>
<section id="about-apparmor"> <title>About AppArmor</title>
<p>AppArmor is an effective and easy-to-use Linux application security system. AppArmor proactively protects the operating system and applications from external or internal threats, even zero-day attacks, by enforcing expected behavior and reducing the risk of even unknown application flaws being exploited. AppArmor security policies completely define what system resources individual applications can access, and with what privileges.</p>
<p>AppArmor confinement is provided through profiles loaded into the kernel, typically on boot.</p>
</section>
<section id="modes"> <title>AppArmor profile modes</title>
<p>AppArmor profiles can be in one of two modes: enforcement and notify. Profiles loaded in enforcement mode will result in enforcement of the policy defined in the profile as well as reporting policy violation attempts (either through syslog or auditd). Profiles in complain mode will not enforce policy but instead report policy violation attempts.</p>
<!-- info taken variously from the links below -->
</section>
<section id="info"> <title>For more information</title>
<ul>
<li>
<xref href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/AppArmor"   format="html" >Ubuntu AppArmor overview</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/AppArmor"   format="html" >Ubuntu AppArmor Documentation</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref href="http://wiki.apparmor.net/index.php/Main_Page"   format="html" >AppArmor Upstream Wiki</xref>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
  <xref href="#topic2805"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
<!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
</section>
</body>
</topic>
