<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" >
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic8573">
  <title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> 1.1: How to build Microsoft Windows Server guest
    images for HPE Helion OpenStack</title>
  <prolog>
    <metadata>
      <othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
      <othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack"/>
      <othermeta name="product-version" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
      <othermeta name="role" content="Systems Administrator"/>
      <othermeta name="role" content="Cloud Architect"/>
      <othermeta name="role" content="Storage Administrator"/>
      <othermeta name="role" content="Network Administrator"/>
      <othermeta name="role" content="Service Developer"/>
      <othermeta name="role" content="Cloud Administrator"/>
      <othermeta name="role" content="Application Developer"/>
      <othermeta name="role" content="Network Engineer"/>
      <othermeta name="role" content="Lou G"/>
      <othermeta name="product-version1" content="HPE Helion Openstack"/>
      <othermeta name="product-version2" content="HPE Helion Openstack 1.1"/>
    </metadata>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>
      <!--PUBLISHED-->
      <!--./commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.create-deploy-certified-microsoft-windows-guest-image.md-->
      <!--permalink: /helion/openstack/1.1/create-deploy/certified-microsoft-windows/guest-image/--></p>
    <p>This document describes how to create and deploy the following Microsoft Windows Server guest
      images on HPE Helion OpenStack<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--><xref
        type="section" href="#topic8573/supported">How to build a supported Microsoft Windows Server
        guest image for HPE Helion OpenStack</xref>
      <xref type="section" href="#topic8573/nonsupported">How to build a non-supported Microsoft
        Windows Server guest image for HPE Helion OpenStack</xref>
    </p>
    <section id="hp-helion-openstack-with-microsoft-windows-server-reference-architecture">
      <title>HPE Helion OpenStack with Microsoft Windows Server Reference Architecture</title>
      <p>HPE Helion OpenStack is HPs hardened, tested, enterprise-grade distribution of OpenStack
        cloud software, designed to deliver the best open source cloud computing technology in a
        stable, maintainable and manageable package. It offers a number of value-added services that
        complement and enhance OpenStack technologies. This document describes how to create a
        Microsoft Windows Server 2012, 2012 R2, 2008, or 2008 R2 image for deployment within HPE
        Helion OpenStack The Microsoft Windows Server images can be created on a 64-bit workstation
        running Ubuntu 13.10 or higher on physical hardware that supports KVM.</p>
      <note>To determine the maximum supported Windows Server VM configuration for a given CPU
        architecture, please review the HPE entries in the <xref
          href="http://www.windowsservercatalog.com/results.aspx?&amp;chtext=&amp;cstext=&amp;csttext=&amp;chbtext=&amp;bCatID=1521&amp;cpID=897&amp;avc=0&amp;ava=0&amp;avq=0&amp;OR=1&amp;PGS=25&amp;ready=0"
            format="html">Windows Server Catalog</xref> for Server
        Virtualization.</note>
    </section>
    <section id="supported">
      <title>How to build a supported Microsoft Windows Server guest image for HPE Helion
        OpenStack</title>
      <p>The following section describes the procedure to create and deploy Microsoft Windows Server
        that is Microsoft SVVP (Server Virtualization Validation Program) compliant on HPE Helion
        OpenStack as a Nova compute VM</p>
    </section>
    <section
      id="create-and-deploy-a-supported-microsoft-windows-server-image-on-hp-helion-openstack">
      <title>Create and deploy a supported Microsoft Windows Server image on HPE Helion
        OpenStack</title>
      <p>In the following steps we will use Windows Server 2012 as the example. Windows Server
        evaluation images are available on the <xref
          href="http://www.microsoft.com/en-us/evalcenter/try"   format="html"
          >Microsoft website</xref> (registration required). To create a Microsoft Windows Server
        2012 guest image, follow these steps:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>
            <b>Download Windows Server 2012</b>
            <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> Download the Windows Server
            installation ISO.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <b>Create the qcow2 image file</b>
            <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> You can use the
              <codeph>qemu-img</codeph> command with the create switch to create the initial image
            file, for example:</p>
          <codeblock>
<codeph>qemu-img create -f qcow2 ws2012.qcow2 15G
</codeph>
</codeblock>
          <p>In this example, a 15GB qcow2 disk image file is created and is named ws2012.qcow2. In
            most cases 15GB is adequate for an operating system only install. If you expect the
            Windows Server 2012 disk image to increase in size, you can specify a larger value.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <b>Start the Windows Server 2012 installation with the virt-install command</b>
            <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> The <codeph>virt-install</codeph>
            command can be used to install a new guest operating system on a disk image file.
              <codeph>virt-install</codeph> is part of the <codeph>virtinst</codeph> package. To
            install the <codeph>virtinst</codeph> package, type the following command, and then
            press Enter:</p>
          <codeblock>
<codeph>sudo apt-get install virtinst
</codeph>
</codeblock>
          <p>In the following example, the <codeph>virt-install</codeph> command is used to install
            Windows Server 2012 on the disk image that you created earlier in Step 2:</p>
          <codeblock>
<codeph>virt-install --connect qemu:///system --name ws2012 --ram 2048 --vcpus 2 --network network=default,model=rtl8139 --disk path=ws2012.qcow2,format=qcow2,device=disk,bus=ide --cdrom &lt;path_to_windows_2012_iso&gt; --vnc --os-type windows --os-variant win2k8
</codeph>
</codeblock>
          <p>Where:<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> --name: The name of the
            Windows Server 2012 virtual
            machine.<!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> --ram: The amount of RAM.
            <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> --vcpus: The number of virtual
            cpus. <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> --network: The type of
            network interface. <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> --disk: Path to
            the disk image (ide bus in the example above).
            <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> --cdrom: Path to operating system
            .iso file. <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> --vnc: Used for console
            connections. <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> --os-type: Operating
            system type. <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> --os-variant:
            (Optional) Used to specify an operating system variant. </p>
          <p>You can use <codeph>virt-manager</codeph> or <codeph>virt-viewer</codeph> to connect to
            the VMs console and start the windows installation. Make sure that you shut down the
            windows guest image after the installation is complete.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <b>Upload the qcow2 image to glance</b>
            <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> You can use the glance
              <codeph>image-create</codeph> command to upload the Windows Server 2012 image to
            Glance, for example:</p>
          <codeblock>
<codeph>glance image-create --name WS2012 --disk-format qcow2 --container-format bare --is-public true --file ws2012.qcow2
</codeph>
</codeblock>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <b>Set metadata properties to the Glance image</b>
            <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> You can add useful metadata
            information to the image, such as operating system information or hardware details by
            using the glance image-update command, for example:</p>
          <codeblock>
<codeph>glance image-update WS2012 --property os_type=windows --property hw_disk_bus=ide --property hw_vif_model=rtl8139
</codeph>
</codeblock>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section id="nonsupported">
      <title>How to build a non-supported Microsoft Windows Server guest image for HPE Helion
        OpenStack</title>
      <p>In the following steps we will use Windows Server 2012 as the example. Windows Server
        evaluation images are available on the <xref
          href="http://www.microsoft.com/en-us/evalcenter/try"   format="html"
          >Microsoft website</xref> (registration required). To create a Microsoft Windows Server
        2012 guest image, follow these steps: </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          <p>
            <b>Download Windows Server 2012</b>
            <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> Download the Windows Server
            installation ISO.</p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <b>Step 2: Download virtual drivers</b>
            <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--> Download signed VirtIO drivers ISO
            from the <xref href="http://alt.fedoraproject.org/pub/alt/virtio-win/latest/images/."
                format="html">Fedora website</xref>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>
            <b>Start the installation of Windows Server 2012</b> Use Virt-manager to start
            Installation of Windows Server 2012 and provide the following information:</p>
          <ol>
            <li>In the <b>Name</b> field, enter a descriptive name.</li>
            <li>Select <b>Local install media</b>, and then click <b>Forward</b>.</li>
            <li>Click <b>Browse</b> and select the location where the ISO image is located, and then
              click <b>Forward</b>.</li>
            <li>Assign <b>4096</b> MB of memory and <b>4</b> CPUs, and then click
              <b>Forward</b>.</li>
            <li>Create a disk of <b>30</b> GB. Uncheck the <b>Allocate entire disk now</b> option,
              and then click <b>Forward</b>.</li>
            <li>Click to enable the <b>Customize configuration before install</b> option.</li>
            <li>Under <b>Advanced options</b>, in the <b>Disk</b> section, set disk bus to
                <b>Virtio</b>.</li>
            <li>Click <b>Add Hardware</b>, and then add an IDE CDROM that points to the download
              location for the VirtIO drivers ISO.</li>
            <li>Click <b>Finish</b> to start the installation.</li>
          </ol>
        </li>
        <li>Enable the VirtIO drivers. The disk is not automatically detected by the Windows
          installer. When requested to choose an installation target, click <b>Load driver</b>.
          Browse the file system, and then select E:\WIN8\AMD64 folder. The Windows installer
          displays a list of drivers to install. Select the drivers, and then continue with the
          installation. Once the installation is completed and the VM restarts, you can define a
          password for the administrator when prompted.</li>
        <li>Login to the VM as administrator and start a command window.</li>
        <li>
          <p>Complete the VirtIO drivers installation by running the following command:</p>
          <p>
            <codeph>pnputil.exe -i -a E:\WIN8\AMD64\*.INF</codeph>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Set the PowerShell execution policy. To allow Cloudbase-Init to run scripts during an
            instance boot, set the PowerShell execution policy to be unrestricted, by running the
            following commands:</p>
          <p>
            <codeph>powershell</codeph>
            <!--A BR tag was used here in the original source.--><codeph>Set-ExecutionPolicy
              Unrestricted</codeph>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>Download Cloudbase-Init x64 version for 64 bit operating system: <xref
            href="https://github.com/stackforge/cloudbase-init"   format="html"
            >https://github.com/stackforge/cloudbase-init</xref>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Install Cloudbase-Init. During the installation of Cloudbase-Init, in the Configuration
            options window, change the following settings:</p>
          <p>
            <codeph>Username : Admin</codeph>
          </p>
          <p>
            <codeph>Network Adapter to configure : Red Hat VirtIO Ethernet Adapter</codeph>
          </p>
          <p>
            <codeph>Serial port for logging : COM1</codeph>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>Complete the Cloudbase-Init setup. Once the installation is complete, in the
              <b>Complete the Cloudbase-Init setup Wizard</b> window, select the <b>Run Sysprep</b>
            and <b>Shutdown</b> check boxes. Click <b>Finish</b> and wait for the Windows Server
            image to shut down.</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section id="more-information">
      <title>More information</title>
      <p>HPE Helion Professional Services are available to assist you along each step of your cloud
        journey, from helping you define your business needs to deploying Microsoft Windows Server
        VMs within your HPE Helion OpenStack cloud. As your trusted adviser, we will show you how to
        get started, the steps you will take to achieve your desired business outcomes, and once
        it's up and running we will show you how to support and scale your cloud based on best
        practices gained in operating one of the world's largest OpenStack clouds and thousands of
        customer cloud deployments.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="learn-more-at">
      <title>Learn more at:</title>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <xref href="http://www8.hp.com/us/en/cloud/helion-overview.html"  
            format="html">hp.com/helion/</xref>
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref href="1.1commercial.index.xml">docs.hpcloud.com/helion/openstack/1.1/</xref>
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/"   format="html"
            >docs.openstack.org/</xref>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        <xref href="#topic8573"> Return to Top </xref>
      </p>
      <!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
