<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic3600">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> Object Operations Service Overview</title>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./community/community.services-object-overview.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/community/services/object/overview/--></p>
<!-- modeled after HPE Cloud Networking Getting Started (network.getting.started.md) -->
<p>Based on OpenStack Swift, HPE Helion OpenStack Object Operations is a redundant, scalable, and dynamic storage service. The core storage system is designed to provide a safe, secure, network accessible way to store data. You can store an unlimited number of files and each file can be as large as 5GB. With segmented objects, you can upload and store objects of almost unlimited size.</p>
<p>Object Operations allows you to store and retrieve files and content through a simple RESTful API interface.</p>
<p>A cloud storage container provides a way for you to organize your objects. The object can be any arbitrary data, including a document, image, video, backup file or anything else required by your application.</p>
<p>Objects have a size limit of 5 gigabytes. However, objects larger than 5GB can be segmented and then concatenated together so that you can upload 5GB segments and download a single concatenated object of any size. You can work with the segments and manifests directly with API requests.</p>
<section id="working-with-the-object-operations-service"> <title>Working with the Object Operations Service</title>
<p>To <xref type="section" href="#topic3600/howto">perform tasks using the Object Operations service</xref>, you can use the dashboard, API or CLI.</p>
</section>
<section id="UI"> <title>Using the dashboards</title>
<p>You can use the <xref href="../community/community.dashboard.how-works.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack Dashboard</xref> to work with the Object Operations service.</p>
</section>
<section id="API"> <title>Using the API to access Object Operations</title>
<p>You can use a low-level, raw REST API access to HPE Object Operations service. See the <xref href="http://developer.openstack.org/api-ref-objectstorage-v1.html" scope="external" format="html" >OpenStack Object Storage API v2.0 Reference</xref>.</p>
</section>
<section id="cli"> <title>Using the CLI</title>
<p>You can use any of several command-line interface software to access HPE Object Operations service. See the <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/cli-reference/content/swiftclient_commands.html" scope="external" format="html" >OpenStack Command Line Interface Reference</xref>.</p>
<p>For more information on installing the CLI, see <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide/content/install_clients.html" scope="external" format="html" >Install the OpenStack command-line clients</xref>.</p>
</section>
<section id="howto"> <title>How To's with the HPE Helion OpenStack Object Operations Service</title>
<!-- Taken from http://wiki.hpcloud.net/display/core/Core+Edition+Use+cases#CoreEditionUsecases-OverCloud -->
<p>The following lists of tasks can be performed by a user or administrator through the <xref href="../commercial/GA1/1.1commercial.dashboard.how-works.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack Dashboard</xref>, the OpenStack <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/cli-reference/content/swiftclient_commands.html" scope="external" format="html" >CLI</xref> or OpenStack <xref href="http://developer.openstack.org/api-ref-objectstorage-v1.html" scope="external" format="html" >API</xref>.</p>
<p>Depending upon your user type, you can perform the following tasks.</p>
</section>
<section id="working-with-containers"> <title>Working with containers</title>
<p>The Object Operations service allows users to create a storage container, move files to and from that storage container, and delete containers that are no longer needed.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<b>Creating, modifying and deleting containers</b> -- Create, configure, and delete storage containers as needed.</li>
<li>
<b>Uploading files to a container</b> -- Upload files from a local system to your storage container.</li>
<li>
<b>Downloading files from a container</b> -- Download files from your container to a local system.</li>
<li>
<b>Deleting files from a container</b> -- Delete any of the files in your storage container.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="for-more-information"> <title>For more information</title>
<p>For information on how to operate your cloud we suggest you read the <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/ops/" scope="external" format="html" >OpenStack Operations Guide</xref>. The <i>Architecture</i> section contains useful information about how an OpenStack Cloud is put together. However, the HPE Helion OpenStack takes care of these details for you. The <i>Operations</i> section contains information on how to manage the system.</p>
<p>
  <xref href="#topic3600"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
<!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
</section>
</body>
</topic>
