<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic6434">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> Community Network Architecture and Configuration - Baremetal Installations Only</title>
<titlealts>
<searchtitle>HPE Helion Openstack Community Network Architecture and Configuration -- Baremetal Installations Only</searchtitle>
</titlealts>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./community/community.network-requirements.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/community/network-requirements/--></p>
<p>This page provides an overview of important information on the network configuration required for a baremetal HPE Helion OpenCloud Community edition installation.</p>
<p>For virtual installations, the installation simulates the deployment of OpenStack by creating and configuring a set of virtual machines (VMs) on a single system. As such, no manual network configuration is required.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic6434/physical-network-architecture">Physical network architecture</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic6434/config">Network configuration for a baremetal installation</xref>

<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic6434/NetworkDefault">Network defaults</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic6434/changedefault">Changing the default networking configuration</xref> </li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<section id="physical-network-architecture"> <title>Physical network architecture</title>
<p>The table in this section provides an overview of the physical network configuration requirements you must meet, with the following assumptions:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Physical network ports on each server:</p>

<ul>
<li>One IPMI/iLO port</li>
<li>One physical ethernet port (for example, eth0) for the hypervisor/OS</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>Network fabric</p>

<ul>
<li>Two physical links, one for IPMI/iLO and one for the hypervisor/OS</li>
<li>Network switches capable of basic VLAN, L2 and L3 functions; no dependency on, for example, VxLAN-capable or OpenFlow-enabled switch</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>The physical hypervisor/OS network is shared by a number of logical networks, and each logical network has its own VLAN and IP subnet.</p>
</li>
<li>The seed VM, the baremetal systems, and the BMC (IPMI controller) for all
baremetal systems must be on a common network.</li>
</ul>
<!--
For detailed information, see the [Reference architecture](/helion/community/reference-architecture/).
-->
<table>
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colname="col1"/>
<colspec colname="col2"/>
<colspec colname="col3"/>
<colspec colname="col4"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry> Network </entry>
<entry> Description </entry>
<entry> VLAN type </entry>
<entry> Server port </entry>

</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry> IPMI / iLO </entry>
<entry> Network for server hardware management </entry>
<entry> Untagged </entry>
<entry> IPMI or iLO</entry>

</row>
<row>
<entry> Undercloud management </entry>
<entry> <ul>
<li>Traffic for undercloud internal OpenStack calls, Glance image downloads, etc.</li>
<li>Provides access to undercloud API endpoints</li>
<li>Used to PXE boot overcloud servers</li>
</ul>
</entry>
<entry> Untagged </entry>
<entry> eth0</entry>

</row>
<row>
<entry> Overcloud management </entry>
<entry> Traffic for overcloud internal OpenStack calls, glance image downloads, etc. </entry>
<entry> Tagged </entry>
<entry> eth0</entry>

</row>
<row>
<entry> SDN </entry>
<entry> Network between workload VMs, e.g. carries VxLAN traffic </entry>
<entry> Tagged </entry>
<entry> eth0</entry>

</row>
<row>
<entry> Storage </entry>
<entry> iSCSi traffic between VMs and storage products like StoreVirtual </entry>
<entry> Tagged </entry>
<entry> eth0</entry>

</row>
<row>
<entry> External </entry>
<entry>
<ul>
<li> Connected to internet or intranet</li>
<li>Provides floating IPs</li>
</ul>
</entry>
<entry> Tagged </entry>
<entry> eth0</entry>

</row>
<row>
<entry> External-API </entry>
<entry> <ul>
<li>Connected to internet or intranet</li>
<li>Provides access to overcloud API endpoints</li>
</ul>
</entry>
<entry> Tagged </entry>
<entry> eth0</entry>

</row>
<row>
<entry> Swift </entry>
<entry> Communication between swift servers (includes user data)  </entry>
<entry> Tagged </entry>
<entry> eth0</entry>

</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>
<section id="config"> <title>Network configuration</title>
<p>Make sure your network is configured to include the following criteria:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The seed VM, the baremetal systems and the IPMI controller for all systems must be on the same network.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Any network interfaces that are not used for PXE boot must be disabled from BIOS to prevent PXE boot attempts from those devices.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Any DHCP servers on the same network as your system must not hand out IP addresses to your physical nodes as they PXE boot.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Make sure there is no wildcard DHCP server on your network. The wildcard DHCP server will likely reply to the booting under/overcloud servers before the seed VM, which will cause the PXE boot process to fail.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The network interface intended as the bridge interface should be configured and working before running the installer. The installer creates a network bridge on the system running the installer, attaching the bridge interface to the network bridge. The installer uses the IP address of the bridge interface for the network bridge.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The IPMI/BMC interfaces of the real hardware must be accessible from the seed VM.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="NetworkDefault"> <title>Network defaults</title>
<p>The installation process includes a number of default configurations. You can change many of these defaults during the installation, using the steps detailed in <xref href="../community/community.install.baremetal.xml" >Community Baremetal Installation and Configuration</xref>.</p>
<p>Note the following default settings:</p>
<ul>
<li>The default network configuration uses a single subnet 192.0.2.0/24 for all networking. </li>
<li>The Seed VM is assigned an IP address of 192.0.2.1, in addition to the IP address assigned by the <xref type="section" href="#topic6434/packages">libvirt package</xref>. </li>
<li>The external interface of host of the seed VM is added to a software bridge, called <i>brbm</i>, on the host and the IP address of the external interface is transferred to the bridge. This allows external traffic on 192.0.2.0/24 to be routed to the seed VM.</li>
<li>The seed VM is the gateway for all traffic outside the baremetal network.</li>
<li>
<p>IP addresses are assigned by default as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>192.0.2.2-192.0.2.20 is used by the seed cloud to administer the undercloud nodes</li>
<li>192.0.2.21-192.0.2.124 is used by the undercloud to administer the overcloud nodes</li>
<li>192.0.2.129-1920.0.2.254 is used as a pool of addresses for floating IPs for the virtual machines in the overcloud.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>The IP address range for the private IPs assigned to new virtual instances is 10.0.0.0/8.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="changedefault"> <title>Changing the default networking configuration</title>
<p>In the default configuration, the default pool of floating IP addresses for the overcloud is within the baremetal subnet. You can select a different pool of addresses during the installation. If you select a pool of addresses outside the baremetal subnet, make sure those addresses are accessible.</p>
<p>
  <b>Example:</b>
</p>
<p>The following example shows how to select a range of IP addresses from 10.23.144.10 to 10.23.151.254 with a subnet mask of 10.23.144.0/21. To avoid overlap with the default private network range of 10.0.0.0/8, <codeph>OVERCLOUD_FIXED_RANGE_CIDR</codeph> is changed to 10.0.0.0/16.</p>
<p>During the <xref href="../community/community.install.baremetal.xml" >installation</xref> you must set <codeph>OVERCLOUD_NeutronPublicInterface</codeph> to the name of the VLAN on which the floating IP addresses will reside (you must create this VLAN separately).</p>
<codeblock>
  <codeph>export FLOATING_START=10.23.144.10
export FLOATING_END=10.23.151.254
export FLOATING_CIDR=10.23.144.0/21
export OVERCLOUD_FIXED_RANGE_CIDR=10.0.0.0/16
export OVERCLOUD_NeutronPublicInterface=vlan1515
export NeutronPublicInterfaceRawDevice=eth0
export OVERCLOUD_VIRTUAL_INTERFACE=eth0
</codeph>
</codeblock>
<p>This example assumes a homogeneous overcloud compute hardware.</p>
<p>
<b>Important:</b> IP addresses in the ranges chosen for the undercloud and overcloud must not be used by other nodes
on your network.</p>
</section>
<section id="next-step"> <title>Next Step</title>
<p>Proceed to the installation in <xref href="../community/community.install.baremetal.xml" >Community Baremetal Installation and Configuration</xref>
</p>
<p>
  <xref href="#topic6434"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
<!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
</section>
</body>
</topic>
