<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic9592">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> Community 1.4 Release Notes</title>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./community/community.release-notes.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/community/release-notes/--></p>
<!--**Product Name:** HPE Helion OpenStack Community
**OpenStack release name:** Icehouse-->
<p>Thanks for your interest in HPE Helion OpenStack Community! These release notes contain the following information about this release:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9592/versions">Available product versions</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9592/features">Features in HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition</xref> </li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9592/supported-services">Supported services</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9592/recommendations">Recommendations for HPE Helion OpenStack Community</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9592/for-further-information">For further information</xref> </li>
</ul>
<section id="versions"> <title>Available product versions</title>
<p>This release of the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition contains a single download of the product that covers both virtual and baremetal deployment:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<i>A virtual deployment of HPE Helion OpenStack Community</i>. First released in early May, 2014, this provides a "cloud-in-a-box" virtual deployment targeted towards enterprises and cloud administrators interested in evaluating, developing and deploying a private cloud based on OpenStack Cloud Software. It's a pure, free and downloadable OpenStack distribution that speeds up deployment and simplifies the management of small-scale, open cloud environments and infrastructure services. It is not intended to be used in a production environment to run real workloads.</li>
<li>
<i>A baremetal deployment of HPE Helion OpenStack Community</i>. First released in June, 2014, this edition installs in a physical environment. The baremetal installation allows you to build an OpenStack cloud spanning multiple physical nodes. During installation, this edition sets up an undercloud host and deploys the overcloud on 3 controller hosts, 2 physical Swift nodes, and up to 36 physical compute nodes. </li>
</ul>
<p>These release notes cover both deployments.</p>
</section>
<section id="features"> <title>Features in HPE Helion OpenStack Community</title>
<p>The following sections list the features in the current version, 1.4, and previous versions.</p>
</section>
<section id="features-in-hp-helion-openstack-community-14"> <title>Features in HPE Helion OpenStack Community 1.4</title>
<p>
<b>Additional overcloud controllers for high availability</b> — The number of installed overcloud controller nodes has been increased to 3. The additional nodes should allow Community to continue operating if a single control node fails. Previously, the Community edition installed a single overcloud controller node.</p>
<p>
<b>Icinga monitoring support</b> — Icinga V1.11.5 is an open source monitoring system which checks the availability of your network resources, notifies users of outages, and generates performance data for reporting. For more information, see the <xref href="https://www.icinga.org/"   format="html" >Icinga web site</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Kibana interface support</b> — Kibana is an open source (Apache Licensed), browser based analytics and search dashboard for ElasticSearch. For more information, see the <xref href="http://www.elasticsearch.org/guide/en/kibana/current/_introduction.html"   format="html" >Kibana web site</xref>
</p>
<p>
<b>OpenStack Juno-2 development milestone</b> — HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition fully supports the second milestone of the OpenStack Juno development cycle, including features and bug fixes implemented since Juno-1.</p>
<p>
<b>Distributed Virtual Routing (DVR)</b> — HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition fully supports the DVR implemented in OpenStack Juno-3 plus some fixes from Juno-final.</p>
</section>
<section id="features-in-hp-helion-openstack-community-ga"> <title>Features in HPE Helion OpenStack Community GA</title>
<p>
<b>Pure OpenStack technology</b> — This edition allows you to experience a cloud deployment using <xref href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO"   format="html" >OpenStack TripleO</xref>.</p>
<p>
<b>Speeds cloud service delivery</b> — Outstanding launch pad for your small-scale open cloud environment or proof-of-concept cloud services, with simple, fast creation of cloud environments and applications to speed business value.</p>
<p>
<b>Close-to-trunk release</b> — Allows your lab or small-scale production environment to continue to benefit from the very latest capabilities of OpenStack technology, closely tracking the community trunk release.</p>
</section>
<section id="supported-services"> <title>Supported services</title>
<p>This release of the Community edition is shipped with the following supported services:</p>
<table>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colname="col1"/>
<colspec colname="col2"/>
<colspec colname="col3"/>
<thead>
<row>
    <entry>OpenStack-powered capabilities</entry>
    <entry>API supported</entry>
    <entry>API version</entry>
  </row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
    <entry>Compute (Nova)</entry>
    <entry>Full support</entry>
    <entry>v2.0</entry>
  </row>
<row>
    <entry>Object Storage (Swift)</entry>
    <entry>Full support</entry>
    <entry>v1.0</entry>
  </row>
<row>
    <entry>Block Storage (Cinder)</entry>
    <entry>Full support</entry>
    <entry>v1.0 and v2.0</entry>
  </row>
<row>
    <entry>Networking (Neutron)</entry>
    <entry>Full support</entry>
    <entry>v2.0</entry>
  </row>
<row>
    <entry>Image Service (Glance)</entry>
    <entry>Full support</entry>
    <entry>v1.0 and v2.0</entry>
  </row>
<row>
    <entry>Identity (Keystone)</entry>
    <entry>Full support</entry>
    <entry>v2.0 and v3.0</entry>
  </row>
<row>
    <entry>Dashboard (Horizon)</entry>
    <entry>Full support</entry>
    <entry>N/A
</entry>
  </row>
<row>
    <entry>Orchestration (Heat)</entry>
    <entry>Full support</entry>
    <entry>N/A
</entry>
  </row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>
<section id="recommendations"> <title>Recommendations for HPE Helion OpenStack Community</title>
<p>This section describes the HPE recommendations for optimizing performance, utility, and functionality with this software version. We have also provided information about some known issues for reference purposes. This section contains:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9592/best-practices">Recommendations for optimizing functionality, performance and reliability</xref> </li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9592/known-issues">Known issues in this release</xref> </li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="best-practices"> <title>Recommendations</title>
<p>HPE recommends the following best practices for this software version.</p>
<p>
  <b>Installation</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li>To enable VM functionality, be sure to install the required Ubuntu packages, as described in the <xref href="../community/community.hwsw-requirements.xml#software" type="section">Software configuration</xref> section in Community Hardware and Software Requirements.</li>
</ul>
<p>
  <b>Operations</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>When issuing Neutron commands from inside the seed VM, we recommend you set the <codeph>LANG</codeph> environment variable to <codeph>C</codeph>.  Add the following line to the appropriate user configuration file:</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>export LANG=C
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
<li>
<p>We recommend cleaning up any VMs using excess space, by executing the following commands:</p>

<ul>
<li>Delete the KVM VMs and their storage volumes with the <codeph>virsh destroy</codeph> command.</li>
<li>Uninstall any packages that you no longer require.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>For optimum VM operation and to avoid generating inaccurate error codes, we recommend you not reboot the overcloud controller but rather restart the applicable services by executing the following commands:</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>sudo service nova-compute restart
sudo service nova-scheduler restart
sudo service nova-conductor restart
sudo service neutron-openvswitch-agent restart
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
<li>
<p>It is possible in busier systems that Kibana logging system might not cope with amount of logs collected. You can correct this issue by increasing the heap size specified in the <codeph>/etc/default/elasticsearch</codeph> file from the default 2G to a higher value and restarting elasticsearch service.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>After deleting a cloud or an entire HPE Helion OpenStack Community installation, make sure you perform a full disk erasure on the associated storage devices to prevent exposure of sensitive data that might have been stored there.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="known-issues"> <title>Known issues in this release</title>
<p>The following are the known issues for HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition:</p>
<p>
  <b>Operations</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li>When a significant update operation is performed, such as adding or removing nodes, connectivity to the VM will drop until the operation is completed. This may last for up to 15 minutes.</li>
<li>When accessing Horizon in a virtual environment, use the public network address, not the management network address. In a default configuration, the URL is http://192.0.8.2.</li>
<li>If you determine that your VM seed has not started correctly when you executed the <codeph>hp_ced_host_manager.sh</codeph> script, run the script a second time to ensure you start the seed.</li>
<li>VM installations do not currently persist across reboots.  When you reboot your system, be sure to start a new VM installation.</li>
<li>
<p>If after an overcloud controller reboot you determine the VMs are in an ERROR state, execute the following commands to restart the services and remove the error:</p>

<codeblock>
<codeph>sudo service nova-compute restart
sudo service nova-scheduler restart
sudo service nova-conductor restart
sudo service neutron-openvswitch-agent restart
</codeph>
</codeblock>
</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>
<b>Live Migration of Instance in Stopped, Suspended, or Rescued State May Fail</b> Make sure instances are not in the Stopped, Suspended, or Rescued state before attempting to migrate them to a new host. A 400 error may appear; a message "Failed to migrate instance..." may be received; or the client may quietly time out, leaving the instance stuck in the Migrating state and thus unmanageable.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="for-further-information"> <title>For further information</title>
<p>The kit comes with a README.txt which lists a number of recommendations and requirements. Please read and follow it carefully.</p>
<p>For additional information on HPE Helion OpenStack Community, OpenStack Cloud Software and TripleO:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<xref href="../community/community.index.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack Community Documentation web site</xref>: Provides the topics listed below.</li>
<li>
<xref href="../community/community.faq.xml" >FAQ</xref>: Contains some frequently asked questions about the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition release</li>
<li>
  <xref href="community.install-overview.xml" >Installation and configuration</xref>: A set of tasks that walk you through the installation and configuration process.</li>
<li>
<xref href="../community/community.related-topics.xml" >Related Topics</xref>: Links to pertinent HPE Helion OpenStack Community and OpenStack documentation.</li>
<li>
<xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/"   format="html" >OpenStack documentation home page</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO"   format="html" >TripleO documentation</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref href="https://ask.openstack.org/en/questions/scope:all/sort:activity-desc/tags:hphelion/page:1/"   format="html" >HPE Helion OpenStack Support Forum</xref> (Tag your questions with HPHelion)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="legal-notices-disclaimer"> <title>Legal Notices and Disclaimer</title>
<ul>
<li>
<xref href="../community/community.3rd-party-license-agreements.xml" >Open Source and Third-Party Software License Agreements</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref href="../community/community.eula.xml" >End User License Agreement</xref>
</li>
</ul>
<!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
</section>
</body>
</topic>
