<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" ><topic xml:lang="en-us" id="topic9044">
<title>HPE Helion <tm tmtype="reg">OpenStack</tm> Community FAQ</title>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<othermeta name="layout" content="default"/>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>
<!--PUBLISHED-->
 <!--./community/community.faq.md-->
 <!--permalink: /helion/community/faq/--></p>
<!--

-->
<p>You've got questions. We have the answers.</p>
<section id="understanding-the-hp-helion-openstack-community-edition"> <title>Understanding the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition</title>
<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/whatcommunity">What is HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? And how does it tie into the overall HPE Helion portfolio?</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/distroenable">What does this distro enable customers to do?</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/howcompare">How does HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition compare to other OpenStack distributions on the market?</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/distrocost">Is there a cost associated with this distribution?</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/TripleO">What is TripleO?</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/preview">What is available in the current version</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/localized">Is the release localized for non-English speaking markets?</xref> </li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/hybridorpubliccloud">Will the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition work with hybrid or public cloud projects?</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/nodes">How many nodes does it support?</xref> </li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/virtualmachines">How many virtual machines does it support?</xref>  </li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/softwareupdate">How can customers update the software?</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/includeOS">Does it include an operating system (OS)?</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/upgrade">Is HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition upgradeable?</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/nonhphardware">Can HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition be run on non-HPE hardware?</xref>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="support-and-additional-resources"> <title>Support and additional resources</title>
<ul>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/supportservices">Are HPE support services included with HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition?</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/supportoptions">What support options are available?</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/MoreInfo">Where can customers find more information?</xref>
</li>
<li>
<xref type="section" href="#topic9044/reportissues">How can customers report issues and participate in HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition related discussions?</xref> </li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="whatcommunity"> <title>What is HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? And how does it tie into the overall HPE Helion portfolio?</title>
<p>HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition is the first OpenStack distribution from HP. It is free to download and will be kept updated frequently to stay current with OpenStack developments. It will be a foundational technology for all HPE Helion products in the future.</p>
</section>
<section id="distroenable"> <title>What does this distro enable customers to do?</title>
<p>Customers have consistently asked us to release a distribution of OpenStack cloud, tested, hardened and supported by HP.</p>
<p>The final version of this free distribution will enable customers to evaluate HPE Helion OpenStack and to deploy small-scale private clouds in production (up to 30 nodes). They will be able to do this more quickly and easily with HP's simplified installation and update mechanisms.</p>
</section>
<section id="howcompare"> <title>How does HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition compare to other OpenStack cloud distributions on the market?</title>
<p>HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition is one of the first distributions in the market, based on up-to-date code from the OpenStack community. It is derived from pure OpenStack software and open source technologies, configured and packaged by HP. For example, TripleO, which is used for installation and update, is the official OpenStack project for deployment.</p>
</section>
<section id="distrocost"> <title>Is there a cost associated with this distribution?</title>
<p>It is free to download. An optional support package is available to purchase from HPE for access to HPE Helion OpenStack technical support.</p>
</section>
<section id="TripleO"> <title>What is TripleO?</title>
<p>OpenStack on OpenStack or TripleO, is the OpenStack community's official project for deployment of OpenStack systems. It builds on the core resource-provisioning strengths of OpenStack technology. It enables you to administer your cloud, and deploy and maintain virtual and baremetal installations of the OpenStack platform using the same APIs you are familiar with for deploying workloads on an OpenStack cloud. A template-based deployment engine (using OpenStack Heat) allows for rigorous testing and reliable, repeatable deployments of known configurations.</p>
<p>A TripleO installation includes a seed, the undercloud, and the overcloud.</p>
</section>
<section id="preview"> <title>What is available in the current version?</title>
<p>On May 7<sup>th</sup>, we announced a virtual preview of HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition that allows our customers to deploy an OpenStack cloud-in-a-box on a single physical machine. Customers are able to experience TripleO based deployment and to evaluate the Icehouse release of OpenStack cloud.</p>
<p>On June 12<sup>th</sup>, we announced a GA version of HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition with support for baremetal installation, allowing the creation of OpenStack systems spanning up to 30 physical servers.</p>
<p>On July 22nd, we announced a refresh of the GA version with several new features and bug fixes with the availability of Foundation Care Support Service for purchase.</p>
<p>HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition will be updated frequently to keep pace with OpenStack platform  developments. We plan to release new versions roughly every six weeks, and to track the community development cycle.</p>
</section>
<section id="localized"> <title>Is the release localized for non-English speaking markets?</title>
<p>No. The 2014 release is English only.</p>
</section>
<section id="hybridorpubliccloud"> <title>Will HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition work with hybrid or public cloud projects?</title>
<p>HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition is API-compatible with HPE Helion Public Cloud, allowing workloads developed on one to be deployed on the other.  Compatibility with other Public Clouds will depend on which OpenStack platform features they chose to support. It is tested and supported by HPE for enterprise-grade, small-scale, private cloud deployments. Workloads are upgradeable to <xref href="../community/community.index.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack</xref>, with features and capabilities needed for the enterprise, government, and service provider markets, to be launched later this calendar year.</p>
</section>
<section id="nodes"> <title>How many nodes does it support?</title>
<p>Up to 30 nodes in the final release.</p>
</section>
<section id="virtualmachines"> <title>How many virtual machines does it support?</title>
<p>Up to 600, subject to the size of the VMs and the customer's hardware capacity.</p>
</section>
<section id="softwareupdate"> <title>How can customers update the software?</title>
<p>HPE will be providing an automated update mechanism.</p>
</section>
<section id="includeOS"> <title>Does it include an operating system (OS)?</title>
<p>Yes. It includes an integrated <tm tmtype="reg">Linux</tm> host OS, hardened and tested for OpenStack cloud.</p>
</section>
<section id="upgrade"> <title>Is the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition upgradable?</title>
<p>Yes. Customers who begin with HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition can migrate to larger, enterprise-grade installations using full HPE Helion OpenStack</p>
</section>
<section id="nonhphardware"> <title>Can HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition be run on non-HPE hardware?</title>
<p>Yes, provided the hardware meets the minimum specification. HPE will be working with HPE Helion Community edition users to develop a list of third-party hardware on which the distribution is known to run.</p>
<p>
  <xref href="#topic9044"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
</section>
<section id="support-additional-resources"> <title>Support and additional resources</title>
</section>
<section id="supportservices"> <title>Are HPE support services included with HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition?</title>
<p>No. An optional paid support contract from HPE is available for purchase; since July 22nd.</p>
</section>
<section id="supportoptions"> <title>What support options are available?</title>
<p>HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition will be covered by Foundation Care Support Service at an additional cost.  Customers interact with experts in <xref href="http://h20427.www2.hp.com/campaign/hp-cloud-centre-of-excellence/ap/en/index.html" scope="external" format="html" >HP's Global Cloud Center of Excellence</xref> as the single source of support and accountability.</p>
<ul>
<li>Access to HPE Helion OpenStack technical experts, tools, and best practices </li>
<li>HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition software support</li>
<li>Installation advisory support</li>
<li>Help with software features and operational support</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="MoreInfo"> <title>Where can I find more information?</title>
<ul>
<li>
<xref href="http://www8.hp.com/us/en/cloud/hphelion-openstack-community.html" scope="external" format="html" >HPE Helion OpenStack Community Portal</xref>
</li>
<li>
  <xref href="community.index.xml" >HPE Helion OpenStack Community Documentation</xref> </li>
<li>
<xref href="https://ask.openstack.org/en/questions/scope:all/sort:activity-desc/tags:hphelion" scope="external" format="html" >HPE Helion OpenStack Support Forum</xref> (Tag your questions with 'HPHelion')</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="reportissues"> <title>How can I report issues and participate in HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition related discussions?</title>
<p>We are hosting the support discussion forum for the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition at <xref href="https://ask.openstack.org" scope="external" format="html" >https://ask.openstack.org</xref>.  Developers in the community are very familiar with this forum and already participate in OpenStack technology-related discussions there. Please tag your questions with 'HPHelion' to get our attention for any questions and issues you raise.</p>
<!--

####Is HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition integrated with other HPE Helion products and solutions? #### {#integrated}

Yes. These products will reference "Powered by HPE Helion OpenStack"

##Understanding the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition   

* [What is the value I get by using the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition?](#PrimaryValue)
* [How does HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition relate to the larger HPE Helion OpenStack initiative?](#RelateInitiative)
* [Who are the best prospects for the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition?](#BestProspects)
* [What are the main benefits of the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition and the features that support them?](#MainBenefits)
* [What is the competitive positioning, and how do I win?](#Positioning)
* [If HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition is free, why should I waste valuable sales cycles on it?](#Free)
* [When and where will HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition be released?](#WhenWhere) 
* [Where can I download the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition?](#Download)
* [When can I expect support for baremetal deployment?](#BareMetal)

## Understanding the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition

####What is the value I get by using the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? #### {#PrimaryValue}

The HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition speeds deployment and simplifies the management of small-scale, open cloud environments and infrastructure services. This gives you a risk-free opportunity to build toward hybrid cloud delivery in your enterprise by proving the utility of OpenStack software on a reliable distro hardened for that environment.
 
####How does the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition relate to the larger HPE Helion OpenStack initiative?#### {#RelateInitiative}

HPE Helion OpenStack is a hardened product set that speeds deployment and simplifies management of private clouds for developers, enterprises and service providers. It includes a free and pure OpenStack software distribution, HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition, and a commercial version optimized for business. HPE Helion OpenStack will be released later this year.

####Who are the best prospects for the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? #### {#BestProspects}

* Enterprises looking toward trials or PoCs for evaluation and development to gain an early competitive advantage from a distro that is hardened for enterprise. 
* Enterprises seeking a small-scale private cloud deployment, looking at Community edition as a longer-term play over a PoC are ideal for a support package upsell.
* Smart enterprise developers who are interested in participating in the OpenStack community and being on the leading edge of the &#8220;New Style of IT&#8221;  transformation.

####What are the main benefits of the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition and the features that support them? #### {#MainBenefits}

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Features</th>
    <th>Benefits</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td width=50%><p>*First distro based on Icehouse</p> 
    <p>*Automated-live distribution of updates</p> 
    <p>*Contains OpenStack TripleO for installing, upgrading and operating OpenStack clouds</p></td>
    <td valign=top><p>Always a pure, close-to-trunk OpenStack software release, free to license and download so you are always using the latest OpenStack technology</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td width=50%><p>*Includes integrated HPE Linux host OS for better speed, support, and control across the full solution stack</p> 
    <p>*Workloads transferable to HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition</p> </td>
    <td valign=top><p>Perfect for evaluation and small-scale deployments (optimized for up to 30 nodes and 600 VMs)</td>
  </tr>
 <tr>
    <td width=50%><p>*Delivered with an easy-to-use installer/updater</p> 
    <p>*Simplified admin user console</p> </td>
    <td valign=top><p>Simple installation and configuration process (takes 1,200+ manual configurations to a handful of automated steps)</td>
  </tr>
 <tr>
    <td width=50%><p>*Performance and security hardening by HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition</p> 
    <p>*Optional Foundation Care 24x7 support and indemnification</p></td>
    <td valign=top><p>Confident implementation, evaluation, development, and deployment</td>
  </tr>
</table>
 
####What is TripleO? #### {#TripleO}

OpenStack on OpenStack (or TripleO) is the OpenStack community's official deployment of the OpenStack project. It builds on the core resource-provisioning strengths of OpenStack technology to enable cloud administrators to deploy and maintain baremetal installations of OpenStack Using the same APIs that they are familiar with for deploying workloads on an OpenStack cloud, template based deployment engine (OpenStack Heat) allows for rigorous testing and reliable, repeatable deployments of known configurations.

Learn more about <a href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO" target="_blank">TripleO</a>  

####What is the competitive positioning, and how do I win? #### {#Positioning}

The HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition is one of the first distributions in the market based on the most recent Icehouse release of OpenStack from the community. It is pure OpenStack with no proprietary technology or add-ins. For example, TripleO is used for deployment. It comes with HPE Linux as a host OS, hardened and tested for HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition. More competitive information is available on the HPE Helion OpenStack Community battlecard on the sales portal.  

####What is the price for the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? #### {#WhatPrice} 
It is completely free to license and download. 

####If the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition is free, why should I waste valuable sales cycles on it? #### {#Free}

The HPE Helion OpenStack Community preview will be made available worldwide May 7. This preview allows our customers to deploy an OpenStack cloud-in-a-box, experience TripleO based deployment and evaluate Icehouse release of OpenStack technology. It will be followed by a full release with support for baremetal deployments (up to 30 compute nodes) and future releases once every 6 weeks to stay close to the trunk. Download it [here](www.hp.com/helion/openstack). 

####When and where will HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition be released? #### {#WhenWhere}

We are committed to shipping every 6 weeks and this is our first release based on Icehouse which was just released. We are currently testing and hardening our distribution to support baremetal deployment for a small scale private cloud deployment. We expect this to be available in our next release. 

####Where can I download the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? #### {#Download}

You can download it from [here](www.hp.com/helion/openstack).

####Is the latest HPE Helion OpenStack Community release localized for non-English speaking markets? #### {#Localized}

No, the 2014 release is in English only.

####When can I expect support for baremetal deployment? #### {#BareMetal}
We are committed to shipping every six weeks and this is our first release based on Icehouse which was just released. We are currently testing and hardening our distribution to support baremetal deployment for a small scale private cloud deployment. We expect this to be available in our next release. 

####Will the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition work with hybrid or public cloud projects? #### {#hybridorpubliccloud} 

HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition is API-compatible with HPE Helion Public Cloud, allowing workloads developed on one to be deployed on the other.  Compatibility with other Public Clouds will depend on which OpenStack platform features they chose to support.  It is tested and supported by HPE for enterprise-grade, small-scale, private cloud deployments. Workloads are upgradeable to HPE Helion OpenStack with features and capabilities needed for the enterprise, government, and service provider markets, to be launched later this calendar year.

####How many nodes does the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition support? #### {#Nodes}

Up to 30.

####How many virtual machines does the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition support? #### {#VirtualMachines} 

Up to 600.

####How can Clients update the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition software? #### {#SoftwareUpdates}

HPE provides automated, live distribution of updates.

####Does the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition include an operating system (OS)? #### {#IncludeOS}

Yes. It includes an integrated HPE Linux&#174; host OS hardened and tested for this distribution giving HPE full control of the stack (for compute and controller node hypervisors).

####Does the distribution include tools not based on OpenStack technology? #### {#Distribution}

No. HPE Helion OpenStack Community is a pure distro that leverages OpenStack community standards with no mix of proprietary or tools not based on OpenStack software.

####Does this distro include the OpenStack Icehouse release? #### {#Icehouse}

Yes, and HPE is one of the first vendors to release a supported, productized distro based on Icehouse.

####Is the HPE Helion OpenStack Community upgradable? #### {#Upgrades}

Yes. Clients who begin with the free HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition can migrate to large, enterprise-grade production upgrade to HPE Helion OpenStack 

####Can the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition be run on non-HPE hardware? #### {#RunonHardware}

Yes. The advantage of open source is clients can avoid vendor lock-in. Standards-based APIs are portable across OpenStack technology-based public, private, and managed clouds, so they can easily move workloads to any cloud. 


##Installing and Configuring the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition

### Getting Started  
* [What are the prerequisites for installing and configuring the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition?](#prerequisites)
* [How do I install the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition, and what's included?](#HowdoIinstall)
* [What are the minimum and maximum number of configurations allowed?](#minimumandmaximumconfigs)
* [How do I install and set up the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition Admin Node](#installandsetup)
* [I've installed the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition. Now what?](#NowWhat)
* [How long does it take to complete the installation and configuration of the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition?](#Howlonginstallation)
* [Should I reboot after installation?](#rebootafterinstallation)
* [How do I verify that the installation has succeeded?](verifyinstallsucceed)

### Setting up the seed VM 
* [What is a seed?](#Whatisseed)
* [How do I create a VM for the seed based on the CloudOS specifications?](#createVM) 
* [How do I load a undercloud image into the seed VM?](#imageseedcloud) 
* [How do I log into the seed VM and deploy the undercloud?](#deployUC) 

### Setting up the undercloud and overcloud
* [What is an undercloud?](#Whatisundercloud)
* [What is an overcloud?](#Whatisovercloud) 
* [How do I set up the disk configurations of the undercloud and overcloud servers?](#UCOCservers) 
* [How do I configure the physical network connecting the undercloud and overcloud servers?](#physicalnetwork) 
* [How do I install the overcloud?](#installOC) 
* [How do I verify the functionality of the overcloud?](#verifyOC) 
* [How do I deploy a software update to the overcloud?](#updateOC)
* [How do I add a compute node to the overcloud?](#computenode)  
* [How do I verify that the configuration has succeeded?](verifyconfigsucceed) 
* [Should I reboot after configuring the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition?](#rebootafterconfig)
* [How do I shut down and restart the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition?](#ShutdownRestart)

###Understanding how to use the Dashboard UI

* [How do I launch the HPE Helion OpenStack Community Dashboard?](#launchtheDashboard)
* [What are the key actions I can perform within the Dashboard?](#DashboardActions) 

## Managing the overcloud

### Getting started with overcloud
* [What are the identity operations (Keystone) that I need to perform?](#identityoperations)
* [What are the compute operations (Nova) I need to perform?](#computeoperations)  

### Managing the overcloud: Users 
* [How do I create a VM?](#createVM)
* [How do I create a VM that boots from a volume?](#VMboot) 
* [How do I reboot a VM?](#VMreboot) 
* [How do I rebuild a VM?](#VMrebuild) 
* [How do I start a VM?](#VMstart)
* [How do I stop a VM?](#VMstop) 
* [How do I create a snapshot of a VM?](#VMsnapshot)
* [How do I rescue a VM?](#VMrescue) 
* [How do I unrescue a VM?](#VMunrescue)
* [How do I delete a VM?](#VMdelete) 
* [How do I attach a volume to or from a VM?](#VMattachvolume) 
* [How do I detach a volume to or from a VM?](#VMdetachvolume) 
* [How do I get the console log of a VM?](#VMconsolelog) 
* [How do I get the VNC connection to a VM?](#VMVNC) 
* [How do I create a security group?](#createsecuritygroup)
* [How do I edit or delete security group?](#deletesecuritygroup)
* [How do I create a key pair?](#createkeypair)
* [How do I edit or delete a key pair?](#deletekeypair)
* [How do I associate or disassociated a floating IP address?](#IPaddress) 

### Managing the overcloud: Administrators 
* [How do I create a flavor?](#createflavor)
* [How do I edit or delete a flavor?](#deleteflavor)
* [How do I modify the ACL of a flavor?](#modifyflavor)
* [How do I modify the quota of a project?](#projectquota)
* [How do I modify the quota of a user within a project?](#userquota)
* [How do I create an availability zone?](#addzone)  
* [How do I edit or delete an availability zone?](#deletezone) 
* [How do I create an aggregate?](#createaggregate) 
* [How do I edit or delete an aggregate?](#deleteaggregate) 
* [How do I enable or disable a service?](#enableservice) 
* [How do I lock or unlock a VM?](#lockVM) 
* [How do I pause or unpause a VM?](#pauseVM)
* [How do I suspend or Resume a VM?](#resumeVM)<b><font color="red">(Is this a different use case from the one above?)</font></b>

## Managing network operations

### Managing the network operations: Users
* [How do i create a network?](#createnetwork)
* [How do I edit or delete a network?](#deletenetwork)
* [How do I add a router?](#addrouter)
* [How do I edit or delete a router?](#deleterouter) 
* [How do I add subnet to a network?](#addsubnet) 
* [How do I delete a subnet from a network?](#deletesubnet)
* [How do I add a network to a router?](#networkrouter)
* [How do I delete a network from a router?](#removerouter)
* [How do I add an external network to a router?](#externalrouter)
* [How do I remove an external network from a router?](#removeexternalnetwork)
* [How do I create a port on a network?](#createport) 
* [How do I edit or delete a port on a network?](#deleteport) 
* [How do I allocate a floating IP address?](#allocatefloating) 
* [How do I deallocate a floating IP address?](#deallocatefloating)
* [How do I associate a floating IP address to a fixed IP address?](#floatingIPaddress)
* [How do I disassociate a floating IP address from a fixed IP address?](#fixedIPaddress)
* [How do i create a security group?](#createsecuritygroup) 
* [How do i edit or delete a security group?](#deletesecuritygroup) 
* [How do I create a security group rule?](#createrule)
* [How do I edit or delete a security group rule?](#deleterule)  

### Managing the network operations: Administrators 
* [How do create an external network?](#externalnetwork)
* [How do I edit the quota values of a project?](#quotavalues)
* [How do I add a network to a DHCP agent?](#DHCPagent) 
* [How do I remove a network from a DHCP agent?](#removenetwork) 
* [How do I add a router to a L3 agent?](#L3agent) 
* [How do I remove a router from a L3 agent?](#removeL3agent) 

## Managing Collections and Reports 

### Managing Collections 
* [How do I record metering data?](#recorddata)
* [How do I create an alarm?](#createalarm)
* [How do I edit or delete an alarm?](#deletealarm) 
* [How do I record alarm change?](#alarmchange)
* [How do I record a metering event?](#recordevent) 
* [How do I clear expired metering data?](#expireddata) 

### Managing Reports 
* [What types of measurements do I have access to?](#measurementtypes)
* [Where can I get usage data for a specific meter?](#usagedata)
* [Where can I find the computed statistics for a sample within a specific time range?](#sampletimerange)
* [Where can I access a list of resources?](#accesslist) 
* [Where can I find the resource details?](#resourcedetails)
* [Where can I see the API capabilities supported by the current driver?](#currentdriver) 
* [How can I filter and view alarms?](#filterview)
* [Where can I find the details on a specific alarm?](#alarmdetails)
* [Where can I Get the history of a specific alarm?](#alarmhistory) 
* [Where can I find alarm status?](#alarmstatus)  

## Managing Image Operations

### Managing Image operations: Users
* [How do I create a private image?](#createimage)
* [How to I edit or delete a private image?](#deleteimage)
* [How do I add or update metadata for a private image?](#updatemetadata)   

### Managing Image operations: Administrators 
* [How do I create a public image?](#createpublicimage)
* [How do I edit or delete a public image?](#deletepublicimage)
* [How do I add or update metadata for a public image?](#addmetadatapublicimage)

## Managing Volume Operations (Cinder)

### Managing Volume Operations: Users
* [How do I create a volume?](#createvolume)
* [How do I delete a volume?](#deletevolume)
* [How do I create a bootable volume from an image in glance?](#bootablevolume)
* [How do I create a snapshot of a volume?](#createsnapshot) 
* [How do I delete a snapshot of a volume?](#deletesnapshot)
* [How do I create a backup of a volume in swift?](#createvolumebackup)
* [How do I delete a backup of a volume in swift?](#deletevolumebackup)
* [How do I create a volume from a backup in swift?](#createvolumebackup)
* [How do I update the metadata of a volume?](#updatemetadatavolume) 
* [How do I create an image in glance from a volume?](#createimageglance) 
* [How do I rename a volume?](#renamevolume)
* [How do I extend a volume?](#extendvolume)
* [How do I transfer a volume between users?](#transfervolume)
 
### Managing Volume Operations: Administrators 
* [How do I modify the quota values of a project?](#modifyquota)
* [How do I enable or disable a service?](#enableservice)

## Managing Object operations (swift)

### Managing Object operations:Users
* [How do I create a container?](#createcontainer)
* [How do I edit or delete a container?](#deletecontainer)
* [How do I upload files into a container?](#uploadcontainer)
* [How do I download files from a container?](#downloadcontainer) 
* [How do I delete files in a container?](#deletefiles)

##Updating the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition 

* [How can I update the HPE Cloud software?](#updatesoftware)
* [What will future releases of HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition include?](#FutureReleases)
* [Where can I access release notes?](#ReleaseNotes) 

##Support and Troubleshooting  

* [I'm stuck. Where can I get more help?](#gethelp) 
* [Are HPE support services included?](#supportservices)
* [Where can I go to find more information?](#moreinformation)
* [How can I contact HPE Cloud Customer Support?](#contacts) 

####Where can I see a list of use cases supported by the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? #### {#usecases}

####How is HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition different from other OpenStack technology-based clouds? #### {#Howdifferent} 

####What are the key features and components in the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? #### {#Keycomponents}  

####Is the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition secure? #### {#Commuinitysecure}

####How do I get started with the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? #### {GetStarted} 

####Where can I deploy the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? {WhereDeploy} 

####Is the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition integrated with other HPE cloud products and solutions? #### {#IntegratedwithOtherProducts}
Yes. These products will reference &#8220;Powered by HPE Helion OpenStack

####What OpenStack components are supported in the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? #### {#SupportedComponents}

####How much does the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition cost? #### {#Communitycost}
It is completely free to license and download.


####Will the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition work with hybrid or public cloud projects? #### {#hybridorpubliccloud}
HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition is API compatible with HPE Helion Public Cloud, allowing workloads developed on one to be deployed on the other.  Compatibility with other Public Clouds will depend on which OpenStack platform features they chose to support.  It is tested and supported by HPE for enterprise-grade, small-scale, private cloud deployments. Workloads are upgradeable to HPE Helion OpenStack with features and capabilities needed for the enterprise, government and service provider markets, to be launched later this calendar year.

####Does the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition come with any images? #### {#ComeWithImages} 

####How many nodes does the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition support? #### {#Howmanynodes}

####Will the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition work with hybrid or public cloud projects? #### {#WorkWithHybrid} 

####How many virtual machines does the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition support? #### {#Howmanyvirtualmachines}
The HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition supports up to 600 virtual machines.

####Is the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition scalable?  What if I want to grow my cloud beyond 30 nodes and 600 VMs? #### {#CommunityScalable}

##Installing and Configuring the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition



###Getting Started 

####What are the prerequisites for installing and configuring the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? #### {#prerequisites}

HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition is installed using TripleO, which uses three linked installation phases to deploy a complete OpenStack cloud. 

**Hardware Requirements**

TripleO creates several large VMs as part of the demo deployment process, hence it is essential to use a system that meets the following hardware specification:

* At least 16GB of RAM
* 64 bit Linux machine with at least 16GB of memory to act as the host of the seed VM.
* At least 200GB of available disk space
* Virtualization support, enabled in the BIOS

**Software System Preparation**

1. The following packages must be installed:
$ sudo apt-get install -y libvirt-bin openvswitch-switch openvswitch-common pythonlibvirt
qemu-system-x86 qemu-kvm
2. If you've just installed the libvirt packages above, you will need to restart libvirt:
$ sudo /etc/init.d/libvirt-bin restart
3. Ensure that the root user has a public key. Login as root:
$ sudo su -<br />
    Check whether .ssh/id_rsa exists:
    $ ls~root/.ssh/id_rsa
If the key does not exist, create one, omitting a passphrase (just hit return):
$ ssh-keygen -t rsa 

####How do I install the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition, and what's included? #### {#HowdoIinstall}

1. Before you begin, remove the item re. creating a VM for the seed. This is done by the installer tool.
2. Login as root and unpack the tar file into root's home directory:
    $ sudo su -
    $ tar xvf <location-of-.tar.gz-file>

2. This will create and populate a tripleo/ directory within root's home directory.

3. Ensure that no LC_ variables are set:
$ env | grep ^LC_

4. If any variables are set, unset them using a blank export for each variable:
$ export <LC_VARIABLE_NAME>=

5. Start the seed VM:
$ HP_VM_MODE=y bash -x ~root/tripleo/tripleo-incubator/scripts/hp_ced_start_seed.sh

The process of starting the seed will take 5-10 minutes, or possibly longer depending on the capabilities of your system. There is currently a substantial amount of script/debug output that will be disabled in the final
customer version.

Allow the process to continue; you may need to ignore a password prompt for a few minutes, then just hit return until the seed setup continues.

Once the seed has completed its setup processing, you can proceed to the second stage, which is to deploy and configure the undercloud and overcloud, and to start a test guest VM in the overcloud compute node.

$ ssh 192.0.2.1 bash -x ~root/tripleo/tripleo-incubator/scripts/hp_ced_installer.sh

####What are the minimum and maximum number of configurations allowed? #### {#minimumandmaximumconfigs}

The minimum configuration is seven physical servers:

* One VM for the seed 
* One undercloud server
* Three overcloud management servers
* Two Swift object servers
* One compute Server

The maximum supported configuration is 36 servers. 

####How do I install and set up the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition Admin Node? #### {#installandsetup}

It is recommended to install the Admin Node on a virtual machine only. 
Here are general guidelines for creating a virtual machine in an existing or new hypervisor infrastructure:

1. Configure the hypervisor host's network. The host must provide connectivity to the virtual machine Admin Node on an isolated private network 
to all the baremetal nodes' port eth0. And the virtual machine Admin Node must also have connectivity to a routable network for Internet access.

2. Create a virtual machine Admin Node with the suggested hardware configuration. The following configuration must be reviewed during this step:

    a. Ensure the virtual machine Admin Node's primary NIC is bridged or connected to the admin network and the second NIC is bridged or connected to a routable network for Internet access.

    b. For the disk configuration, the default Disk bus type/controller uses proprietary technology. Ensure you set that to the IDE/SCSI type.
 
    c. If your hypervisor is KVM, ensure the virt type is set to KVM.
 
3. Download the HPE Cloud OS ISO to the host's local file system or data store.

4. Configure the virtual machine Admin Node to point to the ISO as a CD/DVD drive or install media ISO image. 

####I've installed the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition. Now what? #### {#NowWhat}

####How long does it take to install the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition? #### {#Howlonginstallation} 


####Should I reboot after installation? #### {#rebootafterinstallation} 

####How do I verify that the installation has succeeded? #### {verifyinstallsucceed}

<b><font color="red"> Raj:We will provide a simple means of running a set of tests to act as a health check </font></b>

## Setting up the seed VM 

####What is a seed? #### {#Whatisseed}

The seed machine is a single node that is effectively just an installer.  Its sole purpose is to create the undercloud, and that is all.  This is the equivalent of your workstation, laptop, or maybe staff-shell (if you ever used it).  It uses nova, glance and heat to install the undercloud.

This is not a full OpenStack installation; it is a cut-down installation providing only the software required in order to enable the installation of the undercloud onto physical systems in the data center.

####How do I create a VM for the Seed based on the CloudOS specifications? #### {#createVM} 

####How do I load a under cloud image into the seed VM? #### {#imageseedcloud} 

####How do I log into the seed VM and deploy the undercloud? #### {#deployUC}   

### Setting up the undercloud and overcloud

####What is an undercloud? #### {#Whatisundercloud}

The undercloud is what you use as an administer to maintain the hardware.  It installs physical machines using nova and the baremetal or ironic driver (in the same way that it was installed from the seed). It then uses heat to deploy and configure the resulting booted systems, which is analogous to the use of Chef in HPE Public Cloud.  The sole purpose of the undercloud is to administer the physical machines in the data center for the purpose of making them run an OpenStack cloud.

This is not a full OpenStack installation, it is a cut-down installation providing only the software required in order to enable the installation of the overcloud onto physical systems in the data center.

####What is an overcloud? #### {#Whatisovercloud}

This is the HPE Public Cloud.  This is the OpenStack installation that you will interact with in the same way you interact with the HPE Public Cloud.  This is where the web interface will be housed, and the cloud in which all instances will be created/objects stored/volumes created etc.

This is a full and feature-rich OpenStack installation.

####How do I set up the disk configurations of the undercloud and overcloud servers? #### {#UCOCservers}

####How do I configure the physical network connecting the undercloud and overcloud servers? #### {#physicalnetwork}

####How do I install the overcloud? #### {#installOC}

####How do I verify the functionality of the overcloud? #### {#verifyOC}

####How do I deploy a software update to the overcloud? #### {#updateOC}

####How do I add a compute node to the overcloud? #### {#computenode}

###Understanding how to use the Dashboard UI 

####How do I launch the HPE Helion OpenStack Community Dashboard? #### {#launchtheDashboard}

After you boot from the HPE Cloud OS ISO, you are ready to launch the Operational Dashboard to set up the Admin Node.

To launch the Operational Dashboard:

1. Get the IP address of your main control plane node via <b><font color="red"><yet to be defined process></font></b>
2. Open a web browser pointing to the IP address.
3. Log in as the 'admin' user using the admin password provided via <b><font color="red"><yet to be defined process></b>
pre-defined login creds: I cannot comment at this point. The admin password MAY be hard-coded into 
images provided, or MAY be randomly generated during install.
Note - don't refer to &#8220;ZIP&#8221;  files. I doubt we'll use the zip format.<.font></b>



####What are the key actions I can perform within the Dashboard? ####{#DashboardActions} 

## Managing the overcloud

### Getting started with overcloud

####What are the identity operations (Keystone) that I need to perform?] ####{#identityoperations}

####What are the compute operations (Nova) I need to perform? #### {#computeoperations}  

### Managing the overcloud: Users 

####How do I create a VM? #### {#createVM}

####How do I create a VM that boots from a volume? #### {#VMboot} 

####How do I reboot a VM?] #### {#VMreboot} 

####How do I rebuild a VM? #### {#VMrebuild} 

####How do I start a VM? #### {#VMstart}

####How do I stop a VM? #### {#VMstop}

####How do I create a snapshot of a VM? #### {#VMsnapshot}

####How do I rescue a VM? #### {#VMrescue} 

####How do I unrescue a VM? #### {#VMunrescue}

####How do I delete a VM? #### {#VMdelete} 

####How do I attach a volume to or from a VM? #### {#VMattachvolume} 

####How do I detach a volume to or from a VM? #### {#VMdetachvolume} 

####How do I get the console log of a VM? #### {#VMconsolelog} 

####How do I get the VNC connection to a VM? #### {#VMVNC}

####How do I create a security group? #### {#createsecuritygroup}

####How do I edit or delete security group? #### {#deletesecuritygroup}

####How do I create a key pair? #### {#createkeypair}

####How do I edit or delete a key pair? #### {#deletekeypair}

####How do I associate or disassociated a floating IP address? #### {#IPaddress} 

### Managing the overcloud: Administrators 

####How do I create a flavor? #### {#createflavor}

####How do I edit or delete a flavor? #### {#deleteflavor}

####How do I modify the ACL of a flavor? #### {#modifyflavor}

####How do I modify the quota of a project? #### {#projectquota}

####How do I modify the quota of a user within a project? #### {#userquota}

####How do I create an availability zone? #### {#addzone}  

####How do I edit or delete an availability zone? #### {#deletezone} 

####How do I create an aggregate? #### {#createaggregate} 

####How do I edit or delete an aggregate? #### {#deleteaggregate} 

####How do I enable or disable a service? #### {#enableservice} 

####How do I lock or unlock a VM? #### {#lockVM} 

####How do I pause or unpause a VM? #### {#pauseVM}

####How do I suspend or Resume a VM? #### {#resumeVM}<b><font color="red">(Is this a different use case from the one above?)</font></b>

## Managing the network operations

### Managing the network operations: Users

####How do i create a network? #### {#createnetwork}
####How do I edit or delete a network? #### {#deletenetwork}
####How do I add a router? #### {#addrouter}
####How do I edit or delete a router? #### {#deleterouter} 
####How do I add subnet to a network? #### {#addsubnet} 
####How do I delete a subnet from a network? #### {#deletesubnet}
####How do I add a network to a router? #### {#networkrouter}
####How do I delete a network from a router? #### {#removerouter}
####How do I add an external network to a router? #### {#externalrouter}
####How do I remove an external network from a router? #### {#removeexternalnetwork}
####How do I create a port on a network? #### {#createport} 
####How do I edit or delete a port on a network? #### {#deleteport} 
####How do I allocate a floating IP address? #### {#allocatefloating} 
####How do I deallocate a floating IP address? #### {#deallocatefloating}
####How do I associate a floating IP address to a fixed IP address? #### {#floatingIPaddress}
####How do I disassociate a floating IP address from a fixed IP address? #### {#fixedIPaddress}
####How do i create a security group? #### {#createsecuritygroup} 
####How do i edit or delete a security group #### {#deletesecuritygroup} 
####How do I create a security group rule? #### {#createrule}
####How do I edit or delete a security group rule? #### {#deleterule}  

### Managing the network operations: Administrators
 
####How do create an external network? #### {#externalnetwork}
####How do I edit the quota values of a project? #### {#quotavalues}
####How do I add a network to a DHCP agent? #### {#DHCPagent) 
####How do I remove a network from a DHCP agent? #### {#removenetwork} 
####How do I add a router to a L3 agent? #### {#L3agent} 
####How do I remove a router from a L3 agent? #### {#removeL3agent} 

## Managing Collections and Reports 

### Managing Collections 

####How do I record metering data? #### {#recorddata}

####How do I create an alarm? #### {#createalarm}

####How do I edit or delete an alarm? #### {#deletealarm} 

####How do I record alarm change? #### {#alarmchange}

####How do I record a metering event? #### {#recordevent}

####How do I clear expired metering data? #### {#expireddata} 

### Managing Reports 

####What types of measurements do I have access to? #### {#measurementtypes}

####Where can I get usage data for a specific meter? #### {#usagedata}

####Where can I find the computed statistics for a sample within a specific time range?#### {#sampletimerange}

####Where can I access a list of resources? #### {#accesslist}

####Where can I find the resource details? #### {#resourcedetails}

####Where can I see the API capabilities supported by the current driver? #### {#currentdriver} 

####How can I filter and view alarms? #### {#filterview}

####Where can I find the details on a specific alarm? #### {#alarmdetails}

####Where can I Get the history of a specific alarm? #### {#alarmhistory} 

####Where can I find alarm status? #### {#alarmstatus}  

## Managing Image Operations

### Managing Image operations: Users

####How do I create a private image? #### {#createimage}

####How to I edit or delete a private image? #### {#deleteimage}

####How do I add or update metadata for a private image? #### {#updatemetadata}   

### Managing Image operations: Administrators 

####How do I create a public image? #### {#createpublicimage}

####How do I edit or delete a public image? #### {#deletepublicimage}

####How do I add or update metadata for a public image? #### {#addmetadatapublicimage}

## Managing Volume Operations (Cinder)

### Managing Volume Operations: Users

####How do I create a volume? #### {#createvolume}

####How do I delete a volume? #### {#deletevolume}

####How do I create a bootable volume from an image in glance? #### {#bootablevolume}

####How do I create a snapshot of a volume? #### {#createsnapshot} 

####How do I delete a snapshot of a volume? #### {#deletesnapshot}

####How do I create a backup of a volume in swift? #### {#createvolumebackup}

####How do I delete a backup of a volume in swift? #### {#deletevolumebackup}

####How do I create a volume from a backup in swift? #### {#createvolumebackup}

####How do I update the metadata of a volume? #### {#updatemetadatavolume} 

####How do I create an image in glance from a volume? #### {#createimageglance} 

####How do I rename a volume? #### {#renamevolume}

####How do I extend a volume? #### {#extendvolume}

####How do I transfer a volume between users? #### {#transfervolume}
 
### Managing Volume Operations: Administrators 
#### How do I modify the quota values of a project? #### {#modifyquota}
#### How do I enable or disable a service? #### {#enableservice}

## Managing Object operations (swift)

### Managing Object operations:Users

####How do I create a container? #### {#createcontainer)

####How do I edit or delete a container? #### {#deletecontainer)

####How do I upload files into a container? #### {#uploadcontainer)

####How do I download files from a container? #### {#downloadcontainer) 

####How do I delete files in a container? #### {#deletefiles)

##Updating the HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition 

####How can I update the HPE Cloud software? #### {#updatesoftware}

####What will future releases of HPE Helion OpenStack Community edition include? #### {#FutureReleases}

####Where can I access release notes? #### {#ReleaseNotes}

##Support and Troubleshooting 

####I'm stuck. Where can I get more help? #### {#gethelp} 

<b><font color="red">Need more info Raj / Gavin</font></b> 

Please visit http:/community.hpcloud.com or  ...

####Where can I go to find more information? #### {#moreinformation}

<b><font color="red">Need more info from Raj / Gavin</font></b>

* HPE Cloud sales portal  
* [HPE Hybrid Cloud Management](https://hp.com/go/cloudmanagement) 
* Download the white paper
* Download the customer-facing presentation
* Watch the video 

####How can I contact HPE Cloud Customer Support? #### {#contacts}

-->
<p>
  <xref href="#topic9044"> Return to Top </xref>
</p>
<!-- ===================== horizontal rule ===================== -->
</section>
</body>
</topic>
