<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="topic_ask_vgb_dv">
 <title>支持资源</title>
 <para>
  要解决您的云的问题，请参阅知识库或联系
  &serviceteam;。
 </para>
 <section xml:id="kb">
  <title>使用知识库</title>
  <para vendor="hpe">
   The public knowledge base for &kw-hos-phrase; can be reached at
   <link xlink:href="http://h20566.www2.hpe.com/portal/site/hpsc/public/psi/home/?sp4ts.oid=7261055#topIssuesAndSolution">Hewlett Packard Enterprise Support Center - &productname;</link>.
  </para>
  <para vendor="hpe">
   You can look through the top issues or search for the specific issue you are
   experiencing. Knowledge documents listed with the content type
   <literal>Knowledge Centered Support</literal> are made by HPE TS Support
   cloud CoE engineers. If you do not find your issue listed then we suggest
   you contact support directly.
  </para>
  <para vendor="suse">
   有关支持信息，请访问 &suse; 支持页面 <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/suse-openstack-cloud/"/>。此页面提供对知识库，论坛和文档的访问。
  </para>
 </section>
 <section vendor="suse">
  <title>联系和 &suse; 支持</title>
  <para>
   有关访问和使用 &suse; 技术支持的信息，请访问<link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/handbook/"/>。此页面包含许多在线支持服务的指南和链接，例如支持帐户管理，事件报告，问题报告，功能请求，培训，咨询。
  </para>
 </section>
 <section vendor="hpe" xml:id="idg-all-operations-troubleshooting-contacting_support-xml-5">
  <title>Contacting the HPE TS Support Cloud CoE</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Call the HPE Support Number</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   Once you have registered for HPE TS Support you will be mailed a Service
   Agreement ID (SAID) and a phone number to call (www.hpe.com/contact). HPE
   customers with a Datacenter Care for Cloud contract will have to use their
   designated contact number. You can use that phone number to log support
   requests. Please have your SAID number available when calling. The support
   agent will log a case with the information you provide and the case will be
   sent to the HPE TS Support Cloud CoE Team. The response time will depend on
   the service level agreement (SLA) in place.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Electronic Case Logging</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   There is the option of visiting the
   <link xlink:href="http://www.hpe.com/support/hpesc">HPE
   Support Center</link> to log a support case via the website. You will be
   asked to setup and provide a PIN code for correct routing of your support
   case to the HPE TS Support Cloud CoE team. Use your HPE Passport and your
   Service Agreement ID (SAID) to electronically log your support case.
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
