<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<chapter id="log-management">
 <title>Log Management</title>
 <para>
  Services and servers in a cloud infrastructure generate huge amounts of log
  data, from simply announcing that everything is healthy to detailed
  information on events or processes. The logs are distributed over many
  physical and virtual servers. <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud
  Monitoring</phrase> collects, stores, and queries these logs and makes them
  accessible to <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> users in one
  central place.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> covers all aspects of an
  enterprise-class log management solution:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Central management of log data from medium and large-size OpenStack
    deployments.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Buffered exchange of log data to provide high data throughput.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Logical isolation of log data through multi-tenancy.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Scalable architecture capable of mastering the data load from a large
    number of nodes in OpenStack environments. The log management solution can
    be horizontally and vertically adapted to constantly changing data loads.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  For managing the log data of your services and the virtual and physical
  servers on which they are provisioned, <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud
  Monitoring</phrase> integrates with Kibana, an open source analytics and
  visualization platform. <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> uses
  Kibana as a front-end application to the log data held in the Elasticsearch
  database.
 </para>
 <para>
  Kibana allows you to easily understand large data volumes. Based on the data
  that is stored in Elasticsearch indices, you can perform advanced data
  analysis and visualize your log data in a variety of charts, tables, or maps.
  Changes to the Elasticsearch indices are displayed in <phrase>SUSE OpenStack
  Cloud Monitoring</phrase> in real time.
 </para>
 <para>
  The log management features of <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud
  Monitoring</phrase> include:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Features for searching, visualizing, and analyzing the log data.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Alerting features for monitoring.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  In the following sections, you will find information on the Log Management
  Window where you search, visualize, and analyze your log data, as well as
  details on how to use the alerting features.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Accessing <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase>
 </bridgehead>
 <para>
  For accessing <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> and performing
  log management tasks, the following prerequisites must be fulfilled:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You must have access to the OpenStack platform as a user with the
    <literal>monasca-user</literal> role.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You must be assigned to the OpenStack project you want to monitor.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  Log in to OpenStack Horizon with your user name and password. The functions
  you can use in OpenStack Horizon depend on your access permissions. To access
  logs and metrics, switch to the <guilabel>monasca</guilabel> tenant in
  Horizon.
 </para>
 <para>
  The <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> functionality is
  available on the <guilabel>Monitoring</guilabel> tab. It provides access to
  the log data of all projects to which you are assigned. The <guilabel>Log
  Management</guilabel> option at the top border of the
  <guilabel>Overview</guilabel> page displays the log management window where
  you can work on the log data.
 </para>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="soc-monitoring-operations-log-manage-window.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="soc-monitoring-operations-index-patterns.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="soc-monitoring-operations-monitoring-log-data.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="soc-monitoring-operations-troubleshooting.xml"/>
</chapter>
