<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<topic id="CS_Ops_Compute_Sum_Sum">
    <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title-10"/>Compute Summary</title>
    <shortdesc>This page provides cards that are a visual representation of compute host usage or allocation.</shortdesc>
    <body>
        <p>This page provides cards that are a visual representation of compute host usage or allocation.</p>
        <p> <b>Compute Host Summary</b> </p>   
        <ul>
                <li>Total number of compute hosts and number of compute hosts that are <b>Up</b>,
                    <b>Unknown</b>, and <b>Down</b>.</li>
                <li>Click to open the <b>Compute Hosts</b> screen.</li>
            </ul>
        <p><b>Virtual CPU</b></p>
            <ul>
                <li>Number of CPU cores designated for instances.</li>
                <li>CPU allocation expressed as a percentage.</li>
            </ul>
        
        <p><b>Virtual Memory</b></p> 
            <ul>
                <li>Amount of memory designated for instances.</li>
                <li>Memory allocation expressed as a percentage.</li>
            </ul>
        
        <p><b>Virtual Storage</b></p> 
            <ul>
                <li>Amount of compute storage designated for instances.</li>
                <li>Compute storage allocation expressed as a percentage.</li>
            </ul>
            
        <p><b>Compute Hosts Status</b></p>
            <ul>
                <li>Total number of compute hosts and number of compute hosts that have a reported
                status of <b>OK</b>, <b>Warning</b>, <b>Error</b>, and <b>Unknown</b>.</li>
            </ul> 
            
        <p><b>CPU usage</b></p>
            <ul>
                <li>Number of actual CPU cores consumed by instances in the last polling cycle.</li>
                <li>CPU utilization expressed as a percentage.</li>
                <li>A high percentage indicates that processes running on the device are consuming a considerable amount of CPU resources. If the percentage appears frozen at or near 100%, a process might not be responding.</li>
            </ul>
        
        <p><b>Memory usage</b></p>
            <ul>
                <li>Amount of actual memory consumed by instances in the last polling cycle.</li>
                <li>Memory utilization expressed as a percentage.</li>
            </ul>
        
        <p><b>Disk usage</b></p>
            <ul>
                <li>Amount of actual compute storage consumed by instances in the last polling cycle.</li>
                <li>Compute storage utilization expressed as a percentage.</li>
            </ul>
            
        <p><b>Instances history</b></p>
            <ul>
                <li>Number of instances created and deleted per day in the past seven days.</li>
                <li>The numbers below the graph are the average number of instances created and deleted in the past seven days.</li>
            </ul>
    </body>
</topic>
