<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.1">
  <title>Getting Involved</title>
  <para>The OpenStack community is a very friendly group and there are places online to
            join in with the community. Feel free to ask questions. This document points
            you to some of the places where you can communicate with people.</para>
  <section>
    <title>How to Join the Community</title>
    <para>Our community welcomes all people interested in open source cloud computing,
                and there are no formal membership requirements. The best way to join the
                community is to talk with others online or at a meetup and offer contributions
                through <link xlink:href="https://launchpad.net/keystone">Launchpad</link>, the <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/">wiki</link>, or blogs. We welcome all types of contributions,
                from blueprint designs to documentation to testing to deployment scripts.</para>
    <section>
      <title>#openstack-keystone on Freenode IRC Network</title>
      <para>You can find Keystone folks in <link xlink:href="irc://freenode.net/#openstack-keystone"/>.
                    This is usually the best place to ask questions and find your way around. IRC
                    stands for Internet Relay Chat and it is a way to chat online in real time.
                    You can also ask a question and come back to the log files to read the answer
                    later. Logs for the #openstack IRC channels are stored at
                    <link xlink:href="http://eavesdrop.openstack.org/irclogs/"/>.</para>
      <para>For more information regarding OpenStack IRC channels please visit the
                    <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/IRC">OpenStack IRC Wiki</link>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>OpenStack Wiki</title>
      <para>The wiki is a living source of knowledge. It is edited by the community, and
                    has collections of links and other sources of information. Typically the pages
                    are a good place to write drafts for specs or documentation, describe a
                    blueprint, or collaborate with others.</para>
      <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/">OpenStack Wiki</link>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/Keystone">useful Keystone project links</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Keystone on Launchpad</title>
      <para>Launchpad is a code hosting that OpenStack is using to track bugs, feature
                    work, and releases of OpenStack. Like other OpenStack projects, Keystone source
                    code is hosted on git.openstack.org</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xlink:href="https://launchpad.net/keystone">Keystone Project Page on Launchpad</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link xlink:href="https://git.openstack.org/cgit/openstack/keystone">Keystone Source Repository</link>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Within launchpad, we use
                    <link xlink:href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/keystone">blueprints</link>, to track feature
                    work, and track <link xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/keystone">bugs</link> as well. If
                    you are looking for a place to get started contributing to keystone, please
                    look at any bugs for Keystone that are tagged as <link xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/keystone/+bugs?field.tag=low-hanging-fruit">low-hanging-fruit</link>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>OpenStack Blog</title>
      <para>The OpenStack blog includes a weekly newsletter that aggregates OpenStack news
                    from around the internet, as well as providing inside information on upcoming
                    events and posts from OpenStack contributors.</para>
      <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://openstack.org/blog">OpenStack Blog</link>
      </para>
      <para>See also: <link xlink:href="http://planet.openstack.org/">Planet OpenStack</link>, an aggregation of
                    blogs about OpenStack from around the internet, combined into a web site and
                    RSS feed. If you’d like to contribute with your blog posts, there are
                    instructions for <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/AddingYourBlog">adding your blog</link>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Twitter</title>
      <para>Because all the cool kids do it: <link xlink:href="http://twitter.com/openstack">@openstack</link>.
                    Also follow the <link xlink:href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23openstack">#openstack</link>
                    tag for relevant tweets.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
