<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="freezerUI">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Backup/Restore Via the Horizon UI</title>
  <body><!--not tested-->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    <section>
      <p>A number of backup and restore tasks can be performed using the Horizon UI. This topic
        lists the available tasks, the access requirements, and limitations of using Horizon for
        backup and restore.</p> 
    </section>

              
    <section><title>Accessing the UI</title>The Backup/Recovery features can be accessed via the
      Horizon Web UI. The Web UI functionality in this release is a non-core/technical preview
      feature. </section>

 


    <section id="access">
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>User name</dt>
          <dd>The only supported user in this version is "hlm_backup". The login credentials are
            available in <codeph>backup.osrc</codeph> located at
              <codeph>/home/stack/backup.osrc/</codeph>
            <note>The location of backup.osrc has now changed from the old location of
              /opt/stack/service/freezer-agent/etc/backup.osrc.</note></dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>UI access</dt>
          <dd> To access the Horizon UI, follow the instructions shown in <xref
              href="../operations/cloudadmin_dashboard.dita#cloudadmin_gui"/>. Once logged in as
            "hlm_backup", navigate to "Disaster Recovery" panel located in the left-hand menu where
            you should see "Backup and Restore."</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
    </section>


    <section id="operations"><title>Backup and Restore Operations Supported in the UI</title> The
      following Operations are supported via the UI <ul>
        <li>Ability to create new jobs to Backup/Restore files </li>
        <li>List the freezer jobs that have completed </li>
        <li>Create sessions to link multiple jobs </li>
        <li>List the various nodes ( hosts/servers) on which the freezer-scheduler and freezer agent
          are installed </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Limitations</title> The following limitations apply to Freezer backups in <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>: <p>
        <ul>
          <li>The UI for backup and restore is supported only if you log in as "hlm_backup". All
            other users will see the UI panel but the UI will not work. </li>
          <li>If Backup/Restore action fails via the UI, you must check the Freezer logs for details
            of the failure.</li>
          <li>Job Status and Job Result on the UI and backend (CLI) are not in sync. </li>
          <li>For a given "Action" the following modes are not supported from the UI:<ul
              id="ul_igj_tyl_j5">
              <li>MongoDB</li>
              <li>Microsoft SQL Server</li>
              <li>Cinder</li>
              <li>Nova</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li> There is a known issue which will be fixed in future releases while using Start and
            End dates and times in creating a job. Please refrain from using those fields. </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section id="WalkThrough" >
      <title>Dashboard Walkthrough of Backup and Restore</title>
      <p>The following video walks through the Horizon dashboard menus and options available for creating backup and restore jobs. </p>
      <sectiondiv  outputclass="DashboardWalkThrough">
        <!-- Used to load the video content via javascript -->
        <p><image href="../../media/video/Horizon/HorizonBackupOverview.png" id="DashboardWalkThrough" /></p>
      </sectiondiv>  
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
