<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_bxm_gxr_st">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Default Automatic Backup Jobs</title>
  <body><!--not tested-->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    <p>By default, the following are <b>automatically</b> backed up. You do not have to do anything
      for these backup jobs to run. However if you want to back up to somewhere outside the cluster,
      you do need to <xref href="cloud_control_plane_backup.xml#topic_jsc_qps_qt">set up SSH
        backups</xref>.<ul>
        <li>All important information on the lifecycle manager</li>
        <li>MySQL database. In the MySQL database is most of the data you need to restore services.
          ESX and Ceph data recovery is not complete, but for other services you will have the data
          you need to recover. Logging data in elastic search is not backed up. Swift objects are
          not backed up because of the redundant nature of Swift.</li>
        <li>Swift rings. Swift rings are backed up so that you can recover more quickly even though
          Swift can rebuild the rings without this data. However automatically rebuilding the rings
          is slower than restoring via a backup.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>The following services will be effectively backed up. In other words, the data needed to
      restore the services is backed up. The critical data that will be backed up are the databases
      and the configuration-related files. Note the data that is not backed up per service:<ul>
        <li>Ceilometer. However, there is no backup of metrics data</li>
        <li>Cinder. However, there is no backup of the volumes</li>
        <li>Glance. However, there is no backup of the images</li>
        <li>Heat</li>
        <li>Horizon</li>
        <li>Keystone</li>
        <li>Neutron</li>
        <li>Nova. However, there is no backup of the images</li>
        <li>Swift. However, there is no backup of the objects. Swift has its own high
          availability/redundancy. Swift rings are backed up. Although Swift will rebuild the rings
          itself, restoring from backup is faster.</li>
        <li>Operations Console</li>
        <li>Monasca. However, there is no backup of the metrics</li>
      </ul></p>
    <section/>
    
    <section>
      <title>Limitations</title> The following limitations apply to backups created by the Freezer
      backup and restore service in <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>: <p>
        <ul>
          <li>Recovery of the following services (or cloud topologies) will be partially backed up.
            They will need additional data (other than the data stored in MySQL) to return to fully functional.<ul>
              <li>ESX Cloud</li>
              <li>Ceph Cloud</li>
              <li>Network services - LBaaS and VPNaaS</li>
            </ul></li>
          <li>Logging data (that is, log files).</li>
          <li>VMs and volumes are not currently backed up.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
