<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="config_vsa">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Configuring for VSA Block Storage
    Backend</title>
  <abstract><shortdesc outputclass="hdphidden">Installation and configuration steps for your VSA
      backend.</shortdesc>This page describes how to configure your VSA backend for the Helion
    Entry-scale with KVM cloud model. This procedure can be performed during or after
    installation.</abstract>
  <body>
    <!-- Joel tested on 4/30/2016 -->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>

    <section id="prereq"><title>Prerequisites</title>
      <p><ul>
          <li>Your <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> cloud must be fully deployed using the a KVM cloud
            model with VSA added. The Entry-Scale KVM with VSA cloud model is an example of such a
            model. For more details on the installation refer to <xref href="installing_kvm.xml"
            />.</li>
          <li>It's important that all of your systems have the correct date/time because the HPE
            StoreVirtual VSA license has a start date. If the start date is later than the system
            time then the installation will fail.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section>

    <section id="notes"><title>Notes</title>
      <p>
        <ul id="ul_kg4_y3k_5v">
          <li>The license for the HPE StoreVirtual VSA license is bundled with <keyword
              keyref="kw-hos"/> and comes with a free trial which allows a maximum limit of 50 TB
            per node. Hence the total amount of the configured storage on an individual VSA node
            should not exceed 50 TB. To extend the 50 TB per node limit, you can add nodes. A VSA
            cluster can support up to 16 nodes, which means configured storage on a VSA cluster can
            be as much as 800 TB. <note type="notice">The HPE StoreVirtual VSA default license is
              for five (5) years with all supported functionality detailed above. During
              installation, the CMC utility may display a message that some features are not
              licensed. This message displays in error and can be ignored.</note>
            <!-- this para for HOS -->
            <p product="HOS">You can deploy VSA with Adaptive Optimization (AO) or without. The
              deployment process for each of these options is similar, you just need to make a
              change in the disk input model. For more detailed information, refer to <b>VSA with or
                without Adaptive Optimization (AO)</b> in <xref
                href="../architecture/modify/modify_entryscale_kvm_vsa.xml#modify_entryscale_kvm_vsa"
              />.</p>
            <!-- this para for CG -->
            <!--<p product="CG">You can deploy VSA with Adaptive Optimization (AO) or without. The
              deployment process for each of these options is similar, you just need to make a
              change in the disk input model. For more detailed information, refer to <b>VSA with or
                without Adaptive Optimization (AO)</b> in <xref href="configure_vsa_ao.xml"
            />.</p>--></li>
          <li>A single VSA node can have a maximum of seven raw disks (excluding the operating
            system disks) attached to it, which is defined in the disk input model for your VSA
            nodes. It is expected that no more than seven disks are specified (including Adaptive
            Optimization disks) per VSA node. For example, if you want to deploy VSA with two disks
            for Adaptive Optimization then your disk input model should not specify more than five
            raw disks for data and two raw disks for Adaptive Optimization. Exceeding the disk limit
            causes VSA deployment failure.</li>
          <li>You can create more than one VSA cluster of same or different type by specifying the
            configuration in cloud model. For more details, refer to <xref
              href="../operations/blockstorage/vsa/create_multiple_vsa_clusters.xml"/>.</li>
          <li>Usernames and passwords designated during VSA configuration or repair must be alphabetic only.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p id="multibackend"><b>Concerning using multiple backends:</b> If you are using multiple
        backend options, ensure that you specify each of the backends you are using when configuring
        your <codeph>cinder.conf.j2</codeph> file using a comma delimited list. An example would be
          <codeph>enabled_backends=vsa-1,3par_iSCSI,ceph1</codeph> and is included in the steps
        below. You will also want to create multiple volume types so you can specify which backend
        you want to utilize when creating volumes. These instructions are included below as well. In
        addition to our documentation, you can also read the OpenStack documentation at <xref
          href="http://docs.openstack.org/admin-guide/blockstorage_multi_backend.html"
            format="html">Configure multiple storage backends</xref> as well.</p>
      <p><b>VSA driver has updated name:</b> In the OpenStack Mitaka release, the VSA driver used
        for HPE Helion integration had its name updated from <codeph>hplefthand_</codeph> to
          <codeph>hpelefthand_</codeph>. To prevent issues when upgrading from previous <keyword
          keyref="kw-hos"/> releases, we left the names as-is in the release and provided a mapping
        so that the integration would continue to work. This will produce a warning in the
          <codeph>cinder-volume.log</codeph> file advising you of the deprecated name. The warning
        will look similar to
        this:<codeblock>Option "hplefthand_username" from group "&lt;your section>" is deprecated. Use option "hpelefthand_username" from group "&lt;your section>"
should be ignored.</codeblock></p>
      <p>These are just warnings and can be ignored.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="create_cluster">
      <title>Configure HPE StoreVirtual VSA</title>
      <p>The process for configuring HPE StoreVirtual VSA for <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> involves
        two major steps:</p>
      <p>
        <ul id="ul_kbm_n3k_5v">
          <li>Creating a cluster</li>
          <li>Configuring VSA as the block storage backend</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>You can perform these tasks in an automated process using the provided Ansible playbooks or
        manually using the HPE StoreVirtual Centralized Management Console (CMC) GUI.</p>
      <note>Using Ansible playbooks to create clusters is strongly recommended. Cluster creation
        using HPE StoreVirtual Centralized Management Console (CMC) GUI is deprecated in <keyword
          keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/>. Clusters created using CMC manually cannot be reconfigured using
        the Ansible playbooks. If you used CMC to create the clusters, you must continue to use CMC
        to administer those clusters.</note>
    </section>

    <section id="ansible"><title>Using Ansible</title>
      <p>Perform the following steps to create the cluster using the provided Ansible playbooks.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Log in to the lifecycle manager.</li>
        <li>Run the following playbook, which will both create your management group and your
          cluster:
          <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible/
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts vsalm-configure-cluster.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>When prompted, enter an administrative user name and password you will use to administer
          the CMC utility. <p>Administrative user naming requirements:</p><ul>
            <li>3 to 30 characters</li>
            <li>Must begin with a letter</li>
            <li>Allowed characters: 0-9, a-z, A-Z, hyphen (-), underline (_)</li>
            <li>Disallowed characters: Multibyte character set</li>
          </ul><p>Administrative user password requirements:</p><ul>
            <li>5 to 40 characters</li>
            <li>Must begin with a letter</li>
            <li>Many ASCII and extended ASCII characters, Multibyte character set</li>
            <li>Disallowed characters: dot (.), colon (:), forward slash (/), comma (,), backward
              slash (\), semi-colon (;), single-quote (‘), space ( ), equals (=)</li>
          </ul><note type="important">You will need to remember these values to access the cluster
            using the CMC utility or to re-run this playbook later if further management of your VSA
            system is needed. Do not change the credentials for one or more clusters using CMC as it
            will make the cluster automation playbook ignore those clusters for
            reconfiguration.</note></li>
        <li>In the output of the Ansible playbook you will see different steps where you can locate
          the values for your VSA cluster name, the virtual IP address, and the IP addresses of each
          of the VSA hosts in the cluster. You will use these values later when configuring your
            backend.<p>The following is an example, with the important information
            bolded.</p><p>This step displays the VSA cluster name and the virtual IP address of the
            cluster:<codeblock>TASK: [vsalm | _create_cluster | Display the status of cluster creation performed in above step] ***
ok: [helion-cp1-vsa0001-mgmt] => {
    "msg": "Created cluster - Name=<b>cluster-vsa</b>, IP=<b>10.13.111.142</b>"
}</codeblock></p></li>
        <li>You can view the added node to the cluster in CMC GUI as follows: <ol id="ol_r5f_ll3_wv">
            <li>Launch the CMC utility. See <xref href="#config_vsa/cmc" format="dita">Launching the
                CMC utility GUI</xref> for more details.</li>
            <li>Find the new VSA system. </li>
            <li>View the added node in the cluster.</li>
          </ol></li>
        <!--<li>Run the following command from your first controller node which will open the HPE
          StoreVirtual Centralized Management Console (CMC) GUI on your local machine:
          <codeblock>/opt/HP/StoreVirtual/UI/jre/bin/java -jar /opt/HP/StoreVirtual/UI/UI.jar</codeblock></li>
        <li>In the CMC GUI, click the Find menu and then select the Find Systems options.Once
          systems are found, new created clusters can been observed in CMC.</li>
        <li>In the CMC GUI, click the <b>Find</b> menu and then select the <b>Find Systems</b>
          options. <p>After the systems are found, the newly created clusters are displayed in
            CMC.</p><p>The management group name is automatically creating using the following
            pattern: <codeph>mg-&lt;resource-prefix></codeph></p><p>The cluster name is
            automatically creating using the following pattern:
              <codeph>cluster-&lt;resource-prefix></codeph></p></li>-->
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section id="cmc">
      <title outputclass="headerH">Using the CMC Utility</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection">
        <p>In <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>, cluster creation using HPE StoreVirtual Centralized
          Management Console (CMC) GUI is deprecated. The clusters created by CMC manually cannot be
          configured using Ansible playbooks.</p>
        <p>Perform the following steps to create the cluster using CMC.</p>
        <p id="launching-cmc-utility"><b>Launching the CMC utility GUI</b></p>
        <p>The HPE StoreVirtual Centralized Management Console (CMC) GUI is an interface where you
          can configure VSA. </p>
        <p>The CMC utility requires a GUI to access it. You can use either of the following methods
          to launch the CMC GUI.</p>
        <p>
          <ul>
            <li><xref href="#config_vsa/vnc" format="dita">RDP/VNC connect</xref></li>
            <li><xref href="#config_vsa/xming" format="dita">Any X Display Tool</xref></li>
          </ul>
        </p>
        <p><b>RDP/VNC connect method</b></p>
        <p id="vnc">Setup VNC connect on the Controller Node</p>
        <p>The following steps will allow you to setup a VNC connect to your controller node so you
          can view the GUI.</p>
        <ol>
          <li>Log in to your first controller node. </li>
          <li>Run the following command to install the package that is required to launch CMC:
            <codeblock>sudo apt-get install -y xrdp</codeblock></li>
          <li>Start <codeph>vnc4server</codeph> using the instructions below. You will be prompted
            for a password (min 6 characters). Enter a password and proceed. A sample output is
            shown below: <codeblock>stack@helion-cp1-c1-m1-mgmt:~$ vnc4server
            
You will require a password to access your desktops.
            
Password:
Verify:
xauth:  file /home/stack/.Xauthority does not exist
            
New 'helion-cp1-c1-m1-mgmt:3 (stack)' desktop is helion-cp1-c1-m1-mgmt:3
            
Creating default startup script /home/stack/.vnc/xstartup
Starting applications specified in /home/stack/.vnc/xstartup
Log file is /home/stack/.vnc/helion-cp1-c1-m1-mgmt:3.log</codeblock>
            <note>If you directly use xrdp to connect to the first controller node without using the
              VNC server then a remote session is created whenever you login. To avoid this, a
              dedicated VNC server instance is launched and connected to that instance by xrdp. This
              helps to maintain the session.</note></li>
          <li>Run <codeph>netstat -anp | grep vnc</codeph> to determine the public port that VNC is
            using. In the example below, the port is 5903: <codeblock>stack@helion-cp1-c1-m1-mgmt:~$ netstat -anp | grep vnc
(Not all processes could be identified, non-owned process info
will not be shown, you would have to be root to see it all.)
tcp        0      0 0.0.0.0:6003            0.0.0.0:*               LISTEN      1413/Xvnc4
tcp6       0      0 :::5903                 :::*                    LISTEN      1413/Xvnc4</codeblock><p>
              <note>If you reboot the controller node then you must repeat the steps <b>3</b> and
                  <b>4</b>.</note>
            </p></li>
          <li>Connect to your controller node through any remote desktop or VNC client. We will show
            the xrdp method first and the VNC method is below it: <ol>
              <li>Connecting through remote desktop client <ol>
                  <li>Login to your remote desktop. You will be prompted with xrdp login screen.<p>
                      <image href="../../media/vsa/xrdp1.PNG"/></p></li>
                  <li>Click the <b>Module</b> drop-down list and select
                        <codeph>vnc-any</codeph>.<p><image href="../../media/vsa/xrdp2.PNG"
                    /></p></li>
                  <li>Enter the IP address, port and password in the respective fields.<p><image
                        href="../../media/vsa/xrdp3.PNG"/></p></li>
                  <li>Click <b>Ok</b>.</li>
                </ol></li>
              <li>Connecting through a VNC client, such as <xref
                  href="https://www.realvnc.com/download/viewer/" format="html"  >VNC
                  Viewer</xref>: <ol>
                  <li>Enter the IP address and port and click <b>Connect</b>. You will be prompted
                    for your password once the connection is established. <p><image
                        href="../../media/vsa/vncview1.png"/></p></li>
                </ol></li>
            </ol>A terminal emulator will be displayed where you can enter the CMC launch command.
            Note that the CMC launch with this method will have the following limitations: by
            default, CMC-xterm disables all the title bars and borders. This is an expected
            behavior.</li>
        </ol>
        <p id="xming"><b>Install (any) X Display Tool </b><note>You can use SSH to an X server but
            the performance may be poor.</note></p>
        <p>You must configure an X display tool to launch CMC. User can select <b>any</b> X display
          tool. In this section we are using <b>Xming</b> tool as an example to launch CMC. The
          following example provides the steps to install Xming and launch CMC in a Windows
          environment. Another alternative (not shown in the documentation) is <xref
            href="http://mobaxterm.mobatek.net/"   format="html">MobaXterm</xref>. <ol>
            <li>Download and install <b>Xming</b> on a Windows machine that can access the lifecycle
              manager. You can download Xming from <xref
                href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/xming/" format="html"  
                >Sourceforge.net</xref>.</li>
            <li>Select <b>Enable X11 forwarding</b> checkbox on the PuTTy session for lifecycle
              manager. You can do this in PuTTY by: <ol>
                <li>Navigate to the <codeph>Connection -> SSH -> X11</codeph> option in PuTTy</li>
                <li>Click the <codeph>Enable X11 forwarding box to ensure it has a checkmark in
                    it</codeph></li>
              </ol>
              <p><image href="../../media/vsa/xming1.png"/></p>
            </li>
            <li>SSH to first control plane node. <codeblock>ssh -X</codeblock><p>and enter the CMC
                command (as mentioned below) to launch CMC.</p></li>
          </ol></p>
        <ol id="ol_yln_fhl_jt">
          <li>Run the following command from your first controller node which will open the CMC GUI
            on your local
              machine:<codeblock>/opt/HP/StoreVirtual/UI/jre/bin/java -jar /opt/HP/StoreVirtual/UI/UI.jar</codeblock><p>By
              default, the CMC GUI is configured to discover the VSA nodes in the subnet in which it
              is installed. This discovery functionality of VSA nodes using the CMC controller node
              is not supported in <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>. Instead, you must manually add each
              VSA node, as shown below.</p></li>
          <li>In the CMC GUI, click the <b>Find</b> menu and then select the <b>Find Systems</b>
            options. <p><image href="../../media/vsa/cmc1.png" id="image_dqt_p3k_5v"/></p>
          </li>
          <li>Click the <b>Add</b> button which will open the <b>Enter IP Address</b> dialogue box
            where you can enter the IP address of your VSA nodes which you noted earlier from your
              <codeph>~/scratch/ansible/next/my_cloud/stage/info/net_info.yml</codeph> file.
                <p><image href="../../media/vsa/cmc2.png" id="image_eqt_p3k_5v"/></p></li>
          <li>Once you have all of your VSA nodes entered, click the <b>Close</b> button. <p><image
                href="../../media/vsa/cmc3.png" id="image_fqt_p3k_5v"/></p></li>
          <li>Next, click the <b>Tasks</b> menu and then navigate to the <b>Management Group</b>
            submenu and select the <b>New Management Group</b> option. <p><image
                href="../../media/vsa/cmc4.png" id="image_gqt_p3k_5v"/></p></li>
          <li>In the Management Group wizard, click <b>Next</b> and then select <b>New Management
              Group</b> and then <b>Next</b> again to continue. <p><image
                href="../../media/vsa/cmc5.png" id="image_hqt_p3k_5v"/></p></li>
          <li>Enter a name in the <b>New Management Group Name</b> field and then click <b>Next</b>.
                <p><image href="../../media/vsa/cmc6.png" id="image_iqt_p3k_5v"/></p></li>
          <li>On the <b>Add Administrative User</b> you will enter a username and password you will
            use to administer the CMC utility. <p>
              <note type="important">You will need to remember these values as you will input them
                into your <codeph>cinder.conf.j2</codeph> file later.</note>
            </p>
            <p><image href="../../media/vsa/cmc7.png" id="image_jqt_p3k_5v"/></p></li>
          <li>Click <b>Next</b> to display the <b>Management Group Time</b> page.</li>
          <li>Add your NTP server information and click <b>Next</b>
            <p><image href="../../media/vsa/cmc8.png" id="image_kqt_p3k_5v"/></p></li>
          <li>Skip the DNS and SMTP sections. To do so, click <b>Next</b> and a popup will display
            where you can choose the <b>Accept Incomplete</b> option. Repeat this to skip SMTP
            section as well. <p><image href="../../media/vsa/cmc9.png" id="image_lqt_p3k_5v"
            /></p></li>
          <li>On the <b>Create a Cluster</b> options, select <b>Standard Cluster</b> from the
            displayed options and click <b>Next</b>. <p><image href="../../media/vsa/cmc10.png"
                id="image_mqt_p3k_5v"/></p></li>
          <li>In the <b>Cluster Name</b> field, enter a name for the cluster and click <b>Next</b>.
                <p><image href="../../media/vsa/cmc11.png" id="image_nqt_p3k_5v"/></p></li>
          <li>On the <b>Assign Virtual IPs and Subnet Masks</b> page, click <b>Add</b> and enter the
            virtual IP address and subnet mask of the cluster in the respective boxes and click
              <b>OK</b>. <note>The virtual IP address will be found as the
                <codeph>cluster_ip</codeph> value in your
                <codeph>~/scratch/ansible/next/my_cloud/stage/info/net_info.yml</codeph> file and
              your subnet mask will be the subnet address from the network your VSA nodes are
              attached to, usually your <codeph>MANAGEMENT</codeph> network.</note>
            <p><image href="../../media/vsa/cmc12.png" id="image_oqt_p3k_5v"/></p></li>
          <li>The CMC utility will verify the virtual IP address information and then you can click
            the <b>Next</b> button.</li>
          <li>Select the checkbox for <b>Skip Volume Creation</b> and click the <b>Finish</b> button
            which will display your VSA management cluster. <p><image
                href="../../media/vsa/cmc13.png" id="image_pqt_p3k_5v"/></p>Cluster creation using
            CMC takes approximately 10 minutes or longer.<note type="attention">You may get a pop-up
              notice telling you that your hostnames are not unique. This can be ignored by clicking
              the OK button.</note></li>
          <li>If this process is successful you will see a summary page at the end which outlines
            what you have completed. <p>
              <note type="important">You can create more than one VSA cluster of same or different
                type by specifying the configuration in cloud model. For more details, refer to
                Modifying Cloud Model to Create Multiple Clusters</note>
            </p></li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>




    <section id="config_backend">
      <title>Configure VSA as the Backend</title>
      <p>You will use the information you input to the CMC utility to configure your Cinder backend
        to use your VSA environment.</p>
      <p>To update your Cinder configuration to add VSA storage you must modify the
          <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud/config/cinder/cinder.conf.j2</codeph> file on your lifecycle
        manager as follows:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Log in to the lifecycle manager.</li>
        <li>Make the following changes to the
            <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud/config/cinder/cinder.conf.j2</codeph> file: <ol>
            <li>Add your VSA backend to the <codeph>enabled_backends</codeph> section: <codeblock># Configure the enabled backends
enabled_backends=vsa-1</codeblock>
              <note type="important">If you are using multiple backend types, you can use a comma
                delimited list here. For example, if you are going to use both VSA and Ceph
                backends, you would specify something like this:
                  <codeph>enabled_backends=vsa-1,ceph1</codeph>.</note></li>
            <li>[OPTIONAL] If you want your volumes to use a default volume type, then enter the
              name of the volume type in the <codeph>[DEFAULT]</codeph> section with the syntax
              below. <b>You will want to remember this value when you create your volume type in the
                next section.</b>
              <p>
                <note type="important">If you do not specify a default type then your volumes will
                  default to a non-redundant RAID configuration. It is recommended that you create a
                  volume type and specify it here that meets your environments needs.</note>
              </p>
              <codeblock>[DEFAULT]
# Set the default volume type
default_volume_type = &lt;your new volume type></codeblock></li>
            <li>Uncomment the <codeph>StoreVirtual (VSA) cluster</codeph> section and fill the
              values as per your cluster information. If you have more than one cluster, you will
              need to add another similar section with its respective values. In the following
              example only one cluster is added. <codeblock>[vsa-1]
hplefthand_password: &lt;vsa-cluster-password>
hplefthand_clustername: &lt;vsa-cluster-name>
hplefthand_api_url: https://&lt;vsa-cluster-vip>:8081/lhos
hplefthand_username: &lt;vsa-cluster-username>
hplefthand_iscsi_chap_enabled: false
volume_backend_name: &lt;vsa-backend-name>
volume_driver: cinder.volume.drivers.san.hp.hp_lefthand_iscsi.HPLeftHandISCSIDriver
hplefthand_debug: false</codeblock>
              <p>where:</p>
              <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_gc4_c5t_5t">
                <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <thead>
                    <row>
                      <entry>Value</entry>
                      <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <row>
                      <entry>hplefthand_password</entry>
                      <entry>Password entered during cluster creation in the CMC utility. If you
                        have chosen to encrypt this password, enter the value in this format: <codeblock>hplefthand_password: {{ '&#60;encrypted vsa-cluster-password>' | hos_user_password_decrypt }}</codeblock>
                        <p>See <xref href="../security/encrypted_storage.xml">Encryption of
                            Passwords and Sensitive Data</xref> for more details.<note
                            type="warning">The <codeph>hos_user_password_decrypt</codeph> filter is
                            applied to strings in <codeph>cinder.conf.j2</codeph>, even if the line
                            is commented out. So if you run a playbook on a
                              <codeph>cinder.conf.j2</codeph> file that has a commented out
                            encrypted password, and if the key in
                              <codeph>HOS_USER_PASSWORD_ENCRYPT_KEY</codeph> is not the one used to
                            encrypt the password, then the decryption will fail and the ansible play
                            will fail. Therefore you should not comment out any lines containing the
                              <codeph>hos_user_password_decrypt</codeph> filter, delete them
                            instead.</note></p></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>hplefthand_clustername</entry>
                      <entry>Name of the VSA cluster provided while creating a cluster in the CMC
                        utility.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>hplefthand_api_url</entry>
                      <entry>Virtual IP address of your VSA cluster, found in your
                          <codeph>~/scratch/ansible/next/my_cloud/stage/info/net_info.yml</codeph>
                        file.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>hplefthand_username</entry>
                      <entry>Username given during cluster creation in the CMC utility.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>hplefthand_iscsi_chap_enabled</entry>
                      <entry>If you set this option as <b>true</b> then the hosts will not be able
                        to access the storage without the generated secrets. And if you set this
                        option as <b>false</b> then no CHAP authentication is required for the ISCSI
                        connection.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>volume_backend_name</entry>
                      <entry>Name given to the VSA backend. You will specify this value later in the
                        Associate the Volume Type to a Backend steps.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>volume_driver</entry>
                      <entry>Cinder volume driver. Leave this as the default value for VSA.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>hplefthand_debug</entry>
                      <entry>If you set this option as true then the Cinder driver for the VSA will
                        generate logging in debug mode; these logging entries can be found in
                          <b>cinder-volume.log</b>.</entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </table>
              <p>[OPTIONAL] <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> supports VSA deployment for KVM
                hypervisor only but it can be used as pre-deployed (or out of the band deployed)
                Lefthand storage boxes or VSA appliances (running on ESX/hyper-v/KVM hypervisor). It
                also supports Cinder configuration of physical Lefthand storage device and VSA
                appliances. Depending upon your setup, you will have to edit the below section if
                your storage array is running LeftHand OS lower than version 11:</p>
              <codeblock>[&lt;unique-section-name>]
volume_driver=cinder.volume.drivers.san.hp.hp_lefthand_iscsi.HPLeftHandISCSIDriver
volume_backend_name=lefthand-cliq
san_ip=&lt;san-ip>
san_login=&lt;san_username>
If adding a password here, then the password can be encrypted using the
mechanism specified in the documentation. If the password has been encrypted
add the value and the hos_user_password_decrypt filter like so:
san_password= {{ '&lt;encrypted san_password>' | hos_user_password_decrypt }}
Note that the encrypted value has to be enclosed in quotes
If you choose not to encrypt the password then the unencrypted password
must be set as follows:
san_password=&lt;san_password>
san_ssh_port=16022
san_clustername=&lt;vsa-cluster-name>
volume_backend_name=&lt;vsa-backend-name></codeblock>
              <note type="attention">
                <p>Similar to your <codeph>hplefthand_password</codeph> in the previous example,
                  encryption for your <codeph>san_password</codeph> is supported. If you chose to
                  use encryption you would use the syntax below to express that: </p>
                <codeblock>san_password= {{ '&#60;encrypted san_password>' | hos_user_password_decrypt }}</codeblock>
                <p>See <xref href="../security/encrypted_storage.xml">Encryption of Passwords and
                    Sensitive Data</xref> for more details.</p>
              </note></li>
          </ol><note type="attention">Do not use <codeph>backend_host</codeph> variable in
              <codeph>cinder.conf</codeph> file. If <codeph>backend_host</codeph> is set, it will
            override the [DEFAULT]/host value which <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> is dependent
            on.</note></li>
        <li>Commit your configuration to a <xref href="using_git.xml">local repository</xref>:
            <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
git add -A
git commit -m "configured VSA backend"</codeblock><note>Before
            you run any playbooks, remember that you need to export the encryption key in the
            following environment variable:<codeph> export
              HOS_USER_PASSWORD_ENCRYPT_KEY=&lt;encryption key></codeph> See <xref
              href="installing_kvm.xml#install_kvm"/> for reference.</note></li>
        <li>Run the configuration processor:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Run the following command to create a deployment
          directory:<codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Run the Cinder Reconfigure Playbook:
          <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts cinder-reconfigure.yml</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section id="post_install"><title>Post-Installation Tasks</title>
      <p>After you have configured VSA as your Block Storage backend, here are some tasks you will
        want to complete:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><xref href="../operations/blockstorage/creating_voltype.xml">Create a Volume Type for
            your Volumes</xref></li>
        <li><xref href="verify_block_storage.xml#verify_block_storage/volume_verify">Verify Your
            Block Storage Configuration</xref></li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
