<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="F5_BIGIP_3600">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Integrating F5 BIG-IP with LBaaS</title>
  <body>
    <!--not tested-->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    <section id="F53600_about">
      <p>Adding F5 Networks products to your deployment can provide critical application delivery
        services consistently across the data center, private cloud, and public cloud. This allows
        hybrid users to experience the availability and performance they expect.</p>
      <p> The F5 Networks BIG-IP product family includes purpose-built hardware, software, and
        virtualized solutions. Depending on the appliance you use, one or more BIG-IP modules can be
        added to get the functionality your deployment requires.</p>
      <p>Creating an application centered strategy using F5 BIG-IP is supported in all of the
        following scenarios:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>architecting a private cloud</li>
        <li>migrating and re-architecting existing applications to a public cloud IbaaS (load
          balancing as a service) provider</li>
        <li>moving to Software as a Service (SaaS)</li>
        <li>deploying applications in a hybrid environment</li>
        <li>ensuring business continuity</li>
      </ul>
      <note>Keep in mind that flexible licensing options are available, based on where you want to
        deploy.</note>
      <p>The HPE Helion Third-Paty Hardware team integrated F5 BIG-IP into a <keyword
          keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> deployment by configuring an F5 BIG-IP device to run as a load
        balancer for Neutron LBaaSv2. The installation uses a VXLAN tunnel (VTEP) to connect a
        private network from the <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> cloud to the F5 BIG-IP appliance.</p>
      <note type="important"><keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> must be deployed before the F5
        installation is performed. This is due to the F5 driver not being built directly into
          <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> by default, and because the F5 installation depends on the
        existence of <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> Neutron environment.</note>
      <p>To learn about how the Helion team deployed F5 BIG-IP features into a Helion deployment,
        use the following topics:</p>
      <ul id="F53600_LBaaSlist">
        <li><xref href="F5BIG_IP_preinst.dita">F5 Pre-Integration Checklist</xref></li>
        <li><xref href="F5BIG_IP_install.dita">Integrate F5 BIG-IP</xref></li>
        <li><xref href="F5BIG_IP_verify.dita">Verify F5 BIG-IP Integration</xref></li>
      </ul>
    </section>

  </body>
</topic>
