<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="install_gui">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Installing via the GUI </title>
  <body><!--not tested-->
    <!--Needs Edit-->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    <section><keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> comes with a UI installer for installing your cloud
      the first time. Rather than searching through and editing a number of YAML files to input your
      specific configuration data, finding the correct location, and maintaining the format of the
      files, the UI presents fields in which you may enter your information. In addition, this
      latest version allows you to populate server information via a .csv file import.</section>
    <section>Using the installer, the series Cobbler and Ansible scripts that initiate the
      installation of <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> are run for you behind the scenes. </section>
    <section>The UI app populates the configuration files that the configuration processor uses as
      input to its processes. Therefore you can inspect the files whenever you like, or before
      reconfiguring your cloud. </section>
    <section>
      <p>Note, the GUI installer will periodically save the configuration files during the process
        and when you click the Deploy button at the end of the process. This also means that if you
        were to try to change anything in the files themselves mid process, the values would get
        overwritten by values you have entered in the GUI.</p>
    </section>
    <section>These YAML configuration files are stored in a local git repository as well, as
      explained in <xref href="using_git.dita">Using git for Configuration
        Management</xref>. <p>When installing via the GUI, you begin with a model (or a cloud
        configuration template) and edit the contents to reflect your environment.</p> However, the
      full range of customizations is not possible via the GUI as some configuration items are not
      exposed. Below is the list of what can and cannot be changed: </section>
    <section><b>Changes to the following items may be made:</b><ul id="ul_hsd_bym_tt">
        <li>servers (including Linux for HPE Helion installation configuration) </li>
        <li>networks </li>
        <li>disk models </li>
        <li>interface models </li>
        <li>NIC mappings </li>
        <li>NTP servers </li>
        <li>Name servers</li>
        <li>tags in network groups</li>
      </ul>
      <b>Changes to the following items cannot be made: </b><ul id="ul_b5d_bym_tt">
        <li>server groups</li>
        <li>server roles</li>
        <li>network groups</li>
        <li>firewall rules</li>
        <li>cloudConfig.yml (i.e. DNS, SMTP, firewall settings)</li>
        <li>control planes</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section><title>Before you begin</title> Before you run the GUI installer to install your cloud,
      there are a number of things you need to do: <ol>
        <li>Prepare your servers</li>
        <li>Gather your information <ul>
            <li>Server names </li>
            <li>IP addresses </li>
            <li>Server Roles </li>
            <li>PXE MAC addresses </li>
            <li>PXE IP addresses </li>
            <li>PXE interfaces </li>
            <li>IPMI/iLO IP address, username, password </li>
          </ul></li>
    
        <li>Choose your <xref keyref="example_configurations">cloud model/example</xref> template.
          No action other than an understanding of your needs is necessary at this point. You will
          indicate which model you wish to deploy in a GUI screen. Note, however, that the only VSA
          options for the <i>Entry-scale KVM with VSA</i> model is to have 0 or 3 VSA nodes.
          <!-- 0 or 3 VSA nodes  and dedicated node for lifecycle manager are these still true ??????????????????/ -->
          Note also that you cannot run the lifecycle manager on a dedicated node using the GUI
          installer; it can only run in the control plane using the models exposed in the GUI.</li>
        <li>Before you use the GUI to install your cloud, you may install the operating system,
          Linux for HPE Helion, on your nodes (servers) if you prefer. Otherwise, the installer will
          install it for you. <p>If you are installing the operating system on all your nodes
            yourself, note that you must do so using the Linux for HPE Helion image   that is
            included in the <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> package. You may find the instructions
            on the following pages helpful even when using your own tools to install the operating
            systems:</p>
          <ul>
            <li><xref keyref="install_entryscale_kvm">Operating system install help
                for KVM-based clouds</xref></li>
            <li><xref keyref="installing_esx_kvm_vsa">Operating system install help
                for ESX-based clouds</xref></li>
          </ul>
          <note>When following the guidance for operating system installation on those pages, stop
            before the sections for <b>Running the configuration processor</b>.
            <!--  still true ??????????????????/ -->The GUI installer will run those steps, and in
            the case where you have the GUI also install the operating systems, it will run all the
            previous steps (playbooks) as well.</note></li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section id="gui_use">
      <title>Creating a CSV file for import</title>
      <!-- removed per DOCS-2776 -->
      <!-- <li>  For ESX installations, at this point you must modify the<b>
            ~/helion/hos/ansible/hlm-deploy.yml</b> to uncomment the line containing eon-deploy.yml.
          You must then comment out the line containing ceph-deploy.yml, vsa-deploy.yml, and
          cmc-deploy.yml. Then if you need to, follow the instructions in <xref
            keyref="install_entryscale_esx_kvm_vsa/optional-eon">Step 4
            here</xref>. They are optional steps to enable centralized logging for the EON
          service.</li>-->
      You may create a CSV file for import into the GUI, indicating your server information rather
      than entering it directly into the GUI. The following table shows the fields you need and
      those that are optional.
      
      <table id="table_e5h_wnk_5v"  frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" >
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
          <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
          <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><b>Field</b></entry>
              <entry><b>Optional</b></entry>
              <entry><b>OS Install Only?</b></entry>
              <entry><b>Aliases</b></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Server ID</entry>
              <entry>NO</entry>
              <entry>NO</entry>
              <entry>server_id, id</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>IP Address</entry>
              <entry>NO</entry>
              <entry>NO</entry>
              <entry>ip, ip_address, address</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>MAC Address</entry>
              <entry>NO</entry>
              <entry>YES</entry>
              <entry>mac, mac_address, mac_addr</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>IPMI IP Address</entry>
              <entry>NO</entry>
              <entry>YES</entry>
              <entry>ipmi_ip, ilo_ip</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>IPMI User</entry>
              <entry>NO</entry>
              <entry>YES</entry>
              <entry>ipmi_user, ilo_user, user</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>IPMI Password</entry>
              <entry>NO </entry>
              <entry>YES</entry>
              <entry>Ipmi_password, ilo_password, password</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Server Role</entry>
              <entry>NO</entry>
              <entry>NO</entry>
              <entry>server_role, role</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Server Group</entry>
              <entry>YES</entry>
              <entry>NO</entry>
              <entry>server_group, group</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>NIC Mapping</entry>
              <entry>NO</entry>
              <entry>NO</entry>
              <entry>server_nic_map, nic_map, nic_mapping</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table><p> </p><p>Here “OS Install Only?” indicates that this field is ONLY needed if you
        have indicated that you want the installer to install HPE Linux on the servers.</p><p>The
        aliases are all the valid names that can be used in the CSV file for the column header for a
        given field. Note field names are not case sensitive and that you can use either ‘ ‘ (space)
        or ‘-‘ (hyphen) in place of underscore for a field name.</p><p> So, an example header line
        in the CSV file could be:</p><p>
        <codeblock>Server ID, ip address, mac-address, IPMI_ip, password, user, server-role, server-GROUP, nic mapping</codeblock>
      </p><p> The order of the fields does NOT have to match the order in the table above.</p>
    </section>
    <section><title>Run the GUI to install your cloud</title>The GUI is found on the lifecycle
      manager node at: <b>http://&lt;lifecycle manager_IP>:79/dayzero</b>
      <p>To create a secure tunnel/port forwarding into Apache from the lifecycle manager to be able
        to use the GUI in a browser, SSH tunnel into the lifecycle manager with the
        username/password set up when installing the lifecycle manager. The username and password
        should be what was set in "Set up the lifecycle manager" in the installation instructions.
        For example:</p>
      <codeblock>ssh -v -N -L 8080:&lt;lifecycle manager_IP>:79 &lt;Username>@&lt;lifecycle manager_IP></codeblock>
      <p>Then on your local machine, the one you are tunneling from, point your web browser to:
          <b>http://localhost:8080/dayzero</b></p>As you proceed through the GUI, you can either
      enter your server names and IP addresses manually or import them from the CSV file using the
      CSV fields described above.</section>
    <section>In the Assign network groups: External VM network fields, <b>do not</b> add entries for
      CIDR, Gateway, or IP Range, only VLAN ID. Neutron will assign these.<p>When the installation
        is complete, the Ansible log will be displayed on the final page.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Use the installer securely</title>
      <p> The GUI installer is a web-based application that runs on the lifecycle manager node and
        is implemented in node.js. Currently this application runs behind Apache 2.0 where requests
        are proxied to the node.js Express Web Server. The node.js Express Server runs on port 3000
        and Apache runs on port 79. </p>
      <p>You should access the installer through Apache and not directly from the Express server. An
        Example URL looks like this: http://&lt;lifecycle manager-host-ip>:79/dayzero When you
        finish installing, the Installer will be disabled via Ansible. It is also disabled once
        deployment is completed following the CLI instructions..</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <p>The GUI is used only once: during the initial installation of your cloud.</p><p>For VSA
        deployments, once the GUI competes its installation, you must follow the steps outlined in
        the <xref href="configure_vsa.dita">VSA Configuration</xref>page.</p>After
      deployment, you may also continue to <xref href="cloud_verification.dita"
        >Verifying Your Installation</xref> and <xref href="postinstall_tasks.dita"
        >Post-Installation Checklist</xref>.<p>To understand a cloud configuration more thoroughly
        and to learn how to make any changes later, visit these documentation pages: <ul
          id="ul_akt_fv2_lt">
          <li><xref keyref="input_model"><keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> Input
            Model</xref></li>
          <li><xref href="using_git.dita#using_git">Using Git for Configuration
              Management</xref></li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <note>
        <p>Because the GUI installer is disabled after deployment is complete, whether you installed
          your cloud via the GUI or via the command line, if you want to re-enable the GUI later but
          are not re-installing from scratch, run these commands:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo a2ensite dayzero-apache.conf
sudo systemctl start dayzero.service</codeblock>
      </note>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Final Steps</title>
      <ul>
        <li>The public Horizon Dashboard connection is over TLS, thus please use HTTPS:// to
          navigate to Horizon with the IP address the installer presents once install is
          complete.</li>
        <li>Visit the <xref href="ceph/ceph_overview.dita">Ceph configuration page</xref>
          for Ceph post-install steps.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
