<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.xml"> %entities; ]><!--Edit status: ready for edit (Nancy)-->
<section id="neutron_overview">
   <title>
      <phrase/>Networking Service Overview</title>
    <para/>
    <para>
      <phrase/> Networking is a virtual networking service that leverages the OpenStack
      Neutron service to provide network connectivity and addressing to <phrase/> Compute
      service devices.</para>
    <para>The Networking service also provides an API to configure and manage a variety of network
      services.</para>
    <para>You can use the Networking service to connect guest servers or you can define and configure
      your own virtual network topology.</para>
    
    
      <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Installing the Networking service</bridgehead>
      <para>Helion Network Administrators are responsible for planning for the Neutron networking
        service, and once installed, to configure the service to meet the needs of their cloud
        network users.</para>
   
    
      <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Working with the Networking service</bridgehead>
      <para>To perform tasks using the Networking service, you can use the dashboard, API or CLI.</para>
   
    
    
      <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Reconfiguring the Networking service</bridgehead>
      <para>If you change any of the network configuration after installation, it is recommended that
        you reconfigure the Networking service by running the neutron-reconfigure playbook.</para>
      <para>On the lifecycle manager:</para>
      <screen>cd ~/helion/hlm/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts neutron-reconfigure.yml</screen>
   
  
    
      <bridgehead renderas="sect4">For more information</bridgehead>
      <para>For information on how to operate your cloud we suggest you read the <ulink url="http://docs.openstack.org/ops/">OpenStack Operations
          Guide</ulink>. The <emphasis>Architecture</emphasis> section contains useful information about how an
        OpenStack Cloud is put together. However, <phrase/> takes care of these
        details for you. The <emphasis>Operations</emphasis> section contains information on how to manage the
        system.</para>
   
  </section>
