<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="entryscale_kvm_vsa">
    <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Entry-scale KVM with VSA Model</title>
    <body>
        <!--not tested-->
        <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>

        <p>This model provides a KVM-based cloud with VSA for volume storage, and has been tested to
            a scale of 100 compute nodes.</p>
        <p>The example is focused on the minimum server count to support a highly-available (HA)
            compute cloud deployment. The first (manually installed) server, often referred to as
            the deployer or lifecycle manager, is also used as one of the controller nodes. This
            model consists of a minimum server count of seven, with three controllers, three VSA
            storage servers, and one compute server. Swift storage in this example is contained on
            the controllers.</p>
        <p>Note that the VSA storage requires a minimum of three servers for a HA configuration,
            although the deployment will work with as little as one VSA node.</p>
        <p>This model can also be deployed without the VSA servers and configured to use an external
            storage device, such as a 3PAR array, which would reduce the minimum server count to
            four.</p>
        
        <p><image href="../../../media/entryScale/Entry-ScaleAllNetworks.png" id="kvm_with_vsa"/></p>
        <p><xref href="../../../media/entryScale/Entry-ScaleAllNetworks.png"
              format="html">Download</xref></p>
        <p product="HOS"><xref href="./../../../media/templates/HOS_Network_Diagram_Template.zip"  
            format="html">Download Editable Visio Network Diagram Template</xref></p>
        
        <p>The example requires the following networks:</p> 
        <ul>
            <li><b>External API</b> - This is the network that users will use to make requests to
                the cloud.</li>
            <li><b>External VM</b> - This is the network that will be used to provide access to
                virtual machines (via floating IP addresses).</li>
            <li><b>Guest/VxLAN</b> - This is the network that will carry traffic between virtual
                machines on private networks within the cloud.</li>
            <li><b>Octavia Management</b> - This is the network that will be used for the Octavia
                load balancing service.</li>
            <li><b>Management</b> - This is the network that will be used for all internal traffic
                between the cloud services, including node provisioning. This network must be on an
                untagged VLAN.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>All of these networks are configured to be presented via a pair of bonded NICs. The
            example also enables additional provider VLANs to be configured in Neutron on this
            interface.</p>
        <p>In the diagram, "External Routing" refers to whatever routing you want to provide to
            allow users to access the External API and External VM networks. Note that the
            EXTERNAL_API network must be reachable from the EXTERNAL_VM network if you want virtual
            machines to be able to make API calls to the cloud. "Internal Routing" refers to
            whatever routing you want to provide to allow administrators to access the Management
            network.</p>
        <p>If you are using <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> to install the operating system, then an
            IPMI/iLO network connected to the IPMI/iLO ports of all servers and routable from the
            lifecycle manager server is also required for BIOS and power management of the nodes
            during the operating system installation process.</p>
        <p>The example uses the following disk configurations:</p>
        <ul>
            <li><b>Controllers</b> - One operating system disk and two disks for Swift storage.</li>
            <li><b>VSA</b> - One operating system disk and two disks for VSA storage.</li>
            <li><b>Compute</b> - One operating system disk and one disk for virtual machine
                ephemeral storage.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>For details about how to modify this example to match your environment, see <xref
                keyref="modify_entryscale_kvm_vsa">Modifying the Entry-scale KVM with VSA model for
                your Environment</xref>.</p>

         <section conref="../../planning/rec_min_entryscale_kvm_vsa.xml#rec_min_entryscale_kvm_vsa/rec_min"/>

    </body>
</topic>
