<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="entryscale_swift">
    <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Entry-scale Swift Model</title>
    <body><!--not tested-->
        <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
        
       
    <p>This example shows how <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> can be configured to provide a Swift-only
        configuration, consisting of three controllers and one or more Swift object servers.</p>
    <p><image href="../../../media/examples/entry_scale_swift.png"/></p>
    <p><xref href="../../../media/examples/entry_scale_swift_lg.png" scope="external" format="html"
        >Download a high-resolution version</xref></p>
        <p><xref href="./../../../media/templates/HOS_Network_Diagram_Template.zip"  scope="external" format="html" >Download Editable Visio Network Diagram Template</xref></p>
    <p>The example requires the following networks:</p>
    <ul>
        <li><b>External API</b> - This is the network that users will use to make requests to the
            cloud.</li>
        <li><b>Swift</b> - This is the network that will be used for all data traffic between the
            Swift services.</li>
        <li><b>Management</b> - This is the network that will be used for all internal traffic
            between the cloud services, including node provisioning. This network must be on an
            untagged VLAN.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>All of these networks are configured to be presented via a pair of bonded NICs. The example
        also enables provider VLANs to be configured in Neutron on this interface.</p>
    <p>In the diagram "External Routing" refers to whatever routing you want to provide to allow
        users to access the External API. "Internal Routing" refers to whatever routing you want to
        provide to allow administrators to access the Management network.</p>
    <p>If you are using <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> to install the operating system, then an
        IPMI/iLO network connected to the IPMI/iLO ports of all servers and routable from the
        lifecycle manager is also required for BIOS and power management of the node during the
        operating system installation process.</p>
    <p>In the example the controllers use one disk for the operating system and two disks for
        Swift proxy and account storage. The Swift object servers use one disk for the operating
        system and four disks for Swift storage. These values can be modified to suit your
        environment.</p>

        <section conref="../../planning/rec_min_swift.xml#rec_min_swift/rec_min"/>
        
    </body>
</topic>


