<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<section id="idg-osoperator-shared-appendix-r-confsettings-logs-xml-1">
 <title>Configuration Settings for the Log Agent</title>
 <para>
  The configuration settings for the Log Agent are provided in the following
  file:
 </para>
 <para>
  <literal>/etc/monasca/monasca-log-agent/agent.conf</literal>
 </para>
 <para>
  Below you find a detailed description of the individual settings.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">monasca_log_api_url</bridgehead>
 <para>
  Mandatory. The URL used to access the machine where the Monitoring Service is
  installed.
 </para>
 <para>
  Example: <literal>http://192.168.10.4:5607/v3.0</literal>
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">keystone_api_url</bridgehead>
 <para>
  Mandatory. The URL used to access the server where the OpenStack Keystone
  service is installed. The service is used for authenticating the user
  specified in <literal>username</literal>.
 </para>
 <para>
  Example: <literal>http://192.168.10.5:35357/v3</literal>
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">project_name </bridgehead>
 <para>
  Mandatory. The name of the OpenStack project for which log data is to be
  retrieved by the agent.
 </para>
 <para>
  Example: <literal>monasca</literal>
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">username</bridgehead>
 <para>
  Mandatory. The user to be used for authenticating the agent against Keystone.
 </para>
 <para>
  The user specified here must have the <literal>monasca-agent</literal> role
  in OpenStack and be assigned to the OpenStack project that is to be monitored
  by the agent. The project is specified in <literal>project_name</literal>.
 </para>
 <para>
  It is recommended that this user is used only for configuration purposes and
  not for actually monitoring services and servers.
 </para>
 <para>
  Example: <literal>admin-agent</literal>
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">password</bridgehead>
 <para>
  Mandatory. The password of the user specified in <literal>username</literal>.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">domain_id</bridgehead>
 <para>
  Mandatory. The ID of the OpenStack Keystone domain to which the user
  specified in <literal>username</literal> is assigned.
 </para>
 <para>
  Example: <literal>default</literal>
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">dimensions </bridgehead>
 <para>
  Optional. Meta information to be collected with the log data that is
  retrieved by the agent. The information can be defined as an array.
 </para>
 <para>
  The meta information defined by a dimension is attached to each log entry. It
  is represented as one or more fields in the log management window. For the
  user who is working with the log data, dimensions provide additional
  filtering options.
 </para>
 <para>
  Example: <literal>['app_type:kafka', 'priority:high']</literal>
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">num_of_logs </bridgehead>
 <para>
  Optional. The maximum number of logs per request that is sent to the Log API.
 </para>
 <para>
  It is recommended that you check the number of logs you have to manage. The
  lower the maximum number of logs you specify, the higher the log management
  performance.
 </para>
 <para>
  Allowed values: Any value above <literal>0</literal>
 </para>
 <para>
  Default: <literal>125</literal>
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">max_data_size_kb </bridgehead>
 <para>
  Optional. The maximum data load in kilobyte for sending a request to the Log
  API.
 </para>
 <para>
  Allowed values: Any value above <literal>0</literal>
 </para>
 <para>
  Default: <literal>5120</literal>
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">elapsed_time_sec </bridgehead>
 <para>
  Optional. The time interval in seconds for sending logs to the Log API.
 </para>
 <para>
  Logs are sent in the interval you specify provided that the maximum number of
  logs specified in <literal>num_of_logs</literal> or the maximum data load
  specified in <literal>max_data_size_kb</literal> is not reached earlier.
 </para>
 <para>
  Allowed values: Any value above <literal>0</literal>
 </para>
 <para>
  Default: <literal>30</literal>
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">delay</bridgehead>
 <para>
  Optional. The delay time in seconds until it is checked whether the time
  interval specified in <literal>elapsed_time_sec</literal> is reached.
 </para>
 <para>
  Allowed values: Any value above <literal>0</literal>
 </para>
 <para>
  Default: <literal>10</literal>
 </para>
</section>
