<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<section id="idg-osoperator-osoperator-install-c-osouninstall-xml-1">
 <title>Uninstallation</title>
 <para>
  As an OpenStack operator you are responsible for uninstalling
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> agents, if required. The OpenStack extensions you have
  installed for your platform are uninstalled by the Monitoring Service
  operator.
 </para>
 <para>
  Before uninstalling an agent, it is recommended that you make a backup of the
  configuration files created for operation. For details on backups, refer to
  <xref linkend="idg-osoperator-osoperator-install-c-osobackup-xml-1"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  To uninstall a Metrics Agent or a Log Agent, proceed as follows:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Log in to the Control Machine.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Open the configuration file of the Control Machine with your favorite
    editor.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen>sudo vim /etc/ansible/hosts</screen>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Check that the hosts from which to uninstall an agent are configured
    correctly. Note that multiple instances of an agent are uninstalled if
    multiple hosts are specified in the file.
   </para>
   <para>
    The IP address of the remote machines as well as the user name of the user
    who is to uninstall the agent must be specified.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     The user who uninstalls the agent must have access to the corresponding
     hosts. Access as a user with root privileges is required.
    </para>
   </note>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To run the uninstaller for one or multiple instances of a Metrics Agent,
    execute the following command:
   </para>
<screen>ansible-playbook /opt/FJSVsvcmm/monasca-agent-uninstaller.yml</screen>
   <para>
    To run the uninstaller for one or multiple instances of a Log Agent,
    execute the following command:
   </para>
<screen>ansible-playbook /opt/FJSVsvcmm/monasca-log-agent-uninstaller.yml</screen>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To remove the technical users that were used by <phrase>CMM</phrase>,
    execute the following commands:
   </para>
<screen>userdel -r mon-agent
userdel -r mon-log-agent</screen>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <para>
  The agents and their dependencies are uninstalled:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The agents are stopped.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The corresponding services are removed
    (<literal>openstack-monasca-agent</literal> or
    <literal>openstack-monasca-log-agent</literal>).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The agents' configuration files and the directories where they are located
    are removed.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</section>
