<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<chapter id="idg-osoperator-install-c-osoinstall-xml-1">
 <title>Installation</title>
 <para>
  The installation of <phrase>CMM</phrase> comprises several steps. They are
  partially executed by the Monitoring Service operator, and partially by the
  OpenStack operator.
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images-installation-type-overview.png" depth="346" width="350"/>
   </imageobject>
   <textobject><phrase>installation-type-overview.png</phrase>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <para>
  The installation of <phrase>CMM</phrase> comprises the following steps:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preparing the installation environment - done by the OpenStack operator and
    the Monitoring Service operator.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Configuring the Control Machine - done by the OpenStack operator and the
    Monitoring Service operator.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Installing the offline resources - done by the Monitoring Service operator
    only.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Installing the OpenStack extensions required for the Monitoring Service -
    done by the OpenStack operator only.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Installing the Monitoring Service - done by the Monitoring Service operator
    only.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <para>
  As an OpenStack operator, you also install and configure the agents you use
  for monitoring your OpenStack services. Your application operators who have
  booked a virtual machine in OpenStack monitor their machine with libvirt. As
  an OpenStack operator, you have to make the required libvirt preparations for
  your application operators. For details, refer to
  <xref linkend="idg-osoperator-prepare-c-osopreparetu-xml-1"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> ships with an installer that is based on Ansible. You
  use it for installing the OpenStack extensions and the required agents.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Recommended Installation Environment</bridgehead>
 <para>
  The following installation environment is recommended:
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images-ansible-installation-connection.png" depth="206" width="327"/>
   </imageobject>
   <textobject><phrase>ansible-installation-connection.png</phrase>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    By default, the Monitoring Service operator installs the offline resources,
    the <phrase>CMM</phrase> components, and the required agents on one host
    (<phrase>CMM</phrase> host). To ensure high availability and improve
    scalability, <phrase>CMM</phrase> can also be clustered and installed on
    multiple hosts. This does not affect your tasks as an OpenStack operator.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    As an OpenStack operator, you install the OpenStack extensions and the
    required agents for the OpenStack Keystone service and the OpenStack
    Horizon service. Depending on your OpenStack environment, Keystone and
    Horizon can either be installed on the same or on two separate hosts.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can install additional agents for monitoring additional OpenStack
    services as required.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  The installation of the <phrase>CMM</phrase> components is managed from a
  so-called Control Machine.
 </para>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="osoperator-install-c-osoprepare.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="osoperator-install-c-osoprepansiblemaster.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="osoperator-install-c-osoinstosext.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="osoperator-install-c-osoinstmetricsagent.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="osoperator-install-c-osoinstlogagent.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="osoperator-install-c-osooperate.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="osoperator-install-c-osouninstall.xml"/>
</chapter>
