<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.1">
  <title>Access Control</title>
  <section>
    <title>Role Based Access Control (RBAC)</title>
    <para>Like many other services, the Key Manager service supports the protection of its
                APIs by enforcing policy rules defined in a policy file.  The Key Manager
                service stores a reference to a policy JSON file in its configuration file,
                <literal>/etc/barbican/barbican.conf</literal>.  Typically this file is named
                <literal>policy.json</literal> and it is stored in <literal>/etc/barbican/policy.json</literal>.</para>
    <para>Each Key Manager API call has a line in the policy file that dictates which
                level of access applies:</para>
    <screen language="ini">API_NAME: RULE_STATEMENT or MATCH_STATEMENT</screen>
    <para>where <literal>RULE_STATEMENT</literal> can be another <literal>RULE_STATEMENT</literal> or a
                <literal>MATCH_STATEMENT</literal>:</para>
    <screen language="ini">RULE_STATEMENT: RULE_STATEMENT or MATCH_STATEMENT</screen>
    <para><literal>MATCH_STATEMENT</literal> is a set of identifiers that must match between the token
                provided by the caller of the API and the parameters or target entities of the
                API in question.  For example:</para>
    <screen language="ini">"secrets:post": "role:admin or role:creator"</screen>
    <para>indicates that to create a new secret via a POST request, you must have either
                the admin or creator role in your token.</para>
    <warning>
      <para>The Key Manager service scopes the ownership of a secret at
                    the project level.  This means that many calls in the API will perform an
                    additional check to ensure that the <literal>project_id</literal> of the token matches the
                    <literal>project_id</literal> stored as the secret owner.</para>
    </warning>
    <section>
      <title>Default Policy</title>
      <para>The policy engine in OpenStack is very flexible and allows for customized
                    policies that make sense for your particular cloud.  The Key Manager service
                    comes with a sample <literal>policy.json</literal> file which can be used as the starting
                    point for a customized policy.  The sample policy defines 5 distinct roles:</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>key-manager:service-admin</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The cloud administrator in charge of the Key Manager service.  This user
                                has access to all management APIs like the project-quotas.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>admin</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Project administrator.  This user has full access to all resources owned
                                by the project for which the admin role is scoped.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>creator</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Users with this role are allowed to create new resources and can only
                                delete resources which are originally created (owned) by them. Users with
                                this role cannot delete other user’s resources managed within same project.
                                They are also allowed full access to existing secrets owned by the project
                                in scope.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>observer</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Users with this role are allowed to access to existing resources but are
                                not allowed to upload new secrets or delete existing secrets.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>audit</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Users with this role are only allowed access to the resource metadata.
                                So users with this role are unable to decrypt secrets.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Access Control List API</title>
    <para>There are some limitations that result from scoping ownership of a secret at the
                project level.  For example, there is no easy way for a user to upload a secret
                for which only they have access.   There is also no easy way to grant a user
                access to only a single secret.</para>
    <para>To address this limitations the Key Manager service includes an Access Control
                List (ACL) API.  For full details see the
                <link xlink:href="http://developer.openstack.org/api-guide/key-manager/acls.html">ACL API User Guide</link></para>
  </section>
</section>
