<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.1">
  <title>Open vSwitch with DPDK datapath</title>
  <para>This page serves as a guide for how to use the OVS with DPDK datapath
            functionality available in the Networking service as of the Mitaka release.</para>
  <section>
    <title>The basics</title>
    <para>Open vSwitch (OVS) provides support for a Data Plane Development Kit (DPDK)
                datapath since OVS 2.2, and a DPDK-backed <literal>vhost-user</literal> virtual interface
                since OVS 2.4. The DPDK datapath provides lower latency and higher performance
                than the standard kernel OVS datapath, while DPDK-backed <literal>vhost-user</literal>
                interfaces can connect guests to this datapath. For more information on DPDK,
                refer to the <link xlink:href="http://dpdk.org/">DPDK</link> website.</para>
    <para>OVS with DPDK, or OVS-DPDK, can be used to provide high-performance networking
                between instances on OpenStack compute nodes.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      <para>Using DPDK in OVS requires the following minimum software versions:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>OVS 2.4</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>DPDK 2.0</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>QEMU 2.1.0</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>libvirt 1.2.13</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Support of <literal>vhost-user</literal> multiqueue that enables use of multiqueue with
                    <literal>virtio-net</literal> and <literal>igb_uio</literal> is available if the following newer
                    versions are used:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>OVS 2.5</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>DPDK 2.2</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>QEMU 2.5</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>libvirt 1.2.17</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>In both cases, install and configure Open vSwitch with DPDK support for each
                    node. For more information, see the
                    <link xlink:href="https://github.com/openvswitch/ovs/blob/master/Documentation/intro/install/dpdk.rst">OVS-DPDK</link>
                    installation guide (select an appropriate OVS version in the
                    <guimenu>Branch</guimenu> drop-down menu).</para>
      <para>In case you wish to configure multiqueue, see the
                    <link xlink:href="http://wiki.qemu.org/Documentation/vhost-user-ovs-dpdk#Enabling_multi-queue">OVS configuration chapter on vhost-user</link>
                    in QEMU documentation.</para>
      <para>The technical background of multiqueue is explained in the corresponding
                    <link xlink:href="https://specs.openstack.org/openstack/nova-specs/specs/liberty/implemented/libvirt-virtiomq.html">blueprint</link>.</para>
      <para>Additionally, OpenStack supports <literal>vhost-user</literal> reconnect feature starting
                    from the Ocata release, as implementation of fix for
                    <link xlink:href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/neutron/+bug/1604924">bug 1604924</link>.
                    Starting from OpenStack Ocata release this feature is used without any
                    configuration necessary in case the following minimum software versions
                    are used:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>OVS 2.6</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>DPDK 16.07</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>QEMU 2.7</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The support of this feature is not yet present in ML2 OVN and ODL
                    mechanism drivers.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Using vhost-user interfaces</title>
    <para>Once OVS and neutron are correctly configured with DPDK support,
                <literal>vhost-user</literal> interfaces are completely transparent to the guest
                (except in case of multiqueue configuration described below).
                However, guests must request huge pages. This can be done through flavors.
                For example:</para>
    <screen language="console">$ openstack flavor set m1.large --property hw:mem_page_size=large</screen>
    <para>For more information about the syntax for <literal>hw:mem_page_size</literal>, refer to the
                <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/admin-guide/compute-flavors.html">Flavors</link> guide.</para>
    <note>
      <para><literal>vhost-user</literal> requires file descriptor-backed shared memory. Currently, the
                    only way to request this is by requesting large pages. This is why instances
                    spawned on hosts with OVS-DPDK must request large pages. The aggregate
                    flavor affinity filter can be used to associate flavors with large page
                    support to hosts with OVS-DPDK support.</para>
    </note>
    <para>Create and add <literal>vhost-user</literal> network interfaces to instances in the same
                fashion as conventional interfaces. These interfaces can use the kernel
                <literal>virtio-net</literal> driver or a DPDK-compatible driver in the guest</para>
    <screen language="console">$ openstack server create --nic net-id=$net_id ... testserver</screen>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Using vhost-user multiqueue</title>
    <para>To use this feature, the following should be set in the flavor extra specs
                (flavor keys):</para>
    <screen language="console">$ openstack flavor set $m1.large --property hw:vif_multiqueue_enabled=true</screen>
    <para>This setting can be overridden by the image metadata property if the feature
                is enabled in the extra specs:</para>
    <screen language="console">$ openstack image set --property hw_vif_mutliqueue_enabled=true IMAGE_NAME</screen>
    <para>Support of <literal>virtio-net</literal> multiqueue needs to be present in kernel of
                guest VM and is available starting from Linux kernel 3.8.</para>
    <para>Check pre-set maximum for number of combined channels in channel
                configuration.
                Configuration of OVS and flavor done successfully should result in
                maximum being more than ‘1’):</para>
    <screen language="console">$ ethtool -l INTERFACE_NAME</screen>
    <para>To increase number of current combined channels run following command in
                guest VM:</para>
    <screen language="console">$ ethtool -L INTERFACE_NAME combined QUEUES_NR</screen>
    <para>The number of queues should typically match the number of vCPUs
                defined for the instance. In newer kernel versions
                this is configured automatically.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Known limitations</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>This feature is only supported when using the libvirt compute driver, and the
                        KVM/QEMU hypervisor.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Huge pages are required for each instance running on hosts with OVS-DPDK.
                        If huge pages are not present in the guest, the interface will appear but
                        will not function.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Expect performance degradation of services using tap devices: these devices
                        do not support DPDK. Example services include DVR, FWaaS, or LBaaS.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</section>
