<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!---->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="roleSegregation"><title>&kw-hos-tm; &kw-hos-version-50;: Service Admin Role Segregation in the Identity
    Service</title>
    <!---->
    <para><para xml:id="idg-all-security-admin_role_segregation-xml-4"><phrase><phrase/></phrase></para></para>

    <sidebar xml:id="idg-all-security-admin_role_segregation-xml-6"><title>Overview</title><para>Under the default OpenStack user policies, a user can have either member privilege or admin
        privilege. Admin privilege is assigned by creating a user account with the role of admin.
        However, the default admin role is too broad and often grants users more privilege than they
        need, giving them access to additional tasks and resources that they really shouldn't have. </para>
<para>Ideally, each user account should only be assigned privileges necessary to perform tasks
        they are required to perform. According to the widely accepted principle of least privilege,
        a user who needs to perform administrative tasks should have a user account with the
        privileges required to perform only those administrative tasks and no others. This prevents
        the granting of too much privilege while retaining the individual accountability of the
        user.</para>
<para>Service Administrator Roles is an alternative to the current one-size-fits-all admin role
        model and can help you institute different privileges for different administrators.</para>
</sidebar>
    
    <sidebar><title> Pre-installed service admin role components</title><para>
       The main components of
      Service Administrator Roles are as follows </para>
<itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>nova_admin role in the identity service (Keystone) and support in nova policy.json </para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>neutron_admin role in the identity service and support in neutron policy.json </para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>cinder_admin role in the identity service and support in cinder policy.json </para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>glance_admin role in the identity service and support in glance policy.json </para>
</listitem>
      </itemizedlist></sidebar>
    
    <sidebar><title>Features and benefits</title><para>
       Service Administrator Roles offer the following
      features and benefits. They:</para>
<itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Support separation of duties through more granular roles </para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>Are enabled by default </para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>Are backwards compatible </para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>Have predefined service administrator roles in the identity service </para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>Have predefined policy.json files with corresponding service admin roles to facilitate
          quick and easy deployment</para>
</listitem>
      </itemizedlist></sidebar>
    
    <sidebar><title>Roles</title><para>The following are the roles defined in &kw-hos-phrase;. These roles serve as a way to group common administrative needs at
      the OpenStack service level. Each role represents administrative privilege into each service.
      Multiple roles can be assigned to a user. You can assign a Service Admin Role to a user once
      you have determined that the user is authorized to perform administrative actions and access
      resources in that service. 
      </para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Pre-installed service admin roles</emphasis></para>
<para>The following service admin roles exist by default: 
        </para>
<variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>nova_admin role</term>
          <listitem><para>Assign this role to users whose job function it is to perform nova compute-related
            administrative tasks.</para>
</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>neutron_admin role</term>
          <listitem><para>Assign this role to users whose job function it is to perform neutron
            networking-related administrative tasks.</para>
</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>cinder_admin role</term>
          <listitem><para> Assign this role to users whose job function it is to perform cinder storage-related
            administrative tasks..</para>
</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>glance_admin role</term>
          <listitem><para> Assign this role to users whose job function it is to perform glance image
            service-related administrative tasks.</para>
</listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
<para> 
      For configuration steps, see <xref linkend="CreateCloudAdmin"/></para>
</sidebar>
 
  </section>
