<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!---->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="networking_alarm_summary">
 <title>Networking Alarm Summary</title>
 <para>
  This page displays the alarms for the Networking (Neutron), DNS, Firewall,
  and Load Balancing services. By default, alarms are sorted by most recent and
  in a table format.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Search and Sort</title>
  <para>
   The search bar allows you to filter the alarms you want to view. Type and
   Status are examples of alarm criteria that can be specified. Additionally,
   you can filter by typing in text similar to searching by keywords.
  </para>
  <para>
   The checkbox allows you to select (or deselect) a group of alarms and apply
   a single condition on the selected alarms:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Select Visible</guimenu> allows you to set a condition on
     selected alarms from the table.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Select All</guimenu> allows you to set a condition on all the
     alarms from the table.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Clear Selection</guimenu> allows you to clear all the selections
     currently selected from the table.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   You can display the alarms by grid, list or table views by selecting the
   corresponding icons next to the <guimenu>Sort By</guimenu> control.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Sort By</guimenu> control contains a drop-down list of ways by
   which you can sort the alarms. Alternatively, you can also sort using the
   column headers in the table.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by State</guimenu> displays the alarms by reported status of
     <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis>,
     <emphasis role="bold">Warning</emphasis>,
     <emphasis role="bold">Error</emphasis>, and
     <emphasis role="bold">Unknown</emphasis>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Alarm</guimenu> displays the alarms by name.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Alarm ID</guimenu> displays the alarms UUID.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Last Check</guimenu> displays the alarms by the date and
     timestamp of the most recent occurrence.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Dimension</guimenu> displays the alarms by device,
     hostname and service which they belong to.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Condition</guimenu> displays the alarms by whether the
     alarm is <emphasis role="bold">Open</emphasis>,
     <emphasis role="bold">Acknowledged</emphasis>, or
     <emphasis role="bold">Resolved</emphasis>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Alarm Table</title>
  <para>
   Each row has a checkbox to allow you to select multiple alarms and set the
   same condition on them.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <emphasis role="bold">State</emphasis> column displays a graphical
   indicator that shows the state of each alarm:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Green square (or green indicator): OK. Good operating state.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Yellow diamond (or yellow indicator): Warning. Low severity, not requiring
     immediate action.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Red ball (or red indicator): Alarm. Varying severity levels and must be
     addressed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Gray square (or gray indicator): Undetermined.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   The <emphasis role="bold">Alarm</emphasis> column identifies the alarm by
   the name it was given when it was originally created.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <emphasis role="bold">Last Check</emphasis> column displays the date and
   time the most recent occurrence of the alarm.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <emphasis role="bold">Dimension</emphasis> column describes the
   components to check in order to clear the alarm.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <emphasis role="bold">Condition</emphasis> column shows the current
   condition of each alarm.
  </para>
  <para>
   The last column, depicted by three dots, reveals an
   <emphasis role="bold">Actions</emphasis> menu that allows you to choose:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>View Details</guimenu>, which opens a separate window that shows
     all the information from the table view and the alarm history. This window
     also allows you set the condition on the alarm to another condition. Note,
     the condition the alarm is currently set to is not selectable, as
     indicated by the grayed-out button.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Set Condition</guimenu>, which opens a separate window that
     allows you to directly apply a condition (<emphasis>Open</emphasis>,
     <emphasis>Acknowledged</emphasis>, or <emphasis>Resolved</emphasis>) to
     that alarm, which can be used for tracking and sorting purposes.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</chapter>
