<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!---->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="topic_ask_vgb_dv">
    <title>Support Resources</title>
    <para>Using the knowledge base and contacting the HPE TS Support Cloud CoE team.</para>
    <para>The public knowledge base and the HPE TS Support Cloud CoE Team can be used as resources
        to solve issues in your cloud.</para>
    <!---->
    <section xml:id="kb">
        <title>Using the Knowledge Base</title>
        <para>The public knowledge base for &kw-hos-phrase; can be reached at <link
                xlink:href="http://h20566.www2.hpe.com/portal/site/hpsc/public/psi/home/?sp4ts.oid=7261055#topIssuesAndSolution"
                >Hewlett Packard Enterprise Support Center - HPE Helion OpenStack</link>.</para>
        <para>You can look through the top issues or search for the specific issue you are
            experiencing. Knowledge documents listed with the content type <literal>Knowledge
                Centered Support</literal> are made by HPE TS Support cloud CoE engineers. If you do
            not find your issue listed then we suggest you contact support directly. </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="idg-all-operations-troubleshooting-contacting_support-xml-5">
        <title>Contacting the HPE TS Support Cloud CoE</title>
        <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Call the HPE Support Number</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>Once you have registered for HPE TS Support you will be mailed a Service Agreement ID
            (SAID) and a phone number to call (www.hpe.com/contact). HPE customers with a Datacenter
            Care for Cloud contract will have to use their designated contact number. You can use
            that phone number to log support requests. Please have your SAID number available when
            calling. The support agent will log a case with the information you provide and the case
            will be sent to the HPE TS Support Cloud CoE Team. The response time will depend on the
            service level agreement (SLA) in place.</para>
        <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Electronic Case Logging</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>There is the option of visiting the <link
                xlink:href="http://www.hpe.com/support/hpesc">HPE Support Center</link> to log a
            support case via the website. You will be asked to setup and provide a PIN code for
            correct routing of your support case to the HPE TS Support Cloud CoE team. Use your HPE
            Passport and your Service Agreement ID (SAID) to electronically log your support
            case.</para>
    </section>
</section>
