<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!---->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="configure_glance"><title>&kw-hos-tm; &kw-hos-version-50;: Configuring the Image Service</title><abstract><para><para>The image service, based on OpenStack Glance, works
      out of the box and does not need any special configuration. However, we show you how to enable
      Glance image caching as well as how to configure your environment to allow the Glance
      copy-from feature if you should choose to do so.</para>The image service, based on
    OpenStack Glance, works out of the box and does not need any special configuration. However,
    there are a few features detailed below that if you wish to use will require some additional
    configuration.</para>
</abstract>
    
    <sidebar xml:id="image_warning"><warning><para>Glance images are assigned IDs upon creation, either automatically or
            specified by the user. The ID of an image should be unique, so if a user
            assigns an ID which already exists, a conflict (409) will occur.
          </para>
<para>This only becomes a problem if users can publicize or share images with
            others. If users can share images AND cannot publicize images then your system
            is not vulnerable. If the system has also been purged (via 'glance-manage db
            purge') then it is possible for deleted image IDs to be reused.
          </para>
<para>If deleted image IDs can be reused then recycling of public and shared images
          becomes a possibility. This means that a new (or modified) image can replace
          an old image, which could be malicious.
          </para>
<para>If this is a problem for you, please contact HPE.</para>
</warning>
</sidebar>

    <para>
      Expand All Sections
      Collapse All Sections
    </para>


    <formalpara xml:id="idg-all-operations-image-configure_glance-xml-6"><title>How to enable Glance image caching</title><para><para>In &kw-hos-phrase;, by default, the Glance image caching option is not
          enabled. You have the option to have image caching enabled and these steps will show you
          how to do that.</para><para>The main benefits to using image caching is that it will allow the Glance service to
          return the images faster and it will cause less load on other services to supply the
          image.</para><para>In order to use the image caching option you will need to supply a logical volume for the
          service to use for the caching.</para><para>If you wish to use the Glance image caching option, you will see the section below in
          your <literal>~/helion/my_cloud/definition/data/disks_controller.yml</literal> file. You
          will specify the mount point for the logical volume you wish to use for this.</para></para>
<orderedlist>
          <listitem><para>Log in to the lifecycle manager.</para>
</listitem>
          <listitem><para>Edit your <literal>~/helion/my_cloud/definition/data/disks_controller.yml</literal> file
            and specify the volume and mount point for your glance-cache. Here is
            example:</para>
<screen># Glance cache: if a logical volume with consumer usage 'glance-cache'
# is defined Glance caching will be enabled. The logical volume can be
# part of an existing volume group or a dedicated volume group.
 - name: glance-vg
   physical-volumes:
     - /dev/sdx
   logical-volumes:
     - name: glance-cache
       size: 95%
       mount: /var/lib/glance/cache
       fstype: ext4
       mkfs-opts: -O large_file
       consumer:
         name: glance-api
         usage: glance-cache</screen><para>
            If you are enabling image caching during your initial installation, prior to running
              <literal>site.yml</literal> the first time, then continue with the installation steps.
            However, if you are making this change post-installation then you will need to commit
            your changes with the steps below.</para>
</listitem>
          <listitem><para>Commit your configuration to the <xref linkend="using_git"/>, as follows:
            </para>
<screen>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
git add -A
git commit -m "My config or other commit message"</screen></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Run the configuration processor:
            </para>
<screen>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</screen></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Update your deployment directory:
            </para>
<screen>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Run the Glance reconfigure playbook:
            </para>
<screen>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts glance-reconfigure.yml</screen></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
</formalpara>

    <formalpara xml:id="copyfrom"><title>Allowing the Glance copy-from option in your
        environment</title><para><para>When creating images, one of the options you have is to copy the image from a remote
          location to your local Glance store. You do this by specifying the
            <literal>--copy-from</literal> option when creating the image. To use this feature though
          you need to ensure the following conditions are met:</para></para>
<itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>The server hosting the Glance service must have network access to the remote location
            that is hosting the image.</para>
</listitem>
          <listitem><para>There cannot be a proxy between Glance and the remote location.</para>
</listitem>
          <listitem><para>The Glance v1 API must be enabled, as v2 does not currently support the
              <literal>copy-from</literal> function.</para>
</listitem>
          <listitem><para>The http Glance store must be enabled in the environment, following the steps
            below.</para>
</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
<para><para><emphasis role="bold">Enabling the HTTP Glance Store</emphasis></para><para><orderedlist>
              <listitem><para>Log in to the lifecycle manager.</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Edit the <literal>~/helion/my_cloud/config/glance/glance-api.conf.j2</literal> file
                and add <literal>http</literal> to the list of Glance stores in the
                  <literal>[glance_store]</literal> section as seen below in bold:
                </para><screen>[glance_store]
stores = {{ glance_stores }}<emphasis role="bold">, http</emphasis></screen></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Commit your configuration to the <xref linkend="using_git"/>, as follows:
                </para><screen>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
git add -A
git commit -m "My config or other commit message"</screen></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Run the configuration processor:
                </para><screen>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</screen></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Update your deployment directory:
                </para><screen>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Run the Glance reconfigure playbook:
                </para><screen>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts glance-reconfigure.yml</screen></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Run the Horizon reconfigure
                playbook:</para><screen>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts horizon-reconfigure.yml</screen></listitem>
            </orderedlist></para></para>
</formalpara>
  </section>
