<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!---->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="alarm_definitions">
 <title>Alarm Definition</title>
 <para>
  This page allows you to define alarms that are useful in generating
  notifications and metrics required by your organization. By default, alarm
  definitions are sorted by name and in a table format.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Search and Sort</title>
  <para>
   The search bar allows you to filter the alarm definitions you want to view.
   Type and Status are examples of alarm criteria that can be specified.
   Additionally, you can filter by typing in text similar to searching by
   keywords.
  </para>
  <para>
   The checkbox allows you to select (or deselect) a group of alarm definitions
   to delete:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Select Visible</guimenu> allows you to delete the selected alarm
     definitions from the table.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Select All</guimenu> allows you to delete all the alarms from the
     table.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Clear Selection</guimenu> allows you to clear all the selections
     currently selected from the table.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   You can display the alarm definitions by grid, list or table views by
   selecting the corresponding icons next to the <guimenu>Sort By</guimenu>
   control.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Sort By</guimenu> control contains a drop-down list of ways by
   which you can sort the alarm definitions. Alternatively, you can also sort
   using the column headers in the table.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Name</guimenu> displays the alarm definitions by the name
     assigned to it when it was created.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Description</guimenu> displays the descriptive details of
     the alarm definitions.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Notifications Enabled</guimenu> displays the alarm
     definitions' notification criteria, such as whether enabled for certain
     types of alarms and how the notification is disseminated (by Email, Web,
     etc.)
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Create Alarm Definitions</title>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Create Alarm Definition</guimenu> button beside the search bar
   allows you to create a new alarm definition.
  </para>
  <para>
   To create a new alarm definition:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Click the <guimenu>Create Alarm Definitions</guimenu> button to open a
     separate window that allows you to configure a new alarm.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In the Create Alarm Definition window, type a name for the alarm in the
     <guimenu>Name</guimenu> text field. The name is required and may be up to
     255 characters in length consisting of letters, numbers, or special
     characters.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Provide some useful details about the alarm in the
     <guimenu>Description</guimenu> text field (optional).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Set the severity level for the alarm in the <guimenu>Severity</guimenu>
     drop-down menu. The severity level is optional but subjective, so choose
     the level appropriate for prioritizing the handling of alarms when they
     occur.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Although not required, in order to specify how to receive notifications,
     you must be able to select the method(s) of notification (Email, Web, API,
     etc.) from the list of options in the Alarm Notifications area. If none
     are available to choose from, you must first configure them in the
     Notifications Methods window. Refer to the Notification Methods help page
     for further instructions.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To turn the notifications on for the alarm, click to select
     <guimenu>Enable Notifications</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Apply the following rules to your alarm by using the Alarm Expression
     form:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Function</guimenu>: determines the output value from a supplied
       input value.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Metric</guimenu>: applies a pre-defined means of measuring
       whatever aspect of the alarm.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Dimension(s)</guimenu>: identifies which aspect (Hostname,
       Region, and Service) of the alarm you want to monitor.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Relational Operator</guimenu>: specifies the operator for how
       you want the alarm to trigger.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Value</guimenu>: determines the numeric threshold associated
       with the operator you specified.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Select whether you want to apply the expressions
     <guimenu>Individually</guimenu> or <guimenu>As a group</guimenu> to the
     previously selected dimension(s).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     When done creating the alarm, click <guimenu>Create Alarm</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   After the alarm definition saves, it can take roughly one minute for the
   alarm definition to appear in the chart.
  </para>
 </section>
</chapter>
