<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="topic-i4l-xhn-tt">
 <title>Disabling Backup/Restore before Deployment</title>
<!---->
  <para>
   Backups are enabled by default. Therefore, you must take action if you want
   backups to be disabled for any reason. This topic explains how to disable
   default backup jobs before completing the installation of your cloud.
  </para>
  <warning>
   <para>
    You should make modifications in the <literal>~/openstack/my_cloud/</literal>
    directory before running the configuration processor and ready-deployment
    steps.
   </para>
  </warning>
 <section xml:id="DisableFreezerDeploy">
  <title>Disable backups before installation:</title>
  <para>
   To disable deployment of the Freezer backup and restore service, remove the
   following lines in <literal>control_plane.yml</literal>:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     freezer-agent
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     freezer-api
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <note>
   <para>
    This action is required even if you already removed Freezer lines from your
    model (<filename>control_plane.yml</filename>).
   </para>
  </note>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="DisableFreezerCompletely">
  <title>Deploy Freezer but disable backup/restore job creation:</title>
  <para>
   It is also possible to allow Freezer deployment yet prevent the lifecycle
   manager from creating automatic backup jobs. By default, the lifecycle
   manager deployment automatically creates jobs for the backup and restore of
   the following:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Lifecycle-manager node
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     MySQL database
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Swift rings
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Before running the configuration processor, you can prevent Freezer from
   automatically creating backup and restore jobs by changing the variables
   <literal>freezer_create_backup_jobs</literal> and
   <literal>freezer_create_restore_jobs</literal> to <literal>false</literal>
   in:
  </para>
<screen>~/openstack/my_cloud/config/freezer/activate_jobs.yml</screen>
  <para>
   Alternatively, you can disable the creation of those jobs while launching
   the deployment process, as follows:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts site.yml -e '{ "freezer_create_backup_jobs": false }' -e '{ "freezer_create_restore_jobs": false }'</screen>
  <para>
   When using these options, the Freezer infrastructure will still be deployed
   but will not execute any backups.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Disable backup and restore jobs for a specific service</title>
  <para>
   To manage which jobs will be enabled, set the appropriate paramters in the
   <literal>jobs.yml</literal> freezer jobs configuration file:
  </para>
<screen>~/openstack/my_cloud/config/freezer/jobs.yml</screen>
  <para>
   You can completely disable the backup of a component by changing the
   <literal>enabled</literal> field that corresponds to that service to false
   in <literal>jobs.yml</literal>.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can specify where a job will store its backup by setting
   <literal>store_in_swift, store_in_ssh</literal>,
   <literal>store_in_local</literal> to true or false. Note that these are not
   mutually exclusive. You can set true for all of these backup targets.
   Setting SSH, Swift, and local to true will cause one backup job (and one
   restore job) per storage target to be created.
  </para>
  <para>
   Note also that even if <literal>store_in_ssh</literal> is set to true, the
   SSH backup job will not be created unless SSH credentials are provided in
   <filename>/openstack/my_cloud/config/freezer/ssh_credentials.yml</filename>.
  </para>
  <para>
   When setting <literal>store_in_local</literal> to <literal>true</literal>,
   the backup job will store backups on the server executing the backup. This
   option is useful, for example, if you plan to mount an NFS share and want
   your backup stored on it. You need to provide the path where the backup will
   be stored by setting the <literal>local_storage_base_dir</literal>
   parameter.
  </para>
  <para>
   By default, one backup job per storage medium per component will be created.
   A corresponding restore job for each of those backup jobs will also be
   created by default. These jobs can be used to quickly restore the
   corresponding backup. To disable the creation of these restore jobs, change
   <literal>also_create_restore_job</literal> to <literal>false</literal>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Activating and deactivating jobs after cloud deployment</title>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make modifications similar to those discussed above in <literal>
     /openstack/my_cloud/config/freezer/jobs.yml</literal>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Commit modifications to the git repo
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;git add -A
&prompt.ardana;git commit -m "A message that explains what modifications have been made"</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run the configuration processor
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible/
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run the ready deployment playbook. (This will update the scratch/...
     directories with all of the above modifications).
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Change directories to scratch
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run _freezer_manage_jobs.yml
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts _freezer_manage_jobs.yml</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
</section>
