<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="topic_bxm_gxr_st">
 <title>Default Automatic Backup Jobs</title>
 <para>
  By default, the following are <emphasis role="bold">automatically</emphasis>
  backed up. You do not have to do anything for these backup jobs to run.
  However if you want to back up to somewhere outside the cluster, you do need
  to <xref linkend="topic_jsc_qps_qt"/>.
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <formalpara>
    <title>&clm; Data</title>
    <para>
     All important information on the &clm;
    </para>
   </formalpara>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <formalpara>
    <title>&mariadb; Database</title>
    <para>
     The &mariadb; database contains most of the data needed to restore
     services. While the &mariadb; database only allows for an incomplete
     recovery of ESX data, for other services it allows full recovery.
     Logging data in &elasticsearch; is not backed up. &swift; objects are
     not backed up because of the redundant nature of &swift;.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <formalpara>
    <title>&swift; Rings</title>
    <para>
     &swift; rings are backed up so that you can recover more quickly even
     though &swift; can rebuild the rings without this data. However
     automatically rebuilding the rings is slower than restoring via a backup.
    </para>
   </formalpara>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  The following services will be effectively backed up. In other words, the
  data needed to restore the services is backed up. The critical data that will
  be backed up are the databases and the configuration-related files. Note the
  data that is not backed up per service:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Ceilometer. However, there is no backup of metrics data
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Cinder. However, there is no backup of the volumes
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Glance. However, there is no backup of the images
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Heat
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Horizon
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Keystone
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Neutron
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Nova. However, there is no backup of the images
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Swift. However, there is no backup of the objects. Swift has its own high
    availability/redundancy. Swift rings are backed up. Although Swift will
    rebuild the rings itself, restoring from backup is faster.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    &opscon;
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Monasca. However, there is no backup of the metrics
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <section xml:id="freezer.backup.limitations">
  <title>Limitations</title>
  <para>
   The following limitations apply to backups created by the Freezer backup and
   restore service in &productname;:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Recovery of the following services (or cloud topologies) will be partially
     backed up. They will need additional data (other than the data stored in
     &mariadb;) to return to fully functional.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       ESX Cloud
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Network services - LBaaS and VPNaaS
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Logging data (that is, log files).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     VMs and volumes are not currently backed up.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</section>
