<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
 <!ENTITY % entitydecl SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entitydecl;
]>
<chapter xml:id="ccp-index" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<title>Welcome to Containerized SUSE OpenStack Cloud Technology Preview</title>
 <info>
  <productname></productname>
  <productnumber></productnumber>
 </info>
<para>
 The socok8s project automates Containerized SUSE OpenStack Cloud provisioning and
lifecycle management on SUSE Container as a Service Platform (CaaSP) and
SUSE Enterprise Storage (SES), using Airship, OpenStack Helm, shell scripts,
and Ansible playbooks.
</para>
<para>
 As a technology preview, this is not meant for production use and a typical
support subscription is not being offered. Some of the functionality currently
in our generally available SUSE OpenStack Cloud product is not available in
this tech preview. This technology preview gives users and partners the
ability to test and see the new technologies that may be offered in SUSE's
future releases.
</para>
<para>
 This release deploys the following set of core OpenStack services:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Cinder
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Glance
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Heat
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Horizon
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Keystone
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Neutron
  </para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
  <para>
   Nova
  </para>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
 This technology preview will not be moved into a production support mode of
 operation. The underlying technology is being considered for the future
 release of SUSE OpenStack Cloud product. There is a possibility of refreshing
 the capabilities of the technology preview later.
</para>
<para>
 This technology preview is provided under the terms of the Apache-2.0 license.
</para>
<para>
 Please provide your feedback using the beta mailing lists that are documented
 on the technology preview download page or contact your SUSE
 representative. We are interested in your experience and use cases. Your
 feedback is appreciated.
</para>
</chapter>
