<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix 
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha.deploy.poc">
 <title>&cloud; Deployment Guide Questionnaire</title>
 <info>
<dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
    <dm:maintainer>fs</dm:maintainer>
    <dm:status>editing</dm:status>
    <dm:deadline/>
    <dm:priority/>
    <dm:translation>no</dm:translation>
    <dm:languages/>
</dm:docmanager>
</info>

<sect1 xml:id="sec.depl.poc.scope">
  <title>Document Scope</title>
  <para>
    This document will help to optimally prepare SUSE and their prospective customers for Proof of Concept on &cloud;. Please note  that this document does not aim to replace any of the official documentations. This document is an addition to the general SUSE OpenStack Deployment Guide (presently at
    <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/suse-openstack-cloud-7"/>) which provides specific details for the Proof of Concept (PoC) implementation.
  </para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="sec.depl.poc.features">
  <title>&cloud; Key Features</title>
  <para>
    The latest version of &cloud; is 7 supports all OpenStack Newton release components for best-in-class capabilities to deploy an open source, private cloud.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>Installation Framework:</emphasis> Integration with the Crowbar project speeds up and simplifies installation and administration of your physical cloud infrastructure.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>Mixed Hypervisor Support:</emphasis> Enhanced virtualization management through support for multi-hypervisor environments that use KVM, Xen, Microsoft Hyper-V, VMware vSphere and IBM z/VM.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>High Availability:</emphasis> Automated deployment and configuration of control plane clusters. Ensures continuous access to business services and delivery of enterprise-grade SLAs.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>High availability for KVM / Xen Compute Nodes and Workloads:</emphasis> Enhanced support for critical workloads not designed for cloud architectures.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>Ceph:</emphasis> Integration with SUSE Enterprise Storage provides a streamlined deployment of a single solution for distributed block, object and virtual machine image storage.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>Docker Support:</emphasis> Build and run innovative containerized application through Magum integration.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>Scalability:</emphasis> Cloud control system designed to grow with your demands.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>Open APIs:</emphasis> Using the standard APIs, customers can enhance and integrate OpenStack with third-party software.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>Block Storage Plug-Ins:</emphasis> Broad choice of from storage vendors such as EMC, NetApp and others.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>Networking Plug-Ins:</emphasis> Whilst natively supporting Open Source SDN’s via Open vSwitch harnessing the power of DPDK in &sls;  12 SP2 or third-party tools from Cisco, Midokura, Infoblox, Nuage Networks, PLUMgrid and even VLAN bridging solutions for flexibility.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>Award-winning Support:</emphasis> Backed by 24X7 worldwide-technical support.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>Full Integration into SUSE Update Processes:</emphasis> Easily maintain and patch cloud deployments.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
	<emphasis>Non-disruptive Upgrade Capabilities:</emphasis> Ease migration to future SUSE OpenStack Cloud releases
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 xml:id="sec.depl.poc.components">
    <title>Main Components<remark>dpopov 2016-11-11: Proof-of-Concept Deployment Guidelines</remark>
    POC Guide</title>
    <para>
      Components for setting up and managing SUSE OpenStack cloud include:
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>Administration Server:</emphasis> The Administration Server provides all services needed to manage and deploy all other nodes in
the cloud. Most of these services are provided by the Crowbar tool that automates in conjunction with Chef all the required installation and configuration tasks. Among the services provided by the server are DHCP, DNS, NTP, PXE, TFTP.
    </para>

    <para>
      The Administration Server also hosts the software repositories for SUSE Linux Enterprise Server and SUSE OpenStack Cloud, since they are needed for node deployment. Optionally (if no other sources for the software repositories are available) it can also host the Subscription Management Tool (SMT), providing up-to-date repositories with updates and patches for all nodes.
    </para>

    <para>
      Control Nodes: The Control Node(s) hosts all OpenStack services needed to orchestrate virtual machines deployed on the Compute Nodes in the SUSE OpenStack Cloud. OpenStack on SUSE OpenStack Cloud uses a PostgreSQL database, which is also hosted on the Control Node(s). The following OpenStack components—if deployed—run on the Control Node(s):
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>PostgreSQL</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Image (Glance)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Identity (Keystone)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Networking (Neutron)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Block Storage (Cinder)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Shared Storage (Manila)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>OpenStack Dashboard</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Keystone</para>
      </listitem>
     <listitem>
	<para>Pacemaker</para>
      </listitem>
     <listitem>
	<para>Nova controller</para>
      </listitem>
     <listitem>
	<para>Message broker</para>
      </listitem>
     <listitem>
	<para>Swift proxy server</para>
      </listitem>
     <listitem>
	<para>Hawk monitor</para>
      </listitem>
     <listitem>
	<para>Heat an orchestration engine</para>
      </listitem>
     <listitem>
	<para>Ceilometer server and agents</para>
      </listitem>
     <listitem>
	<para>Trove a Database-as-a-Service</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Being a central point in the SUSE OpenStack Cloud architecture that runs a lot of services, a single Control Node can quickly become a performance bottleneck, especially in large SUSE OpenStack Cloud deployments. It is possible to distribute the services listed above on more than one Control Node, up to a setup where each service runs on its own node.
    </para>

    <para>
      <emphasis>Compute Nodes:</emphasis> The Compute Nodes are the pool of machines on which the instances are running. These machines need to be equipped with a sufficient number of CPUs and enough RAM to start several instances. They also need to provide sufficient hard disk space.  The Control Node effectively distributes instances within the pool of Compute Nodes and provides the necessary network resources. The OpenStack service Compute (Nova) runs on the Compute Nodes and provides means for setting up, starting, and stopping virtual machines. SUSE OpenStack Cloud supports several hypervisors such as Hyper-V, KVM, VMware vSphere, Xen and Docker. Each image that can be started with an instance is bound to one hypervisor. Each Compute Node can only run one hypervisor at a time. For this PoC SUSE recommends to leverage KVM  as hypervisor of choice.
    </para> 

      <para>
	Optionally Storage Nodes: The Storage Nodes are the pool of machines providing object or block storage. Object storage supports several different backends.
      </para>
</sect1>
<sect1 xml:id="sec.depl.poc.objectives">
  <title>Proof of Concept Deployment Objectives</title>
  <para>
    {Every customers requirements in this will be their own, but take care to define 3-5 clearly defined objectives that are provable, measurable and have a specific time scale in which proof is required.  Flexibility in these objectives is encouraged but only through full agreement of both parties and a re-definition of these goals. Please note that is best to add an extension of proof requirements in this document so it remains a full record of the work completed.}
  </para>
  <sect2 xml:id="sec.depl.poc.preparations">
    <title>Proof of Concept Preparations</title>
    <para>
      This document is a summary of tasks and best-practices of &cloud; PoC. It is important that this document does not aim to replace any of the official documentations. This document is an addition to the publicly available Deployment Guide and shows specific details for the  preparations.
    </para>

    <para>
      Before deploying &cloud;, there are a few requirements to be met and considerations to be made. Some decisions need to be made <emphasis>before</emphasis> deploying SUSE OpenStack Cloud, since they <emphasis>cannot</emphasis> be changed afterward.
    </para>

    <para>
      This document provides preparation steps needed for the deployment of &cloud;. This includes software and hardware components for successful implementation.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
</appendix>
