<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="vsOpenStack">
 <title>&kw-hos-tm; 5.0: Enhancements to OpenStack</title>
 <para>
  How does &kw-hos; differ from a pure OpenStack cloud implementation?
 </para>
 <para>
  There are a number of enhancements in &kw-hos; that are not available
  natively with a pure OpenStack implementation. The enhancements include a
  streamlined, largely automated installation process that provides OpenStack
  service integration, with the same level of automation applied to operations,
  and maintenance. Integrated security features help secure your cloud
  externally, and between tenants and services.
 </para>
 <para>
  During installation of &kw-hos;, the core OpenStack services, such as
  compute, networking, orchestration, storage, identity, etc. are installed
  automatically, and by default. These services are integrated and work
  together out of the box. Rather than configuring each service individually
  and configuring their interaction, the &clm;, a
  collection of Ansible playbooks, script together those integrations for you.
  The playbooks read YAML files that describe your cloud configuration in
  human-readable text which you have entered or edited, and builds your cloud
  based on those configuration settings. In addition, these files, collectively
  referred to as <xref linkend="input_model"/> are pre-populated as your
  starting point for a variety of cloud configurations.
 </para>
 <para>
  &kw-hos; lifecyle manager responsibilities go beyond installation and
  configuration, however. Ongoing management and reconfiguration, in many
  instances, can be achieved using the &clm; rather than the
  OpenStack APIs as the Ansible playbooks themselves use the OpenStack APIs and
  abstract the tasks for you. Beginning with version 2.0, each release adds
  additional automation to management tasks.
 </para>
 <para>
  Granular monitoring of processes and services is integrated into &kw-hos; as
  well using Monasca integration.
 </para>
 <para>
  Additionally, the following security features are built into &kw-hos;:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Data at rest encryption capabilities including encrypted storage of
    passwords and sensitive data
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Reduction of surface vulnerabilities based on extensive years of experience
    running OpenStack in the HPE Public Cloud
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Centralized log management capabilities
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Threat monitoring with HPE ArcSight integration
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Security rules that close all unused ports
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    AppArmor to provide an additional layer of automated protection against VM
    breakouts
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Role-based access control to control who and what can access services and
    resources
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Auditing of inter-service activities
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Barbican key management
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Web single sign-on
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  Finally some of the management features include:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Active health monitoring of the end-to-end cloud infrastructure
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Centralized logging all alerts and alarms for event correlation to
    root-cause analysis
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Telemetry / usage metering and internal usage reporting capabilities for
    showback/chargeback/and billing systems
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Identity management of Active Directory and other LDAP providers
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    An integrated &opscon; for easy monitoring and alarm creation
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</section>
