<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xml:id="esx-prerequisite"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Prerequisites</title>
 <para>
  ESX/vCenter integration is not fully automatic, vCenter administrators are
  advised of the following responsibilities to ensure secure operation:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The &vmware; administrator is responsible for administration of the vCenter
    servers and the ESX nodes using the &vmware; administration tools. These
    responsibilities include:
   </para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Installing and configuring vCenter server
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Installing and configuring ESX server and ESX cluster
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Installing and configuring shared datastores
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Establishing network connectivity between the ESX network and the
      &productnamereg; management network
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The &vmware; administration staff is responsible for the review of vCenter
    logs. These logs are not automatically included in &productnamereg; centralized
    logging.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The &vmware; administrator is responsible for administration of the vCenter
    servers and the ESX nodes using the &vmware; administration tools.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Logging levels for vCenter should be set appropriately to prevent logging
    of the password for the &productnamereg; message queue.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The vCenter cluster and ESX Compute nodes must be appropriately backed up.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Backup procedures for vCenter should ensure that the file containing the
    &productnamereg; configuration as part of nova and cinder volume services is
    backed up and the backups are protected appropriately.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Since the file containing the &productnamereg; message queue password could
    appear in the swap area of a vCenter server, appropriate controls should be
    applied to the vCenter cluster to prevent discovery of the password via
    snooping of the swap area or memory dumps
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    It is recommended to have a common shared storage for all the ESXi hosts in
    a particular cluster.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Ensure that you have enabled HA (High Availability) and DRS (Distributed
    Resource Scheduler) settings in a cluster configuration before running the
    installation. DRS/HA is disabled only for OVSvApp. This is done so that it
    does not move to a different host. If you do not enable DRS/HA prior to
    installation then you will not be able to disable it only for OVSvApp. As a
    result DRS/HA can migrate OVSvApp to different host, which will create a
    network loop.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     No two clusters should have the same name across datacenters in a given
     vCenter.
    </para>
   </note>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    L3 HA VRRP is enabled by default.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
</section>
