<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xml:id="ironic-tls"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>TLS Certificates with Ironic Python Agent (IPA) Images</title>
 <para>
  As part of &product;, ironic Python Agent, better known as IPA in the
  OpenStack community, images are supplied and loaded into glance. Two types of
  image exist. One is a traditional boot ramdisk which is used by the
  <literal>agent_ipmitool</literal>, <literal>pxe_ipmitool</literal>, and
  <literal>pxe_ilo</literal> drivers. The other is an ISO image that is
  supplied as virtual media to the host when using the
  <literal>agent_ilo</literal> driver.
 </para>
 <para>
  As these images are built in advance, they are unaware of any private
  certificate authorities. Users attempting to utilize self-signed certificates
  or a private certificate authority will need to inject their signing
  certificate(s) into the image in order for IPA to be able to boot on a remote
  node, and ensure that the TLS endpoints being connected to in &productname; can be
  trusted. This is not an issue with publicly signed certificates.
 </para>
 <para>
  As two different types of images exist, below are instructions for
  disassembling the image ramdisk file or the ISO image. Once this has been
  done, you will need to re-upload the files to glance, and update any impacted
  node's <literal>driver_info</literal>, for example, the
  <literal>deploy_ramdisk</literal> and <literal>ilo_deploy_iso</literal>
  settings that were set when the node was first defined. Respectively, this
  can be done with the
 </para>
<screen>ironic node-update &lt;node&gt; replace driver_info/deploy_ramdisk=&lt;glance_id&gt;</screen>
 <para>
  or
 </para>
<screen>ironic node-update &lt;node&gt; replace driver_info/ilo_deploy_iso=&lt;glance_id&gt;</screen>
 <xi:include href="installation-installation-ironic-cert_ramdisk.xml"/>
</section>
