<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="installesx"><title>Installation for Helion Entry Scale ESX (with
    OVSvApp, KVM with VSA Model</title>
    
    
    <para>This document describes the procedure for the deployment of an ESX cloud using input model
      and  preparing and deploying ESX Computes and OVSvAPPs.</para>

    <para>It contains the following topics:</para>

    <itemizedlist xml:id="ul_u3x_mlw_5x">
        <listitem/>       
        <listitem/>
        <listitem/>
        <listitem/>
           </itemizedlist>

    <important><para>Before you start your ESX cloud deployment make sure to you read the
        following instructions carefully.</para>
</important>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Important Notes</bridgehead><itemizedlist>
        <listitem xml:id="idg-installation-installation-esx-installing_esx_kvm_vsa-xml-8"><para>If you are looking for information about when to use the GUI installer
          and when to use the CLI, see the <xref linkend="install_overview"/>.</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem xml:id="idg-installation-installation-esx-installing_esx_kvm_vsa-xml-9"><para>Review the <citetitle>FIXME: broken external xref</citetitle> that we have listed.</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem xml:id="idg-installation-installation-esx-installing_esx_kvm_vsa-xml-10"><para>Review the <citetitle>FIXME: broken external xref</citetitle>
          to make yourself aware of any known issues and limitations.</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem xml:id="idg-installation-installation-esx-installing_esx_kvm_vsa-xml-11"><para>The installation process can occur in different phases. For example,
          you can install the control plane only and then add Compute nodes afterwards if you would
          like.</para>
</listitem>
        <!-- consider including steps to achieve this -->
        <listitem xml:id="idg-installation-installation-esx-installing_esx_kvm_vsa-xml-12"><para>If you run into issues during installation, we have put together a
          list of <citetitle>FIXME: broken external xref</citetitle> you can reference.</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem xml:id="idg-installation-installation-esx-installing_esx_kvm_vsa-xml-13"><para>Make sure all disks on the system(s) are wiped before you begin the
          install. (For Swift, refer to <citetitle>FIXME: broken external xref</citetitle>)</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem xml:id="idg-installation-installation-esx-installing_esx_kvm_vsa-xml-14"><para>There is no requirement to have a dedicated network for OS-install
          and system deployment, this can be shared with the management network. More information
          can be found on the 
          page.</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem xml:id="idg-installation-installation-esx-installing_esx_kvm_vsa-xml-15"><para>You may see the terms deployer and lifecycle manager used
          interchangeably. These are referring to the same nodes in your environment.</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem xml:id="idg-installation-installation-esx-installing_esx_kvm_vsa-xml-16"><para>When running the Ansible playbook in this installation guide, if a
          runbook fails you will see in the error response to use the <literal>--limit</literal>
          switch when retrying a playbook. This should be avoided. You can simply re-run any
          playbook without this switch.</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>DVR is not supported with ESX compute.</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>When you attach a Cinder volume to the VM running on the ESXi host, the volume will not
          get detected automatically.
          
          Make sure to set the image metadata <emphasis role="bold">vmware_adaptertype=lsiLogicsas</emphasis> for image before
          launching the instance. This will help to discover the volume change appropriately. </para>
</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Before You Start</bridgehead><para>We have put together a <citetitle>FIXME: broken external xref</citetitle> that should help with the recommended pre-installation tasks.</para>

  </section>
