<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xml:id="ironic_multi_control_plane"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Ironic in Multiple Control Plane</title>
 <para>
  &kw-hos-phrase; introduces the concept of multiple control planes and
  multiple regions - see the Input Model documentation for the relevant
  <!-- FIXME: <xref keyref="concept_controlplanes_regions">concepts</xref> --> and
  <!-- FIXME: <xref keyref="configobj_multiple_control_planes">configuration objects</xref> -->.
  This document covers the use of an Ironic region in a multiple control plane
  cloud model in &kw-hos;.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Networking for Baremetal in Multiple Control Plane</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">IRONIC-FLAT-NET</emphasis> is the network
   configuration for baremetal control plane.
  </para>
  <para>
   You need to set the environment variable
   <emphasis role="bold">OS_REGION_NAME</emphasis> to the ironic region in
   baremetal control plane. This will setup the ironic flat networking in
   neutron.
  </para>
  <screen>export OS_REGION_NAME=&lt;ironic_region&gt;</screen>
  <para>
   To see details of the <literal>IRONIC-FLAT-NETWORK</literal> created during
   configuration, use the following command:
  </para>
  <screen>neutron net-list</screen>
  <figure>
   <title>Architecture of Multiple Control Plane with Ironic</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="media-ironic-ironic_multi_control_plane.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="media-ironic-ironic_multi_control_plane.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Handling Optional Swift Service</title>
  <para>
   Swift is very resource-intensive and as a result, it is now optional in the
   &kw-hos; control plane. A number of services depend on Swift, and if it is
   not present, they must provide a fallback strategy. Fore example, Glance can
   use the filesystem in place of Swift for its backend store.
  </para>
  <para>
   In Ironic, agent-based drivers require Swift - if it is not present, it is
   necessary to disable access to this Ironic feature in the control plane. The
   <literal>enable_agent_driver</literal> flag has been added to the ironic
   configuration data and can have valuse of <literal>true</literal> or
   <literal>false</literal>. Setting this flag to <literal>false</literal> will
   disable swift configurations and the agent based drivers in the ironic
   control plane.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Instance Provisioning</title>
  <para>
   In a multiple control plane cloud setup, changes for glance container name
   in the swift namespace of <literal>ironic-conductor.conf</literal>
   introduces a conflict with the one in <literal>glance-api.conf</literal>.
   Provisioning with agent based drivers requires the container name to be the
   same in ironic and glance. Hence, on instance provisioning with agent based
   drivers (swift enabled), the agent is not able to fetch the images from
   glance store and fails at that point.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can resolve this issue using the following steps:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Copy the value of <literal>swift_store_container</literal> from the file
     <literal>/opt/stack/service/glance-api/etc/glance-api.conf</literal>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Login to the lifecycle manager and use the value for
     <literal>swift_container</literal> in glance namespace of
     <literal>~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible/roles/ironic-common/templates/ironic-conductor.conf.j2</literal>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Run the following playbook:
    </para>
<screen>
cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts ironic-reconfigure.yml
</screen>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
</section>
