<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xml:id="upload-image"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Uploading an Image for Use</title>
 <para>
  To create a Compute instance, you need to obtain an image that you can use.
  The &clm; provides an Ansible playbook that will
  download a CirrOS Linux image, and then upload it as a public image to your
  image repository for use across your projects.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Running the Playbook</title>
  <para>
   Use the following command to run this playbook:
  </para>
<screen>
<?dbsuse-fo font-size="0.70em"?>
cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts glance-cloud-configure.yml -e proxy=&lt;PROXY&gt;</screen>
  <para>
   The table below shows the optional switch that you can use as part of this
   playbook to specify environment-specific information:
  </para>
  <informaltable colsep="1" rowsep="1">
   <tgroup cols="2">
    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Switch</entry>
      <entry>Description</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>-e proxy="&lt;proxy_address:port&gt;"</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Optional. If your environment requires a proxy for the internet, use
        this switch to specify the proxy information.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>How to Curate Your Own Images</title>
  <para>
   OpenStack has created a guide to show you how to obtain, create, and modify
   images that will be compatible with your cloud:
  </para>
  <para>
   <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/image-guide/content/">OpenStack
   Virtual Machine Image Guide</link>
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Using the GlanceClient CLI to Create Images</title>
  <para>
   You can use the GlanceClient on a machine accessible to your cloud or on
   your &clm; where it is automatically installed.
  </para>
  <para>
   The OpenStackClient allows you to create, update, list, and delete images as
   well as manage your image member lists, which allows you to share access to
   images across multiple tenants. As with most of the OpenStack CLI tools, you
   can use the <literal>openstack help</literal> command to get a full list of
   commands as well as their syntax.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you would like to use the <literal>--copy-from</literal> option when
   creating an image, you will need to have your Administrator enable the http
   store in your environment using the instructions outlined at
   <xref linkend="copyfrom"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
