<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>

<section xml:id="install_rhel"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Using the Lifecycle Manager to Deploy RHEL
        Compute Nodes</title>
        
        
        <para>The method used for deploying RHEL compute nodes using Cobbler on the lifecycle manager
            will depend on whether your RHEL nodes are using legacy BIOS or UEFI. We provide steps
            for both.</para>


        <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Deploying legacy BIOS RHEL compute nodes</bridgehead><para>The installation process for RHEL nodes is almost identical to that of HPE Linux
                nodes as described in the topic for . The key differences are: </para>
<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para>The standard RHEL 7.2 iso must be placed in the <literal>stack</literal> home
                        directory on the deployer node before you begin the installation procedure.
                        The file must be named <literal>rhel7.iso</literal>. </para>
</listitem>
                    <listitem><para> You must identify the node(s) on which you want to install RHEL, by adding
                        the key/value pair <literal>distro-id: rhel72-x86_64</literal> to server
                        details in <literal>servers.yml</literal>. You will also need to update
                            <literal>net_interfaces.yml</literal>, <literal>server_roles.yml</literal>,
                            <literal>disk_compute.yml</literal> and
                        <literal>control_plane.yml</literal>. For more information on configuration of
                        the Input Model for RHEL, see . </para>
</listitem>
                </itemizedlist>


        <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Deploying UEFI RHEL compute nodes</bridgehead><para>Before you attempt to use the lifecycle manager to install RHEL on UEFI nodes, you
                should install any Linux for HPE Helion nodes or any RHEL on legacy BIOS nodes
                first.</para>
<para> Execute the following steps to re-image one or more nodes after you have run the
                    <literal>ready-deployment.yml</literal> playbook: </para>
<orderedlist>
                    <listitem><para>Prior to beginning these steps, the following must be true:</para>
<itemizedlist xml:id="ul_eqk_vng_zx">
                            <listitem><para>All of your nodes using Linux for HPE Helion (controller, VSA, etc
                                nodes) must already be installed, either manually for via
                                Cobbler.</para>
</listitem>
                            <listitem><para>Your input model should be configured for your RHEL nodes, per the
                                instructions at .</para>
</listitem>
                            <listitem><para>You should have run the configuration processor and the
                                    <literal>ready-deployment.yml</literal> playbook.</para>
</listitem>
                        </itemizedlist></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Run the following playbook, which will extract the
                            <literal>grubx64.efi</literal> file which will be needed when imaging your
                        RHEL UEFI
                        nodes.</para>
<screen>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook prepare-rhel-loader.yml</screen></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Run the following playbook, ensuring that you specify only your UEFI RHEL
                        nodes using the nodelist. This playbook will reconfigure Cobbler for the
                        nodes
                        listed.</para>
<screen>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook prepare-rhel-grub2.yml -e nodelist=node1[,node2,node3]</screen></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Re-image the node(s), ensuring that you only specify your UEFI RHEL nodes
                        using the
                        nodelist.</para>
<screen>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost bm-reimage.yml -e nodelist=node1[,node2,node3]</screen></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Make backups of the <literal>grub.cfg-*</literal> and
                            <literal>grubx64.efi</literal> files in <literal>/srv/tftp/grub/</literal>
                        as they will be overwritten when running the cobbler-deploy playbook on the
                        next step. You will need these files if you need to reimage the nodes in the
                        future.</para>
</listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Run the <literal>cobbler-deploy</literal> playbook, which will reset Cobbler
                        back to the default
                        values:</para>
<screen>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost cobbler-deploy.yml</screen></listitem>
                </orderedlist>
<para><emphasis role="bold">UEFI Secure Boot</emphasis></para>
<para>Secure Boot is a method used to restrict binaries execution for
                booting the system. With this option enabled, system BIOS will only allow boot
                loaders with trusted cryptographic signatures to be executed, thus enable
                preventing malware from hiding embedded code in the boot chain. Each boot loader
                launched during the boot process is digitally signed and that signature is
                validated against a set of trusted certificates embedded in the UEFI BIOS.
                Secure Boot is completely implemented in the BIOS and does not require special
                hardware.</para>
<para>Thus Secure Boot is: </para>
<orderedlist>
                <listitem><para>Intended to prevent boot-sector malware or kernel code injection.</para>
</listitem>
                <listitem><para>Hardware-based code signing.</para>
</listitem>
                <listitem><para>Extension of the UEFI BIOS architecture.</para>
</listitem>
                <listitem><para>Optional with the ability to enable or disable it through the BIOS.</para>
</listitem>
            </orderedlist><para>In Boot Options of RBSU, <literal>Boot Mode</literal> needs to be set to
                <literal>UEFI Mode</literal> and <literal>UEFI Optimized Boot</literal> should
                be <literal>Enabled</literal>. </para>
<para> Secure Boot is enabled at
                </para>
<screen>System Configuration &gt; BIOS/Platform Configuration (RBSU) &gt; Server Security &gt; Secure Boot Configuration &gt; Secure Boot Enforcement
                </screen>


    </section>
