<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xml:id="MagnumInstall"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Install the Magnum Service</title>
 <para>
  Installing the Magnum Service can be performed as part of a new
  &product; environment or can be added to an existing &product;
  environment. Both installations require container management services,
  running in Magnum cluster VMs with access to specific Openstack API
  endpoints. The following TCP ports need to be open in your firewall to allow
  access from VMs to external (public) &productname; endpoints.
 </para>
 <informaltable colsep="1" rowsep="1">
  <tgroup cols="2">
   <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
   <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
   <thead>
    <row>
     <entry>TCP Port</entry>
     <entry>Service</entry>
    </row>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <row>
     <entry>5000</entry>
     <entry>Identity</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>8004</entry>
     <entry>heat</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>9511</entry>
     <entry>Magnum</entry>
    </row>
   </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </informaltable>
 <para>
  Magnum is dependent on the following OpenStack services.
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    keystone
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    heat
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    nova KVM
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    neutron
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    glance
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    cinder
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    swift
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    barbican
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <warning>
  <para>
   Magnum relies on the public discovery service
   <emphasis>https://discovery.etcd.io</emphasis> during cluster bootstrapping
   and update. This service does not perform authentication checks. Although
   running a cluster cannot be harmed by unauthorized changes in the public
   discovery registry, it can be compromised during a cluster update operation.
   To avoid this, it is recommended that you keep your cluster discovery URL
   (that is,
   <literal>https://discovery.etc.io/<replaceable>SOME_RANDOM_ID</replaceable></literal>)
   secret.
  </para>
 </warning>

 <section>
  <title>Installing Magnum as part of new &product; environment</title>
  <para>
   Magnum components are already included in example &productname; models based on
   nova KVM, such as <emphasis role="bold">entry-scale-kvm</emphasis>,
   <emphasis role="bold">entry-scale-kvm-mml</emphasis> and
   <emphasis role="bold">mid-scale</emphasis>. These models contain the Magnum
   dependencies (see above). You can follow generic installation instruction
   for Mid-Scale and Entry-Scale KM model by using this guide:
   <xref linkend="install-kvm"/>.
  </para>
  <note>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you modify the cloud model to utilize a dedicated &clm;, add
      <literal>magnum-client</literal> item to the list of service components
      for the &clm; cluster.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Magnum needs a properly configured external endpoint. While preparing the
      cloud model, ensure that <literal>external-name</literal> setting in
      <literal>data/network_groups.yml</literal> is set to valid hostname,
      which can be resolved on DNS server, and a valid TLS certificate is
      installed for your external endpoint. For non-production test
      installations, you can omit <literal>external-name</literal>. In test
      installations, the &productname; installer will use an IP address as a public
      endpoint hostname, and automatically generate a new certificate, signed
      by the internal CA. Please refer to <xref linkend="tls30"/> for more
      details.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
  </note>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="sec-magnum-exist">
  <title>Adding Magnum to an Existing &productname; Environment</title>
  <para>
   Adding Magnum to an already deployed &product; installation or during
   an upgrade can be achieved by performing the following steps.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Add items listed below to the list of service components in
     <literal>~/openstack/my_cloud/definition/data/control_plane.yml</literal>.
     Add them to clusters which have <literal>server-role</literal> set to
     <literal>CONTROLLER-ROLE</literal> (entry-scale models) or
     <literal>CORE_ROLE</literal> (mid-scale model).
    </para>
<screen>- magnum-api
- magnum-conductor</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If your environment utilizes a dedicated &clm;, add
     <literal>magnum-client</literal> to the list of service components for the
     &clm;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Commit your changes to the local git repository. Run the following
     playbooks as described in <xref linkend="using-git"/> for your
     installation.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>config-processor-run.yml</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>ready-deployment.yml</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>site.yml</literal>
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Ensure that your external endpoint is configured correctly. The current
     public endpoint configuration can be verified by running the following
     commands on the &clm;.
    </para>
<screen>
<?dbsuse-fo font-size="0.65em"?>
$ source service.osrc
$ openstack endpoint list --interface=public --service=identity
+-----------+---------+--------------+----------+---------+-----------+------------------------+
| ID        | Region  | Service Name | Service  | Enabled | Interface | URL                    |
|           |         |              | Type     |         |           |                        |
+-----------+---------+--------------+----------+---------+-----------+------------------------+
| d83...aa3 | region0 | keystone     | identity | True    | public    | https://10.245.41.168: |
|           |         |              |          |         |           |             5000/v2.0  |
+-----------+---------+--------------+----------+---------+-----------+------------------------+</screen>
    <para>
     Ensure that the endpoint URL is using either an IP address, or a valid
     hostname, which can be resolved on the DNS server. If the URL is using an
     invalid hostname (for example, <literal>myardana.test</literal>), follow
     the steps in <xref linkend="tls30"/> to configure a valid external
     endpoint. You will need to update the <literal>external-name</literal>
     setting in the <literal>data/network_groups.yml</literal> to a valid
     hostname, which can be resolved on DNS server, and provide a valid TLS
     certificate for the external endpoint. For non-production test
     installations, you can omit the <literal>external-name</literal>. The
     &productname; installer will use an IP address as public endpoint hostname, and
     automatically generate a new certificate, signed by the internal CA.
     For more information, see <xref linkend="tls30"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <warning>
   <para>
    By default &productname; stores the private key used by Magnum and its
    passphrase in barbican which provides a secure place to store such
    information. You can change this such that this sensitive information is
    stored on the file system or in the database without encryption. Making
    such a change exposes you to the risk of this information being exposed
    to others. If stored in the database then any database backups, or a
    database breach, could lead to the disclosure of the sensitive
    information. Similarly, if stored unencrypted on the file system this
    information is exposed more broadly than if stored in barbican.
   </para>
  </warning>
 </section>
</section>
