<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xml:id="install_gui"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Installing via the GUI</title>
 <para>
  &kw-hos-phrase; comes with a UI installer for installing your cloud the first
  time. Rather than searching through and editing a number of YAML files to
  input your specific configuration data, finding the correct location, and
  maintaining the format of the files, the UI presents fields in which you may
  enter your information. In addition, this latest version allows you to
  populate server information via a .csv file import.
 </para>
 <para>
  Using the installer, the series Cobbler and Ansible scripts that initiate the
  installation of &kw-hos; are run for you behind the scenes.
 </para>
 <para>
  The UI app populates the configuration files that the configuration processor
  uses as input to its processes. Therefore you can inspect the files whenever
  you like, or before reconfiguring your cloud.
 </para>
 <para>
  Note, the GUI installer will periodically save the configuration files during
  the process and when you click the Deploy button at the end of the process.
  This also means that if you were to try to change anything in the files
  themselves mid process, the values would get overwritten by values you have
  entered in the GUI.
 </para>
 <para>
  These YAML configuration files are stored in a local git repository as well,
  as explained in <xref linkend="using_git"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  When installing via the GUI, you begin with a model (or a cloud configuration
  template) and edit the contents to reflect your environment.
 </para>
 <para>
  However, the full range of customizations is not possible via the GUI as some
  configuration items are not exposed. Below is the list of what can and cannot
  be changed:
 </para>
 <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Changes to the following items may be made:</emphasis>
 </para>
 <itemizedlist xml:id="ul_hsd_bym_tt">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    servers (including Linux for HPE Helion installation configuration)
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    networks
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    disk models
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    interface models
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    NIC mappings
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    NTP servers
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Name servers
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    tags in network groups
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Changes to the following items cannot be made:
  </emphasis>
 </para>
 <itemizedlist xml:id="ul_b5d_bym_tt">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    server groups
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    server roles
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    network groups
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    firewall rules
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    cloudConfig.yml (i.e. DNS, SMTP, firewall settings)
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    control planes
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
<section>
<title>Before you begin</title>
 <para>
  Before you run the GUI installer to install your cloud, there are a number of
  things you need to do:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Prepare your servers
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Gather your information
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Server names
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      IP addresses
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Server Roles
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      PXE MAC addresses
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      PXE IP addresses
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      PXE interfaces
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      IPMI/iLO IP address, username, password
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Choose your
    <!-- FIXME: <xref keyref="example_configurations">cloud model/example</xref> -->
    template. No action other than an understanding of your needs
    is necessary at this point. You will indicate which model you wish to
    deploy in a GUI screen. Note, however, that the only VSA options for the
    <emphasis>Entry-scale KVM with VSA</emphasis> model is to have 0 or 3 VSA
    <!-- FIXME: Comment in DITA original: "0 or 3 VSA nodes and dedicated
    node for lifecycle manager are these still true ??????????????????" -->
    nodes. Note also that you cannot run the lifecycle manager on a dedicated
    node using the GUI installer; it can only run in the control plane using
    the models exposed in the GUI.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Before you use the GUI to install your cloud, you may install the operating
    system, Linux for HPE Helion, on your nodes (servers) if you prefer.
    Otherwise, the installer will install it for you.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you are installing the operating system on all your nodes yourself, note
    that you must do so using the Linux for HPE Helion image that is included
    in the &kw-hos-phrase; package. You may find the instructions on the
    following pages helpful even when using your own tools to install the
    operating systems:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <!-- FIXME: <xref keyref="install_entryscale_kvm">Operating system install help for KVM-based clouds</xref>-->
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <!-- FIXME: <xref keyref="installing_esx_kvm_vsa">Operating system install help for ESX-based clouds</xref>-->
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <note>
    <para>
     When following the guidance for operating system installation on those
     pages, stop before the sections for <emphasis role="bold">Running the
     configuration processor</emphasis>.
     <!-- FIXME: Comment in DITA original: "still true ??????????????????" -->
     The GUI installer will run those
     steps, and in the case where you have the GUI also install the operating
     systems, it will run all the previous steps (playbooks) as well.
    </para>
   </note>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 </section>
<section>
<title>Creating a CSV file for import</title>
 <para>
  You may create a CSV file for import into the GUI, indicating your server
  information rather than entering it directly into the GUI. The following
  table shows the fields you need and those that are optional.
 </para>
 <informaltable xml:id="table_e5h_wnk_5v" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
  <tgroup cols="4">
   <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
   <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
   <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
   <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
   <tbody>
    <row>
     <entry><emphasis role="bold">Field</emphasis>
     </entry>
     <entry><emphasis role="bold">Optional</emphasis>
     </entry>
     <entry><emphasis role="bold">OS Install Only?</emphasis>
     </entry>
     <entry><emphasis role="bold">Aliases</emphasis>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>Server ID</entry>
     <entry>NO</entry>
     <entry>NO</entry>
     <entry>server_id, id</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>IP Address</entry>
     <entry>NO</entry>
     <entry>NO</entry>
     <entry>ip, ip_address, address</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>MAC Address</entry>
     <entry>NO</entry>
     <entry>YES</entry>
     <entry>mac, mac_address, mac_addr</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>IPMI IP Address</entry>
     <entry>NO</entry>
     <entry>YES</entry>
     <entry>ipmi_ip, ilo_ip</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>IPMI User</entry>
     <entry>NO</entry>
     <entry>YES</entry>
     <entry>ipmi_user, ilo_user, user</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>IPMI Password</entry>
     <entry>NO </entry>
     <entry>YES</entry>
     <entry>Ipmi_password, ilo_password, password</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>Server Role</entry>
     <entry>NO</entry>
     <entry>NO</entry>
     <entry>server_role, role</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>Server Group</entry>
     <entry>YES</entry>
     <entry>NO</entry>
     <entry>server_group, group</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>NIC Mapping</entry>
     <entry>NO</entry>
     <entry>NO</entry>
     <entry>server_nic_map, nic_map, nic_mapping</entry>
    </row>
   </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </informaltable>
 <para>
  Here “OS Install Only?” indicates that this field is ONLY needed if you
  have indicated that you want the installer to install HPE Linux on the
  servers.
 </para>
 <para>
  The aliases are all the valid names that can be used in the CSV file for the
  column header for a given field. Note field names are not case sensitive and
  that you can use either ‘ ‘ (space) or ‘-‘ (hyphen) in place of
  underscore for a field name.
 </para>
 <para>
  So, an example header line in the CSV file could be:
 </para>
<screen>Server ID, ip address, mac-address, IPMI_ip, password, user, server-role, server-GROUP, nic mapping</screen>
 <para>
  The order of the fields does NOT have to match the order in the table above.
 </para>
 </section>
<section>
<title>Run the GUI to install your cloud</title>
 <para>
  The GUI is found on the lifecycle manager node at:
  <emphasis role="bold">http://&lt;lifecycle
  manager_IP&gt;:79/dayzero</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  To create a secure tunnel/port forwarding into Apache from the lifecycle
  manager to be able to use the GUI in a browser, SSH tunnel into the lifecycle
  manager with the username/password set up when installing the lifecycle
  manager. The username and password should be what was set in "Set up the
  lifecycle manager" in the installation instructions. For example:
 </para>
<screen>ssh -v -N -L 8080:&lt;lifecycle manager_IP&gt;:79 &lt;Username&gt;@&lt;lifecycle manager_IP&gt;</screen>
 <para>
  Then on your local machine, the one you are tunneling from, point your web
  browser to: <emphasis role="bold">http://localhost:8080/dayzero</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  As you proceed through the GUI, you can either enter your server names and IP
  addresses manually or import them from the CSV file using the CSV fields
  described above.
 </para>
 <para>
  In the Assign network groups: External VM network fields,
  <emphasis role="bold">do not</emphasis> add entries for CIDR, Gateway, or IP
  Range, only VLAN ID. Neutron will assign these.
 </para>
 <para>
  When the installation is complete, the Ansible log will be displayed on the
  final page.
 </para>
 </section>
<section>
<title>Use the installer securely</title>
 <para>
  The GUI installer is a web-based application that runs on the lifecycle
  manager node and is implemented in node.js. Currently this application runs
  behind Apache 2.0 where requests are proxied to the node.js Express Web
  Server. The node.js Express Server runs on port 3000 and Apache runs on port
  79.
 </para>
 <para>
  You should access the installer through Apache and not directly from the
  Express server. An Example URL looks like this: http://&lt;lifecycle
  manager-host-ip&gt;:79/dayzero When you finish installing, the Installer will
  be disabled via Ansible. It is also disabled once deployment is completed
  following the CLI instructions..
 </para>
 <para>
  The GUI is used only once: during the initial installation of your cloud.
 </para>
 <para>
  For VSA deployments, once the GUI competes its installation, you must follow
  the steps outlined in <!-- FIXME: <xref linkend="config_vsa"/> -->.
 </para>
 <para>
  After deployment, you may also continue to
  <!-- FIXME: <xref linkend="cloud_verification"/> --> and
  <!-- FIXME: <xref linkend="postinstall_checklist"/> -->.
 </para>
 <para>
  To understand a cloud configuration more thoroughly and to learn how to make
  any changes later, visit these documentation pages:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist xml:id="ul_akt_fv2_lt">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <!-- FIXME: xref keyref="input_model"><keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> Input Model</xref> -->
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <!-- FIXME: <xref href="using_git.xml#using_git">Using Git for Configuration Management</xref> -->
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <note>
  <para>
   Because the GUI installer is disabled after deployment is complete, whether
   you installed your cloud via the GUI or via the command line, if you want to
   re-enable the GUI later but are not re-installing from scratch, run these
   commands:
  </para>
<screen>sudo a2ensite dayzero-apache.conf
sudo systemctl start dayzero.service</screen>
 </note>
 </section>
<section>
<title>Final Steps</title>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The public Horizon Dashboard connection is over TLS, thus please use
    HTTPS:// to navigate to Horizon with the IP address the installer presents
    once install is complete.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Visit the <!-- FIXME: <xref linkend="ceph_overview"/> --> for Ceph post-install steps.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</section>
