<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<chapter xml:id="install-esx-ovsvapp"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Installing ESX Computes and OVSvAPP</title>
 <para>
  This section describes the installation step requirements for ESX
  Computes (nova-proxy) and OVSvAPP.
 </para>

 <!-- Before You Start -->
 <section xml:id="sec-ironic-prereqs">
  <xi:include xpointer="element(/1/3/1)" href="installation-kvm_xpointer.xml"/>
  <xi:include xpointer="element(/1/3/2)" href="installation-kvm_xpointer.xml"/>
 </section>

 <!-- Setting Up the &clm; -->
 <section xml:id="sec-ironic-setup-deployer">
  <xi:include xpointer="element(/1/4/1)" href="installation-kvm_xpointer.xml"/>
  <xi:include xpointer="element(/1/4/2)" href="installation-kvm_xpointer.xml"/>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="esxi-overview">
  <title>Overview of ESXi and OVSvApp</title>
  <para>
   ESXi is a hypervisor developed by VMware for deploying and serving virtual
   computers. OVSvApp is a service VM that allows for leveraging advanced
   networking capabilities that OpenStack Neutron provides. As a result,
   OpenStack features can be added quickly with minimum effort where ESXi is
   used. OVSvApp allows for hosting VMs on ESXi hypervisors together with the
   flexibility of creating port groups dynamically on Distributed Virtual
   Switches (DVS). Network traffic can then be steered through the OVSvApp VM
   which provides VLAN and VXLAN underlying infrastructure for VM communication
   and security features based on OpenStack. More information is available at
   the <link
   xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Neutron/Networking-vSphere">OpenStack
   wiki</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   The diagram below illustrates the OVSvApp architecture.
  </para>
  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="OVSvApp-Architecture.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="OVSvApp-Architecture.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>VM Appliances Used in OVSvApp Implementation</title>
  <para>
   The default configuration deployed with the &clm; for VMware ESX hosts uses
   service appliances that run as VMs on the VMware hypervisor. There is one
   OVSvApp VM per VMware ESX host and one nova Compute Proxy per VMware cluster
   or VMware vCenter Server. Instructions for how to create a template for the
   Nova Compute Proxy or ovsvapp can be found at 
   <xref linkend="create-vapp-template"/>.
  </para>
 <section>
  <title>OVSvApp VM</title>
  <para>
   OVSvApp implementation is comprised of:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     a service VM called OVSvApp VM hosted on each ESXi hypervisor within a
     cluster, and
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     two vSphere Distributed vSwitches (DVS).
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   OVSvApp VMs run &sle; and have Open vSwitch installed with an agent called
   <literal>OVSvApp agent</literal>. The OVSvApp VM routes network traffic to
   the various VMware tenants and cooperates with the &ostack; deployment to
   configure the appropriate port and network settings for VMware tenants.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>&o_comp; Compute Proxy VM</title>
  <para>
   The &o_comp; compute proxy is the <literal>nova-compute</literal> service
   for VMware ESX. Only one instance of this service is required for each ESX
   cluster that is deployed and is communicating with a single VMware vCenter
   server. (This is not like KVM where the <literal>nova-compute</literal>
   service must run on every KVM Host.) The single instance of
   <literal>nova-compute</literal> service can run in the &ostack; controller
   node or any other service node in your cloud. The main component of the
   <literal>nova-compute</literal> VM is the OVSvApp nova VCDriver that talks
   to the VMware vCenter server to perform VM operations such as VM creation
   and deletion.
  </para>
 </section>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Prerequisites for Installing ESXi and Managing with vCenter</title>
  <para>
   ESX/vCenter integration is not fully automatic. vCenter administrators are
   responsible for taking steps to ensure secure operation.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The VMware administrator is responsible for administration of the vCenter
     servers and the ESX nodes using the VMware administration tools. These
     responsibilities include:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Installing and configuring vCenter server
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Installing and configuring ESX server and ESX cluster
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Installing and configuring shared datastores
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Establishing network connectivity between the ESX network and the &clm;
       &ostack; management network
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The VMware administration staff is responsible for the review of vCenter
     logs. These logs are not automatically included in &clm; &ostack; centralized logging.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The VMware administrator is responsible for administration of the vCenter
     servers and the ESX nodes using the VMware administration tools.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Logging levels for vCenter should be set appropriately to prevent logging
     of the password for the &clm; &ostack; message queue.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The vCenter cluster and ESX Compute nodes must be appropriately backed up.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Backup procedures for vCenter should ensure that the file containing the
     &clm; &ostack; configuration as part of &o_comp; and &o_blockstore; volume
     services is backed up and the backups are protected appropriately.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Since the file containing the &clm; &ostack; message queue password could
     appear in the swap area of a vCenter server, appropriate controls should
     be applied to the vCenter cluster to prevent discovery of the password via
     snooping of the swap area or memory dumps.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     It is recommended to have a common shared storage for all the ESXi hosts
     in a particular cluster.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Ensure that you have enabled HA (High Availability) and DRS (Distributed
     Resource Scheduler) settings in a cluster configuration before running the
     installation. DRS and HA are disabled only for OVSvApp. This is done so that it
     does not move to a different host. If you do not enable DRS and HA prior to
     installation then you will not be able to disable it only for OVSvApp. As
     a result DRS or HA could migrate OVSvApp to a different host, which would create a
     network loop.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <note>
  <para>
   No two clusters should have the same name across datacenters in a given
   vCenter.
  </para>
  </note>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>ESXi/vCenter System Requirements</title>
  <para>
   For information about recommended hardware minimums, consult
   <xref linkend="rec-min-entryscale-esx-kvm"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <xi:include href="create-esx-cluster.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="config-dvs-pg.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="create-vapp_template-vcenter.xml"/>
 <section>
 <title>ESX Network Model Requirements</title>
   <para>
     For this model the following networks are needed:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
     <para><literal>MANAGEMENT-NET</literal> : This is an untagged network this is used for the control plane as well as the esx-compute proxy and ovsvapp VMware instance.  It is tied to the MGMT DVS/PG in vSphere. 
     </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para><literal>EXTERNAL-API_NET</literal> : This is a tagged network for the external/public API. There is no difference in this model from those without ESX and there is no additional setup needed in vSphere for this network.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para><literal>EXTERNAL-VM-NET</literal> : This is a tagged network used for Floating IP (FIP) assignment to running instances. There is no difference in this model from those without ESX and there is no additional setup needed in vSphere for this network.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para><literal>GUEST-NET</literal> : This is a tagged network used internally for neutron.  It is tied to the GUEST PG in vSphere.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para><literal>ESX-CONF-NET</literal> : This is a separate configuration network for ESX that must be reachable via the MANAGEMENT-NET.  It is tied to the ESX-CONF PG in vSphere.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para><literal>TRUNK-NET</literal> : This is an untagged network used internally for ESX. It is tied to the TRUNC DVS/PG in vSphere.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <xi:include href="create-vms-vapp_template.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="collect-vcenter-credentials.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="edit-input_models.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="run-config-processor.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="test-esx-environment.xml"/>
 </chapter>
