<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<chapter xml:id="integrate-nsx-vsphere"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Integrating NSX for vSphere</title>
 <para>
  This section describes the installation and integration of NSX-v, a Software
  Defined Networking (SDN) network virtualization and security platform for
  VMware's vSphere.
 </para>
 <para>
  VMware's NSX embeds networking and security functionality, normally handled
  by hardware, directly into the hypervisor. NSX can reproduce, in software, an
  entire networking environment, and provides a complete set of logical
  networking elements and services including logical switching, routing,
  firewalling, load balancing, VPN, QoS, and monitoring. Virtual networks are
  programmatically provisioned and managed independent of the underlying
  hardware.
 </para>
 <para>
  VMware's &o_netw; plugin called NSX for vSphere (NSX-v) has been tested under
  the following scenarios:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Virtual &productname; deployment
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Baremetal &productname; deployment
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  Installation instructions are provided for both scenarios. This documentation
  is meant as an example of how to integrate VMware's NSX-v &o_netw; plugin
  with &productname;. The examples in this documentation are not suitable for
  all environments. To configure this for your specific environment, use the
  design guide <link
  xlink:href="https://communities.vmware.com/servlet/JiveServlet/downloadBody/27683-102-8-41631/NSX">Reference
  Design: VMware&reg; NSX for vSphere (NSX) Network Virtualization Design
  Guide</link>.
 </para>
 <para>
  This section includes instructions for:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Integrating with NSX for vSphere on Baremetal
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Integrating with NSX for vSphere on virtual machines with changes necessary
    for Baremetal integration
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Verifying NSX-v functionality
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <xi:include href="nsx-vsphere-vm.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="nsx-vsphere-baremetal.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="nsx-verification.xml"/>
 </chapter>
