<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="tech_overview_openstack">
 <title>&productnamereg;: OpenStack Services</title>
 <para>
  &productname; is based on the OpenStack offering which brings many benefits:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    OpenStack is a proven infrastructure-as-a-service platform used by many
    enterpises.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    OpenStack has an open, well-defined, modular API architecture that
    facilitates the integration with infrastructure and management products,
    such as HPE 3PAR StoreServ or HPE OneView.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    OpenStack is designed to easily extend to support new hardware, software,
    and identity services, while allowing for massive scalability.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  The following table provides a brief summary of the OpenStack services on
  which &productname; is based.
 </para>
 <table xml:id="tb_openstackservices" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
  <title>&ostack; Services</title>
  <tgroup cols="2">
   <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
   <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
   <thead>
    <row>
     <entry>Service Name</entry>
     <entry>Service Description</entry>
    </row>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Dashboard (Horizon)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       The HPE OpenStack Horizon dashboard provides administrators and users a
       Web based self-service portal to access, provision and automate
       cloud-based resources. The extensible design makes it easy to plug in
       and expose third party products and services, such as billing,
       monitoring and additional management tools.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Compute (Nova)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Compute Operation services, based on OpenStack Nova, provide
       services and associated libraries for massively scalable, on-demand,
       self-service access to compute resources, including bare metal, virtual
       machines, and containers.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Image (Glance)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Image services, based on OpenStack Glance, provide a service where
       users can upload and discover data assets that are meant to be used with
       other services, like images for Nova and templates for Heat.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Networking (Neutron)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Networking services, based on OpenStack Neutron, provide services
       and associated libraries for on-demand, scalable, and
       technology-agnostic network abstraction.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Object Storage (Swift)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Object Storage service, based on OpenStack Swift, is a highly
       available, distributed, eventually consistent object/blob store.
       Organizations can use Swift to store lots of data efficiently, safely,
       and cheaply.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Block Storage (Cinder)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Block Storage Service, based on OpenStack Cinder, implements
       services and libraries to provide on-demand, self-service access to
       Block Storage resources via abstraction and automation on top of other
       block storage devices.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Identity (Keystone)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Identity Service, based on OpenStack Keystone, facilitates API
       client authentication, service discovery, distributed multi-tenant
       authorization, and auditing.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Data Collection (Ceilometer)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Data Collection service, based on OpenStack Ceilometer, efficiently
       collects, normalise and transform data produced by OpenStack services.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Orchestration (Heat)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Orchestration service, based on OpenStack Heat, orchestrates
       composite cloud applications using a declarative template format through
       an OpenStack-native REST API.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Bare Metal (Ironic)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Bare Metal service, based on OpenStack Ironic, provides a service
       and associated libraries capable of managing and provisioning physical
       machines, and to do this in a security-aware and fault-tolerant manner.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Dashboard (Horizon)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Dashboard, based on OpenStack Horizon, provides an extensible,
       unified, web based user interface for all OpenStack services.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Monitoring Service (Monasca)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Monitoring Service, based on OpenStack Monasca, provides a
       multi-tenant, highly scalable, performant, fault-tolerant
       monitoring-as-a-service solution for metrics, complex event processing
       and logging.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Key Manager Service (Barbica)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Key Manager Service, based on OpenStack Barbican, produces a secret
       storage and generation system capable of providing key management for
       services wishing to enable encryption feature.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Container Service (Magnum)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       HPE Container Service, based on OpenStack Magnum, implements container
       orchestration engines such as Docker Swarm, Kubernetes, and Apache Mesos
       available as first class resource.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
   </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </table>
</section>
