<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!---->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="Metering-NewFunctions">
 <title>Metering Service New Functionality</title>
 <section xml:id="newfunct">
  <title>New Metering Functionality in &kw-hos-phrase;</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Ceilometer is now integrated with Monasca to use it as the datastore.
     Ceilometer API also now queries the Monasca datastore using the Monasca
     API (query) instead of the MySQL database
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The default meters and other items configured for the Ceilometer API can
     now be modified and additional meters can be added. It is highly
     recommended that customers test overall &kw-hos; performance prior to
     deploying any Ceilometer modifications to ensure the addition of new
     notifications or polling events does not negatively affect overall system
     performance.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Ceilometer Central Agent (pollster) is now called Polling Agent and is
     configured to support HA (Active-Active)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Notification Agent has built-in HA (Active-Active) with support for
     pipeline transformers, but workload partitioning has been disabled in
     &productname;
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     SWIFT Poll-based account level meters will be enabled by default with an
     hourly collection cycle.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Integration with centralized monitoring (Monasca) and centralized logging
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Support for upgrade and reconfigure operations
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-metering-metering-newfunctions-xml-7">
  <title>Limitations</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The Ceilometer Post Meter API is disabled by default.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The Ceilometer Events and Traits API is not supported and disabled by
     default.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The Number of metadata attributes that can be extracted from
     resource_metadata has a maximum of 16. This is the number of fields in the
     metadata section of the
     <emphasis role="bold">monasca_field_definitions.yaml</emphasis> file for
     any service. It is also the number that is equal to fields in
     metadata.common and fields in metadata.&lt;service.meters&gt; sections.
     The total number of these fields cannot be more than 16.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Several network-related attributes are accessible using a colon ":" but
     are returned as a period ".". For example, you can access a sample list
     using the following command:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;source ~/service.osrc
&prompt.ardana;ceilometer --debug sample-list network -q "resource_id=421d50a5-156e-4cb9-b404-
d2ce5f32f18b;resource_metadata.provider.network_type=flat"</screen>
    <para>
     However, in response you will see the following:
    </para>
<screen>provider.network_type</screen>
    <para>
     instead of
    </para>
<screen>provider:network_type</screen>
    <para>
     This limitation is known for the following attributes:
    </para>
<screen>provider:network_type
provider:physical_network
provider:segmentation_id</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Ceilometer Expirer is unsupported. Data retention expiration is now
     handled by Monasca with a default retention period of 45 days.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Ceilometer Collector is unsupported.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The Ceilometer Alarms API is disabled by default. &kw-hos-phrase; provides
     an alternative operations monitoring service that will provide support for
     operations monitoring, alerts, and notifications use cases.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</section>
