<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!---->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="reconfig_metering">
 <title>Configure the Ceilometer Metering Service</title>
<!---->
 <para>
  &product; automatically deploys Ceilometer to use the Monasca database.
  Ceilometer is deployed on the same control plane nodes along with other
  OpenStack services such as Keystone, Nova, Neutron, Glance, and Swift.
 </para>
 <para>
  The Metering Service can be configured using one of the procedures described
  below.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-metering-metering_reconfig-xml-7">
  <title>Run the Upgrade Playbook</title>
  <para>
   Follow Standard Service upgrade mechanism available in the &clm;
   distribution. For Ceilometer, the playbook included with &productname; is
   <emphasis role="bold">ceilometer-upgrade.yml</emphasis>
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="metering_services">
  <title>Enable Services for Messaging Notifications</title>
  <para>
   After installation of &productname;, the following services are enabled
   by default to send notifications:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Nova
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Cinder
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Glance
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Neutron
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Swift
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   The list of meters for these services are specified in the Notification
   Agent or Polling Agent's pipeline configuration file.
  </para>
  <para>
   For steps on how to edit the pipeline configuration files, see:
   <xref linkend="notifications"/>
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="Ceilo_StopStart">
  <title>Restart the Polling Agent</title>
  <para>
   The Polling Agent is responsible for coordinating the polling activity. It
   parses the <emphasis role="bold">pipeline.yml</emphasis> configuration file
   and identifies all the sources where data is collected. The sources are then
   evaluated and are translated to resources that a dedicated pollster can
   retrieve. The Polling Agent follows this process:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     At each identified interval, the
     <emphasis role="bold">pipeline.yml</emphasis> configuration file is
     parsed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The resource list is composed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The pollster collects the data.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The pollster sends data to the queue.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   Metering processes should normally be operating at all times. This need is
   addressed by the Upstart event engine which is designed to run on any Linux
   system. Upstart creates events, handles the consequences of those events,
   and starts and stops processes as required. Upstart will continually attempt
   to restart stopped processes even if the process was stopped manually. To
   stop or start the Polling Agent and avoid the conflict with Upstart, using
   the following steps.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">To restart the Polling Agent:</emphasis>
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     To determine whether the process is running, run:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl status ceilometer-agent-notification
#SAMPLE OUTPUT:
ceilometer-agent-notification.service - ceilometer-agent-notification Service
   Loaded: loaded (/etc/systemd/system/ceilometer-agent-notification.service; enabled; vendor preset: disabled)
   Active: active (running) since Tue 2018-06-12 05:07:14 UTC; 2 days ago
 Main PID: 31529 (ceilometer-agen)
    Tasks: 69
   CGroup: /system.slice/ceilometer-agent-notification.service
           ├─31529 ceilometer-agent-notification: master process [/opt/stack/service/ceilometer-agent-notification/venv/bin/ceilometer-agent-notification --config-file /opt/stack/service/ceilometer-agent-noti...
           └─31621 ceilometer-agent-notification: NotificationService worker(0)

Jun 12 05:07:14 ardana-qe201-cp1-c1-m2-mgmt systemd[1]: Started ceilometer-agent-notification Service.
</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To stop the process, run:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl stop ceilometer-agent-notification</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To start the process, run:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl start ceilometer-agent-notification</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="ceilo_replace_cntrler">
  <title>Replace a Logging, Monitoring, and Metering Controller</title>
  <para>
   In a medium-scale environment, if a metering controller has to be replaced
   or rebuilt, use the following steps:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     <xref linkend="replacing_controller"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If the Ceilometer nodes are not on the shared control plane, to implement
     the changes and replace the controller, you must reconfigure Ceilometer.
     To do this, run the ceilometer-reconfigure.yml ansible playbook
     <emphasis role="bold">without</emphasis> the limit option
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="ceilo_monitoring">
  <title>Configure Monitoring</title>
  <para>
   The Monasca HTTP Process monitors Ceilometer's notification and polling
   agents are monitored. If these agents are down, Monasca monitoring alarms
   are triggered. You can use the notification alarms to debug the issue and
   restart the notifications agent. However, for
   <literal>Central-Agent</literal> (polling) and <literal>Collector</literal>
   the alarms need to be deleted. These two processes are not started after an
   upgrade so when the monitoring process checks the alarms for these
   components, they will be in <literal>UNDETERMINED</literal>
   state. &productname; does not monitor these processes anymore. To resolve
   this issue, manually delete alarms that are no longer used but are
   installed.
  </para>
  <para>
   To resolve notification alarms, first check the
   <emphasis role="bold">ceilometer-agent-notification</emphasis> logs for
   errors in the <emphasis role="bold">/var/log/ceilometer</emphasis>
   directory. You can also use the &opscon; to access Kibana and
   check the logs. This will help you understand and debug the error.
  </para>
  <para>
   To restart the service, run the
   <emphasis role="bold">ceilometer-start.yml</emphasis>. This playbook starts
   the ceilometer processes that has stopped and only restarts during install,
   upgrade or reconfigure which is what is needed in this case. Restarting the
   process that has stopped will resolve this alarm because this Monasca alarm
   means that ceilometer-agent-notification is no longer running on certain
   nodes.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can access Ceilometer data through Monasca. Ceilometer publishes samples
   to Monasca with credentials of the following accounts:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">ceilometer</emphasis> user
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">services</emphasis>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   Data collected by Ceilometer can also be retrieved by the Monasca REST API.
   Make sure you use the following guidelines when requesting data from the
   Monasca REST API:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Verify you have the monasca-admin role. This role is configured in the
     monasca-api configuration file.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Specify the <literal>tenant id</literal> of the
     <emphasis role="bold">services</emphasis> project.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   For more details, read the
   <link xlink:href="https://github.com/openstack/monasca-api/blob/master/docs/monasca-api-spec.md">Monasca
   API Specification</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To run Monasca commands at the command line, you must be have the
   <emphasis role="bold">admin</emphasis> role. This allows you to use the
   Ceilometer account credentials to replace the default admin account
   credentials defined in the <emphasis role="bold">service.osrc</emphasis>
   file. When you use the Ceilometer account credentials, Monasca commands will
   only return data collected by Ceilometer. At this time, Monasca command line
   interface (CLI) does not support the data retrieval of other tenants or
   projects.
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
