<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<section id="concept-E8D43EB4494E41D2AB42D4A89396D1CMM">
 <title>Working with Data Visualizations</title>
 <para>
  The user interface for monitoring your services, servers, and log data
  integrates with Grafana, an open source application for visualizing
  large-scale monitoring data. Use the options at the top border of the
  <guilabel>Overview</guilabel> page to access Grafana.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> ships with preconfigured
  metrics dashboards. You can instantly use them for monitoring your
  environment. You can also use them as a starting point for building your own
  dashboards.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Preconfigured Metrics Dashboard for <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase>
 </bridgehead>
 <para>
  As a Monitoring Service operator, you use the <guilabel>Monasca
  Health</guilabel> option on the <guilabel>Overview</guilabel> page to view
  the metrics data on the Monitoring Service. The OpenStack operator uses the
  <guilabel>Dashboard</guilabel> option to view the metrics data on the
  OpenStack services.
 </para>
 <figure>
  <title>Metrics Dashboard&mdash;Monitoring Service Operator's View</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-msoperator-dashboard.png" width="95%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-msoperator-dashboard.png" width="90%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
 <para>
  The preconfigured dashboard shows the following data on the Monitoring
  Service:
  <remark condition="clarity">
   2017-05-31 - shermann: @jgrassler: To be checked whether the following list
   is valid in SOCM for the Monitoring Service operator.
  </remark>
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Status of the main <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase>
    components (<literal>UP</literal> or <literal>DOWN</literal>).
   </para>
   <para>
    In the upper part of the dashboard the components are grouped into metrics
    and log management components as well as common components that are used by
    metrics-based and log-based monitoring.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Information on system resources.
   </para>
   <para>
    The dashboard shows metrics data on CPU usage: the percentage of time the
    CPU is used in total (<literal>cpu.percent</literal>), at user level
    (<literal>cpu.user_perc</literal>), and at system level
    (<literal>cpu.system_perc</literal>), as well as the percentage of time the
    CPU is idle when no I/O requests are in progress
    (<literal>cpu.wait_perc</literal>).
   </para>
   <para>
    The dashboard shows metrics data on memory usage: the number of megabytes
    of total memory (<literal>mem.total_mb</literal>), used memory
    (<literal>mem.used_mb</literal>), total swap memory
    (<literal>mem.swap_total_mb</literal>), and used swap memory
    (<literal>mem.swap_used_mb</literal>), as well as the number of megabytes
    used for the page cache (<literal>mem.used_cache</literal>).
   </para>
   <para>
    The dashboard visualizes metrics on the percentage of disk space that is
    being used on a device (<literal>disk.space_used_perc</literal>).
   </para>
   <para>
    The dashboard shows metrics data on the <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud
    Monitoring</phrase> system load over different periods
    (<literal>load.avg_1_min</literal>, <literal>load.avg_5_min</literal>, and
    <literal>load.avg_15_min</literal>).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The network usage of <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The dashboard shows the number of network bytes received and sent per
    second (<literal>net.in_bytes_sec</literal> and
    <literal>net.out_bytes_sec</literal>).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Metrics data on each <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase>
    component. The metrics that are visualized differ slightly from component
    to component. The dashboard shows, for example, the percentage of CPU that
    is consumed by a component (<literal>process.cpu_perc.value </literal>),
    the amount of physical memory that is allocated to the component
    (<literal>process.mem.rss_mbytes.value</literal>), or the number of
    processes that exist with the corresponding component name
    (<literal>process.pid_count.value</literal>).
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Building Dashboards</bridgehead>
 <para>
  Each metrics dashboard is composed of one or more panels that are arranged in
  one or more rows. A row serves as a logical divider within a dashboard. It
  organizes your panels in groups. The panel is the basic building block for
  visualizing your metrics data.
 </para>
 <para>
  For building dashboards, you have two options:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Start from scratch and create a new dashboard.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Take the dashboard that is shipped with <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud
    Monitoring</phrase> as a starting point and customize it.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  The following sections provide introductory information on dashboards, rows,
  and panels, and make you familiar with the first steps involved in building a
  dashboard. For additional information, you can also refer to the
  <ulink url="http://docs.grafana.org/"> Grafana documentation </ulink>.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Creating a Dashboard</bridgehead>
 <para>
  To create a new dashboard, use the <guilabel>Open</guilabel> icon in the
  top right corner of your dashboard window. The option provides access to
  various features for administrating dashboards. Click <guilabel>New</guilabel>
  to create an empty dashboard that serves as a starting point for adding rows
  and panels.
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-new-dashboard.png" width="95%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-new-dashboard.png" width="90%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <para>
  On the left side of an empty dashboard, there is a green rectangle displayed.
  Hover over this rectangle to access a <guilabel>Row</guilabel> menu. To
  insert your first panel, you can use the options in the <guilabel>Add
  Panel</guilabel> submenu. See below for details on the available panel types.
 </para>
 <para>
  As soon as you have inserted an empty panel, you can add additional rows. For
  this purpose, use the <guilabel>Add Row</guilabel> option on the right side
  of the dashboard.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Editing Rows</bridgehead>
 <para>
  Features for editing rows can be accessed via the green rectangle that is
  displayed to the left of each row.
 </para>
 <para>
  In addition to adding panels to a row, you can collapse or remove a row, move
  the position of the row within your dashboard, or set the row height. Row
  settings allows you, for example, to insert a row title or to hide the
  <guilabel>Row</guilabel> menu so that the row can no longer be edited.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Editing Panels</bridgehead>
 <para>
  Grafana distinguishes between three panel types:
 </para>
 <para>
  Panels of type <guilabel>Graph</guilabel> are used to visualize metrics data.
  A query editor is provided to define the data to be visualized. The editor
  allows you to combine multiple queries. This means that any number of metrics
  and data series can be visualized in one panel.
 </para>
 <figure>
  <title>A Graph Panel</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-panel-graph.png" width="95%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-panel-graph.png" width="90%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
 <para>
  Panels of type <guilabel>Singlestat</guilabel> are also used to visualize
  metrics data, yet they reduce a single query to a single number. The single
  number can be, for example, the minimum, maximum, average, or sum of values
  of the data series. The single number can be translated into a text value, if
  required.
 </para>
 <para>
  Panels of type <guilabel>Text</guilabel> are used to insert static text. The
  text may, for example, provide information for the dashboard users. Text
  panels are not connected to any metrics data.
 </para>
 <para>
  As soon as you have added a panel to your dashboard, you can access the
  options for editing the panel content. For this purpose, click the panel
  title and use <guilabel>Edit</guilabel>:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    For panels of type <guilabel>Text</guilabel>, a simple text editor is
    displayed for entering text. Plain text, HTML, and markdown format are
    supported.
   </para>
   <figure>
    <title>Editing a Text Panel</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="socm-panel-text.png" width="75%"
       format="PNG"></imagedata>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="socm-panel-text.png" width="90%"
       format="PNG"></imagedata>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    For panels of type <guilabel>Graph</guilabel> and
    <guilabel>Singlestat</guilabel>, a query editor is displayed to define
    which data it to be shown. You can add multiple metrics, and apply
    functions to the metrics. The query results will be visualized in your
    panel in real time.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  A large number of display and formatting features are provided to customize
  how the content is presented in a panel. Click the panel title to access the
  corresponding options. The menu that is displayed also allows you to
  duplicate or remove a panel. To change the size of a panel, click the
  <guilabel>+</guilabel> and <guilabel>-</guilabel> icons.
 </para>
 <para>
  You can move panels on your dashboard by simply dragging and dropping them
  within and between rows.
 </para>
 <para>
  By default, the time range for panels is controlled by dashboard settings.
  Use the time picker in the top right corner of your dashboard window to
  define relative or absolute time ranges. You can also set an auto-refresh
  interval, or manually refresh the data that is displayed.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Saving and Sharing Dashboards</bridgehead>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> allows you to save a metrics
  dashboard and export it to a JSON file. The JSON file can be edited, it can
  be shared with other users, and it can be imported to <phrase>SUSE OpenStack
  Cloud Monitoring</phrase> again.
 </para>
 <para>
  To save a dashboard, use <guilabel>Save</guilabel> in the top right corner of
  your dashboard window. You can enter a name for the dashboard and simply save
  it to your browser's local storage. Use <guilabel>Dashboard JSON</guilabel>
  to directly view the corresponding JSON syntax, or use <guilabel>Export
  dashboard</guilabel> to download the JSON file. The JSON file can be
  forwarded to other users, if required. To import a JSON file, use
  <guilabel>Open dashboard</guilabel> in the top left corner of the dashboard
  window.
 </para>
</section>
