<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="configureMTU">
 <title>Configuring Maximum Transmission Units in Neutron</title>
 <para>
  This topic explains how you can configure MTUs, what to look out for, and
  the results and implications of changing the default MTU settings. It is
  important to note that every network within a network group will have the
  same MTU.
 </para>
 <warning>
  <para>
   An MTU change will not affect existing networks that have had VMs created
   on them. It will only take effect on new networks created after the
   reconfiguration process.
  </para>
 </warning>
 <section>
  <title>Overview</title>
  <para>
   A Maximum Transmission Unit, or MTU is the maximum packet size (in bytes)
   that a network device can or is configured to handle. There are a number of
   places in your cloud where MTU configuration is relevant: the physical
   interfaces managed and configured by &productname;, the virtual
   interfaces created by Neutron and Nova for Neutron networking, and the
   interfaces inside the VMs.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">&kw-hos;-managed physical interfaces </emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   &kw-hos;-managed physical interfaces include the physical interfaces and the
   bonds, bridges, and VLANs created on top of them. The MTU for these
   interfaces is configured via the 'mtu' property of a network group. Because
   multiple network groups can be mapped to one physical interface, there may
   have to be some resolution of differing MTUs between the untagged and tagged
   VLANs on the same physical interface. For instance, if one untagged VLAN,
   vlan101 (with an MTU of 1500) and a tagged VLAN vlan201 (with an MTU of
   9000) are both on one interface (eth0), this means that eth0 can handle
   1500, but the VLAN interface which is created on top of eth0 (that is,
   <literal>vlan201@eth0</literal>) wants 9000. However, vlan201 cannot have a
   higher MTU than eth0, so vlan201 will be limited to 1500 when it is brought
   up, and fragmentation will result.
  </para>
  <para>
   In general, a VLAN interface MTU must be lower than or equal to the base
   device MTU. If they are different, as in the case above, the MTU of eth0 can
   be overridden and raised to 9000, but in any case the discrepancy will have
   to be reconciled.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Neutron/Nova interfaces </emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   Neutron/Nova interfaces include the virtual devices created by Neutron and
   Nova during the normal process of realizing a Neutron network/router and
   booting a VM on it (qr-*, qg-*, tap-*, qvo-*, qvb-*, etc.). There is
   currently no support in Neutron/Nova for per-network MTUs in which every
   interface along the path for a particular Neutron network has the correct
   MTU for that network. There is, however, support for globally changing the
   MTU of devices created by Neutron/Nova (see network_device_mtu below). This
   means that if you want to enable jumbo frames for any set of VMs, you will
   have to enable it for all your VMs. You cannot just enable them for a
   particular Neutron network.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">VM interfaces</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   VMs typically get their MTU via DHCP advertisement, which means that the
   dnsmasq processes spawned by the neutron-dhcp-agent actually advertise a
   particular MTU to the VMs. In &kw-hos-phrase;, the DHCP server advertises to
   all VMS a 1400 MTU via a forced setting in dnsmasq-neutron.conf. This is
   suboptimal for every network type (vxlan, flat, vlan, etc) but it does
   prevent fragmentation of a VM's packets due to encapsulation.
  </para>
  <para>
   For instance, if you set the new *-mtu configuration options to a default of
   1500 and create a VXLAN network, it will be given an MTU of 1450 (with the
   remaining 50 bytes used by the VXLAN encapsulation header) and will
   advertise a 1450 MTU to any VM booted on that network. If you create a
   provider VLAN network, it will have an MTU of 1500 and will advertise 1500
   to booted VMs on the network. It should be noted that this default starting
   point for MTU calculation and advertisement is also global, meaning you
   cannot have an MTU of 8950 on one VXLAN network and 1450 on another. However,
   you can have provider physical networks with different MTUs by using the
   physical_network_mtus config option, but Nova still requires a global MTU
   option for the interfaces it creates, thus you cannot really take advantage
   of that configuration option.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Network settings in the input model</title>
  <para>
   MTU can be set as an attribute of a network group in network_groups.yml.
   Note that this applies only to KVM. That setting means that every network in
   the network group will be assigned the specified MTU. The MTU value must be
   set individually for each network group. For example:
  </para>
<screen>network-groups:
        - name: GUEST
        mtu: 9000
        ...

        - name: EXTERNAL-API
        mtu: 9000
        ...

        - name: EXTERNAL-VM
        mtu: 9000
        ... </screen>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Infrastructure support for jumbo frames</title>
  <para>
   If you want to use jumbo frames, or frames with an MTU of 9000 or more, the
   physical switches and routers that make up the infrastructure of the &productname;
   installation must be configured to support them. To realize the advantages,
   generally all devices in the same broadcast domain must have the same MTU.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you want to configure jumbo frames on compute and controller nodes, then
   all switches joining the compute and controller nodes must have jumbo frames
   enabled. Similarly, the "infrastructure gateway" through which the external
   VM network flows, commonly known as the default route for the external VM
   VLAN, must also have the same MTU configured.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can also consider anything in the same broadcast domain to be anything
   in the same VLAN or anything in the same IP subnet.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Enabling end-to-end jumbo frames for a VM</title>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Add an 'mtu' attribute to all the network groups in your model. Note that
     adding the MTU for the network groups will only affect the configuration
     for physical network interfaces.
    </para>
    <para>
     To add the mtu attribute, find the YAML file that contains your
     network-groups entry. We will assume it is network_groups.yml, unless you
     have changed it. Whatever the file is named, it will be found in
     ~/openstack/my_cloud/definition/data/.
    </para>
    <para>
     To edit these files, begin by checking out the
     <emphasis role="bold">site</emphasis> branch on the &clm;
     node. You may already be on that branch. If so, you will remain there.
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;git checkout site</screen>
    <para>
     Then begin editing the files. In network_groups.yml, add mtu: 9000
    </para>
<screen>network-groups:
            - name: GUEST
            hostname-suffix: guest
            mtu: 9000
            tags:
            - neutron.networks.vxlan</screen>
    <para>
     This will set the physical interface managed by &kw-hos-phrase; that has
     the GUEST network group tag assigned to it. This can be found in the
     interfaces_set.yml file under the interface-models section.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Next, edit the layer 2 agent config file, ml2_conf.ini.j2, found in
     ~/openstack/my_cloud/config/neutron/ to set the path_mtu to 0, this ensures
     that global_physnet_mtu is used.
    </para>
<screen>[ml2]
...
path_mtu = 0</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Next, edit neutron.conf.j2 found in ~/openstack/my_cloud/config/neutron/ to
     set advertise_mtu (to true) and global_physnet_mtu to 9000 under
     [DEFAULT]:
    </para>
<screen>[DEFAULT]
...
advertise_mtu = True
global_physnet_mtu = 9000</screen>
    <para>
     This allows Neutron to advertise the optimal MTU to instances (based upon
     global_physnet_mtu minus the encapsulation size).
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Next, remove the "dhcp-option-force=26,1400" line from
     <filename>~/openstack/my_cloud/config/neutron/dnsmasq-neutron.conf.j2</filename>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     OvS will set <literal>br-int</literal> to the value of the lowest physical
     interface. If you are using Jumbo frames on some of your networks,
     <literal>br-int</literal> on the controllers may be set to 1500 instead of
     9000. Work around this condition by running:
    </para>
    <screen>ovs-vsctl set int br-int mtu_request=9000</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Commit your changes
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;git add -A
&prompt.ardana;git commit -m "your commit message goes here in quotes"</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If &kw-hos; has not been deployed yet, do normal deployment and skip to
     step 8.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Assuming it has been deployed already, continue here:
    </para>
    <para>
     Run the configuration processor:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</screen>
    <para>
     and ready the deployment:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen>
    <para>
     Then run the network_interface-reconfigure.yml playbook, changing
     directories first:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts network_interface-reconfigure.yml</screen>
    <para>
     Then run neutron-reconfigure.yml:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts neutron-reconfigure.yml</screen>
    <para>
     Then nova-reconfigure.yml:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts nova-reconfigure.yml </screen>
    <para>
     Note: adding/changing network-group mtu settings will likely require a
     network restart during network_interface-reconfigure.yml.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Follow the normal process for creating a Neutron network and booting a VM
     or two. In this example, if a VXLAN network is created and a VM is booted
     on it, the VM will have an MTU of 8950, with the remaining 50 bytes used
     by the VXLAN encapsulation header.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Test and verify that the VM can send and receive jumbo frames without
     fragmentation. You can use ping. For example, to test an MTU of 9000 using
     VXLAN:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ping –M do –s 8950 <replaceable>YOUR_VM_FLOATING_IP</replaceable></screen>
    <para>
     Just substitute your actual floating IP address for the
     <replaceable>YOUR_VM_FLOATING_IP</replaceable>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="optimal-mtu">
  <title>Enabling Optimal MTU Advertisement Feature</title>
  <para>
   To enable the optimal MTU feature, follow these steps:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Edit <literal>~/openstack/my_cloud/config/neutron/neutron.conf.j2</literal>
     to <emphasis role="bold">remove</emphasis> advertise_mtu variable under
     [DEFAULT]
    </para>
<screen>[DEFAULT]
...
advertise_mtu = False #remove this</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Remove the <literal>dhcp-option-force=26,1400</literal> line from
     <literal>~/openstack/my_cloud/config/neutron/dnsmasq-neutron.conf.j2</literal>
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If &kw-hos; has already been deployed, follow the remaining steps,
     otherwise follow the normal deployment procedures.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Commit your changes
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;git add -A
&prompt.ardana;git commit -m "your commit message goes here in quotes"</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run the configuration processor:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run ready deployment:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run the <literal>network_interface-reconfigure.yml</literal> playbook,
     changing directories first:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts network_interface-reconfigure.yml</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run neutron-reconfigure.yml:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts neutron-reconfigure.yml</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <important>
   <para>
    If you are upgrading an existing deployment, attention must be paid to
    avoid creating MTU mismatch between network interfaces in preexisting VMs
    and that of VMs created after upgrade. If you do have an MTU mismatch, then
    the new VMs (having interface with 1500 minus the underlay protocol
    overhead) will not be able to have L2 connectivity with preexisting VMs
    (with 1400 MTU due to dhcp-option-force).
   </para>
  </important>
 </section>
</section>
