<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="HP2-0LBaaSAdmin">
 <title>Configuring Load Balancing as a Service (LBaaS)</title>
 <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">&product; LBaaS Configuration</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  Load Balancing as a Service (LBaaS) is an advanced networking service that
  allows load balancing of multi-node environments. It provides the ability to
  spread requests across multiple servers thereby reducing the load on any
  single server. This document describes the installation steps and the
  configuration for LBaaS v2.
 </para>
 <warning>
  <para>
   The LBaaS architecture is based on a driver model to support different load
   balancers. LBaaS-compatible drivers are provided by load balancer vendors
   including F5 and Citrix. A new software load balancer driver was introduced
   in the OpenStack Liberty release called "<emphasis>Octavia</emphasis>". The
   Octavia driver deploys a software load balancer called HAProxy. Octavia is
   the default load balancing provider in &product; for LBaaS V2.
   Until Octavia is configured the creation of load balancers will fail with an
   error. Refer to <xref linkend="OctaviaInstall"/> document for
   information on installing Octavia.
  </para>
 </warning>
 <warning>
  <para>
   Before upgrading to &productname; &productnumber;, contact F5 and
   &vendor; to determine which F5 drivers have been certified for use with
   &productname;. Loading drivers not certified by &vendor; may result in
   failure of your cloud deployment.
  </para>
 </warning>
 <para>
  LBaaS V2 offers with <xref linkend="OctaviaInstall"/> a software load
  balancing solution that supports both a highly available control plane and
  data plane. However, should an external hardware load balancer be selected
  the cloud operation can achieve additional performance and availability.
 </para>
 <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">LBaaS v2</emphasis>
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Your vendor already has a driver that supports LBaaS v2. Many hardware load
    balancer vendors already support LBaaS v2 and this list is growing all the
    time.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You intend to script your load balancer creation and management so a UI is
    not important right now (horizon support will be added in a future
    release).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You intend to support TLS termination at the load balancer.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You intend to use the Octavia software load balancer (adding HA and
    scalability).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You do not want to take your load balancers offline to perform
    subsequent LBaaS upgrades.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You intend in future releases to need L7 load balancing.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <para>
  Reasons not to select this version.
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Your LBaaS vendor does not have a v2 driver.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You must be able to manage your load balancers from horizon.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You have legacy software which utilizes the LBaaS v1 API.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <para>
  LBaaS v2 is installed by default with &productname; and requires
  minimal configuration to start the service.
 </para>
 <note>
  <para>
   LBaaS V2 API currently supports load balancer failover with Octavia.
   LBaaS v2 API includes automatic failover of a deployed load balancer with
   Octavia. More information about this driver can be found in
   <xref linkend="OctaviaInstall"/>.
  </para>
 </note>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-networking-lbaas-admin-xml-7">
  <title>Prerequisites</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">&productname; LBaaS v2</emphasis>
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &productname; must be installed for LBaaS v2.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Follow the instructions to install <xref linkend="OctaviaInstall"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
</section>
