<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="HP2.0LBaaSAdmin">
 <title>Configuring Load Balancing as a Service (LBaaS)</title>
 <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">&product; LBaaS Configuration</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  Load Balancing as a Service (LBaaS) is an advanced networking service that
  allows load balancing of multi-node environments. It provides the ability to
  spread requests across multiple servers thereby reducing the load on any
  single server. This document describes the installation steps for LBaaS v1
  (see prerequisites) and the configuration for LBaaS v1 and v2.
 </para>
 <para>
  &product; can support either LBaaS v1 or LBaaS v2 to allow for wide
  ranging customer requirements. If the decision is made to utilize LBaaS v1 it
  is highly unlikely that you will be able to perform an on-line upgrade of the
  service to v2 after the fact as the internal data structures are
  significantly different. Should you wish to attempt an upgrade, support will
  be needed from &serviceteam; and your chosen load balancer partner.
 </para>
 <warning>
  <para>
   The LBaaS architecture is based on a driver model to support different load
   balancers. LBaaS-compatible drivers are provided by load balancer vendors
   including F5 and Citrix. A new software load balancer driver was introduced
   in the OpenStack Liberty release called "<emphasis>Octavia</emphasis>". The
   Octavia driver deploys a software load balancer called HAProxy. Octavia is
   the default load balancing provider in &product; for LBaaS V2.
   <!-- FIXME: Removed version number 3.0 from product name above. Still
   correct? - sknorr, 2018-03-27 -->
   Until Octavia is configured the creation of load balancers will fail with an
   error. Please refer to <xref linkend="OctaviaInstall"/> document for
   information on installing Octavia.
  </para>
 </warning>
 <warning>
  <para>
   Before upgrading to &productname; &productnumber;, contact F5 and
   &vendor; to determine which F5 drivers have been certified for use with
   &productname;. Loading drivers not certified by &vendor; may result in
   failure of your cloud deployment.
  </para>
 </warning>
 <para>
  LBaaS V2 offers with <xref linkend="OctaviaInstall"/> a software load
  balancing solution that supports both a highly available control plane and
  data plane. However, should an external hardware load balancer be selected
  the cloud operation can achieve additional performance and availability.
 </para>
 <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">LBaaS v1</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  Reasons to select this version.
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You must be able to configure LBaaS via Horizon.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Your hardware load balancer vendor does not currently support LBaaS v2.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <para>
  Reasons not to select this version.
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    No active development is being performed on this API in the OpenStack
    community. (Security fixes are still being worked upon).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    It does not allow for multiple ports on the same VIP (for example, to
    support both port 80 and 443 on a single VIP).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    It will never be able to support TLS termination/re-encryption at the load
    balancer.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    It will never be able to support L7 rules for load balancing.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    LBaaS v1 will likely become officially deprecated by the OpenStack
    community at the Tokyo (October 2015) summit.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">LBaaS v2</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  Reasons to select this version.
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Your vendor already has a driver that supports LBaaS v2. Many hardware load
    balancer vendors already support LBaaS v2 and this list is growing all the
    time.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You intend to script your load balancer creation and management so a UI is
    not important right now (Horizon support will be added in a future
    release).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You intend to support TLS termination at the load balancer.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You intend to use the Octavia software load balancer (adding HA and
    scalability).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You do not want to take your load balancers offline to perform
    subsequent LBaaS upgrades.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You intend in future releases to need L7 load balancing.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <para>
  Reasons not to select this version.
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Your LBaaS vendor does not have a v2 driver.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You must be able to manage your load balancers from Horizon.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You have legacy software which utilizes the LBaaS v1 API.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <para>
  LBaaS v1 requires configuration changes prior to installation and is not
  recommended. LBaaS v2 is installed by default with &productname; and requires
  minimal configuration to start the service.
 </para>
<!-- Commented in DITA original -->
<!-- Original note from Tim Cuddy
<note>Neither LBaaS API currently supports load balancer failover. If a load balancer is deleted
it will need to be manually recreated. Future releases of the v2 API are targeted to include
automatic failover of a deployed load balancer. This functionality is targeted for the
OpenStack Mitaka release via the Octavia software driver. More information about this driver
can be found at: <xref href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8n7FGhtOiXk" format="html"
scope="external"/>.</note>
-->
 <note>
  <para>
   Only LBaaS V2 API currently supports load balancer failover with Octavia.
   However, in LBaaS V1 and if Octavia is not deployed when a load balancer is
   deleted it will need to be manually recreated. LBaaS v2 API includes
   automatic failover of a deployed load balancer with Octavia. More
   information about this driver can be found in
   <xref linkend="OctaviaInstall"/>.
  </para>
 </note>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-networking-lbaas_admin-xml-7">
  <title>Prerequisites</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">&productname; LBaaS v1</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   Installing LBaaS v1
  </para>
  <important>
   <para>
    It is not recommended that LBaaS v1 is used in a production environment. It
    is recommended you use LBaaS v2. If you do deploy LBaaS v1, the upgrade to
    LBaaS v2 is non-trivial and may require the use of professional services.
   </para>
  </important>
  <note>
   <para>
    If you need to run LBaaS v1 instead of the default LBaaS v2, you should
    make appropriate installation preparations during &productname; installation
    since LBaaS v2 is the default. If you have selected to install and use
    LBaaS v1 you will replace the <filename>control_plane.yml</filename>
    directories and <filename>neutron.conf.j2</filename> file to use version 1.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   Before you modify the control_plane.yml file, it is recommended that you
   back up the original version of this file. Once you have backed them up,
   modify the control_plane.yml file.
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Edit ~/openstack/my_cloud/definition/data/control_plane.yml - depending on
     your installation the control_plane.yml file might be in a different
     location.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In the section specifying the compute nodes (resources/compute) replace
     neutron-lbaasv2-agent with neutron-lbaas-agent - there will only be one
     occurrence in that file.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Save the modified file.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Follow the steps in <xref linkend="using_git"/> to commit and apply the
     changes.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To test the installation follow the steps outlined in
     <xref linkend="OctaviaInstall"/> after you have created a suitable subnet,
     see: <xref linkend="create_extnet"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">&productname; LBaaS v2</emphasis>
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &productname; must be installed for LBaaS v2.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Follow the instructions to install <xref linkend="OctaviaInstall"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
</section>
