<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xml:id="nsx-prepare-clusters"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Prepare Clusters for NSX Management</title>
 <para>
  During <guimenu>Host Preparation</guimenu>, the NSX Manager:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Installs the NSX kernel modules on ESXi hosts that are members of vSphere
    clusters
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Builds the NSX control-plane and management-plane infrastructure
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  The NSX kernel modules are packaged in <filename>VIB</filename>
  (vSphere Installation Bundle) files. They run within the hypervisor kernel and
  provide services such as distributed routing, distributed firewall, and VXLAN
  bridging capabilities. These files are installed on a per-cluster level, and
  the setup process deploys the required software on all ESXi hosts in the
  target cluster. When a new ESXi host is added to the cluster, the required
  software is automatically installed on the newly added host.
 </para>
 <para>
  Before beginning the NSX host preparation process, make sure of the following
  in your environment:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Register vCenter with NSX Manager and deploy the NSX controllers.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Verify that DNS reverse lookup returns a fully qualified domain name when
    queried with the IP address of NSX Manager.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Verify that the ESXi hosts can resolve the DNS name of vCenter server.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Verify that the ESXi hosts can connect to vCenter Server on port 80.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Verify that the network time on vCenter Server and the ESXi hosts is
    synchronized.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    For each vSphere cluster that will participate in NSX, verify that the ESXi
    hosts within each respective cluster are attached to a common VDS.
   </para>
   <para>
    For example, given a deployment with two clusters named Host1 and
    Host2. Host1 is attached to VDS1 and VDS2. Host2 is attached to VDS1 and
    VDS3. When you prepare a cluster for NSX, you can only associate NSX with
    VDS1 on the cluster. If you add another host (Host3) to the cluster and
    Host3 is not attached to VDS1, it is an invalid configuration, and Host3
    will not be ready for NSX functionality.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    If you have vSphere Update Manager (VUM) in your environment, you must
    disable it before preparing clusters for network virtualization. For
    information on how to check if VUM is enabled and how to disable it if
    necessary, see the <link
    xlink:href="http://kb.vmware.com/kb/2053782">VMware knowledge base</link>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    In the vSphere web client, ensure that the cluster is in the resolved state
    (listed under the <guimenu>Host Preparation</guimenu> tab). If the Resolve option does not
    appear in the cluster's Actions list, then it is in a resolved state.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  To prepare the vSphere clusters for NSX:
 </para>
 <procedure>
  <step>
   <para>
    In vCenter, select <menuchoice><guimenu>Home</guimenu><guimenu>Networking
    &amp; Security</guimenu><guimenu>Installation</guimenu></menuchoice>, and
    then select the <guimenu>Host Preparation</guimenu> tab.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Continuing with the example in these instructions, click on the
    <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> button (gear icon) and select
    <guimenu>Install</guimenu> for both the control-plane cluster and compute
    cluster (if you are using something other than this example, then only
    install on the clusters that require NSX logical switching, routing, and
    firewalls).
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Monitor the installation until the <literal>Installation Status</literal>
    column displays a green check mark.
   </para>
   <important>
    <para>
     While installation is in
     progress, do not deploy, upgrade, or uninstall any service or component.
    </para>
   </important>
   <important>
    <para>
     If the <literal>Installation Status</literal> column displays a red
     warning icon and says <literal>Not Ready</literal>, click
     <guimenu>Resolve</guimenu>. Clicking <guimenu>Resolve</guimenu> might
     result in a reboot of the host. If the installation is still not
     successful, click the warning icon. All errors will be displayed. Take the
     required action and click <guimenu>Resolve</guimenu> again.
    </para>
   </important>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    To verify the VIBs (<filename>esx-vsip</filename> and
    <filename>esx-vxlan</filename>) are installed and registered, SSH into an
    ESXi host within the prepared cluster. List the names and versions of the
    VIBs installed by running the following command:
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.user;esxcli software vib list | grep esx</screen>
   <screen>...
esx-vsip      6.0.0-0.0.2732470    VMware  VMwareCertified   2015-05-29
esx-vxlan     6.0.0-0.0.2732470    VMware  VMwareCertified   2015-05-29
...
   </screen>
  </step>
 </procedure>
 <important>
  <para>
   After host preparation:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A host reboot is not required
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you add a host to a prepared cluster, the NSX VIBs are automatically
     installed on the host.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you move a host to an unprepared cluster, the NSX VIBs are
     automatically uninstalled from the host. In this case, a host reboot
     is required to complete the uninstall process.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </important>
</section>
