<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xml:id="nsx-deploy-os-cobbler"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Deploying the Operating System with Cobbler</title>
 <procedure>
  <step>
   <para>
    From the &clm;, run Cobbler to install the operating system on the nodes
    after it has to be deployed:
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost cobbler-deploy.yml
   </screen>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Verify the nodes that will have an operating system installed by Cobbler by
    running this command:
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.sudo;cobbler system find --netboot-enabled=1</screen>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Reimage the nodes using Cobbler.  Do not use Cobbler to reimage the nodes
    running as ESX virtual machines. The command below is run on a setup where
    the &o_comp; ESX compute proxies are VMs. Controllers 1, 2, and 3 are
    running on physical servers.
   </para>
   <screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost bm-reimage.yml -e \
   nodelist=controller1,controller2,controller3</screen>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    When the playbook has completed, each controller node should have an
    operating system installed with an IP address configured on
    <literal>eth0</literal>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    After your controller nodes have been completed, you should install the
    operating system on your &o_comp; compute proxy virtual machines. Each
    configured virtual machine should be able to PXE boot into the operating
    system installer.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    From within the vSphere environment, power on each &o_comp; compute proxy
    virtual machine and watch for it to PXE boot into the OS installer via its
    console.
   </para>
   <substeps>
    <step>
     <para>
    If successful, the virtual machine will have the operating system
    automatically installed and will then automatically power off.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      When the virtual machine has powered off, power it on and let it boot
      into the operating system.
     </para>
    </step>
   </substeps>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Verify network settings after deploying the operating system to each node.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Verify that the NIC bus mapping specified in the cloud model input file
      (<filename>~/ardana/my_cloud/definition/data/nic_mappings.yml</filename>)
      matches the NIC bus mapping on each &ostack; node.
     </para>
     <para>
      Check the NIC bus mapping with this command:
     </para>
     <screen>&prompt.sudo;cobbler system list</screen>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      After the playbook has completed, each controller node should have an
      operating system installed with an IP address configured on eth0.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    When the ESX compute proxy nodes are VMs, install the operating system if
    you have not already done so.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
</section>
