<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xml:id="nsx-add-controllers"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Add NSX Controllers</title>
 <para>
  The NSX controllers serve as the central control point for all logical
  switches within the vSphere environment's network, and they maintain
  information about all hosts, logical switches (VXLANs), and distributed
  logical routers.
 </para>
 <para>
  NSX controllers will each be deployed as a virtual appliance on the ESXi
  hosts within the control-plane cluster to form the NSX Controller
  cluster. For details about NSX controllers and the NSX control plane in
  general, refer to <link
  xlink:href="https://pubs.vmware.com/NSX-62/index.jsp?topic=%2Fcom.vmware.nsx.install.doc%2FGUID-4E0FEE83-CF2C-45E0-B0E6-177161C3D67C.html">VMware's
  NSX documentation</link>.
 </para>
 <important>
  <para>
   Whatever the size of the NSX deployment, the following conditions must be
   met:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Each NSX Controller cluster must contain three controller nodes. Having a
     different number of controller nodes is not supported.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Before deploying NSX Controllers, you must deploy an NSX Manager appliance
     and register vCenter with NSX Manager.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Determine the IP pool settings for your controller cluster, including the
     gateway and IP address range. DNS settings are optional.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The NSX Controller IP network must have connectivity to the NSX Manager
     and to the management interfaces on the ESXi hosts.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </important>
  <para>
   Log in to the vSphere web client and do the following steps to add the NSX
   controllers:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     In vCenter, navigate to <guimenu>Home</guimenu>, select
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Networking &amp;
     Security</guimenu><guimenu>Installation</guimenu></menuchoice>, and then
     select the <guimenu>Management</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>NSX Controller nodes</guimenu> section, click the
     <guimenu>Add Node</guimenu> icon represented by a green plus sign.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter the NSX Controller settings appropriate to your
     environment. If you are following this example, use the control-plane
     clustered ESXi hosts and control-plane DVS port group for the controller
     settings.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If it has not already been done, create an IP pool for the NSX Controller
     cluster with at least three IP addressess by clicking <guimenu>New IP
     Pool</guimenu>. Individual controllers can be in separate IP subnets, if
     necessary.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to deploy the controller. After the first controller is
     completely deployed, deploy two additional controllers.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <important>
   <para>
    Three NSX controllers is mandatory. VMware recommends configuring a DRS
    anti-affinity rule to prevent the controllers from residing on the same
    ESXi host. See more information about <link
    xlink:href="https://pubs.vmware.com/vsphere-51/index.jsp?topic=%2Fcom.vmware.vsphere.resmgmt.doc%2FGUID-FF28F29C-8B67-4EFF-A2EF-63B3537E6934.html">DRS
    Affinity Rules</link>.
   </para>
  </important>
</section>
