<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xml:id="nsx-install-manager"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Install NSX Manager</title>
 <para>
  The NSX Manager is the centralized network management component of NSX. It
  provides a single point of configuration and REST API entry-points.
 </para>
 <para>
   The NSX Manager is installed as a virtual appliance on one of the ESXi hosts
   within the vSphere environment. This guide will cover installing the
   appliance on one of the ESXi hosts within the control-plane cluster. For
   more detailed information, refer to <link
   xlink:href="https://pubs.vmware.com/NSX-62/index.jsp?topic=%2Fcom.vmware.nsx.install.doc%2FGUID-D8578F6E-A40C-493A-9B43-877C2B75ED52.html">VMware's
   NSX Installation Guide.</link>
 </para>
 <para>
  To install the NSX Manager, download the virtual appliance from <link
  xlink:href="https://www.vmware.com/go/download-nsx-vsphere">VMware</link> and
  deploy the appliance within vCenter onto one of the ESXi hosts. For
  information on deploying appliances within vCenter, refer to VMware's
  documentation for ESXi <link
  xlink:href="https://pubs.vmware.com/vsphere-55/index.jsp?topic=%2Fcom.vmware.vsphere.vm_admin.doc%2FGUID-AFEDC48B-C96F-4088-9C1F-4F0A30E965DE.html">5.5</link>
  or <link
  xlink:href="https://pubs.vmware.com/vsphere-60/index.jsp?topic=%2Fcom.vmware.vsphere.vm_admin.doc%2FGUID-AFEDC48B-C96F-4088-9C1F-4F0A30E965DE.html">6.0</link>.
 </para>
 <para>
  During the deployment of the NSX Manager appliance, be aware of the
  following:
 </para>
 <para>
  When prompted, select <guimenu>Accept extra configuration options</guimenu>.
  This will present options for configuring IPv4 and IPv6 addresses, the
  default gateway, DNS, NTP, and SSH properties during the installation, rather
  than configuring these settings manually after the installation.
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Choose an ESXi host that resides within the control-plane cluster.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Ensure that the network mapped port group is the DVS port group that
    represents the VLAN the NSX Manager will use for its networking (in this
    example it is labeled as the <literal>NSX Management</literal> network).
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <note>
  <para>
   The IP address assigned to the NSX Manager must be able to resolve
   reverse DNS.
  </para>
 </note>
 <para>
  Power on the NSX Manager virtual machine after it finishes deploying and wait
  for the operating system to fully load. When ready, carry out the following
  steps to have the NSX Manager use single sign-on (SSO) and to
  register the NSX Manager with vCenter:
 </para>
 <procedure>
  <step>
   <para>
    Open a web browser and enter the hostname or IP address that was assigned
    to the NSX Manager during setup.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Log in with the username <literal>admin</literal> and the
    password set during the deployment.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    After logging in, click on <guimenu>Manage vCenter Registration</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Configure the NSX Manager to connect to the vCenter server.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Configure NSX manager for single sign on (SSO) under the <guimenu>Lookup
    Server URL</guimenu> section.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
 <note>
  <para>
   When configuring SSO, use <literal>Lookup Service Port 443</literal> for
   vCenter version 6.0. Use <literal>Lookup Service Port 7444</literal> for
   vCenter version 5.5.
  </para>
  <para>
   SSO makes vSphere and NSX more secure by allowing the various components to
   communicate with each other through a secure token exchange mechanism,
   instead of requiring each component to authenticate a user separately. For
   more details, refer to VMware's documentation on <link
   xlink:href="https://pubs.vmware.com/NSX-62/index.jsp?topic=%2Fcom.vmware.nsx.install.doc%2FGUID-523B0D77-AAB9-4535-B326-1716967EC0D2.html">Configure
   Single Sign-On</link>.
  </para>
 </note>
 <para>
  Both the <literal>Lookup Service URL</literal> and the <literal>vCenter
  Server</literal> sections should have a status of
  <literal>connected</literal> when configured properly.
 </para>
 <para>
  Log into the vSphere Web Client (log out and and back in if already logged
  in). The NSX Manager will appear under the <guimenu>Networking &amp;
  Security</guimenu> section of the client.
 </para>
 <note>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Networking &amp; Security</guimenu> section will not appear
   under the vSphere desktop client. Use of the web client is required for the
   rest of this process.
  </para>
 </note>
</section>
