<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xml:id="nsx-create-transport-zone"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <title>Create a Transport Zone</title>
 <para>
  A transport zone controls which hosts a logical switch can reach and has the
  following characteristics.
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    It can span one or more vSphere clusters.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Transport zones dictate which clusters can participate in the use of a
    particular network. Therefore they dictate which VMs can participate in the
    use of a particular network.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    A vSphere NSX environment can contain one or more transport zones based on the
    environment's requirements.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    A host cluster can belong to multiple transport
    zones.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    A logical switch can belong to only one transport zone.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <note>
  <para>
   &ostack; has only been verified to work with a single transport zone within
   a vSphere NSX-v environment. Other configurations are currently not
   supported.
  </para>
 </note>
  <para>
   For more information on transport zones, refer to <link
   xlink:href="https://pubs.vmware.com/NSX-62/topic/com.vmware.nsx.install.doc/GUID-0B3BD895-8037-48A8-831C-8A8986C3CA42.html">VMware's
   Add A Transport Zone</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To create a transport zone:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the vSphere web client, navigate to
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Home</guimenu><guimenu>Networking &amp;
     Security</guimenu><guimenu>Installation</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the <guimenu>Logical Network Preparation</guimenu> tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Transport Zones</guimenu>, and then click the <guimenu>New
     Transport Zone</guimenu> (New Logical Switch) icon.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>New Transport Zone</guimenu> dialog box, type a name and
     an optional description for the transport zone.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     For these example instructions, select the control plane mode as
     <literal>Unicast</literal>.
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      Whether there is a controller in the environment or if the environment is
      going to use multicast addresses will determine the control plane mode to
      select:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literal>Unicast</literal> (what this set of instructions uses): The
        control plane is handled by an NSX controller. All unicast traffic
        leverages optimized headend replication. No multicast IP addresses or
        special network configuration is required.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literal>Multicast</literal>: Multicast IP addresses in the physical
        network are used for the control plane. This mode is recommended only
        when upgrading from older VXLAN deployments. Requires PIM/IGMP in the
        physical network.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <literal>Hybrid</literal>: Offloads local traffic replication to the
        physical network (L2 multicast). This requires IGMP snooping on the
        first-hop switch and access to an IGMP querier in each VTEP subnet, but
        does not require PIM. The first-hop switch handles traffic replication
        for the subnet.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the clusters to be added to the transport zone.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to save your changes.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
</section>
