<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="swift_weight_att">
 <title>Using the Weight-Step Attributes to Prepare for Ring Changes</title>
 <para>
  Swift rings are built during a deployment and this process sets the weights
  of disk drives such that smaller disk drives have a smaller weight than
  larger disk drives. When making changes in the ring, you should limit the
  amount of change that occurs. &kw-hos-phrase; does this by limiting the
  weights of the new drives to a smaller value and then building new rings.
  Once the replication process has finished, &kw-hos-phrase; will increase the
  weight and rebuild rings to trigger another round of replication. (For more
  information, see <xref linkend="swift_ring_rebalance"/>.)
 </para>
 <para>
  In addition, you should become familiar with how the replication process
  behaves on your system during normal operation. Before making ring changes,
  use the <literal>swift-recon</literal> command to determine the typical
  oldest replication times for your system. For instructions, see
  <xref linkend="topic_ohx_j1t_4t"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  In &kw-hos;, the weight-step attribute is set in the ring specification of
  the input model. The weight-step value specifies a maximum value for the
  change of the weight of a drive in any single rebalance. For example, if you
  add a drive of 4TB, you would normally assign a weight of 4096. However, if
  the weight-step attribute is set to 1024 instead then when you add that drive
  the weight is initially set to 1024. The next time you rebalance the ring,
  the weight is set to 2048. The subsequent rebalance would then set the weight
  to the final value of 4096.
 </para>
 <para>
  The value of the weight-step attribute is dependent on the size of the
  drives, number of the servers being added, and how experienced you are with
  the replication process. A common starting value is to use 20% of the size of
  an individual drive. For example, when adding X number of 4TB drives a value
  of 820 would be appropriate. As you gain more experience with your system,
  you may increase or reduce this value.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="setting-weight-step-attribute">
  <title>Setting the weight-step attribute</title>
  <para>
   Perform the following steps to set the weight-step attribute:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Log in to the &clm;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Edit the
     <literal>~/openstack/my_cloud/definition/data/swift/rings.yml</literal> file
     containing the ring-specifications for the account, container, and object
     rings.
    </para>
    <para>
     Add the weight-step attribute to the ring in this format:
    </para>
<screen>
- name: account
  weight-step: <replaceable>WEIGHT_STEP_VALUE</replaceable>
  display-name: Account Ring
  min-part-hours: 16
  ...</screen>
    <para>
     For example, to set weight-step to 820, add the attribute like this:
    </para>
<screen>- name: account
  weight-step: <emphasis role="bold">820</emphasis>
  display-name: Account Ring
  min-part-hours: 16
  ...</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Repeat step 2 for the other rings, if necessary (container, object-0,
     etc).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Run the configuration processor:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use the playbook to create a deployment directory:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To complete the configuration, use the ansible playbooks documented in
     <xref linkend="swift_ansible_playbooks"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
</section>
