<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="crt-components">
 <title>Components for Capacity Reporting</title>
 <section>
  <title>Monasca Transform: Data Aggregation Reporting</title>
  <para>
   Monasca-transform is a new component which provides mechanism to aggregate
   or transform metrics and publish new aggregated metrics to Monasca.
  </para>
  <para>
   Monasca Transform is a data driven Apache Spark based data aggregation
   engine which collects, groups and aggregates existing individual Monasca
   metrics according to business requirements and publishes new transformed
   (derived) metrics to the Monasca Kafka queue.
  </para>
  <para>
   Since the new transformed metrics are published as any other metric in
   Monasca, alarms can be set and triggered on the transformed metric, just
   like any other metric.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Object Storage and Compute Capacity Summary &opscon; UI</title>
  <para>
   A new "Capacity Summary" tab for Compute and Object Storage will displays
   all the aggregated metrics under the "Compute" and "Object Storage"
   sections.
  </para>
  <para>
   &opscon; UI makes calls to Monasca API to retrieve and display various
   tiles and graphs on Capacity Summary tab in Compute and Object Storage
   Summary UI pages.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Persist new metrics and Trigger Alarms</title>
  <para>
   New aggregated metrics will be published to Monasca's Kafka queue and will
   be ingested by monasca-persister. If thresholds and alarms have been set on
   the aggregated metrics, Monasca will generate and trigger alarms as it
   currently does with any other metric. No new/additional change is expected
   with persisting of new aggregated metrics or setting threshold/alarms.
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
