<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="changing_swift_zone">
 <title>Changing Swift Zone Layout</title>
 <para>
  Before changing the number of Swift zones or the assignment of servers to
  specific zones, you must ensure that your system has sufficient storage
  available to perform the operation. Specifically, if you are adding a new
  zone, you may need additional storage. There are two reasons for this:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    You cannot simply change the Swift zone number of disk drives in the ring.
    Instead, you need to remove the server(s) from the ring and then re-add
    the server(s) with a new Swift zone number to the ring. At the point where
    the servers are removed from the ring, there must be sufficient spare
    capacity on the remaining servers to hold the data that was originally
    hosted on the removed servers.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The total amount of storage in each Swift zone must be the same. This is
    because new data is added to each zone at the same rate. If one zone has a
    lower capacity than the other zones, once that zone becomes full, you
    cannot add more data to the system – even if there is unused space in
    the other zones.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  As mentioned above, you cannot simply change the Swift zone number of disk
  drives in an existing ring. Instead, you must remove and then re-add
  servers. This is a summary of the process:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Identify appropriate server groups that correspond to the desired Swift
    zone layout.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Remove the servers in a server group from the rings. This process may be
    protracted, either by removing servers in small batches or by using the
    weight-step attribute so that you limit the amount of replication traffic
    that happens at once.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Once all the targeted servers are removed, edit the
    <literal>swift-zones</literal> attribute in the ring specifications to add
    or remove a Swift zone.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Re-add the servers you had temporarily removed to the rings. Again you may
    need to do this in batches or rely on the weight-step attribute.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Continue removing and re-adding servers until you reach your final
    configuration.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-operations-objectstorage-changing_swift_zone-xml-5">
  <title>Process for Changing Swift Zones</title>
  <para>
   This section describes the detailed process or reorganizing Swift zones. As
   a concrete example, we assume we start with a single Swift zone and the
   target is three Swift zones. The same general process would apply if you
   were reducing the number of zones as well.
  </para>
  <para>
   The process is as follows:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Identify the appropriate server groups that represent the desired final
     state. In this example, we are going to change the Swift zone layout as
     follows:
    </para>
    <informaltable colsep="1" rowsep="1">
     <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
      <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
      <thead>
       <row>
        <entry>Original Layout</entry>
        <entry>Target Layout</entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>
<screen>swift-zones:
  - 1d: 1
    server-groups:
       - AZ1
       - AZ2
       - AZ3</screen>
        </entry>
        <entry>
<screen>swift-zones:
   - 1d: 1
     server-groups:
        - AZ1
   - id: 2
        - AZ2
   - id: 3
        - AZ3</screen>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
     The plan is to move servers from server groups <literal>AZ2</literal> and
     <literal>AZ3</literal> to a new Swift zone number. The servers in
     <literal>AZ1</literal> will remain in Swift zone 1.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you have not already done so, consider setting the weight-step
     attribute as described in <xref linkend="swift_weight_att"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Identify the servers in the <literal>AZ2</literal> server group. You may
     remove all servers at once or remove them in batches. If this is the first
     time you have performed a major ring change, we suggest you remove one or
     two servers only in the first batch. When you see how long this takes and
     the impact replication has on your system you can then use that experience
     to decide whether you can remove a larger batch of servers, or increase or
     decrease the weight-step attribute for the next server-removal cycle. To
     remove a server, use steps 2-9 as described in
     <xref linkend="remove_swift_node"/> ensuring that you
     do not remove the servers from the input model.
     <!-- FIXME: <xref/> for steps 2-9 -->
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     This process may take a number of ring rebalance cycles until the disk
     drives are removed from the ring files. Once this happens, you can edit
     the ring specifications and add Swift zone 2 as shown in this example:
    </para>
<screen>swift-zones:
  - id: 1
    server-groups:
      - AZ1
      - AZ3
  - id: 2
       - AZ2</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The server removal process in step #3
     <!-- FIXME: <xref> addition needed for "step #3". -->
     set the "remove" attribute in the
     <literal>pass-through</literal> attribute of the servers in server group
     <literal>AZ2</literal>. Edit the input model files and remove this
     <literal>pass-through</literal> attribute. This signals to the system that
     the servers should be used the next time we rebalance the rings (that is,
     the server should be added to the rings).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Commit your configuration to the local Git repository
     (<xref linkend="using_git"/>), as follows:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;git add -A
&prompt.ardana;git commit -m "My config or other commit message"</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Run the configuration processor:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use the playbook to create a deployment directory:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Rebuild and deploy the Swift rings containing the re-added servers by
     running this playbook:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-deploy.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Wait until replication has finished. For more details, see
     <xref linkend="topic_ohx_j1t_4t"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You may need to continue to rebalance the rings. For instructions, see the
     "Final Rebalance Stage" steps at <xref linkend="change_swift_rings"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     At this stage, the servers in server group <literal>AZ2</literal> are
     responsible for Swift zone 2. Repeat the process in steps #3-9 to remove
     the servers in server group <literal>AZ3</literal> from the rings and then
     re-add them to Swift zone 3. The ring specifications for zones (step 4)
     should be as follows:
    </para>
<screen>swift-zones:
  - 1d: 1
    server-groups:
      - AZ1
  - id: 2
      - AZ2
  - id: 3
      - AZ3</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Once complete, all data should be dispersed (that is, each replica is
     located) in the Swift zones as specified in the input model.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
</section>
