<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="topic_ohx_j1t_4t">
 <title>Determining When to Rebalance and Deploy a New Ring</title>
 <para>
  Before deploying a new ring, you must be sure the change that has been
  applied to the last ring is complete (that is, all the partitions are in
  their correct location). There are three aspects to this:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Is the replication system busy?
   </para>
   <para>
    You might want to postpone a ring change until after replication has
    finished. If the replication system is busy repairing a failed drive, a
    ring change will place additional load on the system. To check that
    replication has finished, use the <literal>swift-recon</literal> command
    with the <emphasis role="bold">--replication</emphasis> argument. (For more
    information, see <xref linkend="swift_recon"/>.) The
    oldest completion time can indicate that the replication process is very
    busy. If it is more than 15 or 20 minutes then the object replication
    process are probably still very busy. The following example indicates
    that the oldest completion is 120 seconds, so that the replication
    process is probably not busy:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;swift-recon --replication
===============================================================================
--&gt; Starting reconnaissance on 3 hosts
===============================================================================
[2015-10-02 15:31:45] Checking on replication
[replication_time] low: 0, high: 0, avg: 0.0, total: 0, Failed: 0.0%, no_result: 0, reported: 3
Oldest completion was 2015-10-02 15:31:32 (120 seconds ago) by 192.168.245.4:6000.
Most recent completion was 2015-10-02 15:31:43 (10 seconds ago) by 192.168.245.3:6000.
===============================================================================</screen>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Are there drive or server failures?
   </para>
   <para>
    A drive failure does not preclude deploying a new ring. In principle, there
    should be two copies elsewhere. However, another drive failure in the
    middle of replication might make data temporary unavailable. If possible,
    postpone ring changes until all servers and drives are operating normally.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Has <literal>min-part-hours</literal> elapsed?
   </para>
   <para>
    The <literal>swift-ring-builder</literal> will refuse to build a new ring
    until the <literal>min-part-hours</literal> has elapsed since the last time
    it built rings. You must postpone changes until this time has elapsed.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can determine how long you must wait by running the
    <literal>swift-compare-model-rings.yml</literal> playbook, which will tell
    you how long you until the <literal>min-part-hours</literal> has elapsed.
    For more details, see <xref linkend="swift_ansible_playbooks"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can change the value of <literal>min-part-hours</literal>. (For
    instructions, see <xref linkend="min_part_hours"/>).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Is the Swift dispersion report clean?
   </para>
   <para>
    Run the <literal>swift-dispersion-report.yml</literal> playbook (as
    described in <xref linkend="swift_healthcheck"/>) and
    examine the results. If the replication process has not yet replicated
    partitions that were moved to new drives in the last ring rebalance, the
    dispersion report will indicate that some containers or objects are
    missing a copy.
   </para>
   <para>
    For example:
   </para>
<screen>There were 462 partitions missing one copy.</screen>
   <para>
    Assuming all servers and disk drives are operational, the reason for the
    missing partitions is that the replication process has not yet managed to
    copy a replica into the partitions.
   </para>
   <para>
    You should wait an hour and rerun the dispersion report process and examine
    the report. The number of partitions missing one copy should have reduced.
    Continue to wait until this reaches zero before making any further ring
    rebalances.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     It is normal to see partitions missing one copy if disk drives or
     servers are down. If all servers and disk drives are mounted, and you
     did not recently perform a ring rebalance, you should investigate
     whether there are problems with the replication process. You can use the
     &opscon; to investigate replication issues.
    </para>
   </note>
   <important>
    <para>
     If there are any partitions missing two copies, you must reboot or repair
     any failed servers and disk drives as soon as possible. Do not shutdown
     any Swift nodes in this situation. Assuming a replica count of 3, if you
     are missing two copies you are in danger of losing the only remaining
     copy.
    </para>
   </important>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</section>
