<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="sec-operation-identity-overview">
 <title>The Identity Service</title>
 <para>
  This topic explains the purpose and mechanisms of the identity service.
 </para>
 <para>
  The &productname; Identity service, based on the OpenStack keystone API, is
  responsible for providing UserID authentication and access authorization to
  enable organizations to achieve their access security and compliance
  objectives and successfully deploy OpenStack. In short, the Identity service
  is the gateway to the rest of the OpenStack services.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-operations-configuring-identity-identity-overview-xml-7">
  <title>Which version of the Identity service should you use?</title>
  <para>
   Use Identity API version 3.0, as previous versions no longer exist as
   endpoints for Identity API queries.
  </para>
  <para>
   Similarly, when performing queries, you must use the OpenStack CLI (the
   <command>openstack</command> command), and not the keystone CLI
   (<command>keystone</command>) as the latter is only compatible with API
   versions prior to 3.0.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-operations-configuring-identity-identity-overview-xml-8">
  <title>Authentication</title>
  <para>
   The authentication function provides the initial login function to
   OpenStack. keystone supports multiple sources of authentication, including a
   native or built-in authentication system. The keystone native system can be
   used for all user management functions for proof of concept deployments or
   small deployments not requiring integration with a corporate authentication
   system, but it lacks some of the advanced functions usually found in user
   management systems such as forcing password changes. The focus of the
   keystone native authentication system is to be the source of authentication
   for OpenStack-specific users required for the operation of the various
   OpenStack services. These users are stored by keystone in a default domain;
   the addition of these IDs to an external authentication system is not
   required.
  </para>
  <para>
   keystone is more commonly integrated with external authentication systems
   such as OpenLDAP or Microsoft Active Directory. These systems are usually
   centrally deployed by organizations to serve as the single source of user
   management and authentication for all in-house deployed applications and
   systems requiring user authentication. In addition to LDAP and Microsoft
   Active Directory, support for integration with Security Assertion Markup
   Language (SAML)-based identity providers from companies such as Ping, CA,
   IBM, Oracle, and others is also nearly "production-ready".
  </para>
  <para>
   keystone also provides architectural support via the underlying Apache
   deployment for other types of authentication systems such as Multi-Factor
   Authentication. These types of systems typically require driver support and
   integration from the respective provider vendors.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    While support for Identity Providers and Multi-factor authentication is
    available in keystone, it has not yet been certified by the &productname;
    engineering team and is an experimental feature in &productname;.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   LDAP-compatible directories such as OpenLDAP and Microsoft Active Directory
   are recommended alternatives to using the keystone local authentication.
   Both methods are widely used by organizations and are integrated with a
   variety of other enterprise applications. These directories act as the
   single source of user information within an organization. keystone can be
   configured to authenticate against an LDAP-compatible directory on a
   per-domain basis.
  </para>
  <para>
   Domains, as explained in <xref linkend="sec-operation-identity"/>,
   can be configured so that based on the user ID, a incoming user is
   automatically mapped to a specific domain. This domain can then be
   configured to authenticate against a specific LDAP directory. The user
   credentials provided by the user to keystone are passed along to the
   designated LDAP source for authentication. This communication can be
   optionally configured to be secure via SSL encryption. No special LDAP
   administrative access is required, and only read-only access is needed for
   this configuration. keystone will not add any LDAP information. All user
   additions, deletions, and modifications are performed by the application's
   front end in the LDAP directories. After a user has been successfully
   authenticated, they are then assigned to the groups, roles, and projects
   defined by the keystone domain or project administrators. This information
   is stored within the keystone service database.
  </para>
  <para>
   Another form of external authentication provided by the keystone service is
   via integration with SAML-based Identity Providers (IdP) such as Ping
   Identity, IBM Tivoli, and Microsoft Active Directory Federation Server. A
   SAML-based identity provider provides authentication that is often called
   "single sign-on". The IdP server is configured to authenticate against
   identity sources such as Active Directory and provides a single
   authentication API against multiple types of downstream identity sources.
   This means that an organization could have multiple identity storage sources
   but a single authentication source. In addition, if a user has logged into
   one such source during a defined session time frame, they do not need to
   re-authenticate within the defined session. Instead, the IdP will
   automatically validate the user to requesting applications and services.
  </para>
  <para>
   A SAML-based IdP authentication source is configured with keystone on a
   per-domain basis similar to the manner in which native LDAP directories are
   configured. Extra mapping rules are required in the configuration that
   define which keystone group an incoming UID is automatically assigned to.
   This means that groups need to be defined in keystone first, but it also
   removes the requirement that a domain or project admin assign user roles and
   project membership on a per-user basis. Instead, groups are used to define
   project membership and roles and incoming users are automatically mapped to
   keystone groups based on their upstream group membership. This provides a
   very consistent role-based access control (RBAC) model based on the upstream
   identity source. The configuration of this option is fairly straightforward.
   IdP vendors such as Ping and IBM are contributing to the maintenance of this
   function and have also produced their own integration documentation.
   Microsoft Active Directory Federation Services (ADFS) is used for functional
   testing and future documentation.
  </para>
  <!-- Commented in DITA -->
  <!--horizon support for web single sign-on is also now available in the
  OpenStack Kilo release but not yet validated for &productname;.-->
  <para>
   The third keystone-supported authentication source is known as Multi-Factor
   Authentication (MFA). MFA typically requires an external source of
   authentication beyond a login name and password, and can include options
   such as SMS text, a temporal token generator, a fingerprint scanner, etc.
   Each of these types of MFA are usually specific to a particular MFA vendor.
   The keystone architecture supports an MFA-based authentication system, but
   this has not yet been certified or documented for &productname;.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-operations-configuring-identity-identity-overview-xml-9">
  <title>Authorization</title>
  <para>
   The second major function provided by the keystone service is access
   authorization that determines what resources and actions are available based
   on the UserID, the role of the user, and the projects that a user is
   provided access to. All of this information is created, managed, and stored
   by keystone. These functions are applied via the horizon web interface, the
   OpenStack command-line interface, or the direct keystone API.
  </para>
  <para>
   keystone provides support for organizing users via three entities including:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Domains</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Domains provide the highest level of organization. Domains are intended
      to be used as high-level containers for multiple projects. A domain can
      represent different tenants, companies or organizations for an OpenStack
      cloud deployed for public cloud deployments or represent major business
      units, functions, or any other type of top-level organization unit in an
      OpenStack private cloud deployment. Each domain has at least one Domain
      Admin assigned to it. This Domain Admin can then create multiple projects
      within the domain and assign the project admin role to specific project
      owners. Each domain created in an OpenStack deployment is unique and the
      projects assigned to a domain cannot exist in another domain.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Projects</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Projects are entities within a domain that represent groups of users,
      each user role within that project, and how many underlying
      infrastructure resources can be consumed by members of the project.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Groups</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Groups are an optional function and provide the means of assigning
      project roles to multiple users at once.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
   keystone also provides the means to create and assign roles to groups of
   users or individual users. The role names are created and user assignments
   are made within keystone. The actual function of a role is defined currently
   per each OpenStack service via scripts. When a user requests access to an
   OpenStack service, his access token contains information about his assigned
   project membership and role for that project. This role is then matched to
   the service-specific script and the user is allowed to perform functions
   within that service defined by the role mapping.
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
