<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="opsconsole-compute-instances">
 <title>Compute Instances</title>
 <para>
  This &opscon; page allows you to monitor your Compute instances.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Search and Sort</title>
  <para>
   The search bar allows you to filter the alarm definitions you want to view.
   Type and Status are examples of alarm criteria that can be specified.
   Additionally, you can filter by typing in text similar to searching by
   keywords.
  </para>
  <para>
   The checkbox allows you to select (or deselect) a group of alarm definitions
   to delete:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Select Visible</guimenu> allows you to delete the selected alarm
     definitions from the table.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Select All</guimenu> allows you to delete all the alarms from the
     table.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Clear Selection</guimenu> allows you to clear all the selections
     currently selected from the table.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   You can display the alarm definitions by grid, list or table views by
   selecting the corresponding icons next to the <guimenu>Sort By</guimenu>
   control.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Sort By</guimenu> control contains a drop-down list of ways by
   which you can sort the compute nodes. Alternatively, you can also sort using
   the column headers in the table.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Name</guimenu> displays the compute instances by the name
     assigned to it when it was created.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by State</guimenu> displays the compute instances by their
     current state.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Status</guimenu> displays the compute instances by their
     current status.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Host</guimenu> displays the compute instances by their
     host.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Image</guimenu> displays the compute instances by the
     image being used.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by IP Address</guimenu> displays the compute instances by
     their IP address.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</section>
