<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="UsingVPNaaS">
 <title>Using VPN as a Service (VPNaaS)</title>
 <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">&productname; &productnumber; VPNaaS Configuration</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  This document describes the configuration process and requirements for the
  &productname; &productnumber; Virtual Private Network (VPN) as a Service
  (VPNaaS) module.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-networking-vpnaas-xml-7">
  <title>Prerequisites</title>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &productname; must be installed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Before setting up VPNaaS, you will need to have created an external
     network and a subnet with access to the internet. Information on how to
     create the external network and subnet can be found in
     <xref linkend="sec.vpnaas.more"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You should assume 172.16.0.0/16 as the ext-net CIDR in this document.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="Considerations">
  <title>Considerations</title>
  <para>
   Using the Neutron plugin-based VPNaaS causes additional processes to be run
   on the Network Service Nodes. One of these processes, the ipsec charon
   process from StrongSwan, runs as root and listens on an external network. A
   vulnerability in that process can lead to remote root compromise of the
   Network Service Nodes. If this is a concern customers should consider using
   a VPN solution other than the Neutron plugin-based VPNaaS and/or deploying
   additional protection mechanisms.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-networking-vpnaas-xml-9">
  <title>Configuration</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Setup Networks</emphasis> You can setup VPN as a
   Service (VPNaaS) by first creating networks, subnets and routers using the
   <literal>neutron</literal> command line. The VPNaaS module enables the
   ability to extend access between private networks across two different
   &productname; clouds or between a &productname; cloud and a non-cloud network. VPNaaS
   is based on the open source software application called StrongSwan.
   StrongSwan (more information available
   at <link xlink:href="http://www.strongswan.org/"/>)
   is an IPsec implementation and provides basic VPN gateway functionality.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    You can execute the included commands from any shell with access to the
    service APIs. In the included examples, the commands are executed from the
    lifecycle manager, however you could execute the commands from the
    controller node or any other shell with aforementioned service API access.
   </para>
  </note>
  <note>
   <para>
    The use of floating IP's is not possible with the current version of
    VPNaaS when DVR is enabled. Ensure that no floating IP is associated to
    instances that will be using VPNaaS when using a DVR router. Floating IP
    associated to instances are ok when using CVR router.
   </para>
  </note>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the &clm;, create first private network, subnet and
     router assuming that <emphasis>ext-net</emphasis> is created by admin.
    </para>
<screen>openstack network create privateA
openstack subnet create --name subA privateA 10.1.0.0/24 --gateway 10.1.0.1
openstack router create router1
openstack router add subnet router1 subA
openstack router set router1 ext-net</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create second private network, subnet and router.
    </para>
<screen>openstack network create privateB
openstack subnet create --name subB privateB 10.2.0.0/24 --gateway 10.2.0.1
openstack router create router2
openstack router add subnet router2 subB
openstack router set router2 ext-net</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <procedure xml:id="pro.vpnaas.start">
   <title>Starting Virtual Machines</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the &clm; run the following to start the virtual
     machines. Begin with adding secgroup rules for SSH and ICMP.
    </para>
<screen>openstack security group rule create default --protocol icmp
openstack security group rule create default --protocol tcp --port-range-min 22 --port-range-max 22</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the virtual machine in the privateA subnet. Using <emphasis>nova
     images-list</emphasis>, use the image id to boot image instead of the
     image name. After executing this step, it is recommended that you wait
     approximately 10 seconds to allow the virtual machine to become active.
    </para>
<screen>NETA=$(openstack network list | awk '/privateA/ {print $2}')
openstack server create --flavor 1 --image &lt;id&gt; --nic net-id=$NETA vm1</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the virtual machine in the privateB subnet.
    </para>
<screen>NETB=$(openstack network list | awk '/privateB/ {print $2}')
openstack server create --flavor 1 --image &lt;id&gt; --nic net-id=$NETB vm2</screen>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="st.vpnaas.obtain-ip">
    <para>
     Verify private IP's are allocated to the respective vms. Take note of IP's
     for later use.
    </para>
<screen>openstack server show vm1
openstack server show vm2</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <procedure>
   <title>Create VPN</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     You can set up the VPN by executing the below commands from the lifecycle
     manager or any shell with access to the service APIs. Begin with creating
     the policies with <literal>vpn-ikepolicy-create</literal> and
     <literal>vpn-ipsecpolicy-create </literal>.
    </para>
<screen>neutron vpn-ikepolicy-create ikepolicy
neutron vpn-ipsecpolicy-create ipsecpolicy</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create the VPN service at router1.
    </para>
<screen>neutron vpn-service-create --name myvpnA --description "My vpn service" router1 subA</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Wait at least 5 seconds and then run
     <literal>ipsec-site-connection-create</literal> to create a ipsec-site
     connection. Note that <literal>--peer-address</literal> is the assign
     ext-net IP from router2 and <literal>--peer-cidr</literal> is subB cidr.
    </para>
<screen>neutron ipsec-site-connection-create --name vpnconnection1 --vpnservice-id myvpnA \
--ikepolicy-id ikepolicy --ipsecpolicy-id ipsecpolicy --peer-address 172.16.0.3 \
--peer-id 172.16.0.3 --peer-cidr 10.2.0.0/24 --psk secret</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create the VPN service at router2.
    </para>
<screen>neutron vpn-service-create --name myvpnB --description "My vpn serviceB" router2 subB </screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Wait at least 5 seconds and then run
     <literal>ipsec-site-connection-create</literal> to create a ipsec-site
     connection. Note that <literal>--peer-address</literal> is the assigned
     ext-net IP from router1 and <literal>--peer-cidr</literal> is subA cidr.
    </para>
<screen>neutron ipsec-site-connection-create --name vpnconnection2 --vpnservice-id myvpnB \
--ikepolicy-id ikepolicy --ipsecpolicy-id ipsecpolicy --peer-address 172.16.0.2 \
--peer-id 172.16.0.2 --peer-cidr 10.1.0.0/24 --psk secret</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the &clm;, run the
     <literal>ipsec-site-connection-list</literal> command to see the active
     connections. Be sure to check that the vpn_services are ACTIVE. You can
     check this by running <literal>vpn-service-list</literal> and then
     checking ipsec-site-connections status. You should expect that the time
     for both vpn-services and ipsec-site-connections to become ACTIVE could
     take as long as 1 to 3 minutes.
    </para>
<screen>neutron ipsec-site-connection-list
+--------------------------------------+----------------+--------------+---------------+------------+-----------+--------+
| id                                   | name           | peer_address | peer_cidrs    | route_mode | auth_mode | status |
+--------------------------------------+----------------+--------------+---------------+------------+-----------+--------+
| 1e8763e3-fc6a-444c-a00e-426a4e5b737c | vpnconnection2 | 172.16.0.2   | "10.1.0.0/24" | static     | psk       | ACTIVE |
| 4a97118e-6d1d-4d8c-b449-b63b41e1eb23 | vpnconnection1 | 172.16.0.3   | "10.2.0.0/24" | static     | psk       | ACTIVE |
+--------------------------------------+----------------+--------------+---------------+------------+-----------+--------+</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Verify VPN</emphasis> In the case of non-admin users,
   you can verify the VPN connection by pinging the virtual machines.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Check the VPN connections.
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      vm1-ip and vm2-ip denotes private IP's for vm1 and vm2 respectively.
      The private IPs are obtained, as described in of
      <xref linkend="st.vpnaas.obtain-ip"/>. If you are unable to SSH to the
      private network due to a lack
      of direct access, the VM console can be accessed through Horizon.
     </para>
    </note>
<screen>ssh cirros@vm1-ip
password: &lt;password&gt;

# ping the private IP address of vm2
ping ###.###.###.###</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In another terminal.
    </para>
<screen>ssh cirros@vm2-ip
password: &lt;password&gt;

# ping the private IP address of vm1
ping ###.###.###.###</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     You should see ping responses from both virtual machines.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   As the admin user, you should check to make sure that a route exists between
   the router gateways. Once the gateways have been checked, packet encryption
   can be verified by using traffic analyzer (tcpdump) by tapping on the
   respective namespace (qrouter-* in case of non-DVR and snat-* in case of
   DVR) and tapping the right interface (qg-***).
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    When using DVR namespaces, all the occurrences of qrouter-xxxxxx in the
    following commands should be replaced with respective snat-xxxxxx.
   </para>
  </note>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Check the if the route exists between two router gateways. You can get the
     right qrouter namespace id by executing <emphasis>sudo ip
     netns</emphasis>. Once you have the qrouter namespace id, you can get the
     interface by executing <emphasis>sudo ip netns qrouter-xxxxxxxx ip
     addr</emphasis> and from the result the interface can be found.
    </para>
<screen>sudo ip netns
sudo ip netns exec qrouter-&lt;router1 UUID&gt; ping &lt;router2 gateway&gt;
sudo ip netns exec qrouter-&lt;router2 UUID&gt; ping &lt;router1 gateway&gt;</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Initiate a tcpdump on the interface.
    </para>
<screen>sudo ip netns exec qrouter-xxxxxxxx tcpdump -i qg-xxxxxx</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Check the VPN connection.
    </para>
<screen>ssh cirros@vm1-ip
password: &lt;password&gt;

# ping the private IP address of vm2
ping ###.###.###.###</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Repeat for other namespace and right tap interface.
    </para>
<screen>sudo ip netns exec qrouter-xxxxxxxx tcpdump -i qg-xxxxxx</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In another terminal.
    </para>
<screen>ssh cirros@vm2-ip
password: &lt;password&gt;

# ping the private IP address of vm1
ping ###.###.###.###</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     You will find encrypted packets containing ‘ESP’ in the tcpdump trace.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="sec.vpnaas.more">
  <title>More Information</title>
  <para>
   VPNaaS currently only supports Pre-shared Keys (PSK) security between VPN
   gateways. A different VPN gateway solution should be considered if stronger,
   certificate-based security is required.
  </para>
  <para>
   For more information on the neutron command-line interface (CLI) and VPN as
   a Service (VPNaaS), see the OpenStack networking command-line client
   reference:
   <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/python-openstackclient/rocky/"/>
  </para>
  <para>
   For information on how to create an external network and subnet, see the
   OpenStack manual:
   <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide/dashboard_create_networks.html"/>
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
