<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="creating-voltype">
 <title>Creating a Volume Type for your Volumes</title>
 <para>
  Creating volume types allows you to create standard specifications for your
  volumes.
 </para>
 <para>
  Volume types are used to specify a standard Block Storage back-end and
  collection of extra specifications for your volumes. This allows an
  administrator to give its users a variety of options while simplifying the
  process of creating volumes.
 </para>
 <para>
  The tasks involved in this process are:
 </para>
 <section xml:id="create-volumetype">
  <title>Create a Volume Type for your Volumes</title>
  <para>
   The default volume type will be thin provisioned and will have no fault
   tolerance (RAID 0). You should configure Cinder to fully provision volumes,
   and you may want to configure fault tolerance. Follow the instructions below
   to create a new volume type that is fully provisioned and fault tolerant:
  </para>
  <para>
   Perform the following steps to create a volume type using the Horizon GUI:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in to the Horizon dashboard.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Ensure that you are scoped to your <literal>admin</literal> Project. Then
     under the <guimenu>Admin</guimenu> menu in the navigation pane, click on
     <guimenu>Volumes</guimenu> under the <guimenu>System</guimenu> subheading.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the <guimenu>Volume Types</guimenu> tab and then click the
     <guimenu>Create Volume Type</guimenu> button to display a dialog box.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Enter a unique name for the volume type and then click the
     <guimenu>Create Volume Type</guimenu> button to complete the
     action.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   The newly created volume type will be displayed in the <literal>Volume
   Types</literal> list confirming its creation.
  </para>
  <important>
   <para>
    You must set a <literal>default_volume_type</literal> in
    <filename>cinder.conf.j2</filename>, whether it is
    <literal>default_type</literal> or one you have created. For more
    information, see <xref linkend="config-fc"/>.
   </para>
  </important>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="associate-volumetype">
  <title>Associate the Volume Type to the Back-end</title>
  <para>
   After the volume type(s) have been created, you can assign extra
   specification attributes to the volume types. Each Block Storage back-end
   option has unique attributes that can be used.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <xref linkend="extraspecs-3par"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   To map a volume type to a back-end, do the following:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log into the Horizon dashboard.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Ensure that you are scoped to your <guimenu>admin</guimenu> Project (for
     more information, see <xref linkend="scopeToDomain"/>. Then under the
     <guimenu>Admin</guimenu> menu in the navigation pane, click on
     <guimenu>Volumes</guimenu> under the <guimenu>System</guimenu> subheading.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guimenu>Volume Type</guimenu> tab to list the volume types.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> column of the Volume Type you created
     earlier, click the drop-down option and select <guimenu>View Extra
     Specs</guimenu> which will bring up the <guimenu>Volume Type Extra
     Specs</guimenu> options.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guimenu>Create</guimenu> button on the <literal>Volume Type
     Extra Specs</literal> screen.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <literal>Key</literal> field, enter one of the key values in the
     table in the next section. In the <literal>Value</literal> box, enter its
     corresponding value. Once you have completed that, click the
     <guimenu>Create</guimenu> button to create the extra volume type specs.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   Once the volume type is mapped to a back-end, you can create volumes with
   this volume type.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="extraspecs-3par">
  <title>Extra Specification Options for 3PAR</title>
  <para>
   3PAR supports volumes creation with additional attributes. These attributes
   can be specified using the extra specs options for your volume type. The
   administrator is expected to define appropriate extra spec for 3PAR volume
   type as per the guidelines provided at
   <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/liberty/config-reference/content/hp-3par-supported-ops.html"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   The following Cinder Volume Type extra-specs options enable control over the
   3PAR storage provisioning type:
  </para>
  <informaltable colsep="1" rowsep="1">
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
    <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Key</entry>
      <entry>Value</entry>
      <entry>Description</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>volume_backend_name</entry>
      <entry><emphasis>volume backend name</emphasis>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        The name of the back-end to which you want to associate the volume type,
        which you also specified earlier in the
        <literal>cinder.conf.j2</literal> file.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>hp3par:provisioning (optional)</entry>
      <entry>thin, full, or dedup</entry>
      <entry/>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
  <para>
   For more information, see <xref linkend="config-3par"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
