<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="change-swift-rings">
 <title>Applying Input Model Changes to Existing Rings</title>
 <para>
  This page describes a general approach for making changes to your existing
  swift rings. This approach applies to actions such as adding and removing a
  server and replacing and upgrading disk drives, and must be performed as a
  series of phases, as shown below:
 </para>
 <section xml:id="change-inputmodel">
  <title>Changing the Input Model Configuration Files</title>
  <para>
   The first step to apply new changes to the swift environment is to update
   the configuration files. Follow these steps:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Log in to the &clm;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Set the weight-step attribute, as needed, for the nodes you are altering.
     (For instructions, see <xref linkend="swift-weight-att"/>).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Edit the configuration files as part of the Input Model as appropriate.
     (For general information about the Input Model, see
     <xref linkend="configobj-networks"/>. For more specific information about
     the swift parts of the configuration files, see
     <xref linkend="modify-input-model"/>)
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Once you have completed all of the changes, commit your configuration to
     the local git repository. (For more information,
     see<xref linkend="using-git"/>.) :
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;git add -A
&prompt.root;git commit -m "commit message"</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Run the configuration processor:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Create a deployment directory:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Run the swift playbook that will validate your configuration files and
     give you a report as an output:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
&prompt.root;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-compare-model-rings.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use the report to validate that the number of drives proposed to be added
     or deleted, or the weight change, is correct. Fix any errors in your input
     model. At this stage, no changes have been made to rings.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="first-rebalance">
  <title>First phase of Ring Rebalance</title>
  <para>
   To begin the rebalancing of the swift rings, follow these steps:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     After going through the steps in the section above, deploy your changes to
     all of the swift nodes in your environment by running this playbook:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-deploy.yml </screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Wait until replication has finished or <literal>min-part-hours</literal>
     has elapsed (whichever is longer). For more information, see
     <xref linkend="topic-ohx-j1t-4t"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="weight-change">
  <title>Weight Change Phase of Ring Rebalance</title>
  <para>
   At this stage, no changes have been made to the input model. However, when
   you set the <literal>weight-step</literal> attribute, the rings that were
   rebuilt in the previous rebalance phase have weights that are different than
   their target/final value. You gradually move to the target/final weight by
   rebalancing a number of times as described on this page. For more
   information about the weight-step attribute, see
   <xref linkend="swift-weight-att"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   To begin the re-balancing of the rings, follow these steps:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Rebalance the rings by running the playbook:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-update-from-model-rebalance-rings.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Run the reconfiguration:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-reconfigure.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Wait until replication has finished or <literal>min-part-hours</literal>
     has elapsed (whichever is longer). For more information, see
     <xref linkend="topic-ohx-j1t-4t"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Run the following command and review the report:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-compare-model-rings.yml --limit SWF*</screen>
    <para>
     The following is an example of the output after executing the above
     command. In the example <emphasis role="bold">no</emphasis> weight changes
     are proposed:
    </para>
<screen>TASK: [swiftlm-ring-supervisor | validate-input-model | Print report] *********
ok: [padawan-ccp-c1-m1-mgmt] =&gt; {
    "var": {
        "report.stdout_lines": [
            "Need to add 0 devices",
            "Need to remove 0 devices",
            "<emphasis role="bold">Need to set weight on 0 devices</emphasis>"
        ]
    }
}</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     When there are no proposed weight changes, you proceed to the final phase.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If there are proposed weight changes repeat this phase again.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="final-rebalance">
  <title>Final Rebalance Phase</title>
  <para>
   The final rebalance phase moves all replicas to their final destination.
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Rebalance the rings by running the playbook:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-update-from-model-rebalance-rings.yml | tee /tmp/rebalance.log</screen>
    <note>
     <para>
      The output is saved for later reference.
     </para>
    </note>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Review the output from the previous step. If the output for all rings is
     similar to the following, the rebalance had no effect. That is, the rings
     are balanced and no further changes are needed. In addition, the ring
     files were not changed so you do not need to deploy them to the swift
     nodes:
    </para>
<screen>"Running: swift-ring-builder /etc/swiftlm/cloud1/cp1/builder_dir/account.builder rebalance 999",
      "NOTE: No partitions could be reassigned.",
      "Either none need to be or none can be due to min_part_hours [16]."</screen>
    <para>
     The text <emphasis role="bold">No partitions could be
     reassigned</emphasis> indicates that no further rebalances are necessary.
     If this is true for all the rings, you have completed the final phase.
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      You must have allowed enough time to elapse since the last rebalance.
      As mentioned in the above example, <literal>min_part_hours [16]</literal>
      means that you must wait at least 16 hours since the last rebalance. If
      not, you should wait until enough time has elapsed and repeat this
      phase.
     </para>
    </note>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Run the <literal>swift-reconfigure.yml</literal> playbook:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-reconfigure.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Wait until replication has finished or <literal>min-part-hours</literal>
     has elapsed (whichever is longer). For more information see
     <xref linkend="topic-ohx-j1t-4t"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Repeat the above steps until the ring is rebalanced.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="system-changes">
  <title>System Changes that Change Existing Rings</title>
  <para>
   There are many system changes ranging from adding servers to replacing
   drives, which might require you to rebuild and rebalance your rings.
  </para>
<!-- Comment from DITA original: -->
<!--Note: This section provides an overview of these changes and a summary of
the required actions. More detailed procedures are provided elsewhere.-->
  <informaltable colsep="1" rowsep="1">
   <tgroup cols="2">
    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry><emphasis role="bold">Actions</emphasis>
      </entry>
      <entry><emphasis role="bold">Process</emphasis>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>Adding Server(s)</entry>
      <entry>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          If not already done, set the weight change attribute. For
          instructions, see <xref linkend="swift-weight-att"/>
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Add servers in phases:
         </para>
         <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            This reduces the impact of the changes on your system.
           </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
           <para>
<<<<<<< HEAD
            If your rings use Swift zones, ensure that you add the same
=======
            If your rings use swift zones, ensure that you remove the same
>>>>>>> f20f5b78... Updating project names to lowercase (SOC-9552)
            number of servers to each zone at each phase.
           </para>
          </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          To add a server, see <xref linkend="sec-swift-add-object-node"/>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Incrementally change the weights and perform the final rebalance. For
          instructions, see <xref linkend="final-rebalance"/>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Removing Server(s)</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        In &productname;, when you remove servers from the input model, the
        disk drives are removed from the ring - the weight is not gradually
        reduced using the <literal>weight-step</literal> attribute.
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Remove servers in phases:
         </para>
         <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            This reduces the impact of the changes on your system.
           </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            If your rings use swift zones, ensure you remove the same number of
            servers for each zone at each phase.
           </para>
          </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          To remove a server, see <xref linkend="remove-swift-node"/>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          To perform the final rebalance, see <xref linkend="final-rebalance"/>.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       Adding Disk Drive(s)
      </entry>
      <entry>
	<itemizedlist>
	 <listitem>
	  <para>
	   If not already done, set the weight attribute. For instructions, see <xref linkend="swift-weight-att"/>.
	  </para>
	 </listitem>
	 <listitem>
	  <para>
	   Add the drives to your input model.
	  </para>
	 </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Replacing Disk Drive(s)</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        When a drive fails, replace it as soon as possible. Do not attempt to
        remove it from the ring - this creates operator overhead. swift will
        continue to store the correct number of replicas by handing off objects
        to other drives instead of the failed drive.
       </para>
       <para>
        If the disk drives are of the same size as the original when the
        drive is replaced, no ring changes are required. You can confirm this
        by running the
        <literal>swift-update-from-model-rebalance-rings.yml</literal>
        playbook. It should report that no weight changes are needed.
       </para>
       <para>
        For a single drive replacement, even if the drive is significantly
        larger than the original drives, you do not need to rebalance the ring
        (however, the extra space on the drive will not be used).
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Upgrading Disk Drives</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        If the drives are different size (for example, you are upgrading your
        system), you can proceed as follows:
       </para>
       <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          If not already done, set the weight-step attribute
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Replace drives in phases:
         </para>
         <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            Avoid replacing too many drives at once.
           </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            If your rings use swift zones, upgrade a number of drives in the
            same zone at the same time - not drives in several zones.
           </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            It is also safer to upgrade one server instead of drives in several
            servers at the same time.
           </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
           <para>
            Remember that the final size of all swift zones must be the same,
            so you may need to replace a small number of drives in one zone,
            then a small number in second zone, then return to the first zone
            and replace more drives, etc.
           </para>
          </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       Removing Disk Drive(s)
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
	When removing a disk drive from the input model, keep in mind that this
	drops the disk out of the ring without allowing Swift to move the data
	off it first. While it should be fine in a properly replicated healthy
cluster, we do not recommend this approach. A better solution is to step
	down eight to 0 to allow Swift to move data.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
 </section>
</section>
