<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="topic_overview_audit_logs">
 <title>Audit Logging Overview</title>
 <para>
  Existing OpenStack service logging varies widely across services. Generally,
  log messages do not have enough detail about who is requesting the
  application program interface (API), or enough context-specific details about
  an action performed. Often details are not even consistently logged across
  various services, leading to inconsistent data formats being used across
  services. These issues make it difficult to integrate logging with existing
  audit tools and processes.
 </para>
 <para>
  To help you monitor your workload and data in compliance with your corporate,
  industry or regional policies, &productname; provides auditing support as a basic
  security feature. The audit logging can be integrated with customer Security
  Information and Event Management (SIEM) tools and support your efforts to
  correlate threat forensics.
 </para>
 <para>
  The &productname; audit logging feature uses Audit Middleware for Python services.
  This middleware service is based on OpenStack services which use the Paste
  Deploy system. Most OpenStack services use the paste deploy mechanism to find
  and configure WSGI servers and applications. Utilizing the paste deploy
  system provides auditing support in services with minimal changes.
 </para>
 <para>
  By default, audit logging as a post-installation feature is disabled in the
  cloudConfig file on the &lcm; and it can only be enabled after
  &productname; installation or upgrade.
 </para>
 <para>
  The tasks in this section explain how to enable services for audit logging in
  your environment. &productname; provides audit logging for the following services:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Nova
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Barbican
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Keystone
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Cinder
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Ceilometer
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Neutron
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Glance
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Heat
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  For audit log backup information see <xref linkend="backup_audit_logs"/>
 </para>
 <xi:include href="operations-audit_logs_checklist.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="operations-audit_logs_enable.xml"/>
</section>
