<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!---->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="notification_methods">
 <title>Notification Methods</title>
 <para>
  This page allows you to define notification methods that are used by the
  alarms. By default, notification methods are sorted by name and in a table
  format.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Search and Sort</title>
  <para>
   The search bar allows you to filter the notification methods you want to
   view.
  </para>
  <para>
   The checkbox allows you to select (or deselect) a group of notification
   methods to delete:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Select Visible</guimenu> allows you to delete the selected
     notification methods from the table.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Select All</guimenu> allows you to delete all the notification
     methods from the table.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Clear Selection</guimenu> allows you to clear all the selections
     currently selected from the table.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   You can display the notification methods by grid, list or table views by
   selecting the corresponding icons next to the <guimenu>Sort By</guimenu>
   control.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Sort By</guimenu> control contains a drop-down list of ways by
   which you can sort the alarm definitions. Alternatively, you can also sort
   using the column headers in the table.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Status</guimenu> displays the notification methods by
     their status.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Metric</guimenu> displays the descriptive details of the
     alarm definitions.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Sort by Severity</guimenu> displays the alarm definitions'
     notification criteria, such as whether enabled for certain types of alarms
     and how the notification is disseminated (by Email, Web, etc.)
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Create Notification Methods</title>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Create Notification Methods</guimenu> button beside the search
   bar allows you to create a new notification method.
  </para>
  <para>
   To create a new notification method:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guimenu>Create Notification Method</guimenu> button to open a
     separate window that allows you to configure a new notification method.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the Create Notification Method window, type a name for the notification
     in the <guimenu>Name</guimenu> text field. The name is required and may be
     up to 255 characters in length consisting of letters, numbers, or special
     characters.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select a <guimenu>Type</guimenu> in the drop down. Choices are:.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>URL</guimenu> allows you to enter in an internet address Also
       referred to as a <guimenu>Web Hook</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Email</guimenu> allows you to enter in an email address. See
       Note Below.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>PagerDuty</guimenu> allows you to enter in a PagerDuty address.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Address/Key</guimenu> text field, enter in a valid value
     based on the type you chose.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     When done creating the notification method, click <guimenu>Create
     Notification Method</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   After the notification method saves, the Notification Methods window
   refreshes with the new notification method populated in the table.
  </para>
 </section>
</chapter>
