<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="supported-upstream-keystone-features">
 <title>Supported Upstream Keystone Features</title>
 <section xml:id="section-azv-113-jx">
  <title>OpenStack upstream features that are enabled by default in &product;</title>
  <para>
   The following supported keystone features are enabled by default in the
   &product; release.
  </para>
  <informaltable>
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Name</entry>
      <entry>User/Admin</entry>
      <entry>Note: API support only. No CLI/UI support</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>Implied Roles</entry>
      <entry>Admin</entry>
      <entry>https://blueprints.launchpad.net/keystone/+spec/implied-roles</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Domain-Specific Roles</entry>
      <entry>Admin</entry>
      <entry>https://blueprints.launchpad.net/keystone/+spec/domain-specific-roles</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Fernet Token Provider</entry>
      <entry>User and Admin</entry>
      <entry>https://docs.openstack.org/keystone/rocky/admin/identity-fernet-token-faq.html</entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Implied rules</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   To allow for the practice of hierarchical permissions in user roles, this
   feature enables roles to be linked in such a way that they function as a
   hierarchy with role inheritance.
  </para>
  <para>
   When a user is assigned a superior role, the user will also be assigned all
   roles implied by any subordinate roles. The hierarchy of the assigned roles
   will be expanded when issuing the user a token.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Domain-specific roles</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   This feature extends the principle of <emphasis role="bold">implied
   roles</emphasis> to include a set of roles that are specific to a domain. At
   the time a token is issued, the domain-specific roles are not included in
   the token, however, the roles that they map to are.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Fernet token provider</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   Provides tokens in the Fernet format. This feature is automatically configured
   and is enabled by default. Fernet tokens are preferred and used by default
   instead of the older UUID token format.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="section-rpw-21h-jx">
  <title>OpenStack upstream features that are disabled by default in &product;</title>
  <para>
   The following is a list of features which are fully supported in the
   &product; release, but are disabled by default. Customers can run a
   playbook to enable the features.
  </para>
  <informaltable>
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Name</entry>
      <entry>User/Admin</entry>
      <entry>Reason Disabled</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>Support multiple LDAP backends via per-domain configuration</entry>
      <entry>Admin</entry>
      <entry>Needs explicit configuration.</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>WebSSO</entry>
      <entry>User and Admin</entry>
      <entry>Needs explicit configuration.</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>keystone-to-keystone (K2K) federation</entry>
      <entry>User and Admin</entry>
      <entry>Needs explicit configuration.</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Domain-specific config in SQL</entry>
      <entry>Admin</entry>
      <entry>Domain specific configuration options can be stored in SQL instead of
                        configuration files, using the new REST APIs.</entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Multiple LDAP backends for each domain</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   This feature allows identity backends to be configured on a domain-by-domain
   basis. Domains will be capable of having their own exclusive LDAP service
   (or multiple services). A single LDAP service can also serve multiple
   domains, with each domain in a separate subtree.
  </para>
  <para>
   To implement this feature, individual domains will require domain-specific
   configuration files. Domains that do not implement this feature will
   continue to share a common backend driver.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">WebSSO</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   This feature enables the keystone service to provide federated identity
   services through a token-based single sign-on page. This feature is disabled
   by default, as it requires explicit configuration.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">keystone-to-keystone (K2K) federation</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   This feature enables separate keystone instances to federate identities
   among the instances, offering inter-cloud authorization. This feature is
   disabled by default, as it requires explicit configuration.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Domain-specific config in SQL</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   Using the new REST APIs, domain-specific configuration options can be stored
   in a SQL database instead of in configuration files.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="section-fm3-mch-jx">
  <title>Stack upstream features that have been specifically disabled in &product;</title>
  <para>
   The following is a list of extensions which are disabled by default in
   &product;, according to keystone policy.
  </para>
  <informaltable>
   <tgroup cols="4">
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Target Release</entry>
      <entry>Name</entry>
      <entry>User/Admin</entry>
      <entry>Reason Disabled</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>TBD</entry>
      <entry>Endpoint Filtering</entry>
      <entry>Admin</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        This extension was implemented to facilitate service activation.
        However, due to lack of enforcement at the service side, this feature
        is only half effective right now.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>TBD</entry>
      <entry>Endpoint Policy</entry>
      <entry>Admin</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        This extension was intended to facilitate policy (policy.json)
        management and enforcement. This feature is useless right now due to
        lack of the needed middleware to utilize the policy files stored in
        keystone.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>TBD</entry>
      <entry>OATH 1.0a</entry>
      <entry>User and Admin</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Complexity in workflow. Lack of adoption. Its alternative, keystone
        Trust, is enabled by default. HEAT is using keystone Trust.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>TBD</entry>
      <entry>Revocation Events</entry>
      <entry>Admin</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        For PKI token only and PKI token is disabled by default due to
        usability concerns.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>TBD</entry>
      <entry>OS CERT</entry>
      <entry>Admin</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        For PKI token only and PKI token is disabled by default due to
        usability concerns.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>TBD</entry>
      <entry>PKI Token</entry>
      <entry>Admin</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        PKI token is disabled by default due to usability concerns.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>TBD</entry>
      <entry>Driver level caching</entry>
      <entry>Admin</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Driver level caching is disabled by default due to complexity in setup.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>TBD</entry>
      <entry>Tokenless Authz</entry>
      <entry>Admin</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Tokenless authorization with X.509 SSL client certificate.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>TBD</entry>
      <entry>TOTP Authentication</entry>
      <entry>User</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Not fully baked. Has not been battle-tested.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>TBD</entry>
      <entry>is_admin_project</entry>
      <entry>Admin</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        No integration with the services.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
 </section>
</section>
