<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="opsconsole-alarm-definitions">
 <title>Alarm Definition</title>
 <para>
  The <guimenu>Alarm Definition</guimenu> section under
  <guimenu>Monitoring</guimenu> allows you to define alarms that are useful
  in generating
  notifications and metrics required by your organization. By default, alarm
  definitions are sorted by name and in a table format.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Filter and Sort</title>
  <para>
   The search feature allows you to search and filter alarm entries by name
   and description.
  </para>
  <para>
   The check box above the top left of the table is used to select all alarm
   definitions on the current page.
  </para>
  <para>
   To sort the table, click the desired column header. To reverse the
   sort order, click the column again.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Create Alarm Definitions</title>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Create Alarm Definition</guimenu> button next to the search bar
   allows you to create a new alarm definition.
  </para>
  <para>
   To create a new alarm definition:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Click <guimenu>Create Alarm Definition</guimenu> to open the
     <guimenu>Create Alarm Definition</guimenu> dialog.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In the Create Alarm Definition window, type a name for the alarm in the
     <guimenu>Name</guimenu> text field. The name is mandatory and can be up to
     255 characters long. The name can include letters, numbers, and special
     characters.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Provide a short description of the alarm in the
     <guimenu>Description</guimenu> text field (optional).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Select the desired severity level of the alarm from the
     <guimenu>Severity</guimenu> drop-down box. The severity level is
     subjective, so choose
     the level appropriate for prioritizing the handling of alarms when they
     occur.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Although not required, in order to specify how to receive notifications,
     you must be able to select the method(s) of notification (Email, Web, API,
     etc.) from the list of options in the Alarm Notifications area. If none
     are available to choose from, you must first configure them in the
     Notifications Methods window. Refer to the Notification Methods help page
     for further instructions.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To enable notifications for the alarm, enable the check box next to the
     desired alarm notification method.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Apply the following rules to your alarm by using the Alarm Expression
     form:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Function</guimenu>: determines the output value from a supplied
       input value.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Metric</guimenu>: applies a pre-defined means of measuring
       whatever aspect of the alarm.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Dimension(s)</guimenu>: identifies which aspect (Hostname,
       Region, and Service) of the alarm you want to monitor.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Comparator</guimenu>: specifies the operator for how
       you want the alarm to trigger.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Threshold</guimenu>: determines the numeric threshold associated
       with the operator you specified.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Match By</guimenu> (optional): group results by a specific
     dimension that is not part of the Dimension(s) solution.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To save the changes and add the new alarm definition to the table, click
     <guimenu>Create Alarm Definition</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
</section>
