<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="liveInstMigration">
 <title>Live Migration of Instances</title>
 <para>
  Live migration allows you to move active compute instances between compute
  nodes, allowing for less downtime during maintenance.
 </para>
 <para>
  &productname; nova offers a set of commands that allow you to move compute
  instances between compute hosts. Which command you use will depend on the
  state of the host, what operating system is on the host, what type of storage
  the instances are using, and whether you want to migrate a single instance or
  all of the instances off of the host. We will describe these options on this
  page as well as give you step-by-step instructions for performing them.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="options">
  <title>Migration Options</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">If your compute node has failed</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   A compute host failure could be caused by hardware failure, such as the data
   disk needing to be replaced, power has been lost, or any other type of
   failure which requires that you replace the baremetal host. In this
   scenario, the instances on the compute node are unrecoverable and any data
   on the local ephemeral storage is lost. If you are utilizing block storage
   volumes, either as a boot device or as additional storage, they should be
   unaffected.
  </para>
  <para>
   In these cases you will want to use one of the nova evacuate commands, which
   will cause nova to rebuild the instances on other hosts.
  </para>
  <para>
   This table describes each of the evacuate options for failed compute nodes:
  </para>
  <informaltable colsep="1" rowsep="1">
   <tgroup cols="2">
    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Command</entry>
      <entry>Description</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>nova evacuate &lt;instance&gt; &lt;hostname&gt;</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        This command is used to evacuate a single instance from a failed host.
        You specify the compute instance UUID and the target host you want to
        evacuate it to. If no host is specified then the nova scheduler will
        choose one for you.
       </para>
       <para>
        See <literal>nova help evacuate</literal> for more information and
        syntax. Further details can also be seen in the OpenStack documentation
        at
        <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/admin-guide/cli_nova_evacuate.html"/>.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>nova host-evacuate &lt;hostname&gt; --target_host
        &lt;target_hostname&gt;</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        This command is used to evacuate all instances from a failed host. You
        specify the hostname of the compute host you want to evacuate.
        Optionally you can specify a target host. If no target host is
        specified then the nova scheduler will choose a target host for each
        instance.
       </para>
       <para>
        See <literal>nova help host-evacuate</literal> for more information and
        syntax.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
  <para>
   If your compute host is active, powered on and the data disks are in working order
   you can utilize the migration commands to migrate your compute instances.
   There are two migration features, "cold" migration (also referred to simply
   as "migration") and live migration. Migration and live migration are two
   different functions.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Cold migration</emphasis> is used to copy an instances
   data in a <literal>SHUTOFF</literal> status from one compute host to
   another. It does this using passwordless SSH access which has security
   concerns associated with it. For this reason, the <literal>openstack server
   migrate</literal> function has been disabled by default but you have the
   ability to enable this feature if you would like. Details on how to do this
   can be found in <xref linkend="enabling-the-nova-resize"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Live migration</emphasis> can be performed on
   instances in either an <literal>ACTIVE</literal> or
   <literal>PAUSED</literal> state and uses the QEMU hypervisor to manage the
   copy of the running processes and associated resources to the destination
   compute host using the hypervisors own protocol and thus is a more secure
   method and allows for less downtime. There may be a short network outage,
   usually a few milliseconds but could be up to a few seconds if your compute
   instances are busy, during a live migration. Also there may be some
   performance degredation during the process.
  </para>
  <para>
   The compute host must remain powered on during the migration process.
  </para>
  <para>
   Both the cold migration and live migration options will honor nova group
   policies, which includes affinity settings. There is a limitation to keep in
   mind if you use group policies and that is discussed in the
   <xref linkend="liveInstMigration"/> section.
  </para>
  <para>
   This table describes each of the migration options for active compute nodes:
  </para>
  <informaltable colsep="1" rowsep="1">
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="4*"/>
    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
    <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Command</entry>
      <entry>Description</entry>
      <entry>&slsa;</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>openstack server migrate &lt;instance_uuid&gt;</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Used to cold migrate a single instance from a compute host. The
        <literal>nova-scheduler</literal> will choose the new host.
       </para>
       <para>
        This command will work against instances in an
        <literal>ACTIVE</literal> or <literal>SHUTOFF</literal> state. The
        instances, if active, will be shutdown and restarted. Instances in a
        <literal>PAUSED</literal> state cannot be cold migrated.
       </para>
       <para>
        See the difference between cold migration and live migration at the
        start of this section.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry/>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>nova host-servers-migrate &lt;hostname&gt;</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Used to cold migrate all instances off a specified host to other
        available hosts, chosen by the <literal>nova-scheduler</literal>.
       </para>
       <para>
        This command will work against instances in an
        <literal>ACTIVE</literal> or <literal>SHUTOFF</literal> state. The
        instances, if active, will be shutdown and restarted. Instances in a
        <literal>PAUSED</literal> state cannot be cold migrated.
       </para>
       <para>
        See the difference between cold migration and live migration at the
        start of this section.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry/>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>nova live-migration &lt;instance_uuid&gt; [&lt;target
        host&gt;]</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Used to migrate a single instance between two compute hosts. You can
        optionally specify a target host or you can allow the nova scheduler to
        choose a host for you. If you choose to specify a target host, ensure
        that the target host has enough resources to host the instance prior to
        live migration.
       </para>
       <para>
        Works for instances that are booted from a block storage volume or that
        have any number of block storage volumes attached.
       </para>
       <para>
        This command works against instances in <literal>ACTIVE</literal> or
        <literal>PAUSED</literal> states only.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>X</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>nova live-migration --block-migrate &lt;instance_uuid&gt;
        [&lt;target host&gt;]</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Used to migrate a single instance between two compute hosts. You can
        optionally specify a target host or you can allow the nova scheduler to
        choose a host for you. If you choose to specify a target host, ensure
        that the target host has enough resources to host the instance prior to
        live migration.
       </para>
       <para>
        Works for instances that are booted from local (ephemeral) disk(s) only
        or if your instance has a mix of ephemeral disk(s) and block storage
        volume(s) but are not booted from a block storage volume.
       </para>
       <para>
        This command works against instances in <literal>ACTIVE</literal> or
        <literal>PAUSED</literal> states only.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>X</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>nova host-evacuate-live &lt;hostname&gt; [--target-host
        &lt;target_hostname&gt;]</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Used to live migrate all instances off of a compute host. You can
        optionally specify a target host or you can allow the nova scheduler to
        choose a host for you. If you choose to specify a target host, ensure
        that the target host has enough resources to host the instance prior to
        live migration.
       </para>
       <para>
        Works for instances that are booted from a block storage volume or that
        have any number of block storage volumes attached.
       </para>
       <para>
        This command works against instances in <literal>ACTIVE</literal> or
        <literal>PAUSED</literal> states only.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>X</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <literal>nova host-evacuate-live --block-migrate &lt;hostname&gt;
        [--target-host &lt;target_hostname&gt;]</literal>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Used to live migrate all instances off of a compute host. You can
        optionally specify a target host or you can allow the nova scheduler to
        choose a host for you. If you choose to specify a target host, ensure
        that the target host has enough resources to host the instance prior to
        live migration.
       </para>
       <para>
        Works for instances that are booted from local (ephemeral) disk(s) only
        or if your instance has a mix of ephemeral disk(s) and block storage
        volume(s) but are not booted from a block storage volume.
       </para>
       <para>
        This command works against instances in <literal>ACTIVE</literal> or
        <literal>PAUSED</literal> states only.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>X</entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-operations-maintenance-live-migration-xml-10">
  <title>Limitations of these Features</title>
  <para>
   There are limitations that may impact your use of this feature:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To use live migration, your compute instances must be in either an
     <literal>ACTIVE</literal> or <literal>PAUSED</literal> state on the
     compute host. If you have instances in a <literal>SHUTOFF</literal> state
     then cold migration should be used.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Instances in a <literal>Paused</literal> state cannot be live migrated
     using the horizon dashboard. You will need to utilize the novaClient CLI
     to perform these.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Both cold migration and live migration honor an instance's group policies.
     If you are utilizing an affinity policy and are migrating multiple
     instances you may run into an error stating no hosts are available to
     migrate to. To work around this issue you should specify a target host
     when migrating these instances, which will bypass the
     <literal>nova-scheduler</literal>. You should ensure that the target host
     you choose has the resources available to host the instances.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <literal>nova host-evacuate-live</literal> command will produce an
     error if you have a compute host that has a mix of instances that use
     local ephemeral storage and instances that are booted from a block storage
     volume or have any number of block storage volumes attached. If you have a
     mix of these instance types, you may need to run the command twice,
     utilizing the <literal>--block-migrate</literal> option. This is described
     in further detail in <xref linkend="liveInstMigration"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Instances on KVM hosts can only be live migrated to other KVM hosts.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The migration options described in this document are not available on ESX
     compute hosts.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Ensure that you read and take into account any other limitations that
     exist in the release notes. See the release notes for
     more details.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="liveMigrate">
  <title>Performing a Live Migration</title>
  <para>
   Cloud administrators can perform a migration on an instance using either the
   horizon dashboard, API, or CLI. Instances in a <literal>Paused</literal>
   state cannot be live migrated using the horizon GUI. You will need to
   utilize the CLI to perform these.
  </para>
  <para>
   We have documented different scenarios:
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="failed-host">
  <title>Migrating instances off of a failed compute host</title>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in to the &clm;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If the compute node is not already powered off, do so with this playbook:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost bm-power-down.yml -e nodelist=&lt;node_name&gt;</screen>
    <note>
     <para>
      The value for <literal>&lt;node_name&gt;</literal> will be the name that
      Cobbler has when you run <command>sudo cobbler system list</command> from
      the &clm;.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Source the admin credentials necessary to run administrative commands
     against the nova API:
    </para>
<screen>source ~/service.osrc</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Force the <literal>nova-compute</literal> service to go down on the
     compute node:
    </para>
<screen>openstack compute service set --down <replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable> nova-compute</screen>
    <note>
     <para>
      The value for <replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable> can be obtained by
      using <command>openstack host list</command> from the &clm;.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Evacuate the instances off of the failed compute node. This will cause the
     nova-scheduler to rebuild the instances on other valid hosts. Any local
     ephemeral data on the instances is lost.
    </para>
    <para>
     For single instances on a failed host:
    </para>
<screen>nova evacuate &lt;instance_uuid&gt; &lt;target_hostname&gt;</screen>
    <para>
     For all instances on a failed host:
    </para>
<screen>nova host-evacuate &lt;hostname&gt; [--target_host &lt;target_hostname&gt;]</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     When you have repaired the failed node and start it back up again, when
     the <command>nova-compute</command> process starts again, it will clean
     up the evacuated instances.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="active-host">
  <title>Migrating instances off of an active compute host</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Migrating instances using the horizon
   dashboard</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   The horizon dashboard offers a GUI method for performing live migrations.
   Instances in a <literal>Paused</literal> state will not provide you the live
   migration option in horizon so you will need to use the CLI instructions in
   the next section to perform these.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log into the horizon dashboard with admin credentials.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Navigate to the menu <menuchoice><guimenu>Admin</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Compute</guimenu><guimenu>Instances</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Next to the instance you want to migrate, select the drop down menu and
     choose the <guimenu>Live Migrate Instance</guimenu> option.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the Live Migrate wizard you will see the compute host the instance
     currently resides on and then a drop down menu that allows you to choose
     the compute host you want to migrate the instance to. Select a destination
     host from that menu. You also have two checkboxes for additional options,
     which are described below:
    </para>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Disk Over Commit</guimenu> - If this is not checked
     then the value will be <literal>False</literal>. If you check this box
     then it will allow you to override the check that occurs to ensure the
     destination host has the available disk space to host the instance.
    </para>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Block Migration</guimenu> - If this is not checked
     then the value will be <literal>False</literal>. If you check this box
     then it will migrate the local disks by using block migration. Use this
     option if you are only using ephemeral storage on your instances. If you
     are using block storage for your instance then ensure this box is not
     checked.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     To begin the live migration, click <guimenu>Submit</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Migrating instances using the novaClient
   CLI</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   To perform migrations from the command-line, use the novaClient.
   The &clm; node in your cloud environment should have
   the novaClient already installed. If you will be accessing your environment
   through a different method, ensure that the novaClient is
   installed. You can do so using Python's <command>pip</command> package
   manager.
  </para>
  <para>
   To run the commands in the steps below, you need administrator
   credentials. From the &clm;, you can source the
   <filename>service.osrc</filename> file which is provided that has the
   necessary credentials:
  </para>
<screen>source ~/service.osrc</screen>
  <para>
   Here are the steps to perform:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in to the &clm;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Identify the instances on the compute node you wish to migrate:
    </para>
<screen>openstack server list --all-tenants --host &lt;hostname&gt;</screen>
    <para>
     Example showing a host with a single compute instance on it:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana; openstack server list --host ardana-cp1-comp0001-mgmt --all-tenants
+--------------------------------------+------+----------------------------------+--------+------------+-------------+-----------------------+
| ID                                   | Name | Tenant ID                        | Status | Task State | Power State | Networks              |
+--------------------------------------+------+----------------------------------+--------+------------+-------------+-----------------------+
| 553ba508-2d75-4513-b69a-f6a2a08d04e3 | test | 193548a949c146dfa1f051088e141f0b | ACTIVE | -          | Running     | adminnetwork=10.0.0.5 |
+--------------------------------------+------+----------------------------------+--------+------------+-------------+-----------------------+</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     When using live migration you can either specify a target host that the
     instance will be migrated to or you can omit the target to allow the
     nova-scheduler to choose a node for you. If you want to get a list of
     available hosts you can use this command:
    </para>
<screen>openstack host list</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Migrate the instance(s) on the compute node using the notes below.
    </para>
    <para>
     If your instance is booted from a block storage volume or has any number
     of block storage volumes attached, use the <literal>nova
     live-migration</literal> command with this syntax:
    </para>
<screen>nova live-migration &lt;instance uuid&gt; [&lt;target compute host&gt;]</screen>
    <para>
     If your instance has local (ephemeral) disk(s) only or if your instance
     has a mix of ephemeral disk(s) and block storage volume(s), you should use
     the <literal>--block-migrate</literal> option:
    </para>
<screen>nova live-migration --block-migrate &lt;instance uuid&gt; [&lt;target compute host&gt;]</screen>
    <note>
     <para>
      The <literal>[&lt;target compute host&gt;]</literal> option is
      optional. If you do not specify a target host then the nova scheduler
      will choose a node for you.
     </para>
    </note>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">Multiple instances</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
     If you want to live migrate all of the instances off a single compute host
     you can utilize the <literal>nova host-evacuate-live</literal> command.
    </para>
    <para>
     Issue the host-evacuate-live command, which will begin the live migration
     process.
    </para>
    <para>
     If all of the instances on the host are using at least one local
     (ephemeral) disk, you should use this syntax:
    </para>
<screen>nova host-evacuate-live --block-migrate &lt;hostname&gt;</screen>
    <para>
     Alternatively, if all of the instances are only using block storage
     volumes then omit the <literal>--block-migrate</literal> option:
    </para>
<screen>nova host-evacuate-live &lt;hostname&gt;</screen>
    <note>
     <para>
      You can either let the nova-scheduler choose a suitable target host or
      you can specify one using the
      <literal>--target-host &lt;hostname&gt;</literal> switch. See
      <command>nova help host-evacuate-live</command> for details.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-operations-maintenance-live-migration-xml-14">
  <title>Troubleshooting migration or host evacuate issues</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Issue:</emphasis> When attempting to use <literal>nova
   host-evacuate-live</literal> against a node, you receive the error below:
  </para>
<screen>$ nova host-evacuate-live ardana-cp1-comp0001-mgmt --target-host ardana-cp1-comp0003-mgmt
+--------------------------------------+-------------------------+--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+
| Server UUID                          | Live Migration Accepted | Error Message                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        |
+--------------------------------------+-------------------------+--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+
| 95a7ded8-ebfc-4848-9090-2df378c88a4c | False                   | Error while live migrating instance: ardana-cp1-comp0001-mgmt is not on shared storage: Live migration can not be used without shared storage except a booted from volume VM which does not have a local disk. (HTTP 400) (Request-ID: req-9fd79670-a780-40ed-a515-c14e28e0a0a7)     |
| 13ab4ef7-0623-4d00-bb5a-5bb2f1214be4 | False                   | Error while live migrating instance: ardana-cp1-comp0001-mgmt is not on shared storage: Live migration cannot be used without shared storage except a booted from volume VM which does not have a local disk. (HTTP 400) (Request-ID: req-26834267-c3ec-4f8b-83cc-5193d6a394d6)     |
+--------------------------------------+-------------------------+---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+</screen>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Fix:</emphasis> This occurs when you are attempting to
   live evacuate a host that contains instances booted from local storage and
   you are not specifying <literal>--block-migrate</literal> in your command.
   Re-attempt the live evacuation with this syntax:
  </para>
<screen>nova host-evacuate-live <emphasis role="bold">--block-migrate</emphasis> &lt;hostname&gt; [--target-host &lt;target_hostname&gt;]</screen>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Issue:</emphasis> When attempting to use <literal>nova
   host-evacuate-live</literal> against a node, you receive the error below:
  </para>
<screen>$ nova host-evacuate-live --block-migrate ardana-cp1-comp0001-mgmt --target-host ardana-cp1-comp0003-mgmt
+--------------------------------------+-------------------------+-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+
| Server UUID                          | Live Migration Accepted | Error Message                                                                                                                                                                                                     |
+--------------------------------------+-------------------------+-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+
| e9874122-c5dc-406f-9039-217d9258c020 | False                   | Error while live migrating instance: ardana-cp1-comp0001-mgmt is not on local storage: Block migration can not be used with shared storage. (HTTP 400) (Request-ID: req-60b1196e-84a0-4b71-9e49-96d6f1358e1a)     |
| 84a02b42-9527-47ac-bed9-8fde1f98e3fe | False                   | Error while live migrating instance: ardana-cp1-comp0001-mgmt is not on local storage: Block migration can not be used with shared storage. (HTTP 400) (Request-ID: req-0cdf1198-5dbd-40f4-9e0c-e94aa1065112)     |
+--------------------------------------+-------------------------+-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+</screen>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Fix:</emphasis> This occurs when you are attempting to
   live evacuate a host that contains instances booted from a block storage
   volume and you are specifying <literal>--block-migrate</literal> in your
   command. Re-attempt the live evacuation with this syntax:
  </para>
<screen>nova host-evacuate-live &lt;hostname&gt; [--target-host &lt;target_hostname&gt;]</screen>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Issue:</emphasis> When attempting to use <literal>nova
   live-migration</literal> against an instance, you receive the error below:
  </para>
<screen>$ nova live-migration 2a13ffe6-e269-4d75-8e46-624fec7a5da0 ardana-cp1-comp0002-mgmt
ERROR (BadRequest): ardana-cp1-comp0001-mgmt is not on shared storage: Live migration can not be used without shared storage except a booted from volume VM which does not have a local disk. (HTTP 400) (Request-ID: req-158dd415-0bb7-4613-8529-6689265387e7)</screen>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Fix:</emphasis> This occurs when you are attempting to
   live migrate an instance that was booted from local storage and you are not
   specifying <literal>--block-migrate</literal> in your command. Re-attempt
   the live migration with this syntax:
  </para>
<screen>nova live-migration <emphasis role="bold">--block-migrate</emphasis> &lt;instance_uuid&gt; &lt;target_hostname&gt;</screen>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Issue:</emphasis> When attempting to use <literal>nova
   live-migration</literal> against an instance, you receive the error below:
  </para>
<screen>$ nova live-migration --block-migrate 84a02b42-9527-47ac-bed9-8fde1f98e3fe ardana-cp1-comp0001-mgmt
ERROR (BadRequest): ardana-cp1-comp0002-mgmt is not on local storage: Block migration can not be used with shared storage. (HTTP 400) (Request-ID: req-51fee8d6-6561-4afc-b0c9-7afa7dc43a5b)</screen>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Fix:</emphasis> This occurs when you are attempting to
   live migrate an instance that was booted from a block storage volume and you
   are specifying <literal>--block-migrate</literal> in your command.
   Re-attempt the live migration with this syntax:
  </para>
<screen>nova live-migration &lt;instance_uuid&gt; &lt;target_hostname&gt;</screen>
 </section>
</section>
