<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="opsconsole-alarm_explorer">
 <title>Alarm Explorer</title>
 <para>
  This page displays the alarms for all services and appliances. By default,
  alarms are sorted by their state.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Filter and Sort</title>
  <para>
   Using the <guimenu>Filter Alarms</guimenu> button, you can filter the
   alarms by their IDs and dimensions. The <guimenu>Filter Alarms</guimenu>
   dialog lets you configure a filtering rule using the <guimenu>Alarm
   ID</guimenu> field and options in the <guimenu>Dimension(s)</guimenu>
   section.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can display the alarms by grid, list or table views by selecting the
   corresponding icons next to the <guimenu>Sort By</guimenu> control.
  </para>
  <para>
   To sort the alarm list, click the desired column header. To reverse the
   sort order, click the column again.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Alarm Table</title>
  <para>
   Each row has a checkbox to allow you to select multiple alarms and set the
   same condition on them.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis> column displays a graphical
   indicator that shows the state of each alarm:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Green indicator: OK. Good operating state.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Yellow indicator: Warning. Low severity, not requiring
     immediate action.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Red indicator: Alarm. Varying severity levels and must be
     addressed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Gray indicator: Unknown.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   The <emphasis role="bold">Alarm</emphasis> column identifies the alarm by
   the name it was given when it was originally created.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <emphasis role="bold">Last Check</emphasis> column displays the date and
   time the most recent occurrence of the alarm.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <emphasis role="bold">Dimension</emphasis> column describes the
   components to check in order to clear the alarm.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Notification Methods</title>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Notification Methods</guimenu> section of the Alarm Explorer
   allows you to define notification methods that are used by the alarms. By
   default, notification methods are sorted by name.
  </para>

  <section>
   <title>Filter and Sort</title>
   <para>
    The filter bar allows you to filter the notification methods by specifying a
    filter criteria. You can sort the available notification methods by clicking
    on the desired column header in the table.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section>
   <title>Create Notification Methods</title>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Create Notification Methods</guimenu> button beside the search
   bar allows you to create a new notification method.
  </para>
  <para>
   To create a new notification method:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guimenu>Create Notification Method</guimenu> button.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Create Notification Method</guimenu> window, specify a
     name for the notification in the <guimenu>Name</guimenu> text field. The
     name is required, and it can be up to 255 characters in length, consisting
     of letters, numbers, or special characters.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select a <guimenu>Type</guimenu> in the drop down and select the desired
     option:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Web Hook</guimenu> allows you to enter in an internet
       address, also referred to as a <emphasis>Web Hook</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Email</guimenu> allows you to enter in an email address. For
       this method to work you need to have a SMTP server specified.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>PagerDuty</guimenu> allows you to enter in a PagerDuty
       address.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the <guimenu>Address/Key</guimenu> text field, provide the required
     values.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Press <guimenu>Create Notification Method</guimenu>, and you should see
     the created notification method in the table.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  </section>
 </section>
</section>
