<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="opsconsole-manage-swift">
 <title>Managing swift Performance</title>
 <para>
  In &opscon; you can monitor your swift cluster to ensure long-term
  data protection as well as sufficient performance.
 </para>
 <para>
  OpenStack swift is an object storage solution with a focus on availability.
  While there are various mechanisms inside swift to protect stored data and
  ensure a high availability, you must still closely monitor your swift cluster
  to ensure long-term data protection as well as sufficient performance. The
  best way to manage swift is to collect useful data that will detect possible
  performance impacts early on.
 </para>
 <para>
  The new Object Summary Dashboard in &opscon; provides
  an overview of your swift environment.
 </para>
 <important>
  <para>
   If swift is not installed and configured, you will not be able to access
   this dashboard. The swift endpoint must be present in keystone for the
   Object Summary to be present in the menu.
  </para>
 </important>
 <para>
  In &opscon;'s object storage dashboard, you can easily review the
  following information:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Performance Summary: <xref linkend="opsconsole-swift-summary"/>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Inventory Summary: <xref linkend="opsconsole-swift-inventory"/>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Capacity Summary: <xref linkend="opsconsole-swift-capacity"/>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Alarm Summary: <xref linkend="opsconsole-swift-alarmsumm"/>
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <section xml:id="opsconsole-swift-summary">
  <title>Performance Summary</title>
  <para>
   View a comprehensive summary of current performance values.
  </para>
  <para>
   To access the object storage performance dashboard:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To open &opscon;, in a browser enter either the URL or
     Virtual IP connected to &opscon;.
    </para>
    <para>
     For example:
    </para>
<screen>https://myardana.test:9095
https://VIP:9095</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     On the <emphasis role="bold">Home</emphasis> screen, click the menu
     represented by 3 horizontal lines (&opscon-hamburger-icon;).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In the menu, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Storage</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Object Storage Summary</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   Performance data includes:
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Healthcheck Latency from monasca</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This latency is the average time it takes for swift to respond to a
      healthcheck, or ping, request. The swiftlm-uptime monitor program reports
      the value. A large difference between average and maximum may indicate a
      problem with one node.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Operational Latency from monasca</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Operational latency is the average time it takes for swift to respond to
      an upload, download, or object delete request. The swiftlm-uptime monitor
      program reports the value. A large difference between average and maximum
      may indicate a problem with one node.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Service Availability</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This is the availability over the last 24 hours as a percentage.
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">100%</emphasis> - No outages in the last 24 hours
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">50%</emphasis> - swift was unavailable for a
        total of 12 hours in the last 24-hour period
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Graph of Performance Over Time</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Create a visual representation of performance data to see when swift
      encountered longer-than-normal response times.
     </para>
     <para>
      To create a graph:
     </para>
     <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Choose the length of time you want to graph in
        <guimenu>Date Range</guimenu>.
        This sets the length of time for the x-axis which
        counts backwards until it reaches the present time. In the example
        below, 1 day is selected, and so the x axis shows performance starting
        from 24 hours ago (-24) until the present time.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Look at the y-axis to understand the range of response times. The first
        number is the smallest value in the data collected from the backend,
        and the last number is the longest amount of time it took swift to
        respond to a request. In the example below, the shortest time for a
        response from swift was 16.1 milliseconds.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Look for spikes which represent longer than normal response times. In
        the example below, swift experienced long response times 21 hours ago
        and again 1 hour ago.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Look for the latency value at the present time. The line running across
        the x-axis at 16.1 milliseconds shows you what the response time is
        currently.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </orderedlist>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="media-opsconsole-ObjStorageSumm2.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="media-opsconsole-ObjStorageSumm2.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="opsconsole-swift-inventory">
  <title>Inventory Summary</title>
  <para>
   Monitor details about all the swift resources deployed in your cloud.
  </para>
  <para>
   To access the object storage inventory screen:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To open &opscon;, in a browser enter either the URL or
     Virtual IP connected to &opscon;.
    </para>
    <para>
     For example:
    </para>
<screen>https://myardana.test:9095
https://VIP:9095</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Home</guimenu> screen, click the menu
     represented by 3 horizontal lines (&opscon-hamburger-icon;).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In the menu, click
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Storage</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Object Storage Summary</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Summary</guimenu> page, click
     <guimenu>Inventory Summary</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="media-opsconsole-ObjStorageInventory1.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="media-opsconsole-ObjStorageInventory1.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
   General swift metrics are available for the following attributes:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Time to replicate</guimenu>: The average time in
     seconds it takes all hosts to complete a replication cycle.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Oldest replication</guimenu>: The time in seconds
     that has elapsed since the object replication process completed its last
     replication cycle.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Async Pending</guimenu>: This is the number of
     failed requests to add an entry in the container server's database.There
     is one async queue per swift disk, and a cron job queries all swift
     servers to calculate the total. When an object is uploaded into swift, and
     it is successfully stored, a request is sent to the container server to
     add a new entry for the object in the database. If the container update
     fails, the request is stored in what swift calls an Async Pending Queue.
    </para>
    <important>
     <para>
      On a public cloud deployment, this value can reach millions. If it
      continues to grow, it means that the container updates are not keeping up
      with the requests. It is also normal for it this number to grow if a node
      hosting the swift container service is down.
     </para>
    </important>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Total number of alarms</guimenu>: This number
     includes all nodes that host swift services, including proxy, account,
     container, and object storage services.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Total nodes</guimenu>: This number includes all
     nodes that host swift services, including proxy, account, container, and
     object storage services. The number in the colored box represents the
     number of alarms in that state. The following colors are used to show the
     most severe alarm triggered on all nodes:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Green</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Indicates all alarms are in a known and untriggered state. For example,
        if there are 5 nodes and they are all known with no alarms, you will
        see the number 5 in the green box, and a zero in all the other colored
        boxes.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Yellow</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Indicates that some low or medium alarms have been triggered but no
        critical or high alarms. For example, if there are 5 nodes, and there
        are 3 nodes with untriggered alarms and 2 nodes with medium severity
        alarms, you will see the number 3 in the green box, the number 2 in the
        yellow box, and zeros in all the other colored boxes.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Red</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Indicates at least one critical or high severity alarm has been
        triggered on a node. For example, if there are 5 nodes, and there are 3
        nodes with untriggered alarms, 1 node with a low severity, and 1 node
        with a critical alarm, you will see the number 3 in the green box, the
        number 1 in the yellow box, the number 1 in the red box,and a zero in
        the gray box.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Gray</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Indicates that all alarms on the nodes are unknown. For example, if
        there are 5 nodes with no data reported, you will see the number 5 in
        the gray box, and zeros in all the other colored boxes.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Cluster breakdown of nodes</guimenu>: In the
     example screen above, the cluster consists of 2 nodes named SWPAC and
     SWOBJ. Click a node name to bring up more detailed information about
     that node.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="opsconsole-swift-capacity">
  <title>Capacity Summary</title>
  <para>
   Use this screen to view the size of the file system space on all nodes and
   disk drives assigned to swift. Also shown is the remaining space available
   and the total size of all file systems used by swift. Values are given in
   megabytes (MB).
  </para>
  <para>
   To access the object storage alarm summary screen:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To open &opscon;, in a browser enter either the URL or
     Virtual IP connected to &opscon;.
    </para>
    <para>
     For example:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;https://myardana.test:9095
https://VIP:9095</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Home</guimenu> screen, click the menu
     represented by 3 horizontal lines (&opscon-hamburger-icon;).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In the menu, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Storage</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Object Storage Summary</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     On the <emphasis role="bold">Summary</emphasis> page, click
     <emphasis role="bold">Capacity Summary</emphasis>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="media-opsconsole-ObjStorageCapacity.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="media-opsconsole-ObjStorageCapacity.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="opsconsole-swift-alarmsumm">
  <title>Alarm Summary</title>
  <para>
   Use this page to quickly see the most recent alarms and triage all alarms
   related to object storage.
  </para>
  <para>
   To access the object storage alarm summary screen:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To open &opscon;, in a browser enter either the URL or
     Virtual IP connected to &opscon;.
    </para>
    <para>
     For example:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;https://myardana.test:9095
https://VIP:9095</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     On the <guimenu>Home</guimenu> screen, click the menu
     represented by 3 horizontal lines (&opscon-hamburger-icon;).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     In the menu, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Storage</guimenu>
     <guimenu>Object Storage Summary</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     On the <emphasis role="bold">Summary</emphasis> page, click
     <emphasis role="bold">Alarm Summary</emphasis>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="media-opsconsole-OpsConsoleswiftAlarmSumm.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="media-opsconsole-OpsConsoleswiftAlarmSumm.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
  <para>
   Each row has a checkbox to allow you to select multiple alarms and set the
   same condition on them.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>State</guimenu> column displays a graphical
   indicator representing the state of each alarm:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Green indicator: OK. Good operating state.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Yellow indicator: Warning. Low severity, not requiring
     immediate action.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Red indicator: Alarm. Varying severity levels and must be
     addressed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Gray indicator: Undetermined.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Alarm</guimenu> column identifies the alarm by
   the name it was given when it was originally created.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Last Check</guimenu> column displays the date and
   time the most recent occurrence of the alarm.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Dimension</guimenu> column describes the
   components to check in order to clear the alarm.
  </para>
  <para>
   The last column, depicted by three dots, reveals an
   <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> menu that allows
   you to choose:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>View Details</guimenu>, which opens a separate window that shows
     all the information from the table view and the alarm history.
    </para>
    <para>
     Comments can be updated by clicking <guimenu>Update Comment</guimenu>.
     Click <guimenu>View Alarm Definition</guimenu> to go
     to the <guimenu>Alarm Definition</guimenu> tab showing that specific alarm
     definition.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</section>
