<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="topic-qtp-cn3-bt">
 <title>Identity Service Notes and Limitations</title>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-operations-configuring-identity-identity-limitations-xml-6">
  <title>Notes</title>
  <para>
   This topic describes limitations of and important notes pertaining to the
   identity service. <emphasis role="bold">Domains</emphasis>
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Domains can be created and managed by the Horizon web interface, Keystone
     API and OpenStackClient CLI.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The configuration of external authentication systems requires the creation
     and usage of Domains.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     All configurations are managed by creating and editing specific
     configuration files.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     End users can authenticate to a particular project and domain via the
     Horizon web interface, Keystone API and OpenStackClient CLI.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A new Horizon login page that requires a Domain entry is now installed by
     default.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Keystone-to-Keystone Federation</emphasis>
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Keystone-to-Keystone (K2K) Federation provides the ability to authenticate
     once with one cloud and then use these credentials to access resources on
     other federated clouds.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     All configurations are managed by creating and editing specific
     configuration files.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Multi-Factor Authentication (MFA)</emphasis>
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The Keystone architecture provides support for MFA deployments.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     MFA provides the ability to deploy non-password based authentication; for
     example: token providing hardware and text messages.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Hierarchical Multitenancy</emphasis>
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Provides the ability to create sub-projects within a Domain-Project
     hierarchy.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-operations-configuring-identity-identity-limitations-xml-7">
  <title>Limitations</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Authentication with external authentication systems
   (LDAP, Active Directory (AD) or Identity Providers)</emphasis>
  </para>
  <itemizedlist xml:id="ul-u52-jpd-bt">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     No Horizon web portal support currently exists for the creation and
     management of external authentication system configurations.
    </para>
   </listitem>
<!-- Commented in DITA original: -->
<!-- <li>A new Domain Admin API has been included in the Kilo release of
OpenStack but is currently an "experimental" function and is not recommended
for production use until a future OpenStack release.</li> -->
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Integration with LDAP services</emphasis>
   &product; domain-specific configuration:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     No Global User Listing: Once domain-specific driver configuration is
     enabled, listing all users and listing all groups are not supported
     operations. Those calls require a specific domain filter and a
     domain-scoped token for the target domain.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You cannot have both a file store and a database store for domain-specific
     driver configuration in a single identity service instance. Once a
     database store is enabled within the identity service instance, any file
     store will be ignored, and vice versa.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The identity service allows a list limit configuration to globally set the
     maximum number of entities that will be returned in an identity collection
     per request but it does not support per-domain list limit setting at this
     time.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Each time a new domain is configured with LDAP integration the single CA
     file gets overwritten. Ensure that you place certs for all the LDAP
     back-end domains in the cacert parameter. Detailed CA file inclusion
     instructions are provided in the comments of the sample YAML configuration
     file <filename>keystone_configure_ldap_my.yml</filename>
     (see <xref linkend="filestore"/>).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     LDAP is only supported for identity operations (reading users and groups
     from LDAP).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Keystone assignment operations from LDAP records such as managing or
     assigning roles and projects, are not currently supported.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The &productname; 'default' domain is pre-configured to store service account
     users and is authenticated locally against the identity service. Domains
     configured for external LDAP integration are non-default domains.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     When using the current OpenStackClient CLI you must use the user ID rather
     than the user name when working with a non-default domain.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Each LDAP connection with the identity service is for read-only
     operations. Configurations that require identity service write operations
     (to create users, groups, etc.) are not currently supported.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     LDAP is only supported for identity operations (reading users and groups
     from LDAP). Keystone assignment operations from LDAP records such as
     managing or assigning roles and projects, are not currently supported.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     When using the current OpenStackClient CLI you must use the user ID rather
     than the user name when working with a non-default domain.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   &product; API-based domain-specific configuration management
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     No GUI dashboard for domain-specific driver configuration management
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     API-based Domain specific config does not check for type of option.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     API-based Domain specific config does not check for option values
     supported.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     API-based Domain config method does not provide retrieval of default
     values of domain-specific configuration options.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Status: Domain-specific driver configuration database store is a non-core
     feature for &product;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Keystone-to-Keystone federation</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     When a user is disabled in the identity provider, the issued federated
     token from the service provider still remains valid until the token is
     expired based on the Keystone expiration setting.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     An already issued federated token will retain its scope until its
     expiration. Any changes in the mapping on the service provider will not
     impact the scope of an already issued federated token. For example, if an
     already issued federated token was mapped to group1 that has scope on
     project1, and mapping is changed to group2 that has scope on project2, the
     prevously issued federated token still has scope on project1.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Access to service provider resources is provided only through the
     python-keystone CLI client or the Keystone API. No Horizon web interface
     support is currently available.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Domains, projects, groups, roles, and quotas are created per the service
     provider cloud. Support for federated projects, groups, roles, and quotas
     is currently not available.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Keystone-to-Keystone federation and WebSSO cannot be configured by putting
     both sets of configuration attributes in the same config file; they will
     overwrite each other. Consequently, they need to be configured
     individually.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Scoping the federated user to a domain is not supported by default in the
     playbook. To enable it, see the steps in <xref linkend="scopeToDomain"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     No Horizon web portal support currently exists for the creation and
     management of federation configurations.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     All end user authentication is available only via the Keystone API and
     OpenStackClient CLI.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Additional information can be found at
     <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">WebSSO</emphasis>
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The WebSSO function supports only Horizon web authentication. It is not
     supported for direct API or CLI access.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     WebSSO works only with Fernet token provider. See <xref linkend="fernet-tokens"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The &productname; WebSSO function was tested with Microsoft Active Directory
     Federation Services (ADFS). The instructions provided are pertinent to
     ADFS and are intended to provide a sample configuration for deploying
     WebSSO with an external identity provider. If you have a different
     identity provider such as Ping Identity or IBM Tivoli, consult with those
     vendors for specific instructions for those products.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Only WebSSO federation using the SAML method is supported in
     &product; . OpenID-based federation is not currently supported.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">WebSSO has a change password option in User
     Settings, but note that this function is not accessible for users
     authenticating with external systems such as LDAP or SAML Identity
     Providers.</emphasis>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Multi-factor authentication (MFA)</emphasis>
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &productname; MFA support is a custom configuration requiring &serviceteam; support.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     MFA drivers are not included with &productname; and need to be provided by a
     specific MFA vendor.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Additional information can be found at
     <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/security-guide/content/identity-authentication-methods.html#identity-authentication-methods-external-authentication-methods"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Hierarchical multitenancy</emphasis>
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     This function requires additional support from various OpenStack services
     to be functional. It is a non-core function in &productname; and is not ready
     for either proof of concept or production deployments.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Additional information can be found at
     <link xlink:href="http://specs.openstack.org/openstack/keystone-specs/specs/juno/hierarchical_multitenancy.html"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Missing quota information for compute
   resources</emphasis>
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    An error message that will appear in the default Horizon page if you are
    running a Swift-only deployment (no Compute service). In this
    configuration, you will not see any quota information for Compute
    resources and will see the following error message:
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   <emphasis>The Compute service is not installed or is not configured
   properly. No information is available for Compute resources.</emphasis> This
   error message is expected as no Compute service is configured for this
   deployment. Please ignore the error message.
  </para>
  <para>
   The following is the benchmark of the performance that is based on 150
   concurrent requests and run for 10 minute periods of stable load time.
  </para>
  <informaltable colsep="1" rowsep="1">
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.42*"/>
    <colspec colname="newCol3" colnum="3" colwidth="2.48*"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Operation </entry>
      <entry>In &product; (secs/request)</entry>
      <entry>In &product; 3.0 (secs/request)</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>Token Creation </entry>
      <entry>0.86</entry>
      <entry>0.42</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Token Validation</entry>
      <entry>0.47</entry>
      <entry>0.41</entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
  <para>
   Considering that token creation operations do not happen as frequently as
   token validation operations, you are likely to experience less of a
   performance problem regardless of the extended time for token creation.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="sec-keystone-cron">
  <title>System cron jobs need setup</title>
  <para>
   Keystone relies on two cron jobs to periodically clean up expired tokens and
   for token revocation. The following is how the cron jobs appear on the
   system:
  </para>
  <screen>1 1 * * * /opt/stack/service/keystone/venv/bin/keystone-manage token_flush
1 1,5,10,15,20 * * * /opt/stack/service/keystone/venv/bin/revocation_cleanup.sh </screen>
  <para>
   By default, the two cron jobs are enabled on controller node 1 only, not on
   the other two nodes. When controller node 1 is down or has failed for any
   reason, these two cron jobs must be manually set up on one of the other two
   nodes.
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
