<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="swift_ring_rebalance">
 <title>Rebalancing Swift Rings</title>
 <para>
  The Swift ring building process tries to distribute data evenly among the
  available disk drives. The data is stored in partitions. (For more
  information, see <xref linkend="ring-specification"/>.) If you, for example,
  double the number of disk drives in a ring, you need to move 50% of the
  partitions to the new drives so that all drives contain the same number of
  partitions (and hence same amount of data). However, it is not possible to
  move the partitions in a single step. It can take minutes to hours to move
  partitions from the original drives to their new drives (this process is
  called the replication process).
 </para>
 <para>
  If you move all partitions at once, there would be a period where Swift would
  expect to find partitions on the new drives, but the data has not yet
  replicated there so that Swift could not return the data to the user.
  Therefore, Swift will not be able to find all of the data in the middle of
  replication because some data has finished replication while other bits of
  data are still in the old locations and have not yet been moved. So it is
  considered best practice to move only one replica at a time. If the replica
  count is 3, you could first move 16.6% of the partitions and then wait until
  all data has replicated. Then move another 16.6% of partitions. Wait again
  and then finally move the remaining 16.6% of partitions. For any given
  object, only one of the replicas is moved at a time.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Reasons to Move Partitions Gradually</title>
  <para>
   Due to the following factors, you must move the partitions gradually:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Not all devices are of the same size. &product; automatically
     assigns different weights to drives so that smaller drives store fewer
     partitions than larger drives.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The process attempts to keep replicas of the same partition in different
     servers.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Making a large change in one step (for example, doubling the number of
     drives in the ring), would result in a lot of network traffic due to the
     replication process and the system performance suffers. There are two ways
     to mitigate this:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Add servers in smaller groups
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Set the weight-step attribute in the ring specification. For more
       information, see <xref linkend="swift_weight_att"/>.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</section>
