<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="add_swift_disk">
 <title>Adding Additional Disks to a Swift Node</title>
 <para>
  Steps for adding additional disks to any nodes hosting Swift services.
 </para>
 <para>
  You may have a need to add additional disks to a node for Swift usage and we
  can show you how. These steps work for adding additional disks to Swift
  object or proxy, account, container (PAC) nodes. It can also apply to adding
  additional disks to a controller node that is hosting the Swift service, like
  you would see if you are using one of the entry-scale example models.
 </para>
 <para>
  Read through the notes below before beginning the process.
 </para>
 <para>
  You can add multiple disks at the same time, there is no need to do it one at
  a time.
 </para>
 <important>
  <title>Add the Same Number of Disks</title>
  <para>
   You must add the <emphasis>same</emphasis> number of disks to each server
   that the disk model applies to. For example, if you have a single cluster of
   three Swift servers and you want to increase capacity and decide to add two
   additional disks, you must add two to each of your three Swift servers.
  </para>
 </important>
 <section>
  <title>Adding additional disks to your Swift servers</title>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Verify the general health of the Swift system and that it is safe to
     rebalance your rings. See <xref linkend="topic_ohx_j1t_4t"/> for details
     on how to do this.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Perform the disk maintenance.
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step xml:id="st.swift.add-disk.shutdown">
      <para>
       Shut down the first Swift server you wish to add disks to.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Add the additional disks to the physical server. The disk drives that
       are added should be clean. They should either contain no partitions or a
       single partition the size of the entire disk. It should not contain a
       file system or any volume groups. Failure to comply will cause errors
       and the disk will not be added.
      </para>
      <para>
       For more details, see <xref linkend="topic_d1s_hht_tt"/>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Power the server on.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       While the server was shutdown, data that normally would have been placed
       on the server is placed elsewhere. When the server is rebooted, the
       Swift replication process will move that data back onto the server.
       Monitor the replication process to determine when it is complete. See
       <xref linkend="topic_ohx_j1t_4t"/> for details on how to do this.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Repeat the steps from <xref linkend="st.swift.add-disk.shutdown"/> for
       each of the Swift servers you are adding the disks to, one at a time.
      </para>
       <note>
        <para>
         If the additional disks can be added to the Swift servers online
         (for example, via hotplugging) then there is no need to perform the
         last two steps.
         <!-- FIXME: Which steps are meant here? Previous steps or following
         steps? - sknorr, 2018-05-08 -->
        </para>
       </note>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the &clm;, update your cloud configuration with the details
     of your additional disks.
    </para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       Edit the disk configuration file that correlates to the type of server
       you are adding your new disks to.
      </para>
      <para>
       Path to the typical disk configuration files:
      </para>
<screen>~/openstack/my_cloud/definition/data/disks_swobj.yml
~/openstack/my_cloud/definition/data/disks_swpac.yml
~/openstack/my_cloud/definition/data/disks_controller_*.yml</screen>
      <para>
       Example showing the addition of a single new disk, indicated by the
       <literal>/dev/sdd</literal>, in bold:
      </para>
<screen>device-groups:
  - name: SwiftObject
    devices:
      - name: "/dev/sdb"
      - name: "/dev/sdc"
      <emphasis role="bold">- name: "/dev/sdd"</emphasis>
    consumer:
      name: swift
      ...</screen>
       <note>
        <para>
         For more details on how the disk model works, see
         <xref linkend="configurationobjects"/>.
        </para>
       </note>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Configure the Swift weight-step value in the
       <literal>~/openstack/my_cloud/definition/data/swift/swift_config.yml</literal>
       file. See <xref linkend="swift_weight_att"/> for details on how to do
       this.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Commit the changes to Git:
      </para>
<screen>cd ~/openstack
git commit -a -m "adding additional Swift disks"</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Run the configuration processor:
      </para>
<screen>cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</screen>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Update your deployment directory:
      </para>
<screen>cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run the <literal>osconfig-run.yml</literal> playbook against the Swift
     nodes you have added disks to. Use the <literal>--limit</literal> switch
     to target the specific nodes:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts osconfig-run.yml --limit &lt;hostnames&gt;</screen>
    <para>
     You can use a wildcard when specifying the hostnames with the
     <literal>--limit</literal> switch. If you added disks to all of the Swift
     servers in your environment and they all have the same prefix (for
     example, <literal>ardana-cp1-swobj...</literal>) then you can use a
     wildcard like <literal>ardana-cp1-swobj*</literal>. If you only added
     disks to a set of nodes but not all of them, you can use a comma
     deliminated list and enter the hostnames of each of the nodes you added
     disks to.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Validate your Swift configuration with this playbook which will also
     provide details of each drive being added:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-compare-model-rings.yml --extra-vars "drive_detail=yes"</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Verify that Swift services are running on all of your servers:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-status.yml</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If everything looks okay with the Swift status, then apply the changes to
     your Swift rings with this playbook:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-deploy.yml</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     At this point your Swift rings will begin rebalancing. You should wait
     until replication has completed or min-part-hours has elapsed (whichever
     is longer), as described in <xref linkend="topic_ohx_j1t_4t"/> and then
     follow the "Weight Change Phase of Ring Rebalance" process as described in
     <xref linkend="change_swift_rings"/>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
</section>
