<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="troubleshootingheat">
 <title>heat Troubleshooting</title>
 <para>
  Troubleshooting scenarios with resolutions for the heat service. This page
  describes troubleshooting scenarios for heat.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="rpc-timeout-heat">
  <title>RPC timeout on heat stack creation</title>
  <para>
   If you exerience a remote procedure call (RPC) timeout failure when
   attempting heat stack-create, you can work around the issue by increasing
   the timeout value and purging records of deleted stacks from the database.
   To do so, follow the steps below. An example of the error is:
  </para>
<screen>MessagingTimeout: resources.XXX-LCP-Pair01.resources[0]: Timed out waiting for a reply to message ID e861c4e0d9d74f2ea77d3ec1984c5cb6</screen>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Increase the timeout value.
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/openstack/my_cloud/config/heat</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Make changes to heat config files. In heat.conf.j2 add this timeout value:
    </para>
<screen>rpc_response_timeout=300</screen>
    <para>
     Commit your changes
    </para>
<screen>git commit -a -m "some message"</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Move to ansible directory and run the following playbooks:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Change to the scratch directory and run heat-reconfigure:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts heat-reconfigure.yml</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Purge records of deleted stacks from the database. First delete all stacks
     that are in failed state. Then execute the following
    </para>
<screen>sudo /opt/stack/venv/heat-20151116T000451Z/bin/python2
/opt/stack/service/heat-engine/venv/bin/heat-manage
--config-file /opt/stack/service/heat-engine-20151116T000451Z/etc/heat/heat.conf
--config-file /opt/stack/service/heat-engine-20151116T000451Z/etc/heat/engine.conf purge_deleted 0</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="hrat-stack-create-errors">
  <title>General heat stack creation errors</title>
  <para>
   In heat, in general when a timeout occurs it means that the underlying
   resource service such as nova, neutron, or cinder, fails to complete the
   required action. No matter what error this underlying service reports, heat
   simply reports it back. So in the case of time-out in heat stack create, you
   should look at the logs of the underlying services, most importantly the
   nova service, to understand the reason for the timeout.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="heat-stack-create-failure">
  <title>Multiple heat stack create failure</title>
  <para>
   The monasca AlarmDefinition resource,
   <literal>OS::monasca::AlarmDefinition</literal> used for heat autoscaling,
   consists of an optional property
   <emphasis role="bold"
                                >name</emphasis> for
   defining the alarm name. In case this optional property being specified in
   the heat template, this name must be unique in the same project of the
   system. Otherwise, multiple heat stack create using this heat template will
   fail with the following conflict:
  </para>
<screen>| cpu_alarm_low  | 5fe0151b-5c6a-4a54-bd64-67405336a740 | HTTPConflict: resources.cpu_alarm_low: An alarm definition already exists for project / tenant: 835d6aeeb36249b88903b25ed3d2e55a named: CPU utilization less than 15 percent  | CREATE_FAILED  | 2016-07-29T10:28:47 |</screen>
  <para>
   This is due to the fact that the monasca registers the alarm definition name
   using this name property when it is defined in the heat template. This name
   must be unique.
  </para>
  <para>
   To avoid this problem, if you want to define an alarm name using this
   property in the template, you must be sure this name is unique within a
   project in the system. Otherwise, you can leave this optional property
   undefined in your template. In this case, the system will create an unique
   alarm name automatically during heat stack create.
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
