<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="topic_gll_nsn_15">
 <title>Using Firewall as a Service (FWaaS)</title>
 <para>
  The Firewall as a Service (FWaaS) provides the ability to assign
  network-level, port security for all traffic entering and existing a tenant
  network. More information on this service can be found via the public
  OpenStack documentation located at
  <link xlink:href="http://specs.openstack.org/openstack/neutron-specs/specs/api/firewall_as_a_service__fwaas_.html"/>.
  The following documentation provides command-line interface example
  instructions for configuring and testing a firewall. The Firewall as a
  Service can also be configured and managed by the Horizon web interface.
 </para>
 <para>
  FWaaS is implemented directly in the L3 agent
  (<emphasis>neutron-l3-agent</emphasis>), however if VPNaaS is enabled, FWaaS
  is implemented in the VPNaaS agent (<emphasis>neutron-vpn-agent</emphasis>).
  Because FWaaS does not use a separate agent process or start a specific
  service, there currently are no Monasca alarms for it.
 </para>
 <para>
  If DVR is enabled, the firewall service currently does not filter traffic
  between OpenStack private networks, also known as <emphasis>east-west
  traffic</emphasis> and will only filter traffic from external networks, also
  known as <emphasis>north-south traffic</emphasis>.
 </para>
<section>
 <title>Overview of the &productname; Firewall configuration</title>
 <para>
  The following instructions provide information about how to identify and
  modify the overall &productname; firewall that is configured in front of the
  control services. This firewall is administered only by a cloud admin and is
  not available for tenant use for private network firewall services.
 </para>
 <para>
  During the installation process, the configuration processor will
  automatically generate "allow" firewall rules for each server based on the
  services deployed and block all other ports. These are populated in
  <literal>~/openstack/my_cloud/info/firewall_info.yml</literal>, which includes
  a list of all the ports by network, including the addresses on which the
  ports will be opened. This is described in more detail in
  <xref linkend="concept_firewallconfiguration"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  The <literal>firewall_rules.yml</literal> file in the input model allows you
  to define additional rules for each network group. You can read more about
  this in <xref linkend="configobj_firewallrules"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  The purpose of this document is to show you how to make post-installation
  changes to the firewall rules if the need arises.
 </para>
 <important>
  <para>
   This process is not to be confused with Firewall-as-a-Service,
   which is a separate service that enables the ability for &productname; tenants
   to create north-south, network-level firewalls to provide stateful
   protection to all instances in a private, tenant network. This service is
   optional and is tenant-configured.
  </para>
 </important>
</section>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-networking-fwaas-xml-9">
  <title>&productname; &productnumber; FWaaS Configuration</title>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Check for an enabled firewall.</emphasis>
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You should check to determine if the firewall is enabled. The output of
     the <emphasis>neutron ext-list</emphasis> should contain a firewall entry.
    </para>
<screen>openstack extension list</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Assuming the external network is already created by the admin, this
     command will show the external network.
    </para>
<screen>openstack network list</screen>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Create required assets.</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   Before creating firewalls, you will need to create a network, subnet,
   router, security group rules, start an instance and assign it a floating IP
   address.
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Create the network, subnet and router.
    </para>
<screen>openstack network create private
openstack subnet create --name sub private 10.0.0.0/24 --gateway 10.0.0.1
openstack router create router
openstack router add subnet router sub
openstack router set router ext-net</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Create security group rules. Security group rules filter traffic at VM
     level.
    </para>
<screen>openstack security group rule create default --protocol icmp
openstack security group rule create default --protocol tcp --port-range-min 22 --port-range-max 22
openstack security group rule create default --protocol tcp --port-range-min 80 --port-range-max 80</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Boot a VM.
    </para>
<screen>NET=$(neutron net-list | awk '/private/ {print $2}')
nova boot --flavor 1 --image &lt;image&gt; --nic net-id=$NET vm1 --poll</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Verify if the instance is ACTIVE and is assigned an IP address.
    </para>
<screen>nova list</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Get the port id of the vm1 instance.
    </para>
<screen>fixedip=$(nova list | awk '/vm1/ {print $12}' | awk -F '=' '{print $2}' | awk -F ',' '{print $1}')
vmportuuid=$(neutron port-list | grep $fixedip | awk '{print $2}')</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Create and associate a floating IP address to the vm1 instance.
    </para>
<screen>openstack floating ip create ext-net --port-id $vmportuuid</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Verify if the floating IP is assigned to the instance. The following
     command should show an assigned floating IP address from the external
     network range.
    </para>
<screen>nova show vm1</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Verify if the instance is reachable from the external network. SSH into
     the instance from a node in (or has route to) the external network.
    </para>
<screen>ssh cirros@FIP-VM1
password: &lt;password&gt;</screen>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Create and attach the firewall.</emphasis>
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    By default, an internal "drop all" rule is enabled in IP tables if none of
    the defined rules match the real-time data packets.
   </para>
  </note>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Create new firewall rules using <literal>firewall-rule-create</literal>
     command and providing the protocol, action (allow, deny, reject) and name
     for the new rule.
    </para>
    <para>
     Firewall actions provide rules in which data traffic can be handled. An
     <emphasis role="bold">allow</emphasis> rule will allow traffic to pass
     through the firewall,
     <emphasis role="bold">deny</emphasis>
     will stop and prevent data traffic from passing through the firewall and
     <emphasis role="bold">reject</emphasis>
     will reject the data traffic and return a
     <emphasis>destination-unreachable</emphasis> response. Using
     <emphasis role="bold">reject</emphasis> will speed up failure detection
     time dramatically for legitimate users, since they will not be required to
     wait for retransmission timeouts or submit retries. Some customers should
     stick with <emphasis role="bold">deny</emphasis> where prevention of port
     scanners and similar methods may be attempted by hostile attackers. Using
     <emphasis role="bold">deny</emphasis>
     will drop all of the packets, making it more difficult for malicious
     intent. The firewall action, <emphasis role="bold">deny</emphasis> is the
     default behavior.
    </para>
    <para>
     The example below demonstrates how to allow icmp and ssh while denying
     access to http. See the <literal>neutron</literal> command-line reference
     at <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/cli-reference/content/neutronclient_commands.html"/>
     on additional options such as source IP, destination IP, source port and
     destination port.
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      You can create a firewall rule with an identical name and each instance
      will have a unique id associated with the created rule, however for
      clarity purposes this is not recommended.
     </para>
    </note>
<screen>neutron firewall-rule-create --protocol icmp --action allow --name allow-icmp
neutron firewall-rule-create --protocol tcp --destination-port 80 --action deny --name deny-http
neutron firewall-rule-create --protocol tcp --destination-port 22 --action allow --name allow-ssh</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Once the rules are created, create the firewall policy by using the
     <literal>firewall-policy-create</literal> command with the
     <literal>--firewall-rules</literal> option and rules to include in quotes,
     followed by the name of the new policy. The order of the rules is
     important.
    </para>
<screen>neutron firewall-policy-create --firewall-rules "allow-icmp deny-http allow-ssh" policy-fw</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Finish the firewall creation by using the
     <literal>firewall-create</literal> command, the policy name and the new
     name you want to give to your new firewall.
    </para>
<screen>neutron firewall-create policy-fw --name user-fw</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You can view the details of your new firewall by using the
     <literal>firewall-show</literal> command and the name of your firewall.
     This will verify that the status of the firewall is ACTIVE.
    </para>
<screen>neutron firewall-show user-fw</screen>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Verify the FWaaS is functional.</emphasis>
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Since allow-icmp firewall rule is set you can ping the floating IP address
     of the instance from the external network.
    </para>
<screen>ping &lt;FIP-VM1&gt;</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Similarly, you can connect via ssh to the instance due to the allow-ssh
     firewall rule.
    </para>
<screen>ssh cirros@&lt;FIP-VM1&gt;
password: &lt;password&gt;</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Run a web server on vm1 instance that listens over port 80, accepts
     requests and sends a WELCOME response.
    </para>
<screen>$ vi webserv.sh

#!/bin/bash

MYIP=$(/sbin/ifconfig eth0|grep 'inet addr'|awk -F: '{print $2}'| awk '{print $1}');
while true; do
  echo -e "HTTP/1.0 200 OK

Welcome to $MYIP" | sudo nc -l -p 80
done

# Give it Exec rights
$ chmod 755 webserv.sh

# Execute the script
$ ./webserv.sh</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You should expect to see curl fail over port 80 because of the deny-http
     firewall rule. If curl succeeds, the firewall is not blocking incoming
     http requests.
    </para>
<screen>curl -vvv &lt;FIP-VM1&gt;</screen>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <warning>
   <para>
    When using reference implementation, new networks, FIPs and routers created
    after the Firewall creation will not be automatically updated with firewall
    rules. Thus, execute the firewall-update command by passing the current and
    new router Ids such that the rules are reconfigured across all the routers
    (both current and new).
   </para>
   <para>
    For example if router-1 is created before and router-2 is created after the
    firewall creation
   </para>
<screen>$ neutron firewall-update —router &lt;router-1-id&gt; —router &lt;router-2-id&gt; &lt;firewall-name&gt;</screen>
  </warning>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-operations-configure_firewall-xml-7">
  <title>Making Changes to the Firewall Rules</title>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Log in to your &clm;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Edit your
     <literal>~/openstack/my_cloud/definition/data/firewall_rules.yml</literal>
     file and add the lines necessary to allow the port(s) needed through the
     firewall.
    </para>
    <para>
     In this example we are going to open up port range 5900-5905 to allow VNC
     traffic through the firewall:
    </para>
<screen>
  - name: VNC
    network-groups:
  - MANAGEMENT
    rules:
     - type: allow
       remote-ip-prefix:  0.0.0.0/0
       port-range-min: 5900
       port-range-max: 5905
       protocol: tcp</screen>
    <note>
     <para>
      The example above shows a <literal>remote-ip-prefix</literal> of
      <literal>0.0.0.0/0</literal> which opens the ports up to all IP ranges.
      To be more secure you can specify your local IP address CIDR you will
      be running the VNC connect from.
     </para>
    </note>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Commit those changes to your local git:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;git add -A
&prompt.ardana;git commit -m "firewall rule update"</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Run the configuration processor:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Create the deployment directory structure:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Change to the deployment directory and run the
     <literal>osconfig-iptables-deploy.yml</literal> playbook to update your
     iptable rules to allow VNC:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts osconfig-iptables-deploy.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   You can repeat these steps as needed to add, remove, or edit any of these
   firewall rules.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="sec.hp20fwaas.more">
  <title>More Information</title>
  <para>
   Firewalls are based in IPtable settings.
  </para>
  <para>
   Each firewall that is created is known as an instance.
  </para>
  <para>
   A firewall instance can be deployed on selected project routers. If no
   specific project router is selected, a firewall instance is automatically
   applied to all project routers.
  </para>
  <para>
   Only 1 firewall instance can be applied to a project router.
  </para>
  <para>
   Only 1 firewall policy can be applied to a firewall instance.
  </para>
  <para>
   Multiple firewall rules can be added and applied to a firewall policy.
  </para>
  <para>
   Firewall rules can be shared across different projects via the Share API
   flag.
  </para>
  <para>
   Firewall rules supersede the Security Group rules that are applied at the
   Instance level for all traffic entering or leaving a private, project
   network.
  </para>
  <para>
   For more information on the neutron command-line interface (CLI) and
   firewalls, see the OpenStack networking command-line client reference:
   <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/cli-reference/content/neutronclient_commands.html"/>
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
