<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="sec-trouble-restart-storeage-deployment">
 <title>Restarting the Object Storage Deployment</title>
 <para>
  This page describes the various operational procedures performed by Swift.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="restart-swift-depl">
  <title>Restart the Swift Object Storage Deployment</title>
  <para>
   The structure of ring is built in an incremental stages. When you modify a
   ring, the new ring uses the state of the old ring as a basis for the new
   ring. Rings are stored in the builder file. The
   <literal>swiftlm-ring-supervisor</literal> stores builder files in the
   <literal>/etc/swiftlm/cloud1/cp1/builder_dir/</literal>
   directory on the Ring-Builder node. The builder files are named
   &lt;ring-name&gt; builder. Prior versions of the builder files are stored in
   the
   <literal>/etc/swiftlm/cloud1/cp1/builder_dir/backups</literal>
   directory.
  </para>
  <para>
   Generally, you use an existing builder file as the basis for changes to a
   ring. However, at initial deployment, when you create a ring there will be
   no builder file. Instead, the first step in the process is to build a
   builder file. The deploy playbook does this as a part of the deployment
   process. If you have successfully deployed some of the system, the ring
   builder files will exist.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you change your input model (for example, by adding servers) now, the
   process assumes you are <emphasis>modifying</emphasis> a ring and behaves
   differently than while creating a ring from scratch. In this case, the ring
   is not balanced. So, if the cloud model contains an error or you decide to
   make substantive changes, it is a best practice to start from scratch and
   build rings using the steps below.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="reset-builder-files">
  <title>Reset Builder Files</title>
  <para>
   You must reset the builder files during the initial deployment process
   (only). This process should be used only when you want to restart a
   deployment from scratch. If you reset the builder files after completing
   your initial deployment, then you are at a risk of losing critical system
   data.
  </para>
  <para>
   Delete the builder files in the
   <filename>/etc/swiftlm/cloud1/cp1/builder-dir/</filename>
   directory. For example, for the region0 Keystone region (the default single
   region designation), do the following:
  </para>
<screen>sudo rm /etc/swiftlm/cloud1/cp1/builder_dir/*.builder</screen>
  <note>
   <para>
    If you have successfully deployed a system and accidentally delete the
    builder files, you can recover to the correct state. For instructions, see
    <xref linkend="topic-gbz-13t-mt"/>.
   </para>
  </note>
 </section>
</section>
