<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!---->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="central_log_manage">
 <title>Managing the Centralized Logging Feature</title>
 <para>
  No specific configuration tasks are required to use Centralized Logging, as
  it is enabled by default after installation. However, you can configure the
  individual components as needed for your environment.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="CL_stop_start">
  <title>How Do I Stop and Start the Logging Service?</title>
  <para>
   Although you might not need to stop and start the logging service very
   often, you may need to if, for example, one of the logging services is not
   behaving as expected or not working.
  </para>
  <para>
   You cannot enable or disable centralized logging across all services unless
   you stop all centralized logging. Instead, it is recommended that you enable
   or disable individual log files in the &lt;service&gt;-clr.yml files and
   then reconfigure logging. You would enable centralized logging for a file
   when you want to make sure you are able to monitor those logs in Kibana.
  </para>
  <para>
   In &productname;, the logging-ansible restart playbook has been updated to manage
   the start,stop, and restart of the Centralized Logging Service in a specific
   way. This change was made to ensure the proper stop, start, and restart of
   &elasticsearch;.
  </para>
  <important>
   <para>
    It is recommended that you only use the logging playbooks to perform the
    start, stop, and restart of the Centralized Logging Service. Manually
    mixing the start, stop, and restart operations with the logging playbooks
    will result in complex failures.
   </para>
  </important>
  <para>
   The steps in this section only impact centralized logging. Logrotate is an
   essential feature that keeps the service log files from filling the disk and
   will not be affected.
  </para>
  <important>
   <para>
    These playbooks must be run from the &clm;.
   </para>
  </important>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">To stop the Logging service:</emphasis>
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To change to the directory containing the ansible playbook, run
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To run the ansible playbook that will stop the logging service, run:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts logging-stop.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">To start the Logging service:</emphasis>
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To change to the directory containing the ansible playbook, run
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To run the ansible playbook that will stop the logging service, run:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts logging-start.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="CL_disable">
  <title>How Do I Enable or Disable Centralized Logging For a Service?</title>
  <para>
   To enable or disable Centralized Logging for a service you need to modify
   the configuration for the service, set the
   <emphasis role="bold">enabled</emphasis> flag to
   <emphasis role="bold">true</emphasis> or
   <emphasis role="bold">false</emphasis>, and then reconfigure logging.
  </para>
  <important>
   <para>
    There are consequences if you enable too many logging files for a service.
    If there is not enough storage to support the increased logging, the
    retention period of logs in &elasticsearch; is decreased. Alternatively, if
    you wanted to increase the retention period of log files or if you did not
    want those logs to show up in Kibana, you would disable centralized logging
    for a file.
   </para>
  </important>
  <para>
   To enable Centralized Logging for a service:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Use the documentation provided with the service to ensure it is not
     configured for logging.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To find the &productname; file to edit, run:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;find ~/openstack/my_cloud/config/logging/vars/ -name "*<replaceable>service-name</replaceable>*"</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Edit the file for the service for which you want to enable logging.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To enable Centralized Logging, find the following code and change the
     enabled flag to <emphasis role="bold">true</emphasis>, to disable, change
     the enabled flag to <emphasis role="bold">false</emphasis>:
    </para>
<screen>logging_options:
 - centralized_logging:
        enabled: true
        format: json</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Save the changes to the file.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To commit the changes to your local git repository:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;git add -A
&prompt.ardana;git commit -m "My config or other commit message"</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     To reconfigure logging, run:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts kronos-reconfigure.yml
&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible/
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
</section>
