<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<section>
 <title>The OpenStack Operator's Tasks</title>
 <para>
  In order to use <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> for
  monitoring your OpenStack services and servers, so-called agents must be
  installed and configured:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Metrics Agent is required for monitoring your services and servers.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Log Agent is required for collecting the log data that is generated for
    your services and servers.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Monitoring </bridgehead>
 <para>
  The Metrics agent is responsible for querying metrics and sending them to the
  Monitoring Service for further processing.
 </para>
 <para>
  Metrics are self-describing data structures that are uniquely identified by a
  name and a set of dimensions. Each dimension consists of a key/value pair
  that allows for a flexible and concise description of the data to be
  monitored, for example, region, availability zone, service tier, or resource
  ID.
 </para>
 <para>
  The Metrics Agent supports various types of metrics including the following:
  <remark condition="clarity">
   2017-06-01 - shermann: @jgrassler: Section to be updated depending on which
   metrics will be auto-detected/supported in the first release of SOCM? 
   taroth 2017-06-08: OK as is, see also bsc#1042453
  </remark>
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    System metrics, for example, CPU usage, consumed disk space, or network
    traffic.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Host alive checks. The agent can perform active checks on a host to
    determine whether it is alive using ping (ICMP) or SSH.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Process checks. The agent can check and monitor a process, for example, the
    number of instances, memory size, or number of threads.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    HTTP endpoint checks. The agent can perform up/down checks on HTTP
    endpoints by sending an HTTP request and reporting success or failure to
    the Monitoring Service.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Service checks. The agent can check middleware services, for example,
    MySQL, Kafka, or RabbitMQ.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    OpenStack services. The agent can perform specific checks on each process
    that is part of an OpenStack service.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Log metrics. The agent can check and monitor the number of critical log
    entries in the log data retrieved from the cloud resources.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  Your individual agent configuration determines which metrics are available
  for monitoring your services and servers. For details on installing and
  configuring a Metrics Agent, refer to
  <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/soc/8/html/suse-openstack-cloud-crowbar-all/cha-depl-ostack.html#sec-depl-ostack-monasca"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  As soon as an agent is available, you have access to the <phrase>SUSE
  OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> monitoring features. You work with a
  graphical user interface that is seamlessly integrated into your cloud
  infrastructure. Based on OpenStack Horizon, the user interface enables access
  to all monitoring functionality and the resulting large-scale monitoring
  data. A comfortable dashboard visualizes the health and status of your cloud
  resources.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> provides functions for alarm
  and notification management. <phrase>Template-based alarm definitions allow
  for monitoring a dynamically changing set of resources without the need for
  reconfiguration. While the number of underlying virtual machines is changing,
  for example, this ensures the efficient monitoring of scalable cloud
  services. Alarm definitions allow you to specify expressions that are
  evaluated based on the metrics data that is received. Alarm definitions can
  be combined to form compound alarms. Compound alarms allow you to track and
  process even more complex events. Notifications can be configured in order to
  inform <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> users when an alarm
  is triggered.</phrase>
 </para>
 <para>
  For details on the monitoring functions, refer to
  <xref linkend="idg-osoperator-shared-monitor-c-monitor-xml-1"/>.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Log Management</bridgehead>
 <para>
  The Log Agent collects the log data from the services and servers and sends
  them to the Monitoring Service for further processing. For details on
  installing and configuring a Log Agent, refer to
  <ulink url="https://documentation.suse.com/soc/8/html/suse-openstack-cloud-crowbar-all/cha-depl-ostack.html#sec-depl-ostack-monasca"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> stores the log data in a
  central database. This forms the basis for visualizing the log data for the
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> users. Advanced data
  analysis and visualization of the log data is supported in a variety of
  charts, tables, and maps. Visualizations can easily be combined in dynamic
  dashboards that display changes to search queries in real time.
 </para>
 <para>
  Based on OpenStack Horizon, the customizable dashboards are seamlessly
  integrated into your cloud infrastructure. They enable user access to all log
  management functionality.
 </para>
 <para>
  GUI-based alarm and notification management is also supported for log data.
  Based on a template mechanism, you can configure alarms and notifications to
  monitor the number of critical log events over time. Compound alarms can be
  created to analyze more complex log events. This automation of log handling
  guarantees that you can identify problems in your their infrastructure early
  and find the root cause quickly.
 </para>
 <para>
  For details on the log management functions, refer to
  <xref linkend="idg-osoperator-shared-logging-c-osologging-xml-1"/>.
 </para>
</section>
