<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<section id="idg-osoperator-osoperator-install-c-osoinstallationlogagent-xml-1">
 <title>Installation</title>
 <para>
  To install a Log Agent, proceed as follows:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Log in to the Control Machine.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Open the configuration file of the Control Machine with your favorite
    editor.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen>sudo vim /etc/ansible/hosts</screen>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Configure the hosts on which you want to install an agent. For this
    purpose, check the following section in the configuration file:
   </para>
<screen># Monasca Log Agent Hosts
openstack-monasca-log-agent   ansible_ssh_host={{ openstack_host }} ansible_ssh_user={{ ssh_user_openstack }}</screen>
   <para>
    If required, you can add a line for installing an additional agent on a
    different host. The installer allows you to install one or multiple
    instances of an agent at a time.
   </para>
   <para>
    When adding a line for an additional agent, you have to specify a unique
    alias for the host machine on which to install the agent. In addition, you
    have to add the agent in the <literal>[monasca_log_agent_group]</literal>
    section:
   </para>
<screen>[monasca_log_agent_group] 
openstack-monasca-log-agent</screen>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Replace the host variables with the IP address of the remote machines on
    which to install an agent.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     <phrase>CMM</phrase> supports and has been tested with IPv4. IPv6 and FQDN
     are not supported.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    Replace <literal>&lt;ssh_user_monasca&gt;</literal> with the user name of
    the user who is to install the agent.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     The user who installs the agent must have access to the machine on which
     the agent is to be installed. Access as a user with root privileges is
     required.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    Check that you have removed all curly brackets with your replacements.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To establish the connection between the Control Machine and the remote
    machines, generate the SSH key for Ansible.
   </para>
   <para>
    Execute the following command:
   </para>
   <para>
<screen>ssh-keygen -t rsa</screen>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To copy the SSH key to a remote machine, execute the following command.
    Repeat the command for each remote machine on which to install an agent.
   </para>
<screen>ssh-copy-id &lt;user_name&gt;@&lt;host_ip_address&gt;</screen>
   <para>
    Replace <literal>&lt;user_name&gt;</literal> by the user name to be used
    for accessing the remote machine, and replace
    <literal>&lt;host_ip_address&gt;</literal> by the IP address of the remote
    machine.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example response for a successful connection to a remote machine:
   </para>
<screen>/usr/bin/ssh-copy-id: INFO: attempting to log in with the new key(s), to filter out any that are already installed
/usr/bin/ssh-copy-id: INFO: 1 key(s) remain to be installed -- if you are prompted now it is to install the new keys
&lt;user_name&gt;@&lt;host_ip_address&gt;'s password:

Number of key(s) added: 1

Now try logging into the machine, with:   "ssh '&lt;user_name&gt;@&lt;host_ip_address&gt;'"
and check to make sure that only the key(s) you wanted were added.</screen>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Create a configuration file for each agent. An individual configuration
    file is required for each agent instance that is to be installed.
   </para>
   <para>
    Execute the following command to create a configuration file. Repeat the
    command for all host machines on which to install an agent.
   </para>
<screen>sudo vim /opt/FJSVsvcmm/host_vars/&lt;file_name&gt;</screen>
   <para>
    Replace <literal>&lt;file_name&gt;</literal> with the alias for the host
    machine. <literal>&lt;file_name&gt;</literal> must be identical to the
    alias specified in the configuration file of the Control Machine (see Step
    3 above).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Configure the agents. The following example shows the minimum set of
    parameters that must be configured to start an agent. The minimum set is
    restricted to the credentials of an OpenStack user used for the
    communication between the Monitoring Service and the agent.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can specify additional configuration settings, if required. For details
    on the configuration settings, refer to
    <xref linkend="idg-osoperator-shared-appendix-r-confsettings-logs-xml-1"/>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To define the minimum set of parameters, insert the following content into
    each configuration file. Replace the user credentials with the credentials
    of a valid OpenStack user who is authorized to send monitoring data to the
    Monitoring Service.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen># file: host_vars/monasca-log-agent

# logstash monasca user credentials
monasca_log_agent_project: admin
monasca_log_agent_user: admin-agent
monasca_log_agent_password: "{{ keystone_admin_agent_password }}"
user_domain_name: default
project_domain_name: default</screen>
   <note>
    <para>
     The installation automatically configures the agent so that a minimum set
     of log data can be retrieved. For information on how to update this set of
     log data, refer to
     <xref linkend="idg-osoperator-shared-install-c-configurelogagent-xml-1"/>.
    </para>
   </note>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Provide the passwords required for installing an agent. They are defined in
    the <literal>credentials.yml</literal> file that is located in the
    <literal>/opt/FJSVsvcmm</literal> directory.
   </para>
   <para>
    Open the <literal>credentials.yml</literal> file with your favorite editor.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen>sudo vim /opt/FJSVsvcmm/credentials.yml</screen>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Specify the following passwords in the file:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>keystone_admin_agent_password</literal> for Keystone access of
      the user used for configuration purposes of the agents on the OpenStack
      hosts. The user account is automatically created with the installation.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>keystone_monasca_agent_password</literal> for Keystone access of
      the user used for configuration purposes of the agents on the
      <phrase>CMM</phrase> host. The user account is automatically created with
      the installation.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <note>
    <para id="idg-osoperator-osoperator-install-c-osoinstallationlogagent-xml-4">
     The passwords must be handled in a secure way. Access to the
     <literal>credentials.yml</literal> is controlled by the Linux file
     permissions.
    </para>
   </note>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To run the installer, execute the following command:
   </para>
<screen>ansible-playbook /opt/FJSVsvcmm/monasca-log-agent.yml</screen>
   <para>
    The following response is displayed if the installation is successful.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen>PLAY RECAP ********************************************************
monasca-log-agent  :  ok=40   changed=23   unreachable=0   failed=0</screen>
   <note>
    <para>
     There are checks performed during installation that may result in failures
     or warnings. These failures and warnings are reported but they do not
     block the installation. It is only this final message that is relevant for
     a successful installation.
    </para>
   </note>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <para>
  In case the installation fails, check your configuration settings and
  passwords and retry the installation in verbose mode. To collect debug
  information, you can execute the following command:
 </para>
<screen>ansible-playbook -vvvv /opt/FJSVsvcmm/monasca-log-agent.yml</screen>
 <para>
  The agents are installed, configured, and automatically started after a
  successful installation. The installer creates a startup script that
  automatically starts the agent when the machine is booted.
 </para>
 <para>
  An agent is provided as a LINUX service.
 </para>
</section>
