<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<section id="idg-osoperator-intro-c-osocomponents-xml-1">
 <title>Components</title>
 <para>
  The following illustration provides an overview of the main components of
  <phrase>CMM</phrase>:
  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images-overview-structure.png" depth="210" width="400"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject><phrase>structure_new.png</phrase>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">OpenStack</bridgehead>
 <para id="OpenStack-is-the-underlying-p-concept-conbody-section-2-p">
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> relies on OpenStack as technology for building cloud
  computing platforms for public and private clouds. OpenStack consists of a
  series of interrelated projects delivering various components for a cloud
  infrastructure solution and allowing for the deployment and management of
  Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS) platforms.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Monitoring Service</bridgehead>
 <para id="idg-osoperator-intro-c-osocomponents-xml-8">
  The Monitoring Service is the central <phrase>CMM</phrase> component. It is
  responsible for receiving, persisting, and processing metrics and log data,
  as well as providing the data to the users.
 </para>
 <para>
  The Monitoring Service relies on Monasca. It uses Monasca for high-speed
  metrics querying and integrates the streaming alarm engine and the
  notification engine of Monasca. For details, refer to the
  <ulink url="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Monasca">Monasca Wiki</ulink>.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Horizon Plugin</bridgehead>
 <para>
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> comes with a plugin for the OpenStack Horizon dashboard.
  The plugin extends the main dashboard in OpenStack with a view for
  monitoring. This enables <phrase>CMM</phrase> users to access the monitoring
  functions from a central Web-based graphical user interface. For details,
  refer to the <ulink url="http://docs.openstack.org/developer/horizon/">OpenStack Horizon documentation</ulink>.
 </para>
 <para>
  Based on OpenStack Horizon, the monitoring data is visualized on a
  comfortable and easy-to-use dashboard which fully integrates with the
  following applications:
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Grafana (for metrics data). An open source application for visualizing
     large-scale measurement data.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Kibana (for log data). An open source analytics and visualization platform
     designed to work with Elasticsearch.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Metrics Agent</bridgehead>
 <para id="idg-osoperator-intro-c-osocomponents-xml-14">
  A Metrics Agent is required for retrieving metrics data from the host on
  which it runs and sending it to the Monitoring Service. The agent supports
  metrics from a variety of sources as well as a number of built-in system and
  service checks.
 </para>
 <para id="idg-osoperator-intro-c-osocomponents-xml-15">
  A Metrics Agent can be installed on each virtual or physical server to be
  monitored.
 </para>
 <para id="The-agent-functionality-is-fu-concept-conbody-section-5-p">
  The agent functionality is fully integrated into the source code base of the
  Monasca project. For details, refer to the
  <ulink url="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Monasca">Monasca Wiki</ulink>.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Log Agent</bridgehead>
 <para>
  A Log Agent is needed for collecting log data from the host on which it runs
  and forwarding it to the Monitoring Service for further processing. It can be
  installed on each virtual or physical server from which log data is to be
  retrieved.
 </para>
 <para>
  The agent functionality is fully integrated into the source code base of the
  Monasca project. For details, refer to the
  <ulink url="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Monasca">Monasca Wiki</ulink>.
 </para>
</section>
