<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<section id="idg-osoperator-install-c-osoinstosext-xml-1">
 <title>Installing the OpenStack Extensions</title>
 <para>
  As a prerequisite for installing the OpenStack Extensions, the Monitoring
  Service operator must have installed the offline resources.
 </para>
 <para>
  To install the OpenStack extensions for <phrase>CMM</phrase>, proceed as
  follows:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Log in to the Control Machine.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The installer uses Ansible group variables for configuration purposes. The
    group variables are located in the
    <literal>/opt/FJSVsvcmm/group_vars</literal> directory.
   </para>
   <para>
    Open the <literal>all_group</literal> file with your favorite editor. It
    defines the main configuration settings.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen>sudo vim /opt/FJSVsvcmm/group_vars/all_group</screen>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The installer creates OpenStack user accounts for working with
    <phrase>CMM</phrase>. For this purpose, specify your access credentials for
    the OpenStack Keystone service in the <literal>Keystone Admin
    credentials</literal> section:
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen># Keystone Admin credentials
keystone_admin_token: ADMIN
keystone_admin: 'admin'
keystone_admin_project: 'admin'</screen>
   <note>
    <para>
     If <literal>ADMIN</literal> authentication is disabled for the OpenStack
     Keystone service, <literal>keystone_admin_token: ADMIN</literal> must be
     removed.
    </para>
   </note>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Provide the passwords required for installing the OpenStack extensions.
    They are defined in the <literal>credentials.yml</literal> file that is
    located in the <literal>/opt/FJSVsvcmm</literal> directory.
   </para>
   <para>
    Open the <literal>credentials.yml</literal> file with your favorite editor.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen>sudo vim /opt/FJSVsvcmm/credentials.yml</screen>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Specify the following passwords in the file:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>keystone_monasca_operator_password</literal> for Keystone access
      of the Monitoring Service operator. The user account for the Monitoring
      Service operator is automatically created with the installation.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>keystone_monasca_agent_password</literal> for Keystone access of
      the user used for configuration purposes of the Metrics Agent. The user
      account is automatically created with the installation.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>keystone_admin_agent_password</literal> for Keystone access of
      the user used for configuration purposes of the Log Agent. The user
      account is automatically created with the installation.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <literal>keystone_admin_password</literal> of an OpenStack user account
      that already exists, for example, <literal>admin</literal>. This user
      account is used for creating the new user accounts with the installation.
      It is the user account of the OpenStack operator.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <note>
    <para id="idg-osoperator-install-c-osoinstosext-xml-4">
     The passwords must be handled in a secure way. Access to the
     <literal>credentials.yml</literal> is controlled by the Linux file
     permissions.
    </para>
   </note>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Specify your region name for the OpenStack Keystone service. The region
    name is defined by the <literal>keystone_region</literal> parameter in the
    <literal>/opt/FJSVsvcmm/roles/monasca-keystone/defaults/main.yml</literal>
    file.
   </para>
   <para>
    Open the <literal>main.yml</literal> file with your favorite editor.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen>sudo vim /opt/FJSVsvcmm/roles/monasca-keystone/defaults/main.yml</screen>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Adapt the <literal>keystone_region</literal> parameter in the file to your
    environment.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen>keystone_region: RegionOne</screen>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To install the OpenStack extensions, specific configuration settings are
    required. They are specified in the
    <literal>group_vars/openstack_group</literal> file.
   </para>
   <para>
    The file contains the default configuration. No changes are required.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     Make changes only if you have to deviate from the default.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    To view the default configuration, you can open the file with your favorite
    editor.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen>sudo vim /opt/FJSVsvcmm/group_vars/openstack_group</screen>
   <para>
    By default, the installer creates the following users, roles, and projects
    in OpenStack:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A Monitoring Service operator who is to monitor <phrase>CMM</phrase>.
     </para>
     <para>
      User name: <literal>monasca-operator</literal>. Assigned user role:
      <literal>monasca-user</literal> and <literal>admin</literal>. Assigned
      OpenStack project: <literal>monasca</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A user for configuration purposes of the agents used for monitoring
      <phrase>CMM</phrase>. It is recommended that this user account is used
      only for the agent configurations and not for monitoring and log
      management tasks.
     </para>
     <para>
      User name: <literal>monasca-agent</literal>. Assigned user role:
      <literal>monasca-agent</literal>. Assigned OpenStack project:
      <literal>monasca</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The OpenStack operator who is to monitor the OpenStack platform uses the
      existing <literal>admin</literal> user account.
     </para>
     <para>
      Assigned user role: <literal>monasca-user</literal> and
      <literal>admin</literal>. Assigned OpenStack project:
      <literal>admin</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A user for configuration purposes of the agents used for monitoring the
      OpenStack services. It is recommended that this user account is used only
      for the agent configurations and not for monitoring and log management
      tasks.
     </para>
     <para>
      User name: <literal>admin-agent</literal>. Assigned user role:
      <literal>monasca-agent</literal>. Assigned OpenStack project:
      <literal>admin</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <note>
    <para>
     The roles that are created by the installer must be authorized for
     accessing the Monitoring Service. If you change the default configuration
     of the user accounts, contact your Monitoring Service operator. He is
     responsible for configuring the Monitoring Service.
    </para>
   </note>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To install the OpenStack extensions, execute the following command:
   </para>
<screen>ansible-playbook /opt/FJSVsvcmm/openstack.yml</screen>
   <para>
    The following response is displayed if the installation is successful.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen>PLAY RECAP ********************************************************
horizon-node       : ok=34   changed=21   unreachable=0    failed=0
keystone-node      : ok=21   changed=3    unreachable=0    failed=0</screen>
   <note>
    <para>
     There are checks performed during installation that may result in failures
     or warnings. These failures and warnings are reported but they do not
     block the installation. It is only this final message that is relevant for
     a successful installation.
    </para>
   </note>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <para>
  In case the installation fails, check your configuration settings and
  passwords and retry the installation in verbose mode. To collect debug
  information, you can execute the following command:
 </para>
<screen>ansible-playbook -vvvv /opt/FJSVsvcmm/openstack.yml</screen>
 <para>
  As soon as the OpenStack extensions are successfully installed, the
  Monitoring Service operator can install the Monitoring Service.
 </para>
 <para>
  As soon as the Monitoring Service is successfully installed, you can proceed
  with installing and configuring the agents for monitoring your OpenStack
  platform.
 </para>
</section>
