<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<section id="idg-osoperator-install-c-osoprepansiblemaster-xml-1">
 <title>Configuring the Control Machine</title>
 <para>
  The Control Machine must be connected to all remote machines on which
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> components are to be installed. To configure the Control
  Machine, proceed as follows:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Log in to the Control Machine.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Open the Ansible configuration file with your favorite editor.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen>sudo vim /etc/ansible/ansible.cfg</screen>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Specify the following SSH settings in the file:
   </para>
<screen>[defaults]
transport = ssh

[ssh_connection]
ssh_args = -o ControlMaster=auto -o BatchMode=yes -o ForwardAgent=yes</screen>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Open the configuration file of the Control Machine with your favorite
    editor.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example:
   </para>
<screen>sudo vim /etc/ansible/hosts</screen>
   <para>
    For detailed information on the configuration of the Control Machine, refer
    to the <ulink url="http://docs.ansible.com/intro_inventory.html">Ansible
    Inventory documentation</ulink>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Configure the required hosts in the configuration file.
    <phrase>CMM</phrase> ships with a sample configuration file that you can
    use as a template:
   </para>
   <para>
    <literal>hosts-single-os.j2</literal>
   </para>
   <para>
    The sample is located in the <literal>/opt/FJSVsvcmm/templates</literal>
    directory.
   </para>
   <para>
    Copy the complete content of the sample file to your configuration file.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Replace all variables in the host definitions section:
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>Offline Host</literal> for the offline resources required for
       the installation. Contact your Monitoring Service operator for the IP
       address. He has already installed the offline resources.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>OpenStack Hosts</literal> for installing the OpenStack
       extensions on the Horizon host and the Keystone host.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>Monasca Agent Hosts</literal> for installing a Metrics Agent on
       the Horizon host and the Keystone host.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <literal>Monasca Log Agent Hosts</literal> for installing a Log Agent on
       the Horizon host and the Keystone host.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </para>
   <para>
    Replace <literal>{{ *_host }}</literal> with the IP address of the remote
    machine on which you want to install the corresponding <phrase>CMM</phrase>
    component.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     <phrase>CMM</phrase> supports and has been tested with IPv4. IPv6 and FQDN
     are not supported.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    Replace <literal>{{ ssh_user_* }}</literal> with the user name of the user
    who is to install it. Check that you have removed the curly brackets with
    your replacements.
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     The user who is to install the <phrase>CMM</phrase> component must have
     the privilege to execute sudo commands without password. Check your sudo
     configuration for this purpose.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    Check that you have removed all curly brackets with your replacements.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To establish the connection between the Control Machine and the remote
    machines, generate the SSH key for Ansible.
   </para>
   <para>
    Execute the following command:
   </para>
   <para>
<screen>ssh-keygen -t rsa</screen>
   </para>
   <note>
    <para>
     If you have specified a passphrase for the SSH key, execute any install or
     uninstall command with the <literal>ssh-agent</literal> tool.
    </para>
    <para>
     Make sure to stop the <literal>ssh-agent</literal> tool as soon as the
     installation or uninstallation is successful.
    </para>
   </note>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To copy the SSH key to the remote machines, execute the following command.
    Repeat the command for each remote machine on which to install a software
    component.
   </para>
<screen>ssh-copy-id &lt;user_name&gt;@&lt;host_ip&gt;</screen>
   <para>
    Replace <literal>user_name</literal> by the user name to be used for
    accessing the host, and replace <literal>host_ip</literal> by the IP
    address of the host.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example response for a successful connection to a remote machine:
   </para>
<screen>/usr/bin/ssh-copy-id: INFO: attempting to log in with the new key(s), to filter out any that are already installed
/usr/bin/ssh-copy-id: INFO: 1 key(s) remain to be installed -- if you are prompted now it is to install the new keys
&lt;user_name&gt;@&lt;host_ip&gt;'s password:

Number of key(s) added: 1

Now try logging into the machine, with:   "ssh '&lt;user_name&gt;@&lt;host_ip&gt;'"
and check to make sure that only the key(s) you wanted were added.</screen>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
</section>
