<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<chapter id="idg-overview-log-c-logmanagement-xml-1">
 <title>Log Management</title>
 <para>
  Services and servers in a cloud infrastructure generate huge amounts of log
  data, from simply announcing that everything is healthy to detailed
  information on events or processes. The logs are distributed over many
  physical and virtual servers. <phrase>CMM</phrase> collects, stores, and
  queries these logs and makes them accessible to <phrase>CMM</phrase> users in
  one central place.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> covers all aspects of an enterprise-class log management
  solution:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem id="Central_management_of_log_dat_concept_conbody_section_1_u">
   <para>
    Central management of log data from medium and large-size OpenStack
    deployments.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Buffered exchange of log data to provide high data throughput.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Logical isolation of log data through multi-tenancy.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Scalable architecture capable of mastering the data load from a large
    number of nodes in OpenStack environments. The log management solution can
    be horizontally and vertically adapted to constantly changing data loads.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Basic Usage Scenario</bridgehead>
 <para>
  The basic usage scenario of setting up and using the log management features
  of <phrase>CMM</phrase> looks as follows:
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images-overview-logmgmt.png" depth="298" width="700" align="left"/>
   </imageobject>
   <textobject><phrase>logmanagement.png</phrase>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <para>
  The <emphasis role="bold">Monitoring Service operator</emphasis> is
  responsible for providing the log management features to the OpenStack
  operator. He uses the features himself for retrieving log data on
  <phrase>CMM</phrase>.
 </para>
 <para>
  The <emphasis role="bold">OpenStack operator</emphasis> uses the log
  management features for retrieving log data on the OpenStack services and the
  middleware components that make up the underlying OpenStack platform.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Data Collection</bridgehead>
 <para>
  A Log Agent can be installed and configured on each physical and virtual
  server where log data is to be retrieved. The agent is responsible for
  collecting the log data from the cloud resources and sending them to the
  Monitoring Service for further processing.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> stores the log data in a central database. The central
  database forms the basis for visualizing the log data for the
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> users.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Data Visualization and Analysis</bridgehead>
 <para>
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> supports advanced data visualization and analysis of the
  log data in a variety of charts, tables, or maps. Visualizations can easily
  be combined in dynamic dashboards that display changes to search queries in
  real time.
 </para>
 <para>
  Based on OpenStack Horizon, the customizable dashboards are seamlessly
  integrated into the cloud infrastructure. They enable user access to all log
  management functionality.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Alarms and Notifications</bridgehead>
 <para>
  GUI-based alarm and notification management is also supported for log data.
  <phrase><phrase>CMM</phrase> supports a template mechanism for alarms on log
  data that is not limited to a single cloud resource but can analyze a
  scalable set of resources.</phrase>
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>Alarms and notifications can be configured to inform system operators
  when the number of critical log entries exceeds a defined threshold. Compound
  alarms can be used to analyze more complex log events.</phrase> This
  automation of log handling guarantees that system operators identify problems
  in their infrastructure early and find the root cause of these problems
  quickly.
 </para>
</chapter>
