<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<chapter id="idg-overview-whatiscmm-c-cmm-xml-1">
 <title>What is <phrase>CMM</phrase>?</title>
 <para id="As-more-and-more-applications-concept-conbody-section-p-1">
  As more and more applications are deployed on cloud systems and cloud systems
  are growing in complexity, managing the cloud infrastructure is becoming
  increasingly difficult. <phrase>Cloud Monitoring Manager</phrase>
  (<phrase>CMM</phrase>) helps mastering this challenge by providing a
  sophisticated Monitoring as a Service solution that is operated on top of
  OpenStack-based cloud computing platforms.
 </para>
 <para id="allows-enterprises-to-manage-concept-conbody-section-p-2">
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> allows enterprises to manage, track, and optimize their
  cloud infrastructure and the services they provide to end users. It offers a
  suite of monitoring and analytics tools aimed at improving the health and
  performance of cloud systems.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> assembles and presents metrics and log data in one
  convenient access point. It offers an integrated view of cloud resources,
  based on its seamless integration with OpenStack. While being flexible and
  scalable to instantly reflect changes in the cloud infrastructure of an
  enterprise, <phrase>CMM</phrase> provides the ways and means required to
  ensure multi-tenancy and data security. The high availability architecture of
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> ensures an optimum level of operational performance
  eliminating the risk of component failures and providing for reliable
  crossover.
 </para>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="overview-whatiscmm-c-keyfeatures.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="overview-whatiscmm-c-components.xml"/>
 <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="overview-whatiscmm-c-userroles.xml"/>
</chapter>
