<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<section id="idg-overview-whatiscmm-c-keyfeatures-xml-1">
 <title>Key Features</title>
 <para>
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> is an out-of-the-box solution for monitoring
  OpenStack-based cloud environments. It is provided as a cloud service to
  users. <phrase>CMM</phrase> meets different challenges, ranging from
  small-scale deployments to high-availability deployments and deployments with
  high levels of scalability.
 </para>
 <para>
  The core of <phrase>CMM</phrase> is Monasca, an open source Monitoring as a
  Service solution that integrates with OpenStack. The key features of
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> form an integral part of the Monasca project.
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> extends the source code base of the project through
  active contributions.
 </para>
 <para>
  Compared to the Monasca community edition, <phrase>CMM</phrase> provides the
  following added value:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Packaging as a commercial enterprise solution
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Enterprise-level support
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  The key features of <phrase>CMM</phrase> address public as well as private
  cloud service providers. They include:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Monitoring
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Log management
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Integration with OpenStack
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Monitoring</bridgehead>
 <para>
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> is a highly scalable and fault tolerant monitoring
  solution for OpenStack-based cloud infrastructures.
 </para>
 <para>
  The system operator of the cloud infrastructure and the service providers do
  not have to care for system monitoring software any longer. They use
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> to check whether their services and servers are working
  appropriately.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> provides comprehensive and configurable metrics with
  reasonable defaults for monitoring the status, capacity, throughput, and
  latency of cloud systems. <phrase>CMM</phrase> users can set their own
  warnings and critical thresholds and can combine multiple warnings and
  thresholds to support the processing of complex events. Combined with a
  notification system, these alerting features enable them to quickly analyze
  and resolve problems in the cloud infrastructure.
 </para>
 <para>
  For details, refer to
  <xref linkend="idg-overview-monitor-c-monitoring-xml-1"/>.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Log Management</bridgehead>
 <para>
  With the increasing complexity of cloud infrastructures, it is becoming more
  and more difficult and time-consuming for the system operator to gather,
  store, and query the large amounts of log data manually. To cope with these
  problems, <phrase>CMM</phrase> provides centralized log management features.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> collects log data from all services and servers the
  cloud infrastructure is composed of. The log data from a large number of
  sources can be accessed from a single dashboard. Integrated search, filter,
  and graphics options enable system operators to isolate problems and narrow
  down potential root causes. <phrase>CMM</phrase> thus provides valuable
  insights into the log data, even with large amounts of data resulting from
  highly complex environments.
 </para>
 <para>
  Based on <phrase>CMM</phrase>'s alerting features and notification system,
  users can also configure warnings and critical thresholds for log data. If
  the number of critical log entries reaches a defined threshold, the users
  receive a warning and can instantly analyze their logs and start
  troubleshooting.
 </para>
 <para>
  For details, refer to
  <xref linkend="idg-overview-log-c-logmanagement-xml-1"/>.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Integration with OpenStack </bridgehead>
 <para>
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> is integrated with OpenStack core services. These
  include:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    OpenStack Horizon dashboard for visualizing monitoring metrics and log data
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    OpenStack user management
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    OpenStack security and access control
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</section>
