<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="configobj-clusters" version="5.1">
 <title><!-- Configuration Object - -->
  Clusters</title>
 <informaltable>
  <tgroup cols="2">
   <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
   <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
   <thead>
    <row>
     <entry>Key</entry>
     <entry>Value Description</entry>
    </row>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <row>
     <entry>name</entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Cluster and resource names must be unique within a control plane. This
       value is used to persist server allocations (see
       <xref linkend="persisteddata"/>) and cannot be changed once servers
       have been allocated.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>cluster-prefix (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       The cluster prefix is used in the hostname (see
       <xref linkend="namegeneration"/>). If not supplied then the cluster
       name is used.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>server-role</entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       This can either be a string (for a single role) or a list of roles.
       Only servers matching one of the specified
       <guimenu>server-roles</guimenu> will be allocated to this cluster.
       (see <xref linkend="concept-serverroles"/> for a description of server
       roles)
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>service-components</entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       The list of <guimenu>service-components</guimenu> to be deployed on
       the servers allocated for the cluster. (The common-service-components
       for the control plane are also deployed.)
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>
      <para>
       member-count
      </para>
      <para>
       min-count
      </para>
      <para>
       max-count
      </para>
      <para>
       (all optional)
      </para>
     </entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Defines the number of servers to add to the cluster.
      </para>
      <para>
       The number of servers that can be supported in a cluster depends on the
       services it is running. For example &mariadb; and RabbitMQ can only be
       deployed on clusters on 1 (non-HA) or 3 (HA) servers. Other services may
       support different sizes of cluster.
      </para>
      <para>
       If min-count is specified, then at least that number of servers will be
       allocated to the cluster. If min-count is not specified it defaults to a
       value of 1.
      </para>
      <para>
       If max-count is specified, then the cluster will be limited to that
       number of servers. If max-count is not specified then all servers
       matching the required role and failure-zones will be allocated to the
       cluster.
      </para>
      <para>
       Specifying member-count is equivalent to specifying min-count and
       max-count with the same value.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>failure-zones (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       A list of <guimenu>server-groups</guimenu> that servers will be
       allocated from. If specified, it overrides the list of values
       specified for the control-plane. If not specified, the control-plane
       value is used. (see
       <xref linkend="concept-servergroups-failurezones"/> for a description
       of server groups as failure zones).
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>allocation-policy (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       Defines how failure zones will be used when allocating servers.
      </para>
      <para>
       <emphasis role="bold">strict</emphasis>: Server allocations will be
       distributed across all specified failure zones. (if max-count is not a
       whole number, an exact multiple of the number of zones, then some zones
       may provide one more server than other zones)
      </para>
      <para>
       <emphasis role="bold">any</emphasis>: Server allocations will be made
       from any combination of failure zones.
      </para>
      <para>
       The default allocation-policy for a cluster is
       <emphasis>strict</emphasis>.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>configuration-data (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       A list of configuration-data settings that will be applied to the
       services in this cluster. The values for each service will be combined
       with any values defined as part of the configuration-data list for the
       control-plane. If a value is specified by settings in both lists, the
       value defined here takes precedence.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
   </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </informaltable>
</section>
