<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="topic-r3k-v2c-jt" version="5.1">
 <title>Allocating Proxy, Account, and Container (PAC) Servers for Object Storage</title>
 <para>
  A Swift proxy, account, and container (PAC) server is a node that runs the
  swift-proxy, swift-account and swift-container services. It is used to
  respond to API requests and to store account and container data. The PAC node
  does not store object data.
 </para>
 <para>
  This section describes the procedure to allocate PAC servers during the
  <emphasis role="bold">initial</emphasis> deployment of the system.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>To Allocate Swift PAC servers</title>
  <para>
   Perform the following steps to allocate PAC servers:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Verify if the example input model already contains a suitable server role.
     The server roles are usually described in the
     <literal>data/server_roles.yml</literal> file. If the server role is not
     described, you must add a suitable server role and allocate drives to
     store object data. For instructions, see
     <xref linkend="topic-uh2-td1-kt"/> and
     <xref linkend="allocating-disk-drives"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Verify if the example input model has assigned a cluster to Swift proxy,
     account, container servers. It is usually mentioned in the
     <literal>data/control_plane.yml</literal> file. If the cluster is not
     assigned, then add a suitable cluster. For instructions, see
     <xref linkend="topic-rvj-21c-jt"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Identify the physical servers and their IP address and other detailed
     information.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist xml:id="ul-tzf-pqb-jt">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       You add these details to the servers list (usually in the
       <literal>data/servers.yml</literal> file).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       As with all servers, you must also verify and/or modify the
       server-groups information (usually in
       <literal>data/server_groups.yml</literal>)
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   The only part of this process that is unique to Swift is the allocation of
   disk drives for use by the account and container rings. For instructions,
   see <xref linkend="allocating-disk-drives"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
</section>
