<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="networkroutevalidation" version="5.1">
 <title>Network Route Validation</title>
 <para>
  Once the configuration processor has allocated all of the required
  <guimenu>servers</guimenu> and matched them to the appropriate
  <guimenu>networks</guimenu>, it validates that all
  <guimenu>service-components</guimenu> have the required network routes to
  other <guimenu>service-components</guimenu>.
 </para>
 <para>
  It does this by using the data in the services section of the input model
  which provides details of which <guimenu>service-components</guimenu> need to
  connect to each other. This data is not configurable by the administrator;
  however, it is provided as part of the &productname; release.
 </para>
 <para>
  For each <guimenu>server</guimenu>, the configuration processor looks at the
  list of <guimenu>service-components</guimenu> it runs and determines the
  network addresses of every other <guimenu>service-component</guimenu> it
  needs to connect to (depending on the service, this might be a virtual IP
  address on a load balancer or a set of addresses for the service).
 </para>
 <para>
  If the target address is on a <guimenu>network</guimenu> that this
  <guimenu>server</guimenu> is connected to, then there is no routing required.
  If the target address is on a different <guimenu>network</guimenu>, then the
  Configuration Processor looks at each <guimenu>network</guimenu> the server
  is connected to and looks at the routes defined in the corresponding
  <guimenu>network-group</guimenu>. If the <guimenu>network-group</guimenu>
  provides a route to the <guimenu>network-group</guimenu> of the target
  address, then that route is considered valid.
 </para>
 <para>
  <guimenu>Networks</guimenu> within the same <guimenu>network-group</guimenu>
  are always considered as routed to each other; <guimenu>networks</guimenu>
  from different <guimenu>network-groups</guimenu> must have an explicit entry
  in the <literal>routes</literal> stanza of the
  <guimenu>network-group</guimenu> definition. Routes to a named
  <guimenu>network-group</guimenu> are always considered before a "default"
  route.
 </para>
 <para>
  A warning is given for any routes which are using the "default" route since
  it is possible that the user did not intend to route this traffic. Such
  warning can be removed by adding the appropriate
  <guimenu>network-group</guimenu> to the list of routes.
 </para>
 <para>
  The configuration processor provides details of all routes between networks
  that it is expecting to be configured in the
  <literal>info/route_info.yml</literal> file.
 </para>
 <para>
  To illustrate how network routing is defined in the input model, consider the
  following example:
 </para>
 <para>
  A compute server is configured to run <literal>nova-compute</literal> which requires access to
  the neutron API servers and a block storage service. The neutron API
  servers have a virtual IP address provided by a load balancer in the
  INTERNAL-API network-group and the storage service is connected to the ISCSI
  network-group. <literal>nova-compute</literal> itself is part of the set of components attached
  by default to the MANAGEMENT network-group. The intention is to have virtual
  machines on the compute server connect to the block storage via the ISCSI
  network.
 </para>
 <para>
  The physical network is shown below:
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="media-inputmodel-hphelionopenstack_networkroutevalidation.png"
                    width="75%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="media-inputmodel-hphelionopenstack_networkroutevalidation.png"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <!-- <para>
  <link xlink:href="../../../../media/inputmodel/hphelionopenstack_networkroutevalidation_lg.png">Download
  a high-res version</link>
 </para> -->
 <para>
  The corresponding entries in the <guimenu>network-groups</guimenu> are:
 </para>
<screen>  - name: INTERNAL-API
    hostname-suffix: intapi

    load-balancers:
       - provider: ip-cluster
         name: lb
         components:
           - default
         roles:
           - internal
           - admin

       - name: MANAGEMENT
         hostname-suffix: mgmt
         hostname: true

         component-endpoints:
           - default

         routes:
           - INTERNAL-API
           - default

       - name: ISCSI
         hostname-suffix: iscsi

         component-endpoints:
            - storage service</screen>
 <para>
  And the <guimenu>interface-model</guimenu> for the compute server looks like
  this:
 </para>
<screen>  - name: INTERFACE_SET_COMPUTE
    network-interfaces:
      - name: BOND0
        device:
           name: bond0
        bond-data:
           options:
              mode: active-backup
              miimon: 200
              primary: hed5
           provider: linux
           devices:
              - name: hed4
              - name: hed5
        network-groups:
          - MANAGEMENT
          - ISCSI</screen>
 <para>
  When validating the route from <literal>nova-compute</literal> to the neutron API, the
  configuration processor will detect that the target address is on a network
  in the INTERNAL-API network group, and that the MANAGEMENT network (which is
  connected to the compute server) provides a route to this network, and thus
  considers this route valid.
 </para>
 <para>
  When validating the route from <literal>nova-compute</literal> to a storage service, the
  configuration processor will detect that the target address is on a network
  in the ISCSInetwork group. However, because there is no service component on
  the compute server connected to the ISCSI network (according to the
  network-group definition) the ISCSI network will not have been configured on
  the compute server (see <xref linkend="servernetworkselection"/>. The
  configuration processor will detect that the MANAGEMENT network-group provides
  a "default" route and thus considers the route as valid (it is, of course,
  valid to route ISCSI traffic). However, because this is using the default
  route, a warning will be issued:
 </para>
<screen>#   route-generator-2.0       WRN: Default routing used between networks
The following networks are using a 'default' route rule. To remove this warning
either add an explicit route in the source network group or force the network to
attach in the interface model used by the servers.
  MANAGEMENT-NET-RACK1 to ISCSI-NET
    ardana-ccp-comp0001
  MANAGEMENT-NET-RACK 2 to ISCSI-NET
    ardana-ccp-comp0002
  MANAGEMENT-NET-RACK 3 to SCSI-NET
    ardana-ccp-comp0003</screen>
 <para>
  To remove this warning, you can either add ISCSI to the list of routes in the
  MANAGEMENT network group (routed ISCSI traffic is still a valid
  configuration) or force the compute server to attach to the ISCSI
  network-group by adding it as a forced-network-group in the interface-model,
  like this:
 </para>
<screen>  - name: INTERFACE_SET_COMPUTE
      network-interfaces:
        - name: BOND0
          device:
            name: bond0
          bond-data:
            options:
               mode: active-backup
               miimon: 200
               primary: hed5
            provider: linux
            devices:
               - name: hed4
               - name: hed5
          network-groups:
             - MANAGEMENT
          forced-network-groups:
             - ISCSI</screen>
 <para>
  With the attachment to the ISCSI network group forced, the configuration
  processor will attach the compute server to a network in that group and
  validate the route as either being direct or between networks in the same
  network-group.
 </para>
 <para>
  The generated <literal>route_info.yml</literal> file will include entries
  such as the following, showing the routes that are still expected to be
  configured between networks in the MANAGEMENT network group and the
  INTERNAL-API network group.
 </para>
<screen>  MANAGEMENT-NET-RACK1:
     INTERNAL-API-NET:
        default: false
        used_by:
           nova-compute:
              neutron-server:
              - ardana-ccp-comp0001
   MANAGEMENT-NET-RACK2:
     INTERNAL-API-NET:
        default: false
        used_by:
          nova-compute:
            neutron-server:
            - ardana-ccp-comp0003</screen>
</section>
