<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="deploy-vsa-with-ao-without-ao" version="5.1">
  <title>VSA with or without Adaptive Optimization (AO)</title>
  <para>VSA may be deployed with adaptive optimization (AO) or without AO. AO allows built-in
    storage tiering for VSA. While deploying VSA with or without AO you must ensure to use the
    appropriate disk input model.</para>
  <para>If you are using VSA with AO, you will have an extra device group section where the usage is
    identified as adaptive-optimization as described in the following example: </para>
  <screen>Additional disks can be added if available
          device_groups:
            - name: vsa-data
              consumer:
                name: vsa
                usage: data
              devices:
                - name: /dev/sdc
          - name: /dev/sdd
          - name: /dev/sde
          - name: /dev/sdf
          
            - name: vsa-cache
              consumer:
                name: vsa
                usage: <emphasis role="bold">adaptive-optimization</emphasis>
              devices:
                - name: /dev/sdb</screen>
  <para>VSA without AO consists of only data disks as described in the following example: </para>
  <screen>Additional disks can be added if available
              device_groups:
                - name: vsa-data
                  consumer:
                    name: vsa
                    usage: data
                  devices:
                    - name: /dev/sdc
                    - name: /dev/sdd
                    - name: /dev/sde
                    - name: /dev/sdf</screen>
  <para>It is recommended to use SSD disk for AO. </para>
  <note>
    <para>A single VSA node can have a maximum of seven raw disks (excluding the operating system
      disks) attached to it, which is defined in the disk input model for your VSA nodes. It is
      expected that no more than seven disks are specified (including Adaptive Optimization disks)
      per VSA node. For example, if you want to deploy VSA with two disks for Adaptive Optimization
      then your disk input model should not specify more than five raw disks for data and two raw
      disks for Adaptive Optimization. Exceeding the disk limit causes VSA deployment
      failure.</para>
  </note>

</section>
