<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="rec_min_swift" version="5.1">
 <title>Recommended Hardware Minimums for an Entry-scale Swift Model</title>
 <para>
  These recommended minimums are based on the included
  <xref linkend="example_configurations"/> included with the base installation
  and are suitable only for demo environments. For production systems you will
  want to consider your capacity and performance requirements when making
  decisions about your hardware.
 </para>
 <para>
  The <literal>entry-scale-swift</literal> example runs the Swift proxy,
  account and container services on the three controller servers. However, it
  is possible to extend the model to include the Swift proxy, account and
  container services on dedicated servers (typically referred to as the Swift
  proxy servers). If you are using this model, we have included the recommended
  Swift proxy servers specs in the table below.
 </para>
 <informaltable colsep="1" rowsep="1">
  <tgroup cols="7">
   <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
   <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
   <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
   <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4"/>
   <colspec colname="c5" colnum="5"/>
   <colspec colname="c6" colnum="6"/>
   <colspec colname="c7" colnum="7"/>
<!--<colspec colname="c8" colnum="8"/>-->
   <thead>
    <row>
     <entry morerows="1">Node Type</entry>
     <entry morerows="1">Role Name</entry>
     <entry morerows="1">Required Number</entry>
     <entry namest="c4" nameend="c7" align="center">Server Hardware - Minimum Requirements and
            Recommendations</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>Disk </entry>
     <entry>Memory</entry>
     <entry>Network</entry>
     <entry>CPU </entry>
    </row>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <row>
     <entry>Dedicated &clm; (optional)</entry>
     <entry>Lifecycle-manager</entry>
     <entry>1</entry>
     <entry>300 GB</entry>
     <entry>8 GB</entry>
     <entry>1 x 10 Gbit/s with PXE Support</entry>
     <entry>8 CPU (64-bit) cores total (Intel x86_64)</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>Control Plane</entry>
     <entry>Controller</entry>
     <entry>3</entry>
     <entry>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         1 x 600 GB (minimum) - operating system drive
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         2 x 600 GB (minimum) - Swift account/container data drive
        </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         Fast disks or SSDs are recommended.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </entry>
     <entry>128 GB</entry>
     <entry>2 x 10 Gbit/s with one PXE enabled port</entry>
     <entry>8 CPU (64-bit) cores total (Intel x86_64)</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>Swift Object</entry>
     <entry>swobj</entry>
     <entry>3</entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       If using x3 replication only:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         1 x 600 GB (minimum, see considerations at bottom of page for more
         details)
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
       If using Erasure Codes only or a mix of x3 replication and Erasure
       Codes:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         6 x 600 GB (minimum, see considerations at bottom of page for more
         details)
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </entry>
     <entry>32 GB (see considerations at bottom of page for more details)</entry>
     <entry>2 x 10 Gbit/s with one PXE enabled port</entry>
     <entry>8 CPU (64-bit) cores total (Intel x86_64)</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>Swift Proxy, Account, and Container</entry>
     <entry>swpac</entry>
     <entry>3</entry>
     <entry>2 x 600 GB (minimum, see considerations at bottom of page for more details)</entry>
     <entry>64 GB (see considerations at bottom of page for more details)</entry>
     <entry>2 x 10 Gbit/s with one PXE enabled port</entry>
     <entry>8 CPU (64-bit) cores total (Intel x86_64)</entry>
    </row>
   </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </informaltable>
 <note>
  <para>
   The disk speeds (RPM) chosen should be consistent within the same ring or
   storage policy. It is best to not use disks with mixed disk speeds within the
   same Swift ring.
  </para>
 </note>
 <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Considerations for your Swift object and proxy,
  account, container servers RAM and disk capacity needs</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  Swift can have a diverse number of hardware configurations. For example, a
  Swift object server may have just a few disks (minimum of 6 for erasure
  codes) or up to 70 and beyond. The memory requirement needs to be increased
  as more disks are added. The general rule of thumb for memory needed is 0.5
  GB per TB of storage. For example, a system with 24 hard drives at 8TB each,
  giving a total capacity of 192TB, should use 96GB of RAM. However, this does
  not work well for a system with a small number of small hard drives or a very
  large number of very large drives. So, if after calculating the memory given
  this guideline, if the answer is less than 32GB then go with 32GB of memory
  minimum and if the answer is over 256GB then use 256GB maximum, no need to
  use more memory than that.
 </para>
 <para>
  When considering the capacity needs for the Swift proxy, account, and
  container (PAC) servers, you should calculate 2% of the total raw storage
  size of your object servers to specify the storage required for the PAC
  servers. So, for example, if you were using the example we provided earlier
  and you had an object server setup of 24 hard drives with 8TB each for a
  total of 192TB and you had a total of 6 object servers, that would give a raw
  total of 1152TB. So you would take 2% of that, which is 23TB, and ensure that
  much storage capacity was available on your Swift proxy, account, and
  container (PAC) server cluster. If you had a cluster of three Swift PAC
  servers, that would be ~8TB each.
 </para>
 <para>
  Another general rule of thumb is that if you are expecting to have more than
  a million objects in a container then you should consider using SSDs on the
  Swift PAC servers rather than HDDs.
 </para>
</section>
