<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="concept-serverroles" version="5.1">
 <title>Server Roles</title>
 <para>
  <emphasis><guimenu>Clusters</guimenu> and <guimenu>resources</guimenu> use
  <guimenu>servers</guimenu> with a particular set of
  <guimenu>server-role</guimenu>s.</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  You are going to be running the services on physical
  <guimenu>servers</guimenu>, and you are going to need a way to specify
  which type of servers you want to use where. This is defined via the
  <guimenu>server-role</guimenu>. Each <guimenu>server-role</guimenu> describes
  how to configure the physical aspects of a server to fulfill the needs of a
  particular role. You will generally use a different role whenever the servers
  are physically different (have different disks or network interfaces) or if
  you want to use some specific servers in a particular role (for example to
  choose which of a set of identical servers are to be used in the control
  plane).
 </para>
 <para>
  Each <guimenu>server-role</guimenu> has a relationship to four other
  entities:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>disk-model</guimenu> specifies how to configure and use a
    server's local storage and it specifies disk sizing information for
    virtual machine servers. The disk model is described in the next section.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>interface-model</guimenu> describes how a server's network
    interfaces are to be configured and used. This is covered in more details
    in the networking section.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    An optional <guimenu>memory-model</guimenu> specifies how to configure
    and use huge pages. The memory-model specifies memory sizing information
    for virtual machine servers.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    An optional <emphasis role="bold"> <guimenu>cpu-model</guimenu> </emphasis>
    specifies how the CPUs will be used by nova and by DPDK.
    The cpu-model specifies CPU sizing information for virtual machine
    servers.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</section>
