<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="concept_endpoints" version="5.1">
 <title>Separation of Public, Admin, and Internal Endpoints</title>
 <para>
  The list of endpoint roles for a <guimenu>load-balancer</guimenu> make it
  possible to configure separate <guimenu>load-balancers</guimenu> for public
  and internal access to services, and the configuration processor uses this
  information to both ensure the correct registrations in Keystone and to make
  sure the internal traffic is routed to the correct endpoint. &productname;
  services are configured to only connect to other services via internal
  virtual IP addresses and endpoints, allowing the name and security
  certificate of public endpoints to be controlled by the customer and set to
  values that may not be resolvable/accessible from the servers making up the
  cloud.
 </para>
 <para>
  Note that each <guimenu>load-balancer</guimenu> defined in the input model
  will be allocated a separate virtual IP address even when the load-balancers
  are part of the same <guimenu>network-group</guimenu>. Because of the need to
  be able to separate both public and internal access, &productname; will not allow
  a single <guimenu>load-balancer</guimenu> to provide both public and internal
  access. <guimenu>Load-balancers</guimenu> in this context are logical
  entities (sets of rules to transfer traffic from a virtual IP address to one
  or more endpoints).
  <!-- Multiple <uicontrol>load-balancers</uicontrol> may be implemented by the
  same service within the cloud (e.g. a HA Proxy cluster).-->
 </para>
 <para>
  The following diagram shows a possible configuration in which the hostname
  associated with the public URL has been configured to resolve to a firewall
  controlling external access to the cloud. Within the cloud, &productname; services
  are configured to use the internal URL to access a separate virtual IP
  address.
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="media-inputmodel-hphelionopenstack_loadbalancers.png" width="75%"
          format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="media-inputmodel-hphelionopenstack_loadbalancers.png"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <!--<para>
  <link xlink:href="../../../../media/inputmodel/hphelionopenstack_loadbalancers_lg.png">Download
  a high-res version</link>
 </para>-->
</section>
