<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="concept_networkgroups" version="5.1">
 <title>Network Groups</title>
 <para>
  <emphasis>Service endpoints attach to <guimenu>networks</guimenu> in a
  specific <guimenu>network-group</guimenu>.</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  <emphasis><guimenu>Network-groups</guimenu> can define routes to other
  <guimenu>networks</guimenu>.</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  <emphasis><guimenu>Network-groups</guimenu> encapsulate the configuration for
  <guimenu>services</guimenu> via <guimenu>network-tags</guimenu></emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  A <guimenu>network-group</guimenu> defines the traffic separation model and
  all of the properties that are common to the set of L3 networks that carry
  each type of traffic. They define where services are attached to the network
  model and the routing within that model.
 </para>
 <para>
  In terms of <guimenu>service</guimenu> connectivity, all that has to be
  captured in the <guimenu>network-groups</guimenu> definition are the same
  service-component names that are used when defining
  <guimenu>control-planes</guimenu>. &kw-hos; also allows a default attachment
  to be used to specify "all service-components" that are not explicitly
  connected to another <guimenu>network-group</guimenu>. So, for example, to
  isolate Swift traffic, the swift-account, swift-container, and swift-object
  service components are attached to an "Object"
  <guimenu>network-group</guimenu> and all other services are connected to
  "Management" <guimenu>network-group</guimenu> via the default relationship.
 </para>
 <note>
  <para>
   The name of the "Management" <guimenu>network-group</guimenu> cannot be
   changed. Doing so may cause failures in some situations.
  </para>
 </note>
 <para>
  The details of how each service connects, such as what port it uses, if it
  should be behind a load balancer, if and how it should be registered in
  Keystone, and so forth, are defined in the service definition files provided
  by &kw-hos;.
 </para>
 <para>
  In any configuration with multiple networks, controlling the routing is a
  major consideration. In &kw-hos;, routing is controlled at the
  <guimenu>network-group</guimenu> level. First, all
  <guimenu>networks</guimenu> are configured to provide the route to any other
  <guimenu>networks</guimenu> in the same <guimenu>network-group</guimenu>. In
  addition, a <guimenu>network-group</guimenu> may be configured to provide the
  route any other <guimenu>networks</guimenu> in the same
  <guimenu>network-group</guimenu>; for example, if the internal APIs are in a
  dedicated <guimenu>network-group</guimenu> (a common configuration in a
  complex network because a network group with load balancers cannot be
  segmented) then other <guimenu>network-groups</guimenu> may need to include a
  route to the internal API <guimenu>network-group</guimenu> so that services
  can access the internal API endpoints. Routes may also be required to define
  how to access an external storage network or to define a general default
  route.
 </para>
 <para>
  As part of the &kw-hos; deployment, networks are configured to act as the
  default route for all traffic that was received via that network (so that
  response packets always return via the network the request came from).
 </para>
 <para>
  Note that &kw-hos; will configure the routing rules on the servers it deploys
  and will validate that the routes between services exist in the model, but
  ensuring that gateways can provide the required routes is the responsibility
  of your network configuration. The configuration processor provides
  information about the routes it is expecting to be configured.
 </para>
 <para>
  For a detailed description of how the configuration processor validates
  routes, refer to <xref linkend="networkroutevalidation"/>.
 </para>
 <xi:include href="planning-architecture-input_model-concepts-loadbalancers.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="planning-architecture-input_model-concepts-endpoints.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="planning-architecture-input_model-concepts-networktags.xml"/>
</section>
