<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="register_suse_already_installed"
        version="5.1">
        <title>Registering SUSE Linux from the Installed System</title>

        <section>
                <title>Registering from the Installed System</title>
                <para> If you have skipped the registration during the installation or want to
                        re-register your system, you can register the system at any time using the
                        YaST module <guimenu>Product Registration</guimenu> or the command line tool
                                <guimenu>SUSEConnect</guimenu>. </para>
                <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Registering with YaST</emphasis>
                </para>
                <para> To register the system start <guimenu>YaST -&gt; Software -&gt;
                                Product Registation</guimenu>. Provide the E-mail address associated
                        with the SUSE account you or your organization uses to manage subscriptions.
                        In case you do not have a SUSE account yet, go to the SUSE Customer Center
                        home page (<link xlink:href="https://scc.suse.com/"
                                >https://scc.suse.com/</link>) to create one. </para>
                <para> Enter the Registration Code you received with your copy of SUSE Linux
                        Enterprise Server. Proceed with Next to start the registration process. </para>
                <para> By default the system is registered with the SUSE Customer Center. However,
                        if your organization provides local regsitration servers you can either
                        choose one form the list of auto-detected servers or provide the URl at
                                <guimenu>Register System via local SMT Server</guimenu>. Proceed
                        with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>. </para>
                <para>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Registering with SUSEConnect</emphasis>
                </para>
                <para> To register from the command line, use the command </para>
                <screen>sudo SUSEConnect -r &lt;REGISTRATION_CODE&gt; -e &lt;EMAIL_ADDRESS&gt;</screen>
                <para> Replace &lt;REGISTRATION_CODE&gt; with the Registration Code you
                        received with your copy of SUSE Linux Enterprise Server. Replace
                        &lt;EMAIL_ADDRESS&gt; with the E-mail address associated with the
                        SUSE account you or your organization uses to manage subscriptions. To
                        register with a local registration server, also provide the URL to the
                        server: </para>
                <screen>sudo SUSEConnect -r &lt;REGISTRATION_CODE&gt; -e &lt;EMAIL_ADDRESS&gt; --url "https://suse_register.example.com/"</screen>
        </section>
</section>
