<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="configobj-mtu" version="5.1">
 <title>MTU (Maximum Transmission Unit)</title>
 <para>
  A network group may optionally specify an MTU for its networks to use.
  Because a network-interface in the interface-model may have a mix of one
  untagged-vlan network group and one or more tagged-vlan network groups, there
  are some special requirements when specifying an MTU on a network group.
 </para>
 <para>
  If the network group consists of untagged-vlan network(s) then its specified
  MTU must be greater than or equal to the MTU of any tagged-vlan network
  groups which are co-located on the same network-interface.
 </para>
 <para>
  For example consider a network group with untagged VLANs, NET-GROUP-1, which
  is going to share (via a Network Interface definition) a device (eth0) with
  two network groups with tagged VLANs: NET-GROUP-2 (ID=201, MTU=1550) and
  NET-GROUP-3 (ID=301, MTU=9000).
 </para>
 <para>
  The device (eth0) must have an MTU which is large enough to accommodate the
  VLAN in NET-GROUP-3. Since NET-GROUP-1 has untagged VLANS it will also be
  using this device and so it must also have an MTU of 9000, which results in
  the following configuration.
 </para>
<screen>    +eth0 (9000)   &lt;------ this MTU comes from NET-GROUP-1
    | |
    | |----+ vlan201@eth0 (1550)
    \------+ vlan301@eth0 (9000)</screen>
 <para>
  Where an interface is used only by network groups with tagged VLANs the MTU
  of the device or bond will be set to the highest MTU value in those groups.
 </para>
 <para>
  For example if bond0 is configured to be used by three network groups:
  NET-GROUP-1 (ID=101, MTU=3000), NET-GROUP-2 (ID=201, MTU=1550) and
  NET-GROUP-3 (ID=301, MTU=9000).
 </para>
 <para>
  Then the resulting configuration would be:
 </para>
<screen>    +bond0 (9000)   &lt;------ because of NET-GROUP-3
    | | |
    | | |--+vlan101@bond0 (3000)
    | |----+vlan201@bond0 (1550)
    |------+vlan301@bond0 (9000)</screen>
</section>
