<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="HP3-0HA" version="5.1">
 <title>High Availability</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para>
    This chapter covers High Availability concepts overview and cloud
    infrastructure.
   </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <section xml:id="concepts-overview">
  <title>High Availability Concepts Overview</title>
  <para>
   A highly available (HA) cloud ensures that a minimum level of cloud
   resources are always available on request, which results in uninterrupted
   operations for users.
  </para>
  <para>
   In order to achieve this high availability of infrastructure and workloads,
   we define the scope of HA to be limited to protecting these only against
   single points of failure (SPOF). Single points of failure include:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">Hardware SPOFs</emphasis>: Hardware failures can
     take the form of server failures, memory going bad, power failures,
     hypervisors crashing, hard disks dying, NIC cards breaking, switch ports
     failing, network cables loosening, and so forth.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">Software SPOFs</emphasis>: Server processes can
     crash due to software defects, out-of-memory conditions, operating system
     kernel panic, and so forth.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   By design, &productname; strives to create a system architecture resilient to
   SPOFs, and does not attempt to automatically protect the system against
   multiple cascading levels of failures; such cascading failures will result
   in an unpredictable state. The cloud operator is encouraged to recover and
   restore any failed component as soon as the first level of failure occurs.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="highly-available-cloud-infrastructure">
  <title>Highly Available Cloud Infrastructure</title>
  <para>
   The highly available cloud infrastructure consists of the following:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     High Availability of Controllers
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Availability Zones
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Compute with KVM
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     nova Availability Zones
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Compute with ESX
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Object Storage with swift
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="high-availablity-controllers">
  <title>High Availability of Controllers</title>
  <para>
   The &productname; installer deploys highly available configurations of OpenStack
   cloud services, resilient against single points of failure.
  </para>
  <para>
   The high availability of the controller components comes in two main forms.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Many services are stateless and multiple instances are run across the
     control plane in active-active mode. The API services (nova-api,
     cinder-api, etc.) are accessed through the HA proxy load balancer whereas
     the internal services (nova-scheduler, cinder-scheduler, etc.), are
     accessed through the message broker. These services use the database
     cluster to persist any data.
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      The HA proxy load balancer is also run in active-active mode and
      keepalived (used for Virtual IP (VIP) Management) is run in active-active
      mode, with only one keepalived instance holding the VIP at any one point
      in time.
     </para>
    </note>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The high availability of the message queue service and the database
     service is achieved by running these in a clustered mode across the three
     nodes of the control plane: RabbitMQ cluster with Mirrored Queues and
     &mariadb; Galera cluster.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <figure xml:id="ControlPlane1">
   <title>HA Architecture</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="media-ha30-HPE_HA_Flow.png" width="75%"
                                                format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="media-ha30-HPE_HA_Flow.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   The above diagram illustrates the HA architecture with the focus on VIP
   management and load balancing. It only shows a subset of active-active API
   instances and does not show examples of other services such as
   nova-scheduler, cinder-scheduler, etc.
  </para>
  <para>
   In the above diagram, requests from an OpenStack client to the API services
   are sent to VIP and port combination; for example, 192.0.2.26:8774 for a
   nova request. The load balancer listens for requests on that VIP and port.
   When it receives a request, it selects one of the controller nodes
   configured for handling nova requests, in this particular case, and then
   forwards the request to the IP of the selected controller node on the same
   port.
  </para>
  <para>
   The nova-api service, which is listening for requests on the IP of its host
   machine, then receives the request and deals with it accordingly. The
   database service is also accessed through the load balancer. RabbitMQ, on
   the other hand, is not currently accessed through VIP/HA proxy as the
   clients are configured with the set of nodes in the RabbitMQ cluster and
   failover between cluster nodes is automatically handled by the clients.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="CVR">
  <title>High Availability Routing - Centralized</title>
  <para>
   Incorporating High Availability into a system involves implementing
   redundancies in the component that is being made highly available. In
   Centralized Virtual Router (CVR), that element is the Layer 3 agent (L3
   agent). By making L3 agent highly available, upon failure all HA routers are
   migrated from the primary L3 agent to a secondary L3 agent. The
   implementation efficiency of an HA subsystem is measured by the number of
   packets that are lost when the secondary L3 agent is made the master.
  </para>
  <para>
   In &productname;, the primary and secondary L3 agents run continuously, and
   failover involves a rapid switchover of mastership to the secondary agent
   (IEFT RFC 5798). The failover essentially involves a switchover from an
   already running master to an already running slave. This substantially
   reduces the latency of the HA. The mechanism used by the master and the
   slave to implement a failover is implemented using Linux’s pacemaker HA
   resource manager. This CRM (Cluster resource manager) uses VRRP (Virtual
   Router Redundancy Protocol) to implement the HA mechanism. VRRP is a
   industry standard protocol and defined in RFC 5798.
  </para>
  <figure xml:id="Layer3HA">
   <title>Layer-3 HA</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="media-ha30-HPE_HA_Layer-3HA.png"
                                                width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="media-ha30-HPE_HA_Layer-3HA.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   L3 HA uses of VRRP comes with several benefits.
  </para>
  <para>
   The primary benefit is that the failover mechanism does not involve
   interprocess communication overhead. Such overhead would be in the order of
   10s of seconds. By not using an RPC mechanism to invoke the secondary agent
   to assume the primary agents role enables VRRP to achieve failover within
   1-2 seconds.
  </para>
  <para>
   In VRRP, the primary and secondary routers are all active. As the routers
   are running, it is a matter of making the router aware of its primary/master
   status. This switchover takes less than 2 seconds instead of 60+ seconds it
   would have taken to start a backup router and failover.
  </para>
  <para>
   The failover depends upon a heartbeat link between the primary and
   secondary. That link in &productname; uses keepalived package of the
   pacemaker resource manager. The heartbeats are sent at a 2 second intervals
   between the primary and secondary. As per the VRRP protocol, if the
   secondary does not hear from the master after 3 intervals, it assumes the
   function of the primary.
  </para>
  <para>
   Further, all the routable IP addresses, that is the VIPs (virtual IPs) are
   assigned to the primary agent.
  </para>
<!-- FIXME: <para>For information on more creating HA routers, see:
                   <xref linkend="CreateHARouter"/></para> -->
 </section>

 <section xml:id="availability-zones">
  <title>Availability Zones</title>
  <figure xml:id="DeploymentZones">
   <title>Availability Zones</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="media-ha30-HA_AvailabilityZones_3.png"
                                                width="75%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="media-ha30-HA_AvailabilityZones_3.png"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   While planning your OpenStack deployment, you should decide on how to zone
   various types of nodes - such as compute, block storage, and object storage.
   For example, you may decide to place all servers in the same rack in the
   same zone. For larger deployments, you may plan more elaborate redundancy
   schemes for redundant power, network ISP connection, and even physical
   firewalling between zones (<emphasis>this aspect is outside the scope of
   this document</emphasis>).
  </para>
  <para>
   &productname; offers APIs, CLIs and horizon UIs for the administrator to define
   and user to consume, availability zones for nova, cinder and swift services.
   This section outlines the process to deploy specific types of nodes to
   specific physical servers, and makes a statement of available support for
   these types of availability zones in the current release.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    By default, &productname; is deployed in a single availability zone upon
    installation. Multiple availability zones can be configured by an
    administrator post-install, if required. Refer to <link
    xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/openstack-ansible/rocky/admin/maintenance-tasks.html">OpenStack
    Documentation</link>
   </para>
  </note>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="compute-kvm">
  <title>Compute with KVM</title>
  <para>
   You can deploy your KVM nova-compute nodes either during initial
   installation or by adding compute nodes post initial installation.
  </para>
  <para>
   While adding compute nodes post initial installation, you can specify the
   target physical servers for deploying the compute nodes.
  </para>
  <para>
   Learn more about adding compute nodes in
   <xref linkend="adding-compute-nodes"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="nova-availability-zones">
  <title>nova Availability Zones</title>
  <para>
   nova host aggregates and nova availability zones can be used to segregate
   nova compute nodes across different failure zones.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="compute-esx">
  <title>Compute with ESX Hypervisor</title>
  <para>
   Compute nodes deployed on ESX Hypervisor can be made highly available using
   the HA feature of &vmware; ESX Clusters. For more information on &vmware;
   HA, please refer to your &vmware; ESX documentation.
  </para>
 </section>
<!-- The next two sections are commented out because they mention VSA - dpopov -->
<!-- <section xml:id="block-storage-vsa">
                <title>Block Storage with &storevirtual; VSA</title>
                <para>Highly available cinder block storage volumes are provided by the network RAID
                        10 implementation in the &storevirtual; VSA software. You can deploy the
                        VSA nodes in three node cluster and specify Network RAID 10 protection for
                        cinder volumes.</para>
                <para>The underlying SAN/iQ operating system of the &storevirtual; VSA ensures that
                        the two-way replication maintains two mirrored copies of data for each
                        volume.</para>
                <para>This Network RAID 10 capability ensures that failure of any single server does
                        not cause data loss, and maintains data access to the clients.</para>
                <para>Furthermore, each of the VSA nodes of the cluster can be strategically
                        deployed in different zones of your data center for maximum redundancy and
                        resiliency. For more information on how to deploy VSA nodes on desired
                        target servers, refer to the <xref linkend="config-vsa"/> document.</para>
                <figure xml:id="BlockStorage">
                        <title>SAN/IQ Cluster</title>
                        <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject role="fo">
                                        <imagedata fileref="media-ha30-ha-block-storage.png"
                                                width="75%" format="PNG"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <imageobject role="html">
                                        <imagedata fileref="media-ha30-ha-block-storage.png"/>
                                </imageobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                </figure>
        </section>


        <section xml:id="deploy-vsa-cluster">
                <title>Deploy VSA cluster across Availability Zones/Racks</title>
                <para>In the Availability Zone image above, the input model example has 3 VSA
                        servers in three different server-groups (Racks) (server-groups are are
                        logical separations). You can configure these server-groups in different
                        physical Racks to provide the required hardware isolation. See input model
                        examples for <xref linkend="entry-scale-kvm"/>, <xref
                                linkend="entry-scale-kvm-esx-mml"/>, and <xref
                                linkend="mid-scale-kvm"/></para>
                <para>The recommended configuration for a VSA Cluster is to use RAID 10 with 3
                        mirrors to guarantee that data is replicated across 3 VSA nodes spreading
                        across AZs/Racks. Using one of the two options below, you can expand storage
                        capacity by adding 3 more nodes.</para>
                <procedure>
                        <step>
                                <para>Add new three VSA nodes to the existing cluster and ensure
                                        that each new VSA node is on different AZ/Rack. </para>
                        </step>
                        <step>
                                <para>Create a new VSA cluster with the 3 new nodes.</para>
                        </step>
                </procedure>
                <note>
                        <para>There is a 1500 volumes limit per VSA cluster.</para>
                </note>
        </section> -->
 <section xml:id="cinder-availability-zones">
  <title>cinder Availability Zones</title>
  <para>
   cinder availability zones are not supported for general consumption in the
   current release.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="object-storage-swift">
  <title>Object Storage with swift</title>
  <para>
   High availability in swift is achieved at two levels.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Control Plane</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   The swift API is served by multiple swift proxy nodes. Client requests are
   directed to all swift proxy nodes by the HA Proxy load balancer in
   round-robin fashion. The HA Proxy load balancer regularly checks the node is
   responding, so that if it fails, traffic is directed to the remaining nodes.
   The swift service will continue to operate and respond to client requests as
   long as at least one swift proxy server is running.
  </para>
  <para>
   If a swift proxy node fails in the middle of a transaction, the transaction
   fails. However it is standard practice for swift clients to retry
   operations. This is transparent to applications that use the
   python-swiftclient library.
  </para>
  <para>
   The entry-scale example cloud models contain three swift proxy nodes.
   However, it is possible to add additional clusters with additional swift
   proxy nodes to handle a larger workload or to provide additional resiliency.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Data</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   Multiple replicas of all data is stored. This happens for account, container
   and object data. The example cloud models recommend a replica count of
   three. However, you may change this to a higher value if needed.
  </para>
  <para>
   When swift stores different replicas of the same item on disk, it ensures
   that as far as possible, each replica is stored in a different zone, server
   or drive. This means that if a single server of disk drives fails, there
   should be two copies of the item on other servers or disk drives.
  </para>
  <para>
   If a disk drive is failed, swift will continue to store three replicas. The
   replicas that would normally be stored on the failed drive are “handed
   off” to another drive on the system. When the failed drive is replaced,
   the data on that drive is reconstructed by the replication process. The
   replication process re-creates the <quote>missing</quote> replicas by
   copying them to the drive using one of the other remaining replicas. While
   this is happening, swift can continue to store and retrieve data.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="highly-available-app-workloads">
  <title>Highly Available Cloud Applications and Workloads</title>
  <para>
   Projects writing applications to be deployed in the cloud must be aware of
   the cloud architecture and potential points of failure and architect their
   applications accordingly for high availability.
  </para>
  <para>
   Some guidelines for consideration:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Assume intermittent failures and plan for retries
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis role="bold">OpenStack Service APIs</emphasis>: invocations can
       fail - you should carefully evaluate the response of each invocation,
       and retry in case of failures.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis role="bold">Compute</emphasis>: VMs can die - monitor and
       restart them
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis role="bold">Network</emphasis>: Network calls can fail - retry
       should be successful
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <emphasis role="bold">Storage</emphasis>: Storage connection can hiccup
       - retry should be successful
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Build redundancy into your application tiers
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Replicate VMs containing stateless services such as Web application tier
       or Web service API tier and put them behind load balancers. You must
       implement your own HA Proxy type load balancer in your application VMs.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Boot the replicated VMs into different nova availability zones.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       If your VM stores state information on its local disk (Ephemeral
       Storage), and you cannot afford to lose it, then boot the VM off a
       cinder volume.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Take periodic snapshots of the VM which will back it up to swift through
       glance.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Your data on ephemeral may get corrupted (but not your backup data in
       swift and not your data on cinder volumes).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Take regular snapshots of cinder volumes and also back up cinder volumes
       or your data exports into swift.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Instead of rolling your own highly available stateful services, use
     readily available &productname; platform services such as designate, the DNS
     service.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="what-not-ha">
  <title>What is not Highly Available?</title>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>&clm;</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The &clm; in &productname; is not highly available.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Control Plane</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      High availability (HA) is supported for the Network Service FWaaS. HA is
      <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> supported for VPNaaS.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>nova-consoleauth</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      nova-consoleauth is a singleton service, it can only run on a single node
      at a time. While nova-consoleauth is not high availability, some work has
      been done to provide the ability to switch nova-consoleauth to another
      controller node in case of a failure.
      <!-- FIXME: More Information on troubleshooting nova-consoleauth can be
      found in the <xref linkend="ts-compute"/>. -->
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>cinder Volume and Backup Services</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      cinder Volume and Backup Services are not high availability and started
      on one controller node at a time.
      More information on cinder Volume and Backup Services can
      be found in <xref linkend="sec-operation-manage-block-storage"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>keystone Cron Jobs</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The keystone cron job is a singleton service, which can only run on a
      single node at a time. A manual setup process for this job will be
      required in case of a node failure.
      More information on enabling the cron job for keystone on
      the other nodes can be found in <xref linkend="sec-keystone-cron"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="more-information">
  <title>More Information</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/ha-guide/">OpenStack
     High-availability Guide</link>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <link xlink:href="http://12factor.net/">12-Factor Apps</link>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</chapter>
