<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="servernetworkselection" version="5.1"><title>Server Network Selection</title>
        
        
        

    <para>Once the configuration processor has allocated a <guilabel>server</guilabel> to a
        <guilabel>cluster</guilabel> or <guilabel>resource group</guilabel> it uses the
        information in the associated <guilabel>interface-model</guilabel> to determine which
        <guilabel>networks</guilabel> need to be configured. It does this by:</para>

    <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>Looking at the <guilabel>service-components</guilabel> that are to run on the server
            (from the <guilabel>control-plane</guilabel> definition)</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>Looking to see which <guilabel>network-group</guilabel> each of those components is
            attached to (from the <guilabel>network-groups</guilabel> definition)</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>Looking to see if there are any <guilabel>network-tags</guilabel> related to a
            <guilabel>service-component</guilabel> running on this server, and if so, adding those
            <guilabel>network-groups</guilabel> to the list (also from the
            <guilabel>network-groups</guilabel> definition)</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>Looking to see if there are any <guilabel>network-groups</guilabel> that the
            <guilabel>interface-model</guilabel> says should be forced onto the server</para>
</listitem>
        <listitem><para>It then searches the <guilabel>server-group</guilabel> hierarchy (as described in
            ) to
            find a <guilabel>network</guilabel> in each of the <guilabel>network-groups</guilabel>
            it needs to attach to</para>
</listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>If there is no <guilabel>network</guilabel> available to a server, either because the
        <guilabel>interface-model</guilabel> doesn't include the required
        <guilabel>network-group</guilabel>, or there is no <guilabel>network</guilabel> from
        that group in the appropriate part of the <guilabel>server-groups</guilabel> hierarchy,
        then the configuration processor will generate an error.</para>

    <para>The configuration processor will also generate an error if the
        <guilabel>server</guilabel> address does not match any of the networks it will be
        connected to.</para>



    </section>
