<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="serverallocation" version="5.1">
 <title>Server Allocation</title>
 <para>
  The configuration processor allocates servers to a cluster or resource group
  in the following sequence:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Any <guimenu>servers</guimenu> that are persisted with a state of
    "allocated" are first returned to the <guimenu>cluster</guimenu> or
    <guimenu>resource group</guimenu>. Such servers are always allocated even
    if this contradicts the cluster size, failure-zones, or list of server
    roles since it is assumed that these servers are actively deployed.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    If the <guimenu>cluster</guimenu> or <guimenu>resource group</guimenu> is
    still below its minimum size, then any <guimenu>servers</guimenu> that are
    persisted with a state of "deleted", but where the server is now listed in
    the input model (that is, the server was removed but is now back), are added
    to the group providing they meet the <guimenu>failure-zone</guimenu> and
    <guimenu>server-role</guimenu> criteria. If they do not meet the criteria
    then a warning is given and the <guimenu>server</guimenu> remains in a
    deleted state (that is, it is still not allocated to any other cluster or
    group). These <guimenu>servers</guimenu> are not part of the current
    deployment, and so you must resolve any conflicts before they can be
    redeployed.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    If the <guimenu>cluster</guimenu> or <guimenu>resource group</guimenu> is
    still below its minimum size, the configuration processor will allocate
    additional <guimenu>servers</guimenu> that meet the
    <guimenu>failure-zone</guimenu> and <guimenu>server-role</guimenu>
    criteria. If the allocation policy is set to "strict" then the failure
    zones of servers already in the cluster or resource group are not
    considered until an equal number of servers has been allocated from each
    zone.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
</section>
