<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="entryscale_kvm_dedicated" version="5.1">
    <title>Entry-scale KVM with VSA model with Dedicated Cluster for Metering, Monitoring, and
        Logging</title>




    <para>This model is a variant of the previous Entry-scale KVM with VSA model. It is designed to
        support greater levels of metering, monitoring, and logging.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Metering - All meters required to support charge-back/show-back for core
                Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS) elements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Logging - Run all services at INFO level with the ability to change the settings
                to DEBUG in order to triage specific error conditions. Minimum retention for logs is
                30 days to satisfy audit and compliance requirements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Monitoring - Full performance metrics and health checks for all services.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>In order to provide increased processing power for these services, the following
        configuration changes are made to the control plane in this model:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>All services associated with metering, monitoring, and logging run on a dedicated
                three-node cluster. Three nodes are required for high availability with
                quorum.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>A dedicated three node cluster is used for RabbitMQ message queue and database
                services. This cluster is also used to provide additional processing for the message
                queue and database load associated with the additional metering, monitoring, and
                logging load. Three nodes are required for high availability with quorum.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The main API cluster is reduced to two nodes. These services are stateless and do
                not require a quorum node for high availability.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>This diagram below illustrates the physical networking used in this configuration.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="kvm_with_vsa_dedicated">
        <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="media-entryScaleDed-Entry-ScaleDedicatedAllNetworks.png" width="75%"
                format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="media-entryScaleDed-Entry-ScaleDedicatedAllNetworks.png"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>
        <link xlink:href="../../../media/entryScaleDed/Entry-ScaleDedicatedAllNetworks.png">Download
            the full image</link>
    </para>

    <para>
        <link xlink:href="./../../../media/templates/HOS_Network_Diagram_Template.zip">Download
            Editable Visio Network Diagram Template</link>
    </para>

</section>
