<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="concept-interfacemodel" version="5.1">
 <title>Interface Model</title>
 <para>
  <emphasis>A <guimenu>server-role</guimenu> identifies an
  <guimenu>interface-model</guimenu> that describes how its network interfaces
  are to be configured and used.</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  Network groups are mapped onto specific network interfaces via an
  <guimenu>interface-model</guimenu>, which describes the network devices that
  need to be created (bonds, ovs-bridges, etc.) and their properties.
 </para>
 <para>
  An <guimenu>interface-model</guimenu> acts like a template; it can define how
  some or all of the <guimenu>network-groups</guimenu> are to be mapped for a
  particular combination of physical NICs. However, it is the
  <guimenu>service-components</guimenu> on each server that determine which
  <guimenu>network-groups</guimenu> are required and hence which interfaces and
  <guimenu>networks</guimenu> will be configured. This means that
  <guimenu>interface-models</guimenu> can be shared between different
  <guimenu>server-roles</guimenu>. For example, an API role and a database role
  may share an interface model even though they may have different disk models
  and they will require a different subset of the
  <guimenu>network-groups</guimenu>.
 </para>
 <para>
  Within an <guimenu>interface-model</guimenu>, physical ports are identified
  by a device name, which in turn is resolved to a physical port on a server
  basis via a <guimenu>nic-mapping</guimenu>. To allow different physical
  servers to share an <guimenu>interface-model</guimenu>, the
  <guimenu>nic-mapping</guimenu> is defined as a property of each
  <guimenu>server</guimenu>.
 </para>
 <para>
  The <literal>interface-model</literal> can also used to describe how network
  devices are to be configured for use with DPDK, SR-IOV, and PCI Passthrough.
 </para>
</section>
