<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!---->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="networkroutevalidation"><title>Network Route Validation</title>
        
        


    <para>Once the configuration processor has allocated all of the required
        <guilabel>servers</guilabel> and matched them to the appropriate
        <guilabel>networks</guilabel>, it validates that all
        <guilabel>service-components</guilabel> have the required network routes to other
        <guilabel>service-components</guilabel>.</para>

    <para>It does this by using the data in the services section of the input model which provides
        details of which <guilabel>service-components</guilabel> need to connect to each other.
        This data is not configurable by the administrator; however, it is provided as part of the
        [[[kw-hos]]] release.</para>

    <para>For each <guilabel>server</guilabel>, the configuration processor looks at the list of
        <guilabel>service-components</guilabel> it runs and determines the network addresses of
        every other <guilabel>service-component</guilabel> it needs to connect to (depending on
        the service, this might be a virtual IP address on a load balancer or a set of addresses for
        the service).</para>

    <para>If the target address is on a <guilabel>network</guilabel> that this
        <guilabel>server</guilabel> is connected to, then there is no routing required. If the
        target address is on a different <guilabel>network</guilabel>, then the Configuration
        Processor looks at each <guilabel>network</guilabel> the server is connected to and looks
        at the routes defined in the corresponding <guilabel>network-group</guilabel>. If the
        <guilabel>network-group</guilabel> provides a route to the
        <guilabel>network-group</guilabel> of the target address, then that route is considered
        valid.</para>

    <para><guilabel>Networks</guilabel> within the same <guilabel>network-group</guilabel> are
        always considered as routed to each other; <guilabel>networks</guilabel> from different
        <guilabel>network-groups</guilabel> must have an explicit entry in the
        <literal>routes</literal> stanza of the <guilabel>network-group</guilabel> definition.
        Routes to a named <guilabel>network-group</guilabel> are always considered before a
        "default" route.</para>

    <para>A warning is given for any routes which are using the "default" route since it is possible
        that the user did not intend to route this traffic. Such warning can be removed by adding
        the appropriate <guilabel>network-group</guilabel> to the list of routes.</para>

    <para>The configuration processor provides details of all routes between networks that it is
        expecting to be configured in the <literal>info/route_info.yml</literal> file.</para>

    <para>To illustrate how network routing is defined in the input model, consider the following
        example:</para>

    <para>A compute server is configured to run nova-compute which requires access to the Neutron API
        servers and the VSA block storage service. The Neutron API servers have a virtual IP address
        provided by a load balancer in the INTERNAL-API network-group and the VSA service is
        connected to the ISCSI network-group. Nova-compute itself is part of the set of components
        attached by default to the MANAGEMENT network-group. The intention is to have virtual
        machines on the compute server connect to the VSA storage via the ISCSI network.</para>

    <para>The physical network is shown below:</para>

    <mediaobject><imageobject role="fo"><imagedata fileref="..-media-inputmodel-hphelionopenstack_networkroutevalidation.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/></imageobject><imageobject role="html"><imagedata fileref="..-media-inputmodel-hphelionopenstack_networkroutevalidation.png"/></imageobject></mediaobject>

    <para><link xlink:href="../../../../media/inputmodel/hphelionopenstack_networkroutevalidation_lg.png">Download a high-res version</link></para>

    <para>The corresponding entries in the <guilabel>network-groups</guilabel> are:</para>

        <screen >
  - name: INTERNAL-API  
    hostname-suffix: intapi
        
    load-balancers:
       - provider: ip-cluster
         name: lb
         components:
           - default
         roles:
           - internal
           - admin
        
       - name: MANAGEMENT
         hostname-suffix: mgmt
         hostname: true
        
         component-endpoints:
           - default
        
         routes:
           - INTERNAL-API
           - default
        
       - name: ISCSI
         hostname-suffix: iscsi
         
         component-endpoints:
            - vsa</screen>
    <para>And the <guilabel>interface-model</guilabel> for the compute server looks like this:</para>

        <screen >
  - name: INTERFACE_SET_COMPUTE
    network-interfaces:
      - name: BOND0
        device:
           name: bond0
        bond-data:
           options:
              mode: active-backup
              miimon: 200
              primary: hed5
           provider: linux
           devices:
              - name: hed4
              - name: hed5
        network-groups:
          - MANAGEMENT
          - ISCSI</screen>
    <para>When validating the route from nova-compute to the Neutron API, the configuration processor
        will detect that the target address is on a network in the INTERNAL-API network group, and
        that the MANAGEMENT network (which is connected to the compute server) provides a route to
        this network, and thus considers this route valid.</para>

    <para>When validating the route from nova-compute to VSA, the configuration processor will detect
        that the target address is on a network in the ISCSI network group. However, because there
        is no service component on the compute server connected to the ISCSI network (according to
        the network-group definition) the ISCSI network will not have been configured on the compute
        server (see . The configuration processor will detect that the MANAGEMENT network-group
        provides a "default" route and thus considers the route as valid (it is, of course, valid to
        route ISCSI traffic); however, because this is using the default route, a warning will be
        issued:</para>

        <screen >#   route-generator-2.0       WRN: Default routing used between networks
The following networks are using a 'default' route rule. To remove this warning 
either add an explicit route in the source network group or force the network to 
attach in the interface model used by the servers.
  MANAGEMENT-NET-RACK1 to ISCSI-NET
    helion-ccp-comp0001
  MANAGEMENT-NET-RACK 2 to ISCSI-NET
    helion-ccp-comp0002
  MANAGEMENT-NET-RACK 3 to SCSI-NET
    helion-ccp-comp0003</screen>
    <para>To remove this warning, you can either add ISCSI to the list of routes in the MANAGEMENT
        network group (routed ISCSI traffic is still a valid configuration) or force the compute
        server to attach to the ISCSI network-group by adding it as a forced-network-group in the
        interface-model, like this:</para>

        <screen >
  - name: INTERFACE_SET_COMPUTE
      network-interfaces:
        - name: BOND0
          device:
            name: bond0
          bond-data:
            options:
               mode: active-backup
               miimon: 200
               primary: hed5
            provider: linux
            devices:
               - name: hed4
               - name: hed5
          network-groups:
             - MANAGEMENT
          forced-network-groups:
             - ISCSI</screen>
    <para>With the attachment to the ISCSI network group forced, the configuration processor will
        attach the compute server to a network in that group and validate the route as either being
        direct or between networks in the same network-group.</para>

    <para>The generated <literal>route_info.yml</literal> file will include entries such as the
        following, showing the routes that are still expected to be configured between networks in
        the MANAGEMENT network group and the INTERNAL-API network group.</para>

        <screen >
  MANAGEMENT-NET-RACK1:
     INTERNAL-API-NET:
        default: false
        used_by:
           nova-compute:
              neutron-server:
              - helion-ccp-comp0001
   MANAGEMENT-NET-RACK2:
     INTERNAL-API-NET:
        default: false
        used_by:
          nova-compute:
            neutron-server:
            - helion-ccp-comp0003</screen>


    </section>
