<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="configobj_diskmodels" version="5.1">
 <title><!-- Configuration Object - -->
  Disk Models</title>
 <para>
  The disk-models configuration object is used to specify how the directly
  attached disks on the server should be configured. It can also identify which
  service or service component consumes the disk, for example, Swift object
  server, and provide service-specific information associated with the disk.
  It is also used to specify disk sizing information for virtual machine
  servers.
 </para>
 <para>
  Disks can be used as raw devices or as logical volumes and the disk model
  provides a configuration item for each.
 </para>
 <para>
  If the operating system has been installed by the &productname; installation
  process then the root disk will already have been set up as a volume-group
  with a single logical-volume. This logical-volume will have been created on a
  partition identified, symbolically, in the configuration files as
  <filename>/dev/sda_root</filename>. This is due to the fact that different
  BIOS systems (UEFI, Legacy) will result in different partition numbers on the
  root disk.
 </para>
<screen>---
  product:
     version: 2

  disk-models:
  - name: SES-DISKS

    volume-groups:
       - ...
    device-groups:
       - ...
    vm-size:
       ...</screen>
 <informaltable>
  <tgroup cols="2">
   <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
   <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
   <thead>
    <row>
     <entry>Key</entry>
     <entry>Value Description</entry>
    </row>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <row>
     <entry>name</entry>
     <entry>
      The name of the disk-model that is referenced from one or more
      server-roles.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>volume-groups</entry>
     <entry>
      A list of volume-groups to be configured (see below). There must be at
      least one volume-group describing the root file system.
      <!-- FIXME: xref add instead of this vague "below"? - sknorr, 2018-03-01 -->
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>device-groups (optional)</entry>
     <entry>A list of device-groups (see below)</entry>
     <!-- FIXME: xref add instead of this vague "below"? - sknorr, 2018-03-01 -->
    </row>
   </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </informaltable>
 <xi:include href="planning-architecture-input_model-configobj-volumegroups.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="planning-architecture-input_model-configobj-devicegroups.xml"/>
</section>
