<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="configobj_load_balancers" version="5.1">
 <title>Load Balancers</title>
 <para>
  Load balancers may be defined as part of a network-group object, or as part
  of a control-plane object. When a load-balancer is defined in a
  control-plane, it must be referenced by name only from the associated
  network-group object.
 </para>
 <para>
  For clouds consisting of multiple control planes, load balancers must be
  defined as part of a control-plane object. This allows different load
  balancer configurations for each control plane.
 </para>
 <para>
  In either case, a load-balancer definition has the following attributes:
 </para>
<screen>load-balancers:
        - provider: ip-cluster
          name: extlb
          external-name:

          tls-components:
            - default
          roles:
            - public
          cert-file: cp1-extlb-cert</screen>
 <informaltable>
  <tgroup cols="2">
   <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
   <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
   <thead>
    <row>
     <entry>Key</entry>
     <entry>Value Description</entry>
    </row>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <row>
     <entry>name</entry>
     <entry>
      An administrator defined name for the load balancer. This name is used
      to make the association from a network-group.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>provider</entry>
     <entry>
      The service component that implements the load balancer. Currently only
      <literal>ip-cluster</literal> (ha-proxy) is supported. Future releases
      will provide support for external load balancers.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>roles</entry>
     <entry>
      The list of endpoint roles that this load balancer provides (see
      below). <!-- FIXME: xref instead of vague "below"? -->
      Valid roles are
      <literal>public</literal>, <literal>internal</literal>, and
      <literal>admin</literal>. To ensure separation of concerns, the role
      <literal>public</literal> cannot be combined with any other role. See
      Load Balancers for an example of how the role provides endpoint
      separation.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>components (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      The list of service-components for which the load balancer provides a
      non-encrypted virtual IP address for.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>tls-components (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      The list of service-components for which the load balancer provides
      TLS-terminated virtual IP addresses for.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>external-name (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      The name to be registered in Keystone for the publicURL. If not
      specified, the virtual IP address will be registered. Note that this
      value cannot be changed after the initial deployment.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>cert-file (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      The name of the certificate file to be used for tls endpoints. If not
      specified, a file name will be constructed using the format
      <literal><replaceable>CP-NAME</replaceable>-<replaceable>LB-NAME</replaceable>-cert</literal>,
      where <literal><replaceable>CP-NAME</replaceable></literal> is the
      control-plane name and
      <literal><replaceable>LB-NAME</replaceable></literal> is the
      load-balancer name.
     </entry>
    </row>
   </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </informaltable>
</section>
