<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="topic-tq1-xt5-dt" version="5.1">
 <title>Allocating Object Servers</title>
 <para>
  A swift object server is a node that runs the swift-object service
  (<emphasis role="bold">only</emphasis>) and is used to store object
  data. It does not run the swift-proxy, swift-account, or swift-container
  services.
  <!--The swift object server type is used to store object data.-->
 </para>
 <para>
  This section describes the procedure to allocate a swift object server during
  the <emphasis role="bold">initial</emphasis> deployment of the system.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="procedure">
  <title>To Allocate a swift Object Server</title>
  <para>
   Perform the following steps to allocate one or more swift object servers:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist xml:id="ul-fbk-fj3-kt">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Verify if the example input model already contains a suitable server role.
     The server roles are usually described in the
     <literal>data/server_roles.yml</literal> file. If the server role is not
     described, you must add a suitable server role. For instructions, see
     <xref linkend="topic-uh2-td1-kt"/>. While adding a server role for the
     swift object server, you will also allocate drives to store object data.
     For instructions, see <xref linkend="allocating-disk-drives"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Verify if the example input model has a resource node assigned to swift
     object servers. The resource nodes are usually assigned in the
     <literal>data/control_plane.yml</literal> file. If it is not assigned, you
     must add a suitable resource node. For instructions, see
     <xref linkend="topic-jzk-q1c-jt"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Identify the physical servers and their IP address and other detailed
     information. Add the details for the servers in either of the following
     YAML files and verify the server-groups information:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist xml:id="ul-gmj-ng3-kt">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Add details in the servers list (usually in the
       <literal>data/servers.yml</literal> file).
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       As with all servers, you must also verify and/or modify the
       server-groups information (usually in the
       <literal>data/server_groups.yml</literal> file).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     The only part of this process that is unique to swift is the allocation of
     disk drives for use by the object ring. For instructions, see
     <xref linkend="allocating-disk-drives" />.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</section>
