<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="concept-diskmodel" version="5.1">
 <title>Disk Model</title>
 <para>
  <emphasis>Each physical disk device is associated with a
  <guimenu>device-group</guimenu> or a
  <guimenu>volume-group</guimenu>.</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  <emphasis><guimenu>Device-groups</guimenu> are consumed by
  <guimenu>services</guimenu>.</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  <emphasis><guimenu>Volume-groups</guimenu> are divided into
  <guimenu>logical-volumes</guimenu>.</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  <emphasis><guimenu>Logical-volumes</guimenu> are mounted as file systems or
  consumed by services.</emphasis>
 </para>
 <para>
  Disk-models define how local storage is to be configured and presented to
  <guimenu>services</guimenu>. Disk-models are identified by a name, which you
  will specify. The &productname; examples provide some typical configurations. As
  this is an area that varies with respect to the services that are hosted on a
  server and the number of disks available, it is impossible to cover all
  possible permutations you may need to express via modifications to the
  examples.
 </para>
 <para>
  Within a <guimenu>disk-model</guimenu>, disk devices are assigned to either a
  <guimenu>device-group</guimenu> or a <guimenu>volume-group</guimenu>.
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="media-inputmodel-hphelionopenstack_diskmodels.png" width="75%"
                    format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="media-inputmodel-hphelionopenstack_diskmodels.png"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <!--<para>
  <link xlink:href="../../../../media/inputmodel/hphelionopenstack_diskmodels_lg.png">Download
  a high-res version</link>
 </para>-->
 <para>
  A <guimenu>device-group</guimenu> is a set of one or more disks that are to
  be consumed directly by a service. For example, a set of disks to be used by
  Swift. The device-group identifies the list of disk devices, the service, and
  a few service-specific attributes that tell the service about the intended
  use (for example, in the case of Swift this is the ring names). When a device
  is assigned to a device-group, the associated service is responsible for the
  management of the disks. This management includes the creation and mounting
  of file systems. (Swift can provide additional data integrity when it has
  full control over the file systems and mount points.)
 </para>
 <para>
  A <guimenu>volume-group</guimenu> is used to present disk devices in a LVM
  volume group. It also contains details of the logical volumes to be created
  including the file system type and mount point. Logical volume sizes are
  expressed as a percentage of the total capacity of the volume group. A
  <guimenu>logical-volume</guimenu> can also be consumed by a service in the
  same way as a <guimenu>device-group</guimenu>. This allows services to manage
  their own devices on configurations that have limited numbers of disk drives.
 </para>
 <para>
  Disk models also provide disk sizing information for virtual machine servers.
 </para>
</section>
