<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="concept_loadbalancers" version="5.1">
 <title>Load Balancers</title>
 <para>
  <guimenu>Load-balancers</guimenu> provide a specific type of routing and are
  defined
<!--in <uicontrol>network-groups</uicontrol> -->
  as a relationship between the virtual IP address (VIP) on a network in one
  <guimenu>network group</guimenu> and a set of service endpoints (which may be
  on <guimenu>networks</guimenu> in the same or a different
  <guimenu>network-group</guimenu>).
 </para>
 <para>
  As each <guimenu>load-balancer</guimenu> is defined providing a virtual IP on
  a <guimenu>network-group</guimenu>, it follows that those
  <guimenu>network-group</guimenu>s
  <!--containing a <uicontrol>load-balancer</uicontrol>-->
  can each only have one <guimenu>network</guimenu> associated to them.
 </para>
 <para>
  The <guimenu>load-balancer</guimenu> definition includes a list of
  <guimenu>service-components</guimenu> and endpoint roles it will provide a
  virtual IP for. This model allows service-specific
  <guimenu>load-balancers</guimenu> to be defined on different
  <guimenu>network-groups</guimenu>. A "default" value is used to express "all
  service-components" which require a virtual IP address and are not explicitly
  configured in another <guimenu>load-balancer</guimenu> configuration. The
  details of how the <guimenu>load-balancer</guimenu> should be configured for
  each service, such as which ports to use, how to check for service liveness,
  etc., are provided in the &productname; supplied service definition files.
 </para>
 <para>
  Where there are multiple instances of a service (for example, in a cloud with multiple
  control-planes), each control-plane needs its own set of virtual IP address
  and different values for some properties such as the external name and
  security certificate. To accommodate this in &product;, load-balancers
  are defined as part of the control-plane, with the network groups defining
  just which load-balancers are attached to them.
 </para>
 <para>
  Load balancers are always implemented by an ha-proxy service in the same
  control-plane as the services.
 </para>
</section>
