<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="concept_networking" version="5.1">
 <title>Networking</title>
 <para>
  In addition to the mapping of <guimenu>services</guimenu> to specific
  <guimenu>clusters</guimenu> and <guimenu>resources</guimenu> we must also be
  able to define how the <guimenu>services</guimenu> connect to one or more
  <guimenu>networks</guimenu>.
 </para>
 <para>
  In a simple cloud there may be a single L3 network but more typically there
  are functional and physical layers of network separation that need to be
  expressed.
 </para>
 <para>
  Functional network separation provides different networks for different types
  of traffic; for example, it is common practice in even small clouds to
  separate the External APIs that users will use to access the cloud and the
  external IP addresses that users will use to access their virtual machines.
  In more complex clouds it is common to also separate out virtual networking
  between virtual machines, block storage traffic, and volume traffic onto
  their own sets of networks. In the input model, this level of separation is
  represented by <guimenu>network-groups</guimenu>.
 </para>
 <para>
  Physical separation is required when there are separate L3 network segments
  providing the same type of traffic; for example, where each rack uses a
  different subnet. This level of separation is represented in the input model
  by the <guimenu>networks</guimenu> within each
  <guimenu>network-group</guimenu>.
 </para>
 <xi:include href="planning-architecture-input_model-concepts-networkgroups.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="planning-architecture-input_model-concepts-networks.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="planning-architecture-input_model-concepts-interfacemodel.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="planning-architecture-input_model-concepts-nicmapping.xml"/>
 <xi:include href="planning-architecture-input_model-concepts-firewallconfiguration.xml"/>
</section>
