<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="concept-virtual-machines-as-servers"
        version="5.1">
 <title>Virtual Machines as Servers</title>
 <para>
  Starting in &product;, servers can be configured as hypervisors which
  host virtual machines that are can be defined, instantiated and configured as
  servers for hosting &productname; services. Both the hypervisors and the VMs are
  treated as <quote>servers</quote> within the input model with additional
  attributes to define the relationship.
 </para>
 <para>
  To define a hypervisor in the input model:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Set the attribute <literal>ardana-hypervisor: true</literal> for the
    server.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Define how network groups that are needed by the VMs will be mapped to the
    hypervisor's interfaces by adding
    <literal>passthrough-network-groups</literal> to the interface model of the
    hypervisor.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  To define a virtual machine server in the input model:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Create a server object that includes the <literal>hypervisor-id</literal>
    attribute. This indicates that the server is a virtual machine, and also
    identifies the physical server that will host the VM.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Specify virtual machine CPU sizing information in the server's CPU model.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Specify virtual machine memory sizing information in the server's memory
    model.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Specify virtual machine disk sizing information in the server's disk model.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Specify the virtual machine's network devices in the server's nic-mappings
    object.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  Given the above information, &productname; will configure the hypervisors and
  create the virtual machines running the &slsa; operating system. Subsequent
  configuration of the virtual machine's operating system, and installation and
  configuration of &productname; services on that virtual machine server, use the
  same lifecycle management mechanisms as physical servers.
 </para>
 <para>
  Note that a hypervisor can still be used to run &productname; services, so for
  example a server can be both running VMs (that in turn are running API
  services, &mariadb;, etc) and also be running services that are better not
  virtualized such as swift.
 </para>
</section>
