<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="configobj_servers" version="5.1">
 <title>Servers</title>
 <para>
  The <guimenu>servers</guimenu> configuration object is used to list the
  available servers for deploying the cloud.
 </para>
 <para>
  Optionally, it can be used as an input file to the operating system
  installation process, in which case some additional fields (identified below)
  will be necessary.
 </para>
<screen>---
  product:
    version: 2

  baremetal:
    subnet: 192.168.10.0
    netmask: 255.255.255.0

  servers:
    - id: controller1
      ip-addr: 192.168.10.3
      role: CONTROLLER-ROLE
      server-group: RACK1
      nic-mapping: HP-DL360-4PORT
      mac-addr: b2:72:8d:ac:7c:6f
      ilo-ip: 192.168.9.3
      ilo-password: password
      ilo-user: admin

    - id: controller2
      ip-addr: 192.168.10.4
      role: CONTROLLER-ROLE
      server-group: RACK2
      nic-mapping: HP-DL360-4PORT
      mac-addr: 8a:8e:64:55:43:76
      ilo-ip: 192.168.9.4
      ilo-password: password
      ilo-user: admin</screen>
 <informaltable>
  <tgroup cols="2">
   <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="5*"/>
   <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="25*"/>
   <thead>
    <row>
     <entry>Key</entry>
     <entry>Value Description</entry>
    </row>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <row>
     <entry>id</entry>
     <entry>
      An administrator-defined identifier for the server. IDs must be unique
      and are used to track server allocations. (see
      <xref linkend="persisteddata"/>).
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>ip-addr</entry>
     <entry>
      <para>
       The IP address is used by the configuration processor to install and
       configure the service components on this server.
      </para>
      <para>
       This IP address must be within the range of a <guimenu>network</guimenu>
       defined in this model.
      </para>
      <para>
       When the servers file is being used for operating system installation,
       this IP address will be assigned to the node by the installation
       process, and the associated <guimenu>network</guimenu> must be an
       untagged VLAN.
      </para>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>hostname (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      The value to use for the hostname of the server. If specified this will
      be used to set the hostname value of the server which will in turn be
      reflected in systems such as Nova, Monasca, etc. If not specified the
      hostname will be derived based on where the server is used and the
      network defined to provide hostnames.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>role</entry>
     <entry>
      Identifies the <guimenu>server-role</guimenu> of the server.
      <!-- FIXME: xref missing (see for a description of server roles) -->
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>nic-mapping</entry>
     <entry>
      Name of the <guimenu>nic-mappings</guimenu> entry to apply to this
      server. (See <xref linkend="configobj_nicmappings"/>.)
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>server-group (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      Identifies the <guimenu>server-groups</guimenu> entry that this server
      belongs to. (see <xref linkend="concept_servergroups"/>)
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>boot-from-san (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      Must be set to true is the server needs to be configured to boot from
      SAN storage. Default is False
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>fcoe-interfaces (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      A list of network devices that will be used for accessing FCoE storage.
      This is only needed for devices that present as native FCoE, not
      devices such as Emulex which present as a FC device.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>ansible-options (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      A string of additional variables to be set when defining the server as
      a host in Ansible. For example, <literal>ansible_ssh_port=5986</literal>
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>mac-addr (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      Needed when the servers file is being used for operating system
      installation. This identifies the MAC address on the server that will
      be used to network install the operating system.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>kopt-extras (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      Provides additional command line arguments to be passed to the booting
      network kernel. For example, <literal>vga=769</literal> sets the video
      mode for the install to low resolution which can be useful for remote
      console users.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>ilo-ip (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      Needed when the servers file is being used for operating system
      installation. This provides the IP address of the power management
      (for example, IPMI, iLO) subsystem.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>ilo-user (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      Needed when the servers file is being used for operating system
      installation. This provides the user name of the power management (for
      example, IPMI, iLO) subsystem.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>ilo-password (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      Needed when the servers file is being used for operating system
      installation. This provides the user password of the power management
      (for example, IPMI, iLO) subsystem.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>ilo-extras (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      Needed when the servers file is being used for operating system
      installation. Additional options to pass to ipmitool. For example, this
      may be required if the servers require additional IPMI addressing
      parameters.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>moonshot (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      Provides the node identifier for HPE Moonshot servers, for example,
      <literal>c4n1</literal> where c4 is the cartridge and n1 is node.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>hypervisor-id (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      This attribute serves two purposes: it indicates that this server is a
      virtual machine (VM), and it specifies the server id of the &clm;
      hypervisor that will host the VM.
     </entry>
    </row>
    <row>
     <entry>ardana-hypervisor (optional)</entry>
     <entry>
      When set to True, this attribute identifies a server as a &clm;
      hypervisor. A &clm; hypervisor is a server that may be used to host
      other servers that are themselves virtual machines. Default value is
      <literal>False</literal>.
     </entry>
    </row>
   </tbody>
  </tgroup>
 </informaltable>
 <important vendor="hpe">
  <para>
   &rhla; is only supported for KVM compute hosts. Note that you need to add a
   <literal>-multipath</literal> suffix to the distro-id value when using
   multipath with &rhla;.
  </para>
 </important>
</section>
