<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="persisteddata" version="5.1">
 <title>Persisted Data</title>
 <para>
  The configuration processor makes allocation decisions on servers and IP
  addresses which it needs to remember between successive runs so that if new
  servers are added to the input model they do not disrupt the previously
  deployed allocations.
 </para>
 <para>
  To allow users to make multiple iterations of the input model before
  deployment &kw-hos; will only persist data when the administrator confirms
  that they are about to deploy the results via the "ready-deployment"
  operation. To understand this better, consider the following example:
 </para>
 <para>
  Imagine you have completed your &kw-hos; deployment with servers A, B, and C
  and you want to add two new compute nodes by adding servers D and E to the
  input model.
 </para>
 <para>
  When you add these to the input model and re-run the configuration processor
  it will read the persisted data for A, B, and C and allocate D and E as new
  servers. The configuration processor now has allocation data for A, B, C, D,
  and E -- which it keeps in a staging area (actually a special branch in Git)
  until we get confirmation that the configuration processor has done what you
  intended and you are ready to deploy the revised configuration.
 </para>
 <para>
  If you notice that the role of E is wrong and it became a Swift node instead
  of a Nova node you need to be able to change the input model and re-run the
  configuration processor. This is fine because the allocations of D and E have
  not been confirmed, and so the configuration processor will re-read the data
  about A, B, C and re-allocate D and E now to the correct clusters, updating
  the persisted data in the staging area.
 </para>
 <para>
  You can loop though this as many times as needed. Each time, the
  configuration processor is processing the deltas to what is deployed, not the
  results of the previous run. When you are ready to use the results of the
  configuration processor, you run <literal>ready-deployment.yml</literal>
  which commits the data in the staging area into the persisted data. The next
  run of the configuration processor will then start from the persisted data
  for A, B, C, D, and E.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="persistedserverallocations">
  <title>Persisted Server Allocations</title>
  <para>
   Server allocations are persisted by the administrator-defined server ID (see
   <xref linkend="configobj-servers"/>), and include the
   control plane, cluster/resource name, and ordinal within the cluster or
   resource group.
  </para>
  <para>
   To guard against data loss, the configuration processor persists server
   allocations even when the server ID no longer exists in the input model --
   for example, if a server was removed accidentally and the configuration
   processor allocated a new server to the same ordinal, then it would be very
   difficult to recover from that situation.
  </para>
  <para>
   The following example illustrates the behavior:
  </para>
  <para>
   A cloud is deployed with four servers with IDs of A, B, C, and D that can
   all be used in a resource group with <literal>min-size=0</literal> and
   <literal>max-size=3</literal>. At the end of this deployment they persisted
   state is as follows:
  </para>
  <informaltable>
   <tgroup cols="6">
    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
    <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
    <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4"/>
    <colspec colname="c5" colnum="5"/>
    <colspec colname="c6" colnum="6"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>ID</entry>
      <entry>Control Plane</entry>
      <entry>Resource Group</entry>
      <entry>Ordinal</entry>
      <entry>State</entry>
      <entry>Deployed As</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>A</entry>
      <entry>ccp</entry>
      <entry>compute</entry>
      <entry>1</entry>
      <entry>Allocated</entry>
      <entry>mycloud-ccp-comp0001</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>B</entry>
      <entry>ccp</entry>
      <entry>compute</entry>
      <entry>2</entry>
      <entry>Allocated</entry>
      <entry>mycloud-ccp-comp0002</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>C</entry>
      <entry>ccp</entry>
      <entry>compute</entry>
      <entry>3</entry>
      <entry>Allocated</entry>
      <entry>mycloud-ccp-comp0003</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>D</entry>
      <entry/>
      <entry/>
      <entry/>
      <entry>Available</entry>
      <entry/>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
  <para>
   (In this example server D has not been allocated because the group is at its
   max size, and there are no other groups that required this server)
  </para>
  <para>
   If server B is removed from the input model and the configuration processor
   is re-run, the state is changed to:
  </para>
  <informaltable>
   <tgroup cols="6">
    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
    <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
    <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4"/>
    <colspec colname="c5" colnum="5"/>
    <colspec colname="c6" colnum="6"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>ID</entry>
      <entry>Control Plane</entry>
      <entry>Resource Group</entry>
      <entry>Ordinal</entry>
      <entry>State</entry>
      <entry>Deployed As</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>A</entry>
      <entry>ccp</entry>
      <entry>compute</entry>
      <entry>1</entry>
      <entry>Allocated</entry>
      <entry>mycloud-ccp-comp0001</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>B</entry>
      <entry>ccp</entry>
      <entry>compute</entry>
      <entry>2</entry>
      <entry>Deleted</entry>
      <entry/>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>C</entry>
      <entry>ccp</entry>
      <entry>compute</entry>
      <entry>3</entry>
      <entry>Allocated</entry>
      <entry>mycloud-ccp-comp0003</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>D</entry>
      <entry>ccp</entry>
      <entry>compute</entry>
      <entry>4</entry>
      <entry>Allocated</entry>
      <entry>mycloud-ccp-comp0004</entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
  <para>
   The details associated with server B are still retained, but the
   configuration processor will not generate any deployment data for this
   server. Server D has been added to the group to meet the minimum size
   requirement but has been given a different ordinal and hence will get
   different names and IP addresses than were given to server B.
  </para>
  <para>
   If server B is added back into the input model the resulting state will be:
  </para>
  <informaltable>
   <tgroup cols="6">
    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
    <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
    <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4"/>
    <colspec colname="c5" colnum="5"/>
    <colspec colname="c6" colnum="6"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>ID</entry>
      <entry>Control Plane</entry>
      <entry>Resource Group</entry>
      <entry>Ordinal</entry>
      <entry>State</entry>
      <entry>Deployed As</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>A</entry>
      <entry>ccp</entry>
      <entry>compute</entry>
      <entry>1</entry>
      <entry>Allocated</entry>
      <entry>mycloud-ccp-comp0001</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>B</entry>
      <entry>ccp</entry>
      <entry>compute</entry>
      <entry>2</entry>
      <entry>Deleted</entry>
      <entry/>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>C</entry>
      <entry>ccp</entry>
      <entry>compute</entry>
      <entry>3</entry>
      <entry>Allocated</entry>
      <entry>mycloud-ccp-comp0003</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>D</entry>
      <entry>ccp</entry>
      <entry>compute</entry>
      <entry>4</entry>
      <entry>Allocated</entry>
      <entry>mycloud-ccp-comp0004</entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
  <para>
   The configuration processor will issue a warning that server B cannot be
   returned to the compute group because it would exceed the max-size
   constraint. However, because the configuration processor knows that server B
   is associated with this group it will not allocate it to any other group that
   could use it, since that might lead to data loss on that server.
  </para>
  <para>
   If the max-size value of the group was increased, then server B would be
   allocated back to the group, with its previous name and addresses
   (<literal>mycloud-cp1-compute0002</literal>).
  </para>
  <para>
   Note that the configuration processor relies on the server ID to identify a
   physical server. If the ID value of a server is changed the configuration
   processor will treat it as a new server. Conversely, if a different physical
   server is added with the same ID as a deleted server the configuration
   processor will assume that it is the original server being returned to the
   model.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can force the removal of persisted data for servers that are no longer
   in the input model by running the configuration processor with the
   <literal>remove_deleted_servers</literal> option, like below:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml \
-e remove_deleted_servers="y"</screen>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="persistedaddressallocations">
  <title>Persisted Address Allocations</title>
  <para>
   The configuration processor persists IP address allocations by the generated
   name (see <xref linkend="namegeneration"/> for how names are generated). As
   with servers. once an address has been allocated that address will remain
   allocated until the configuration processor is explicitly told that it is no
   longer required. The configuration processor will generate warnings for
   addresses that are persisted but no longer used.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can remove persisted address allocations that are no longer used in the
   input model by running the configuration processor with the
   <literal>free_unused_addresses</literal> option, like below:
  </para>
<screen>&prompt.ardana;cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
&prompt.ardana;ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml \
-e free_unused_addresses="y"</screen>
 </section>
</section>
