<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="poc-overview">
 <title>Overview</title>
<para> OpenStack is a cloud operating system that controls large pools of compute,
 storage, and networking resources throughout a data center, all managed
 through a dashboard that gives administrators control while empowering
 their users to provision resources through a web interface.
 </para>
 <para>&productname; provides easy to use installation and management workflows
 for OpenStack cloud. It allows an entire OpenStack cloud environment to be modelled
 before deployment, and it deploys and updates the OpenStack cloud environment to
 match the models even as the models are updated.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="about-this-guide">
   <title>About this guide</title>
   <para>
     The following guide is what is known as a Proof of Concept (POC) Guide.
     A POC focuses on whether a test case can be turned into production-grade
     implementation. The details within this guide are generic, and are only
     meant to determine the feasibility of the idea or test case.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="poc-requirements">
    <title>Skill requirements</title>
   <para>
     Before you begin working through this guide, it is important to
     understand your individual use case for your OpenStack deployment.
     We recommend reading this guide with the following questions in mind:
     </para>
     <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           What problem am I trying to solve?
         </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           How does this solve my problem?
         </para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
         <para>
           How do I want to implement my SUSE OpenStack Cloud?
         </para>
       </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
     <para>
       OpenStack is comprised of numerous projects that develop the services
       that can make up your OpenStack cloud.
     </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="openstack-map.png" width="75%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
     <para>
       Depending on your use case requirements, each service provides a different
       function. However, this guide is focusing on a POC implementation and describes
       the use of the following projects:
     </para>
       <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             Identity service (keystone)
           </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             Compute service (nova)
           </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             Block Storage service (cinder)
           </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             Image service (glance)
           </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             Networking service (neutron)
           </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>
             Dashboard service (horizon)
           </para>
         </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
     <para>
      This guide also uses &suse; Enterprise Storage" (SES), powered by Ceph, as
      a software based storage solution on the backend. For more documentation
      on SES, see <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/ses/5.5"/>.
     </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
