<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="idg-all-security-middleware_auditing-xml-1">
 <title>Security Audit Logs</title>
 <section>
  <title>The need for auditing</title>
  <para>
   Enterprises need the ability to audit and monitor workflows and data in
   accordance with their strict corporate, industry or governmental policies
   and compliance requirements such as FIPS-140-2, PCI-DSS, HIPAA, SOX, or ISO.
   To meet this need, &kw-hos; supports CADF (Cloud Auditing Data
   Federation)-compliant security audit logs that can easily be integrated with
   your organization's Security Information and Event Management (SIEM) tools.
   Such auditing is valuable not only to meet regulatory compliance
   requirements, but also for correlating threat forensics.
  </para>
  <para>
   Note that logs from existing OpenStack services can also be used for
   auditing purposes, even though they are not in a consistent audit friendly
   CADF format today. All logs can easily be integrated with a SIEM tool such
   as HPE ArcSight, Splunk etc.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Audit middleware</title>
  <para>
   Audit middleware is python middleware logic that addresses the
   aforementioned logging shortcomings. Audit middleware constructs audit event
   data in easily consumed CADF format. This data can be mined to answer
   critical questions about activities over REST resources such as who made the
   request, when, why, and so forth.
  </para>
  <para>
   Audit middleware supports delivery of audit data via the Oslo messaging
   notifier feature. Each service is configured to route data to an
   audit-specific log file.
  </para>
  <para>
   The following are key aspects of auditing support in &kw-hos-phrase;:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Auditing is disabled by default and can be enabled only after &kw-hos;
     installation.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Auditing support has been added to eight &kw-hos; services (Nova, Cinder,
     Glance, Keystone, Neutron, Heat, Barbican, and Ceilometer).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Auditing has been added for interactions where REST API calls are invoked.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     All audit events are recorded in a service-specific audit log file.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Auditing configuration is centrally managed and indicates for which
     services auditing is currently disabled or enabled.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Auditing can be enabled or disabled on a per-service basis.
    </para>
   </listitem>
<!--<li>Support for centralized delivery of audit events to logstash for
   potential transformation, then to &elasticsearch; and the ability to
   analyze audit events is going to be added in future release(s). </li>-->
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Centralized auditing configuration</title>
  <para>
   In &kw-hos;, all auditing configuration is centrally managed and controlled
   via input model YAML files on the &clm; node. The settings are
   configured in the file
   <literal>~/openstack/my_cloud/definition/cloudConfig.yml</literal> in a newly
   added audit-settings section shown below the following table.
  </para>
  <informaltable colsep="1" rowsep="1">
   <tgroup cols="6">
    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1*"/>
    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="1*"/>
    <colspec colnum="4" colname="col4" colwidth="1.5*"/>
    <colspec colnum="5" colname="col5" colwidth="1*"/>
    <colspec colnum="6" colname="col6" colwidth="4*"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Key</entry>
      <entry>Value (default)</entry>
      <entry>Type</entry>
      <entry>Description</entry>
      <entry>Expected value(s)</entry>
      <entry>Comments</entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>default</entry>
      <entry>disabled</entry>
      <entry>String</entry>
      <entry>Flag to globally enable or disable auditing for all services.</entry>
      <entry><emphasis>disabled, enabled</emphasis>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        A service's auditing behavior is determined via this default key value
        unless it is listed explicitly in the enabled-services or
        disabled-services list.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>enabled-services</entry>
      <entry>[] (empty list)</entry>
      <entry>yaml list</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Setting to explicitly enable auditing for listed services regardless of
        default flag setting.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <emphasis>nova, cinder, glance, keystone, neutron, heat, barbican,
        ceilometer </emphasis>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        To enable a specific service, either add the service name in the
        enabled-services list when default is set to
        <literal>disabled</literal> or remove from disabled-services list when
        default is set to <literal>enabled</literal>.
       </para>
       <para>
        If a service name is present in both enabled-services and
        disabled-services, then auditing will be enabled for that service.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>disabled-services</entry>
      <entry>Nova, Barbican, Keystone, Cinder, Ceilometer, Neutron</entry>
      <entry>yaml list</entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        Setting to explicitly disable auditing for listed services regardless
        of default flag setting.
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        <emphasis>nova, cinder, glance, keystone,neutron, heat, barbican,
        ceilometer </emphasis>
       </para>
      </entry>
      <entry>
       <para>
        To disable a specific service, either add the service name in
        disabled-services when default is set to <literal>enabled</literal>. or
        remove from enabled-services list when default is set to
        <literal>disabled</literal>.
       </para>
      </entry>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
  <para>
   Audit settings in <literal>cloudConfig.yml</literal> with default set to
   <literal>disabled</literal> and services selectively enabled:
  </para>
<screen>product:
    version: 2
    cloud:
    ....
    ....
    # Disc space needs to be allocated to the audit directory before enabling
    # auditing.
    # keystone and nova has auditing enabled
    # cinder, ceilometer, glance, neutron, heat, barbican have auditing disabled
    audit-settings:
    audit-dir: /var/audit
    default: disabled
    enabled-services:
    - keystone
    - nova
    disabled-services:
    - cinder
    - ceilometer</screen>
  <para>
   Audit setting in <literal>cloudConfig.yml</literal> with default set to
   <literal>enabled</literal> and services selectively disabled:
  </para>
<screen>product:
    version: 2
    cloud:
    ....
    ....
    # Disc space needs to be allocated to the audit directory before enabling
    # auditing.
    # keystone, nova, glance, neutron, heat, barbican has auditing enabled
    # cinder, ceilometer has auditing disabled
    audit-settings:
    audit-dir: /var/audit
    default: enabled
    enabled-services:
    - keystone
    - nova
    disabled-services:
    - cinder
    - ceilometer</screen>
  <para>
   Because auditing is disabled by default, you will need to follow the steps
   below to enable it:
  </para>
  <orderedlist xml:id="ul_udn_cft_lv">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <xref linkend="idg-all-operations-audit_logs_checklist-xml-1"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <xref linkend="topic_enable_audit_logs"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
   For instructions on backing up and restoring audit logs, see:
   <xref linkend="backup_audit_logs"/> .
  </para>
 </section>
</chapter>
