<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="idg-all-security-tls_config-xml-1">
 <title>TLS Configuration</title>
 <para>
  In &product;, you can provide your own certificate authority and
  certificates for internal and public virtual IP addresses (VIPs), and you
  should do so for any production cloud. The certificates automatically
  generated by &productname; are useful for testing and setup, but you should always
  install your own for production use. Certificate installation is discussed
  below.
 </para>
 <section>
  <title>Using the Default My Public Cert</title>
  <para>
   Read the following if you are using the default <literal>cert-name:
   my-public-cert</literal> in your model.
  </para>
  <para>
   The bundled test cert for public endpoints, located at
   <literal>~/openstack/my_cloud/config/tls/certs/my-public-cert</literal>, is
   now expired but was left in the product in case you changed the content with
   your valid cert. Please verify if the certificate is expired and generate
   your own by following the guidelines further down on this page or by using a
   generic instruction from the web.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can verify the expiry by running this command:
  </para>
<screen>
openssl x509 -in ~/openstack/my_cloud/config/tls/certs/my-public-cert -noout -enddate
notAfter=Feb 12 01:18:46 2019 GMT</screen>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Certificate Terms</title>
  <para>
   Before you begin, the following list of terms will be helpful when
   generating and installing certificates.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Openstack-generated public CA</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      An OpenStack-generated public CA
      (<literal>openstack_frontend_cacert.crt</literal>) is available for you
      in <literal>/usr/local/share/ca-certificates</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Fully qualified domain name (FQDN) of the public VIP</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The registered domain name. A FQDN is not mandatory. It is valid to have
      no FQDN and use IP addresses instead. You can use FQDNs on public
      endpoints, and you may change them whenever the need arises.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Certificate authority (CA) certificate</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Your certificates must be signed by a CA, such as your internal IT
      department or a public certificate authority. For this example we will
      use a self-signed certificate.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Server certificate</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      It is easy to confuse server certificates and CA certificates. Server
      certificates reside on the server and CA certificates reside on the
      client. A server certificate affirms that the server that sent it serves
      a set of IP addresses, domain names, and set of services. A CA
      certificate is used by the client to authenticate this claim.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>SAN (subject-alt-name)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The set of IP addresses and domain names in a server certificate request:
      A template for a server certificate.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Certificate signing request (CSR)</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A blob of data generated from a certificate request and sent to a CA,
      which would then sign it, produce a server certificate, and send it back.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>External VIP</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      External virtual IP address
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Internal VIP</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Internal virtual IP address
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para>
   The major difference between an external VIP certificate and an internal VIP
   certificate is that the internal VIP has approximately 40 domain names in
   the SAN. This is because each service has a different domain name in
   &product;. So it is unlikely that you can create an internal server
   certificate before running the configuration processor. But after a
   configuration processor run, a certificate request would be created for each
   of your cert-names.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Configuring TLS in the input model</title>
  <para>
   For this example certificate configuration, let us assume there is no FQDN
   for the external VIP and that you are going to use the default IP address
   provided by &product;. Let's also assume that for the internal VIP you
   will use the defaults as well. If you were to call your certificate
   authority "example-CA," the CA certificate would then be called
   "example-CA.crt" and the key would be called "example-CA.key." In the
   following examples, the external VIP certificate will be named
   "example-public-cert" and the internal VIP certificate will be named
   "example-internal-cert."
  </para>
  <para>
   Any time you make a cert change when using your own CA:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You should use a distinct name from those already existing in
     <filename>config/tls/cacerts</filename>. This also means you should not
     <emphasis>reuse</emphasis> your CA names. You should use unique and
     distinguishable names such as MyCompanyXYZ_PrivateRootCA.crt. A new name
     is what indicates that a file is new or changed, so reusing a name means
     that the file is not considered changed even if its contents have changed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You should not remove any existing CA files from
     <filename>config/tls/cacerts</filename>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If you want to remove an existing CA use the following steps:
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <step>
      <para>
       Remove the file.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Then run:
      </para>
<screen>
<?dbsuse-fo font-size="0.70em"?>
ansible -i hosts/verb_hosts FND-STN -a 'sudo keytool -delete -alias debian:&lt;filename to remove&gt; \
-keystore /usr/lib/jvm/java-7-openjdk-amd64/jre/lib/security/cacerts -storepass changeit'</screen>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <important>
   <para>
    Be sure to install your own certificate for all production clouds after
    installing and testing your cloud. If you ever want to test or troubleshoot
    later, you will be able to revert to the sample certificate to get back to
    a stable state for testing.
   </para>
  </important>
  <note>
   <para>
    Unless this is a new deployment, do not update both the certificate and the
    CA together. Add the CA first and then run a site deploy. Then update the
    certificate and run tls-reconfigure, FND-CLU-stop, FND-CLU-start and then
    hlm-reconfigure. If a playbook has failed, rerun it with -vv to get detailed
    error information. The configure, HAproxy restart, and reconfigure steps are
    included below. If this is a new deployment and you are adding your own
    certs/CA before running site.yml this caveat does not apply.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   You can add your own certificate by following the instructions below. All
   changes must go into the following file:
  </para>
<screen>~/openstack/my_cloud/definition/data/network_groups.yml</screen>
  <para>
   The entries for TLS for the internal and admin load balancers are:
  </para>
<screen>- provider: ip-cluster
        name: lb
        tls-components:
        - default
        components:
        # These services do not currently support TLS so they are not listed
        # under tls-components
        - nova-metadata
        roles:
        - internal
        - admin
        cert-file: openstack-internal-cert
        # The openstack-internal-cert is a reserved name and
        # this certificate will be autogenerated. You
        # can bring in your own certificate with a different name

        # cert-file: customer-provided-internal-cert
        # replace this with name of file in "config/tls/certs/"</screen>
  <para>
   The configuration processor will also create a request template for each
   named certificate under <filename>info/cert_reqs/</filename>, which looks
   like:
  </para>
<screen>info/cert_reqs/customer-provided-internal-cert</screen>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Generating and Signing Certificates</title>
  <para>
   These request templates contain the subject <literal>Alt-names</literal>
   that the certificates need. You can add to this template before generating
   your certificate signing request.
  </para>
  <para>
   You would then send the CSR to your CA to be signed, and once you receive
   the certificate, place it in <filename>config/tls/certs</filename>
  </para>
  <para>
   When you bring in your own certificate, you may want to bring in the trust
   chains (or CA certificate) for this certificate. This is usually not
   required if the CA is a public signer that is typically bundled with the
   operating system. However, we suggest you include it anyway by copying the
   file into the directory <filename>config/cacerts/</filename>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-security-tls_config-xml-4">
  <title>User-provided certificates and trust chains</title>
  <para>
   &productname; generates its own internal certificates but is designed to allow
   you to bring in your own certificates for the VIPs. Here is the general
   process.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     You must have a server certificate and a CA certificate to go with it
     (unless the signer is a public CA and it is already bundled with most
     distributions).
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     You must decide the names of the server certificates and configure the
     <filename>network_groups.yml</filename> file in the input model such that
     each load balancer provider has at least one cert-name associated with it.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run the configuration processor. You may or may not have the certificate
     file at this point. The configuration processor would create certificate
     request file artefacts under <filename>info/cert_reqs/</filename> for each
     of the cert-name(s) in the <literal>network_groups.yml</literal> file.
     While there is no special reason to use the request file created for an
     external endpoint VIP certificate, it is important to use the request
     files created for internal certificates since the canonical names for the
     internal VIP as there can be many of them and they will be service
     specific. Each of these needs to be in the Subject Alt Names attribute of
     the certificate.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create a certificate signing request for this request file and send it to
     your internal CA or a public CA to get it certified and issued with a
     certificate. You will now have a server certificate and possibly a trust
     chain or CA certificate.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Upload to the &clm;. Server certificates should be added to
     <filename>config/tls/certs</filename> and CA certificates should be added
     to <filename>config/tls/cacerts</filename>. The file extension should be
     <filename>.crt</filename> for the CA certificate to be processed by
     &productname;. Detailed steps are next.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Edit the Input Model to Include Your Certificate Files</title>
<!-- Commented in DITA original -->
<!-- TODO UPGRADE -->
<!--<note>If you are upgrading and plan to use the <xref href="barbican.dita#barbican">Barbican
          key management service</xref>, there are instructions for configuring Barbican with TLS in
          <xref linkend="barbicanUpgrade">Enabling Barbican
          When Upgrading</xref>.</note>-->
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Edit the load balancer configuration in
     <filename>openstack/my_cloud/definition/data/network_groups.yml</filename>:
    </para>
<screen>
<?dbsuse-fo font-size="0.70em"?>
load-balancers:
 - provider: ip-cluster
 name: lb
 tls-components:
 - default
 components:
 - cassandra
 - nova-metadata
 roles:
 - internal
 - admin
 cert-file: example-internal-cert #&lt;&lt;&lt;-------- Certificate name for the internal VIP

- provider: ip-cluster
 name: extlb
 external-name: myardana.test #&lt;&lt;&lt;------ Use just IP for the external VIP in this example
 tls-components:
 - default
 roles:
 - public
 cert-file: example-public-cert #&lt;&lt;&lt;-------- Certificate name for the external VIP</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Commit your changes to the local git repository and run the configuration
     processor:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
git add -A
git commit -m "changed VIP certificates"
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Verify that certificate requests have been generated by the configuration
     processor for every certificate file configured in the
     <filename>networks_groups.yml</filename> file. In this example, there are
     two files, as shown from the list command:
    </para>
<screen>ls ~/openstack/my_cloud/info/cert_reqs
example-internal-cert
example-public-cert</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="self-signed">
  <title>Generating a Self-signed CA</title>
  <note>
   <para>
    In a production setting you will not perform this step. You will use your
    company's CA or a valid public CA.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   This section demonstrates how you can create your own self-signed CA and
   then use this CA to sign server certificates. This CA can be your
   organization's IT internal CA that is self-signed and whose CA certificates
   are deployed on your organization's machines. This way the server
   certificate becomes legitimate.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Copy the commands below to the command line and execute. This will cause
     the two files to be created: <filename>example-CA.key</filename> and
     <filename>example-CA.crt</filename>.
    </para>
<screen>export EXAMPLE_CA_KEY_FILE='example-CA.key'
export EXAMPLE_CA_CERT_FILE='example-CA.crt'
openssl req -x509 -batch -newkey rsa:2048 -nodes -out "${EXAMPLE_CA_CERT_FILE}" \
-keyout "${EXAMPLE_CA_KEY_FILE}" \
-subj "/C=UK/O=hp/CN=YourOwnUniqueCertAuthorityName" \
-days 365</screen>
    <para>
     You can tweak the subj and days settings above to meet your needs, or to
     test. For instance, if you want to test what happens when a CA expires,
     you can set 'days' to a very low value.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the configuration processor-generated request file from
     <filename>info/cert_reqs/</filename>:
    </para>
<screen>cat ~/openstack/my_cloud/info/cert_reqs/example-internal-cert</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Copy this file to your working directory and append a
     <filename>.req</filename> extension to it.
    </para>
<screen>cp ~/openstack/my_cloud/info/cert_reqs/example-internal-cert \
  example-internal-cert.req</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <example xml:id="privateMetadata">
   <title>Certificate request file</title>
   <para>
    The certificate request file should look similar to the following example:
   </para>
<screen>[req]
distinguished_name = req_distinguished_name
req_extensions = v3_req
prompt = no

[ req_distinguished_name ]
CN = "openstack-vip"

[ v3_req ]
basicConstraints = CA:FALSE
keyUsage = nonRepudiation, digitalSignature, keyEncipherment
subjectAltName = @alt_names

[ alt_names ]
DNS.1 = "deployerincloud-ccp-c0-m1-mgmt"
DNS.2 = "deployerincloud-ccp-vip-CEI-API-mgmt"
DNS.3 = "deployerincloud-ccp-vip-CND-API-mgmt"
<emphasis>[...]</emphasis>
DNS.47 = "192.168.245.5"
IP.1 = "192.168.245.5"

=============end of certificate request file.</screen>
  </example>
  <note>
   <para>
    In the case of a public VIP certificate, please add all the FQDNs you
    want it to support. Currently, &productname; does not add the hostname for
    the external-name specified in <literal>network_groups.yml</literal> to
    the certificate request file. However, you can add it to the certificate
    request file manually. Here we assume that
    <literal>myopenstack.test</literal> is your external-name. In that case you
    would add this line (to the full sample certificate request file shown in
    <xref linkend="privateMetadata"/>):
   </para>
<screen>DNS.48 = "myopenstack.test"</screen>
  </note>
  <note>
   <para>
    Any attempt to use IP addresses rather than FQDNs in certificates must use
    subject alternate name entries that list both the IP address (needed for
    Google) and DNS with an IP (needed for a Python bug workaround). Failure to
    create the certificates in this manner will cause future installations of
    Go-based tools (such as Cloud Foundry, Stackato and other PaaS components)
    to fail.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   In the case of a public VIP certificate, add all the FQDNs you want it to
   support. Openstack does not add the hostname for the external-name specified
   in <filename>network_groups.yml</filename> to the certificate request file.
   However, you can add it to the certificate request file manually. Assuming
   that <filename>myopenstack.test</filename> is your external-name,
   you would add this line to the full sample certificate request file
   shown above.
  </para>
<screen>DNS.48 = "myopenstack.test"</screen>
  <note>
   <para>
    Any attempt to use IP addresses rather than FQDNs in certificates must use
    subject alternate name entries that list both the IP address (needed for
    Google) and DNS with an IP (needed for a Python bug workaround). Failure to
    create the certificates in this manner will cause future installations of
    Go-based tools (such as Cloud Foundry, Stackato and other PaaS components)
    to fail.
   </para>
  </note>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Generate a Certificate Signing Request</title>
  <note>
   <para>
    In a production setting you will not perform this step. You will use your
    company's CA or a valid public CA.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   Now that you have a CA and a certificate request file, it is time to generate
   a CSR.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    Please use a unique CN for your example Certificate Authority and do not
    install multiple CA certificates with the same CN into your cloud.
   </para>
  </note>
<screen>
<?dbsuse-fo font-size="0.70em"?>
export EXAMPLE_SERVER_KEY_FILE='example-internal-cert.key'
export EXAMPLE_SERVER_CSR_FILE='example-internal-cert.csr'
export EXAMPLE_SERVER_REQ_FILE=example-internal-cert.req
openssl req -newkey rsa:2048 -nodes -keyout "$EXAMPLE_SERVER_KEY_FILE" \
-out "$EXAMPLE_SERVER_CSR_FILE" -extensions v3_req -config "$EXAMPLE_SERVER_REQ_FILE"</screen>
  <para>
   In production you would usually send the generated
   <filename>example-internal-cert.csr</filename> file to your IT department.
   But in this example you are your own CA, so sign and generate a server
   certificate.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Generate a Server Certificate</title>
  <note>
   <para>
    In a production setting you will not perform this step. You will send the
    CSR created in the previous section to your company CA or a to a valid
    public CA and have them sign and send you back the certificate.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   This section demonstrates how you would use the self-signed CA that you
   created earlier to sign and generate a server certificate. A server
   certificate is essentially a signed public key, the signer being a CA and
   trusted by a client. When you install this signed CA's certificate (called
   CA certificate or trust chain) on the client machine, you are telling the
   client to trust this CA, and to implicitly trust any server certificates
   that are signed by this CA. This creates a trust anchor.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">CA configuration file</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   When the CA signs the certificate, it uses a configuration file that tells
   it to verify the CSR. Note that in a production scenario the CA takes care
   of this for you.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create a file called <filename>openssl.cnf</filename> and add the
     following contents to it.
    </para>
<screen># Copyright 2010 United States Government as represented by the
# Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.
# All Rights Reserved.
#...

# OpenSSL configuration file.
#

# Establish working directory.

dir = .

[ ca ]
default_ca = CA_default

[ CA_default ]
serial = $dir/serial
database = $dir/index.txt
new_certs_dir = $dir/
certificate = $dir/cacert.pem
private_key = $dir/cakey.pem
unique_subject = no
default_crl_days = 365
default_days = 365
default_md = md5
preserve = no
email_in_dn = no
nameopt = default_ca
certopt = default_ca
policy = policy_match
copy_extensions = copy

[ policy_match ]
countryName = optional
stateOrProvinceName = optional
organizationName = optional
organizationalUnitName = optional
commonName = supplied
emailAddress = optional

[ req ]
default_bits = 1024 # Size of keys
default_keyfile = key.pem # name of generated keys
default_md = md5 # message digest algorithm
string_mask = nombstr # permitted characters
distinguished_name = req_distinguished_name
req_extensions = v3_req
x509_extensions = v3_ca

[ req_distinguished_name ]
# Variable name Prompt string
#---------------------- ----------------------------------
0.organizationName = Organization Name (company)
organizationalUnitName = Organizational Unit Name (department, division)
emailAddress = Email Address
emailAddress_max = 40
localityName = Locality Name (city, district)
stateOrProvinceName = State or Province Name (full name)
countryName = Country Name (2 letter code)
countryName_min = 2
countryName_max = 2
commonName = Common Name (hostname, IP, or your name)
commonName_max = 64

[ v3_ca ]
basicConstraints = CA:TRUE
subjectKeyIdentifier = hash
authorityKeyIdentifier = keyid:always,issuer:always
subjectAltName = @alt_names

[ v3_req ]
basicConstraints = CA:FALSE
subjectKeyIdentifier = hash

[ alt_names ]

######### end of openssl.cnf #########</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Sign the server certificate with your CA. Copy the comands below to the
     command line and execute. This will cause the file,
     <filename>example-internal-cert.crt</filename>, to be created.
    </para>
<screen>export EXAMPLE_SERVER_CERT_FILE='example-internal-cert.crt'
export EXAMPLE_SERVER_CSR_FILE='example-internal-cert.csr'
export EXAMPLE_CA_KEY_FILE='example-CA.key'
export EXAMPLE_CA_CERT_FILE='example-CA.crt'

touch index.txt
openssl rand -hex -out serial 6

openssl ca -batch -notext -md sha256 -in "$EXAMPLE_SERVER_CSR_FILE" \
-cert "$EXAMPLE_CA_CERT_FILE" \
-keyfile "$EXAMPLE_CA_KEY_FILE" \
-out "$EXAMPLE_SERVER_CERT_FILE" \
-config openssl.cnf -extensions v3_req</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Concatenate both the server key and certificate in preparation for
     uploading to the &clm;.
    </para>
<screen>
<?dbsuse-fo font-size="0.70em"?>
cat example-internal-cert.key example-internal-cert.crt &gt; example-internal-cert</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     You have only created the <literal>internal-cert</literal> in this
     example. Repeat the above sequence for
     <literal>example-public-cert</literal>. Make sure you use the appropriate
     certificate request generated by the configuration processor.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Upload to the &clm;</title>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     The two files created from the example above will need to be uploaded to
     the &clm; and copied into <filename>config/tls</filename>:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist xml:id="idg-all-security-tls_config-xml-7">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       example-internal-cert
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       example-CA.crt
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the &clm;, execute the following copy commands. If you created an
     external cert, copy that in a similar manner.
    </para>
<screen>cp example-internal-cert ~/openstack/my_cloud/config/tls/certs/
cp example-CA.crt ~/openstack/my_cloud/config/tls/cacerts/</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log into the &clm; node. Save and commit the changes to the local Git
     repository:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
git add -A
git commit -m "updated certificate and CA"</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Rerun the <literal>config-processor-run</literal> playbook, and run
     <filename>ready-deployment.yml</filename>:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you receive any prompts, enter the required information.
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      For automated installation (for example, CI) you can specify the required
      passwords on the Ansible command line. For example, the command below
      will disable encryption by the configuration processor:
     </para>
<screen>ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml -e encrypt="" -e rekey=""</screen>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Run this series of runbooks to complete the deployment:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts tls-reconfigure.yml
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts FND-CLU-stop.yml
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts FND-CLU-start.yml
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts monasca-stop.yml
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts monasca-start.yml
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts ardana-reconfigure.yml</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-security-tls_config-xml-8">
  <title>Configuring the Cipher Suite</title>
  <para>
   By default, the cipher suite is set to:
   <literal>HIGH:!aNULL:!eNULL:!DES:!3DES</literal>. This setting is
   recommended in the
   <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/security-guide/secure-communication/introduction-to-ssl-and-tls.html">OpenStack
   documentation</link>. You may override this by editing
   <filename>config/haproxy/defaults.yml</filename>. The parameters can be
   found under the <literal>haproxy_globals</literal> list.
  </para>
<screen>- "ssl-default-bind-ciphers HIGH:!aNULL:!eNULL:!DES:!3DES"
- "ssl-default-server-ciphers HIGH:!aNULL:!eNULL:!DES:!3DES"</screen>
  <para>
   Make the changes as needed. Keep the two options identical.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Testing</title>
  <para>
   You can determine if an endpoint is behind TLS by running the following
   command, which probes a Keystone identity service endpoint that is behind
   TLS:
  </para>
<screen>
&prompt.user;echo | openssl s_client -connect 192.168.245.5:5000 | \
  openssl x509 -fingerprint -noout
depth=0 CN = openstack-vip
verify error:num=20:unable to get local issuer certificate
verify return:1
depth=0 CN = openstack-vip
verify error:num=27:certificate not trusted
verify return:1
depth=0 CN = openstack-vip
verify error:num=21:unable to verify the first certificate
verify return:1
DONE
SHA1 Fingerprint=C6:46:1E:59:C6:11:BF:72:5E:DD:FC:FF:B0:66:A7:A2:CC:32:1C:B8</screen>
  <para>
   The next command probes a MariaDB endpoint that is not behind TLS:
  </para>
<screen>
<?dbsuse-fo font-size="0.63em"?>
echo | openssl s_client -connect 192.168.245.5:3306 | openssl x509 -fingerprint -noout
140448358213264:error:140770FC:SSL routines:SSL23_GET_SERVER_HELLO:unknown protocol:s23_clnt.c:795:
unable to load certificate
140454148159120:error:0906D06C:PEM routines:PEM_read_bio:no start line:pem_lib.c:703:Expecting: TRUSTED CERTIFICATE</screen>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Verifying That the Trust Chain is Correctly Deployed</title>
  <para>
   You can determine if the trust chain is correctly deployed by running the
   following commands:
  </para>
<screen>
&prompt.user;echo | openssl s_client -connect 192.168.245.9:5000 2&gt;/dev/null \
  | grep code
Verify return code: 21 (unable to verify the first certificate)
&prompt.user;echo | openssl s_client -connect 192.168.245.9:5000 -CAfile \
  /usr/local/share/ca-certificates/openstack_frontend_cacert.crt 2&gt;/dev/null \
  | grep code
Verify return code: 0 (ok) </screen>
  <para>
   The first command produces error 21, which is then fixed by providing
   the CA certificate file. This verifies that the CA certificate matches the
   server certificate.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Turning TLS on or off</title>
  <para>
   You should leave TLS enabled in production. However, if you need to disable
   it for any reason, you must change <literal>tls-components</literal> to
   <literal>components</literal> in <filename>network_groups.yml</filename> (as
   shown earlier) and comment out the cert-file. Additionally, if you have a
   <filename>network_groups.yml</filename> file from a previous installation,
   TLS will not be enabled unless you change <literal>components</literal> to
   <literal>tls-components</literal> in that file. By default, Horizon is
   configured with TLS in the input model. You should not disable TLS in the
   input model for Horizon as that is a public endpoint and is required.
   Additionally, you should keep all services behind TLS, but using the input
   model file <filename>network_groups.yml</filename> you may turn TLS off for
   a service for troubleshooting or debugging. TLS should always be enabled for
   production environments.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you are using an example input model on a clean install, all supported
   TLS services will be enabled before deployment of your cloud. If you want to
   change this setting later, such as when upgrading, you can change the input
   model and reconfigure the system. The process is as follows:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Edit the input model <filename>network_groups.yml</filename> file
     appropriately as described above, changing
     <literal>tls-components</literal> to <literal>components</literal>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Commit the changes to the Git repository:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/openstack/ardana/ansible/
git add -A
git commit -m "TLS change"</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Change directories again and run the configuration processor and ready
     deployment playbooks:
    </para>
<screen>ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Change directories again and run the reconfigure playbook:
    </para>
<screen>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/ardana/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts ardana-reconfigure.yml</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
</section>
