<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="newsecurity">
 <title>&productnamereg;: Security Features Overview</title>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-security-security_features-xml-6">
  <title>Security features in &product;</title>
  <para>
   Enterprises need protection against security breaches, insider threats, and
   operational issues that increase the risk to sensitive data. By combining
   technologies from both &ostack; services and &mf; Security–Data
   Security products, &product; provides capabilities that help you
   protect your data at rest and in transit, enable centralized key management,
   and comply with Payment Card Industry Data Security Standard (PCI-DSS).
  </para>
  <para>
   In &product;, a number of security enhancements are available to
   strengthen and harden your cloud deployment. Below is an overview of some of
   the features and brief descriptions. Follow the links to the relevant topics
   for instructions on setup, configuration, and use of these security
   features.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="rbac">
  <title>Role-Based Access Control (RBAC) Support for &o_netw; Networks</title>
  <para>
   The RBAC feature in this release enables better security as administrators
   can now control who has access to specific networks. This is a significant
   improvement over the previous all-or-nothing approach to shared networks.
   This is beneficial from a security standpoint as some projects (or tenants)
   have stricter security policies. For example, a finance department must run
   PCI-compliant workloads in isolation from other departments, and thus cannot
   share their &o_netw; network resources. RBAC enables cloud admins to create
   granular security policies for sharing &o_netw; resources with one or more
   tenants or projects using the standard CRUD (Create, Read, Update, Delete)
   model. More information can be found in
   <xref linkend="cha.security.rbac"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="adminRoles">
  <title>Separate Service Administrator Role</title>
  <para>
   Each &ostack; service account now has an optional role available to
   restrict the &ostack; functions each account can access. This feature
   enables cloud administrators to apply service-specific role-based,
   admin-level access to a specific UserID, with the ability to audit
   admin-level actions. This functionality provides better security by not only
   providing full visibility into admin-level activities via audit logs, but
   also by fulfilling compliance requirements such as PCI DSS v3.1 standards.
   More information in
   <xref linkend="idg-all-security-admin_role_segregation-xml-6"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="interservicePasswords">
  <title>Inter-service Password Enhancements</title>
  <para>
   You can conveniently change the inter-service passwords used for
   authenticating communications between services in your &productname; deployment,
   promoting better compliance with your organization’s security policies.
   The inter-service passwords that can be changed include (but are not limited
   to) &o_ident;, &mariadb;, &rabbit;, &clm;, &o_monitor; and &secret_store;. Admins can
   implement this feature by running the configuration processor to generate
   new passwords followed by Ansible playbook commands to change the
   credentials.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="selinux">
  <title>SELinux for KVM</title>
  <para>
   SELinux (also known as Security-Enhanced Linux) provides enhanced security
   at the hypervisor layer on &compnode;s by mitigating the risk of hypervisor
   attacks and strongly isolating the guest VMs. It enforces mandatory access
   control security policies for the &compnode;s (svirt process) running KVM,
   thus reducing the risk of a hypervisor breakout. By providing a locked down
   profile for the KVM/QEMU processes that the guest VMs run in, it strongly
   isolates the guest VMs. With such strong security measures as SELinux,
   malicious attacks on VMs and the underlying host OS are much less
   possible. SELinux provides enhanced security for instances managed by
   <literal>libvirt</literal>. It does not, however, provide enhanced security
   for &ostack; processes.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="in_transit">
  <title>Data In Transit Protection</title>
  <para>
   With &product;, data transmission between internal API endpoints is
   encrypted using TLS v 1.2 to protect sensitive data against unauthorized
   disclosure and modification (spoofing and tampering attacks). Additionally,
   you can configure TLS using your own certificates, from a Certificate
   Authority of your choice, providing deployment flexibility. More at
   <xref linkend="idg-all-security-tls_config-xml-1"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="dataSecurity">
  <title>Data-at-Rest Protection Using Project-Based Encryption</title>
<!-- HPE ESKM (HPE Enterprise Secure Key Manager) needs to be replaced -->
  <para>
   You can encrypt sensitive data-at-rest on per tenant or project basis, while
   storing and managing keys externally and centrally using Enterprise Secure
   Key Manager (ESKM). This capability requires the &secret_store; API and
   OASIS KMIP (Key Management Interoperability Protocol) plug-ins for
   integration, and supports encryption of &o_blockstore; block storage with
   &product;. More information at <xref linkend="dar"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="cadf">
  <title>CADF-Compliant Security Audit Logs</title>
  <para>
   Security audit logs for critical services such as &o_ident;, &o_comp;, &o_blockstore;,
   &o_img;, &o_orch;, &o_netw;, &secret_store; are available in a standard CADF (Cloud
   Audit Data Federation) format. These logs contain information on events such
   as unauthorized logins, admin level access, unsuccessful login attempts, and
   anomalous deletion of VMs that are critical from a security threat
   monitoring standpoint. Audit logs are useful as a tool for risk mitigation,
   identifying suspicious or anomalous activity, and for fulfilling compliance.
   For more information see
   <xref linkend="idg-all-security-middleware_auditing-xml-1"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="pciReady">
  <title>PCI Readiness</title>
  <para>
   &product; is PCI (Payment Card Industry) ready, enabling retail and
   finance industries that are subject to PCI compliance, to become certified.
   The readiness is based on lab assessment and verification conducted by an
   external audit firm, against the more than 250 security requirements
   specified in the PCI DSS (Data Security Standard) v3.1 standards document.
   Since &productname; satisfies the requirements that fall under vendor
   responsibility, customers can proceed with their certification efforts with
   full confidence and peace of mind that &productname; will not be a blocker.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>&o_img;-API Rate Limit to Address CVE-2016-8611</title>
  <para>
   No limits are enforced within the &o_img; service for both v1 and v2/images
   API POST method for authenticated users, resulting in possible denial of
   service through database table saturation. Further explanation and
   instructions for adding a rate-limiter are in <xref
   linkend="glance-rate-limit"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
</chapter>
