<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="newsecurity">
 <title>&productnamereg;: Security Planning and Features</title>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-security-security_planning-xml-1">
  <title>Security Planning</title>
  <para>
   &productnamereg; is a complex system that has many options which
   affect the security of the system and the workloads running within it. Careful planning
   is required to ensure the correct options and features are chosen for your particular
   environment. You should read
   <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/security-guide/introduction/security-boundaries-and-threats.html">Security Boundaries and Threats</link>
   to understand how OpenStack defines security domains. Ensure that the network layout
   you choose for your deployment provides adequate network separation for your specific
   requirements. Carefully examine the other chapters in the
   <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/security-guide/">OpenStack Security Guide</link>
   for further information.
   Take advantage of the security features described below in this section.
  </para>
  <para>
   OpenStack services by design run some commands with root privileges in order to provide
   functionality. Although services run as a non-root user they can escalate privilege
   to root to perform certain operations. If a service process is compromised to the
   extent that an attacker can execute arbitrary code as the service user, then it is
   likely that the attacker can elevate privilege to root and take over the system on
   which the service is running. When planning the security controls for an OpenStack
   deployment, you should consider the services to be running as root when deciding which
   security controls are appropriate for your environment. Timely installation of
   security patches is essential. Other controls such as Intrusion Prevention Systems
   and Web Application Firewalls are recommended.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="idg-all-security-security_features-xml-6">
  <title>Security Features in &product;</title>
  <para>
   Enterprises need protection against security breaches, insider threats, and
   operational issues that increase the risk to sensitive data. &product;
   provides capabilities that help you
   protect your data at rest and in transit, enable centralized key management,
   and meet compliance requirements.
  </para>
  <para>
   In &product;, a number of security features are available to
   strengthen and harden your cloud deployment. Below is an overview of some of
   the features and brief descriptions. Follow the links to the relevant topics
   for instructions on setup, configuration, and use of these security
   features.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="rbac">
  <title>Role-Based Access Control (RBAC) Support for &o_netw; Networks</title>
  <para>
   The RBAC feature for &o_netw; networks enables better security as administrators
   can control who has access to specific networks. This is a significant
   improvement over the all-or-nothing approach to shared networks.
   This is beneficial from a security standpoint as some projects (or tenants)
   have stricter security policies. For example, a finance department must run
   workloads in isolation from other departments, and thus cannot
   share their &o_netw; network resources. RBAC enables cloud admins to create
   granular security policies for sharing &o_netw; resources with one or more
   tenants or projects using the standard CRUD (Create, Read, Update, Delete)
   model. More information can be found in
   <xref linkend="cha.security.rbac"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="adminRoles">
  <title>Separate Service Administrator Role</title>
  <para>
   Each &ostack; service account has an optional role available to
   restrict the &ostack; functions each account can access. This feature
   enables cloud administrators to apply service-specific role-based,
   administration-level access to a specific UserID, with the ability to audit
   administration-level actions. This functionality provides better security by not only
   providing full visibility into administration-level activities via audit logs, but
   also by fulfilling compliance requirements.
   More information can be found in
   <xref linkend="idg-all-security-admin_role_segregation-xml-6"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="interservicePasswords">
  <title>Inter-service Password Enhancements</title>
  <para>
   You can conveniently change the inter-service passwords used for
   authenticating communications between services in your &productname; deployment,
   promoting better compliance with your organization’s security policies.
   The inter-service passwords that can be changed include (but are not limited
   to) &o_ident;, &mariadb;, &rabbit;, &clm;, &o_monitor; and &secret_store;.
   Administrators can
   implement this feature by running the configuration processor to generate
   new passwords followed by Ansible playbook commands to change the
   credentials.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="in_transit">
  <title>Data In Transit Protection</title>
  <para>
   With &product;, data transmission between internal API endpoints is
   encrypted using TLS v 1.2 to protect sensitive data against unauthorized
   disclosure and modification (spoofing and tampering attacks). Additionally,
   you can configure TLS using your own certificates, from a Certificate
   Authority of your choice, providing deployment flexibility. More
   information can be found in
   <xref linkend="idg-all-security-tls_config-xml-1"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="dataSecurity">
  <title>Data-at-Rest Protection Using Project-Based Encryption</title>
<!-- HPE ESKM (HPE Enterprise Secure Key Manager) needs to be replaced -->
  <para>
   You can encrypt sensitive data-at-rest on per tenant or project basis, while
   storing and managing keys externally and centrally using Enterprise Secure
   Key Manager (ESKM). This capability requires the &secret_store; API and
   OASIS KMIP (Key Management Interoperability Protocol) plug-ins for
   integration, and supports encryption of &o_blockstore; block storage with
   &product;. More information can be found in <xref linkend="dar"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="cadf">
  <title>CADF-Compliant Security Audit Logs</title>
  <para>
   Security audit logs for critical services such as &o_ident;, &o_comp;, &o_blockstore;,
   &o_img;, &o_orch;, &o_netw;, and &secret_store; are available in a standard CADF (Cloud
   Audit Data Federation) format. These logs contain information on events such
   as unauthorized logins, administration level access, unsuccessful login attempts, and
   anomalous deletion of VMs that are critical from a security threat
   monitoring standpoint. Audit logs are useful as a tool for risk mitigation,
   identifying suspicious or anomalous activity, and for fulfilling compliance requirements.
   For more information see
   <xref linkend="idg-all-security-middleware_auditing-xml-1"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>&o_img;-API Rate Limit to Address CVE-2016-8611</title>
  <para>
   No limits are enforced within the &o_img; service for both v1 and v2/images
   API POST method for authenticated users, resulting in possible denial of
   service through database table saturation. Further explanation and
   instructions for adding a rate-limiter are in <xref
   linkend="glance-rate-limit"/>.
  </para>
 </section>
</chapter>
