<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="encryption-ephemeral">
 <title>Encryption of Ephemeral Volumes</title>
 <para>
  By default, ephemeral volumes are not encrypted. If you wish to enable this
  feature, you should use the following steps.
 </para>
 <note>
  <para>
   For more details about this feature, see
   <link xlink:href="http://specs.openstack.org/openstack/nova-specs/specs/juno/approved/lvm-ephemeral-storage-encryption.html">Ephemeral
   storage encryption for LVM backend</link>.
  </para>
 </note>

 <section>
  <title>Enabling ephemeral volume encryption</title>
  <para>
   Before deploying the Compute nodes you will need to change the disk
   configuration to create a new <literal>volume-group</literal> which will be
   used for your ephemeral disks. To do this, following these steps:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Log in to the &clm;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Add details about the volume-group you will be using for your encrypted
     volumes. You have two options for this, you can either create a new
     volume-group or add the details for an already existing volume-group.
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To create a new volume-group, add the following lines to your Compute
       disk configuration file.
      </para>
      <para>
       The location of the Compute disk configuration file is:
      </para>
<screen>~/openstack/my_cloud/definition/data/disks_compute.yml</screen>
<screen>name: vg-comp
       physical-volumes:
         - /dev/sdb</screen>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       To utilize an existing volume-group you can add the following lines to
       your <literal>nova.conf</literal> file, using the name of your
       volume-group:
      </para>
<screen>[libvirt]
images_type = lvm
images_volume_group = &lt;volume_group_name&gt;</screen>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <note>
     <para>
      The requirement here is to have free space available on a
      <literal>volume-group</literal>. The correct disk to use and the name for
      the volume group will depend on your environment's needs.
     </para>
    </note>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Modify the <literal>nova.conf</literal> file for the Compute and API
     nodes. Verify that the following entries exist, if they do not then add
     them and then restart the <literal>nova-compute</literal> and
     <literal>nova-api</literal> services:
    </para>
<screen>[libvirt]
images_type = lvm
images_volume_group = vg-comp

[ephemeral_storage_encryption]
key_size = 256
cipher = aes-xts-plain64
enabled = True

[keymgr]
api_class = nova.keymgr.barbican.BarbicanKeyManager

[barbican]
endpoint_template = https://192.168.245.9:9311/v1</screen>
    <para>
     To restart the services, use the following commands:
    </para>
<screen>sudo systemctl restart nova-compute
sudo systemctl restart nova-api</screen>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Assign the role in Keystone using the CLI tool. Using the openstack client
     you can assign the user <literal>key-manager:creator</literal> role for
     the project.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Boot an instance with an ephermal disk and verify that the disk is
     encrypted. Once the instance is active it is possible to check on the
     Compute node if the ephermal disk is encrypted.
    </para>
    <para>
     SSH into the Compute node then run the following commands:
    </para>
<screen>sudo dmsetup status
cryptsetup -v status &lt;name_of_ephemeral_disk&gt;</screen>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </section>
</chapter>
