<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<section id="idg-shared-intro-c-usagescenario-xml-1">
 <title>Basic Usage Scenario</title>
 <para id="The_basic_usage_scenario_of_s_concept_conbody_section_2_p">
  The basic usage scenario of setting up and using the monitoring features of
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> looks as follows:
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images-metricslogs.png" depth="298" width="700" align="left"/>
   </imageobject>
   <textobject><phrase>MetricsLogs.png</phrase>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <para id="A_concept_conbody_section_p_2">
  An <emphasis role="bold">application operator</emphasis> acts as a service
  provider in the OpenStack environment. He books virtual machines to provide
  services to <emphasis role="bold">end users</emphasis> or to host services
  that he needs for his own development activities. <phrase>CMM</phrase> helps
  application operators ensure that their services and the servers on which
  they are provided are configured and working as required.
 </para>
 <para>
  As an <emphasis role="bold">OpenStack operator</emphasis>, you are a special
  application operator who is responsible for administrating and maintaining
  the underlying OpenStack platform. The monitoring and log management services
  of <phrase>CMM</phrase> enable you to ensure the availability and quality of
  your platform. You use <phrase>CMM</phrase> for:
 </para>
 <para>
  <itemizedlist id="Monitoring_physical_and_virtu_concept_conbody_section_p_4">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Monitoring physical and virtual servers, hypervisors, and OpenStack
     services.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Monitoring middleware components, for example, database services.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Retrieving and analyzing the log data of the OpenStack services and
     servers, the middleware components, and the operating system.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </para>
 <para>
  The <emphasis role="bold">Monitoring Service operator</emphasis> is
  responsible for providing the monitoring and log management features to the
  application operators and the OpenStack operator. This enables them to focus
  on operation and the quality of their services and servers without having to
  carry out the tedious tasks implied by setting up and administrating their
  own monitoring software. The Monitoring Service operator uses the monitoring
  services himself for ensuring the quality of <phrase>CMM</phrase>.
 </para>
</section>
