<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="configure-index-patterns">
 <title>Configuring Index Patterns</title>
 <para>
  &productmonitoring; enables the dynamic mapping
  of fields. After configuring an index pattern, the indices that match the
  pattern are automatically scanned to display the list of index fields. This
  guarantees that the fields are correctly visualized in the dashboard.
 </para>
 <para>
  &productmonitoring; ships with a preconfigured
  index pattern that allows you to instantly explore your &elasticsearch; indices
  when accessing the dashboard for the first time. You can create additional
  patterns to view and analyze specific sets of data. One or multiple patterns
  can be created per project. When you create additional patterns, you have to
  set one of them as the default.
 </para>
 <para>
  To configure an additional index pattern, use <guimenu>Settings &gt;
  Indices</guimenu>. Click the index pattern that is displayed in the
  <guimenu>Index Patterns</guimenu> field on the left, and use the
  <guimenu>Add New</guimenu> option.
 </para>
 <para>
  Indices that match the pattern you define must exist in the &elasticsearch;
  database, and they must contain data. For an index pattern, you specify the
  following elements:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <guimenu>Index contains time-based events</guimenu>. It is recommended
    that this option is selected. This improves search performance by enabling
    searches only on those indices that contain data on time-based events.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <guimenu>Use event times to create index names</guimenu>. It is
    recommended that this option is selected. This improves search performance
    by enabling searches only on those indices that contain data in the time
    range you specify.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <guimenu>Index pattern interval</guimenu>. Select
    <literal>Daily</literal> as index pattern interval. Daily intervals are
    supported by the Monitoring Service.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <guimenu>Index name or pattern</guimenu>. The pattern allows you to
    define dynamic index names. Static text in a pattern is denoted using
    brackets. Replace the predefined pattern (<literal>[logstash-]*</literal>
    or <literal>[logstash-]YYYY.MM.DD</literal>) as follows:
   </para>
   <para>
    Replace <literal>logstash-</literal> by the project ID of the OpenStack
    project whose log data is to be visualized in the dashboard.
   </para>
   <para>
    Replace <literal>*</literal> or <literal>YYYY.MM.DD</literal> by
    <literal>YYYY-MM-DD</literal> as naming pattern. This naming pattern is
    supported by the Monitoring Service.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example: <literal>[557aff4bf007473d84069aca202a1633-]YYYY-MM-DD</literal>
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <guimenu>Time-field name</guimenu>. Select <literal>@timestamp</literal>
    as time-field name. <literal>@timestamp</literal> matches the
    <literal>YYYY-MM-DD</literal> naming pattern.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  The default index pattern is automatically loaded when you access the log
  management window. It is marked with an asterisk in front of the pattern name
  in the <guimenu>Index Patterns</guimenu> field at the top left corner of
  the <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> page. Select the pattern you want to set as
  the default from the <guimenu>Index Patterns</guimenu> field. The
  content of the log management window is instantly updated.
 </para>
</section>
