<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<section id="about-operations-monitoring">
 <title>About SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</title>
 <para>
  The monitoring solution of <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase>
  addresses the requirements of large-scale public and private clouds where
  high numbers of physical and virtual servers need to be monitored and huge
  amounts of monitoring data need to be managed. <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud
  Monitoring</phrase> consolidates metrics, alarms, and notifications, as well
  as health and status information from multiple systems, thus reducing the
  complexity and allowing for a higher level analysis of the monitoring data.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> covers all aspects of a
  Monitoring as a Service solution:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Storage of monitoring data in a resilient way.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Multi-tenancy architecture for submitting and streaming metrics. The
    architecture ensures the secure isolation of metrics data.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Horizontal and vertical scalability to support constantly evolving cloud
    infrastructures. When physical and virtual servers are scaled up or down to
    varying loads, the monitoring solution can be adapted accordingly.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> offers various
  features which support you in proactively managing your cloud resources. A
  large number of metrics in combination with early warnings about problems and
  outages assists you in analyzing and troubleshooting any issue you encounter
  in your environment.
 </para>
 <para>
  The monitoring features include:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    A monitoring overview which allows you to access all monitoring
    information.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Metrics dashboards for visualizing your monitoring data.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Alerting features for monitoring.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  In the following sections, you will find information on the monitoring
  overview and the metrics dashboards as well as details on how to define and
  handle alarms and notifications.
 </para>
 <section id="accessing-soc-monitoring">
  <title>Accessing <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase></title>
 <para>
  For accessing <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> and performing
  monitoring tasks, you must have access to the OpenStack platform as a user with
  the <guimenu>monasca-user</guimenu> or <guimenu>monasca-read-only-user</guimenu>
  role in the <guimenu>monasca</guimenu> tenant.
  </para>
 <para>
  Log in to OpenStack Horizon with your user name and password. The functions
  you can use in OpenStack Horizon depend on your access permissions. To access
  logs and metrics, switch to the <guimenu>monasca</guimenu> tenant in
  Horizon. This allows you to access all monitoring data for SUSE OpenStack
  Cloud Monitoring.
 </para>
 <figure id="fig.socm.monasca">
  <title>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Horizon Dashboard&mdash;Monitoring</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-horizon-monasca.png" width="95%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-horizon-monasca.png" width="90%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
</section>
 <section id="monitoring-overview-data">
  <title>Overview</title>
  <para>
   <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> provides one convenient
   access point to your monitoring data. Use <guilabel>Monitoring &gt;
   Overview</guilabel> to keep track of your services and servers and quickly
   check their status. The overview also indicates any irregularities in the log
   data of the system components you are monitoring.
  </para>
  <para>
   On the <guilabel>Overview</guilabel> page, you can:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     View the status of your services, servers, and log data at a glance. As
     soon as you have defined an alarm for a service, a server, or log data and
     metrics data has been received, there is status information displayed on
     the <guilabel>Overview</guilabel> page. Different colors are used for the
     different statuses.
    </para>
<!--    <para>
     For details on the status information, refer to <xref
     linkend="idg-osoperator-shared-monitor-c-monitor-statusinfo-xml-1"/>. For
     details on defining alarms, refer to <xref linkend="sec.osoperator.alarms"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Access a preconfigured dashboard that visualizes your metrics data.
     Starting from this dashboard, you can create your own dashboards for
     visualizing your metrics data as required. For details, refer to
     <xref linkend="concept_E8D43EB4494E41D2AB42D4A89396D1OS"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Access the <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> log management
     functionality. For details, refer to
     <xref linkend="idg-osoperator-shared-logging-c-osologging-xml-1"/>.
   </para>-->
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</section>
