<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<section id="key-features">
 <title>Key Features</title>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> is an out-of-the-box
  solution for monitoring OpenStack-based cloud environments. It is provided as
  a cloud service to users. <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase>
  meets different challenges, ranging from small-scale deployments to
  high-availability deployments and deployments with high levels of
  scalability.
 </para>
 <para>
  The core of <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> is Monasca, an
  open source Monitoring as a Service solution that integrates with OpenStack.
  The key features of <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> form an
  integral part of the Monasca project. <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud
  Monitoring</phrase> extends the source code base of the project through
  active contributions.
 </para>
 <para>
  Compared to the Monasca community edition, <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud
  Monitoring</phrase> provides the following added value:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Packaging as a commercial enterprise solution
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Enterprise-level support
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  The key features of <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> address
  public as well as private cloud service providers. They include:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Monitoring
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Metrics
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Log management
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Integration with OpenStack
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <section id="monitoring">
  <title>Monitoring</title>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> is a highly scalable and
  fault tolerant monitoring solution for OpenStack-based cloud infrastructures.
 </para>
 <para>
  The system operator of the cloud infrastructure and the service providers do
  not have to care for system monitoring software any longer. They use
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> to check whether their
  services and servers are working appropriately.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> provides comprehensive and
  configurable metrics with reasonable defaults for monitoring the status,
  capacity, throughput, and latency of cloud systems. <phrase>SUSE OpenStack
  Cloud Monitoring</phrase> users can set their own warnings and critical
  thresholds and can combine multiple warnings and thresholds to support the
  processing of complex events. Combined with a notification system, these
  alerting features enable them to quickly analyze and resolve problems in the
  cloud infrastructure.
 </para>
</section>
<section id="metrics">
 <title>Metrics</title>
 <para>
  The Metrics agent is responsible for querying metrics and sending them to the
  Monitoring Service for further processing.
 </para>
 <para>
  Metrics are self-describing data structures that are uniquely identified by a
  name and a set of dimensions. Each dimension consists of a key/value pair
  that allows for a flexible and concise description of the data to be
  monitored, for example, region, availability zone, service tier, or resource
  ID.
 </para>
 <para>
  The Metrics Agent supports various types of metrics including the following:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    System metrics, for example, CPU usage, consumed disk space, or network
    traffic.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Host alive checks. The agent can perform active checks on a host to
    determine whether it is alive using ping (ICMP) or SSH.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Process checks. The agent can check and monitor a process, for example, the
    number of instances, memory size, or number of threads.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    HTTP endpoint checks. The agent can perform up/down checks on HTTP
    endpoints by sending an HTTP request and reporting success or failure to
    the Monitoring Service.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Service checks. The agent can check middleware services, for example,
    MySQL, Kafka, or RabbitMQ.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    OpenStack services. The agent can perform specific checks on each process
    that is part of an OpenStack service.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Log metrics. The agent can check and monitor the number of critical log
    entries in the log data retrieved from the cloud resources.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  Your individual agent configuration determines which metrics are available
  for monitoring your services and servers. For details on installing and
  configuring a Metrics Agent, refer to the SUSE OpenStack Cloud <citetitle>Deployment
  Guide</citetitle>, chapter <citetitle>Deploying the OpenStack Services</citetitle>,
  section <citetitle>Deploying Monasca</citetitle>. It is available from
  <ulink url="https://www.suse.com/documentation"></ulink>.
 </para>
 <para>
  As soon as an agent is available, you have access to the <phrase>SUSE
  OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> monitoring features. You work with a
  graphical user interface that is seamlessly integrated into your cloud
  infrastructure. Based on OpenStack Horizon, the user interface enables access
  to all monitoring functionality and the resulting large-scale monitoring
  data. A comfortable dashboard visualizes the health and status of your cloud
  resources.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> provides functions for alarm
  and notification management. <phrase>Template-based alarm definitions allow
  for monitoring a dynamically changing set of resources without the need for
  reconfiguration. While the number of underlying virtual machines is changing,
  for example, this ensures the efficient monitoring of scalable cloud
  services. Alarm definitions allow you to specify expressions that are
  evaluated based on the metrics data that is received. Alarm definitions can
  be combined to form compound alarms. Compound alarms allow you to track and
  process even more complex events. Notifications can be configured in order to
  inform <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> users when an alarm
  is triggered.</phrase>
 </para>
</section>
 <section id="log-management">
  <title>Log Management</title>
 <para>
  With the increasing complexity of cloud infrastructures, it is becoming more
  and more difficult and time-consuming for the system operator to gather,
  store, and query the large amounts of log data manually. To cope with these
  problems, <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> provides
  centralized log management features.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> stores the log data in a
  central database. This forms the basis for visualizing the log data for the
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> users. Advanced data
  analysis and visualization of the log data is supported in a variety of
  charts, tables, and maps. Visualizations can easily be combined in dynamic
  dashboards that display changes to search queries in real time.
 </para>
 <para>The log data from a large number of sources can be accessed from a
  single dashboard. Integrated search, filter, and graphics options enable
  system operators to isolate problems and narrow down potential root causes.
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> thus provides valuable
  insights into the log data, even with large amounts of data resulting
  from highly complex environments.
 </para>
 <para>
  Based on OpenStack Horizon, the customizable dashboards are seamlessly
  integrated into your cloud infrastructure. They enable user access to all log
  management functionality.
 </para>
 <para>
  GUI-based alarm and notification management is also supported for log data.
  Based on a template mechanism, you can configure alarms and notifications to
  monitor the number of critical log events over time. Compound alarms can be
  created to analyze more complex log events. This automation of log handling
  guarantees that you can identify problems in your their infrastructure early
  and find the root cause quickly.
 </para>
</section>
 <section id="openstack-integration">
  <title>Integration with OpenStack</title>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> is integrated with OpenStack
  core services. These include:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    OpenStack Horizon dashboard for visualizing monitoring metrics and log data
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    OpenStack user management
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    OpenStack security and access control
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</section>
