<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<section id="configure-log-management-window">
 <title>Working with the Log Management Window</title>
 <para>
  Index patterns determine which data from the underlying Elasticsearch
  database can be viewed and analyzed in <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud
  Monitoring</phrase>'s log management window. Index patterns are used to
  identify the Elasticsearch indices to run search and analytics against.
 </para>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> ships with a preconfigured
  index pattern which allows you to instantly view and analyze your log data
  when accessing the log management window for the first time. You can
  configure additional index patterns to view and analyze different data from
  different indices.
 </para>
 <para>
  Search queries allow you to search the Elasticsearch indices for data that
  match your information requirements. The query results can be graphically
  represented in visualizations, and visualizations can be organized in
  dashboards.
 </para>
 <para>
  The log management window provides features for:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Querying log data.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Visualizing query results.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Combining visualizations in dashboards.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Filtering query results in dashboards.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Sharing dashboards.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  The following sections provide an introduction to queries, visualizations,
  and dashboards. For additional details, refer to the
  <ulink url="https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/kibana/4.5/index.html">Kibana
  documentation</ulink>.
 </para>
 <section id="query-log-data">
  <title>Querying Log Data</title>
 <para>
  For querying log data, you use the <guilabel>Discover</guilabel> page in the
  log management window. It is instantly displayed when you access the window.
  It shows the most recently collected log data:
 </para>
 <figure>
  <title>The Kibana Dashboard&mdash;Discover Page</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-kibana-dashboard.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-kibana-dashboard.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
 <para>
  The <guilabel>Discover</guilabel> page allows you to access the log data in
  every index that matches the current index pattern. In addition to submitting
  queries, you can view, filter, and analyze the log data that is returned by
  your queries.
 </para>
 <para>
  On the <guilabel>Discover</guilabel> page the following elements assist you
  in analyzing your log data:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Below the main navigation bar at the top of the window, there is a
    <emphasis role="bold">search box</emphasis> for querying your log data. By
    submitting a query, you search all indices that match the current index
    pattern. The name of the current index pattern is displayed directly below
    the search box on the left side. You can select a different index pattern,
    if required.
   </para>
   <para>
    For entering strings in the search box, use the Lucene query syntax. Kibana
    also supports the Elasticsearch Query DSL. For details, refer to the
    <ulink url="https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/elasticsearch/reference/2.3/query-dsl.html">Elasticsearch Reference documentation</ulink>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Use the <emphasis role="bold">clock icon</emphasis> at the top right border
    of the log management window to define a time range for filtering the log
    data. By default, <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> displays
    the log data collected during the last 15 minutes. You can deviate from
    this default. Multiple options are provided for defining relative or
    absolute time ranges. The time range you define is instantly applied to all
    log data.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    In the bottom right part of the <guilabel>Discover</guilabel> page, you can
    view the <emphasis role="bold">log data</emphasis> returned by your search
    queries. Depending on whether you have filtered the data by index fields,
    the log data is either restricted to these fields or entire records are
    displayed.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    On the left side of the <guilabel>Discover</guilabel> page below the search
    box, you see the <emphasis role="bold">index fields</emphasis> from the
    indices that match the current index pattern. You can select individual
    fields to modify which log data is displayed on the right side.
   </para>
   <para>
    Select a field from the <guilabel>Available Fields</guilabel> section for
    this purpose and use <guilabel>Add</guilabel>. To remove a field, select it
    in the <guilabel>Selected Fields</guilabel> section and use
    <guilabel>Remove</guilabel>.
   </para>
   <para>
    From the field list, you can expand a field by simply clicking it. This
    shows the most common values for the field. You can also set field values
    as filter, or you can exclude log data with specific field values.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    If a time field is configured for the current index pattern, the
    distribution of log entries over time is displayed in a
    <emphasis role="bold">histogram</emphasis> in the top right part of the
    <guilabel>Discover</guilabel> page.
   </para>
   <para>
    By default, the histogram shows the number of logs entries versus time,
    matched by the underlying query and time filter. You can click the bars in
    the histogram to narrow down the time filter.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  Queries can be saved and re-used. They can also be shared with other users.
  For this purpose, use the options to the right of the search box at the top
  border of the log management window:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To save a query, use <guilabel>Save Search</guilabel>. Saving a query means
    saving both the query syntax and the current index pattern.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To load a query, use <guilabel>Load Saved Search</guilabel>. A saved query
    can be loaded and used by any OpenStack or Monitoring Service operator.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To share a query with other users, use <guilabel>Share Search</guilabel>.
    The option displays a direct link to the query that you can forward. As a
    prerequisite for using a direct link, a user must have <phrase>SUSE
    OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> access.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</section>
 <section id="visualize-query-results">
  <title>Visualizing Query Results</title>
 <para>
  <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> supports you in building
  graphical representations of your query results. You can choose from
  different visualization types, for example, pie charts, data tables, line
  charts, or vertical bar charts. For visualizing your results, you use the
  <guilabel>Visualize</guilabel> page in the log management window:
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-kibana-visualize.png" width="95%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-kibana-visualize.png" width="90%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <para>
  To create a visualization, use <guilabel>New Visualization</guilabel> to the
  right of the search box at the top border of the window. You have to select a
  visualization type and the query to be used. You can either create a new
  query or load a query you have already saved.
 </para>
 <para>
  Based on the visualization type and the query, you can proceed with designing
  the graphical representation in a visualization editor. Multiple design
  options and a preview function are provided for creating, modifying, and
  viewing the graphical representation.
 </para>
 <para>
  You can save and re-use visualizations. You can also share them with other
  users. For this purpose, use the options to the right of the search box at
  the top border of the log management window:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To save a visualization, use <guilabel>Save Visualization</guilabel>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To load a visualization, use <guilabel>Load Saved Visualization</guilabel>.
    A saved visualization can be loaded and used by any OpenStack or Monitoring
    Service operator.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To share a visualization with other users, use <guilabel>Share
    Visualization</guilabel>. The option displays an HTML snippet that can be
    used to embed the visualization in a Web page. It also displays a direct
    link to the visualization that you can forward. As a prerequisite for using
    an embedded visualization or a direct link, a user must have <phrase>SUSE
    OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</phrase> access.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</section>
 <section id="combine-visualizations-dashboard">
  <title>Combining Visualizations in Dashboards</title>
 <para>
  For correlating related information or providing an overview, you can combine
  visualizations in dashboards. Use the <guilabel>Dashboard</guilabel> page in
  the log management window for this purpose:
 </para>
 <para>
  To create a dashboard from scratch, you use <guilabel>New
  Dashboard</guilabel> to the right of the search box at the top border of the
  window. To add a visualization from a list of existing visualizations, use
  <guilabel>Add Visualization</guilabel>. You need at least one saved
  visualization to create a dashboard. In addition to adding visualizations,
  you can also place the tabular output of query results on your dashboards.
  Switch to the <guilabel>Searches</guilabel> tab when adding a visualization,
  and select a saved query. This adds the query result to your dashboard.
 </para>
 <para>
  A visualization or query result is displayed in a container on your
  dashboard. Various options are provided for arranging containers:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Move a container by clicking and dragging its title bar.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Resize a container by dragging its bottom right corner.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Remove a container using <guilabel>Delete</guilabel> in the top right
    corner of the container.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  Using <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> in the top right corner of a container, you
  can switch to the <guilabel>Visualize</guilabel> or
  <guilabel>Discover</guilabel> page. This allows you to design the graphical
  representation or edit the query. To view the raw data behind a
  visualization, you can click the bar at the bottom of the container. This
  replaces your visualization by the underlying raw data. You can export the
  raw data, if required.
 </para>
 <para>
  For each dashboard, you can configure a refresh interval to automatically
  refresh its content with the latest data. The current interval is displayed
  in the top right border of the log management window. Click the interval if
  you want to change it. You can define the interval in absolute or relative
  terms. Use <guilabel>Auto-Refresh</guilabel> next to the interval in the
  border of the log management window to instantly submit the underlying
  queries and refresh the dashboard content.
 </para>
 <para>
  By default, dashboards are displayed with a light background. Using
  <guilabel>Options</guilabel> in the top right border of the log management
  window, you can switch to a dark color scheme.
 </para>
</section>
 <section id="filter-query-dashboard">
  <title>Filtering Query Results in Dashboards</title>
 <para>
  By submitting a query on the data displayed in a dashboard, you can filter
  out specific sets of data that you want to aggregate while not changing the
  logic of the individual visualizations.
 </para>
 <para>
  Use the search box below the main navigation bar at the top of the log
  management window for entering a query on the whole dashboard. If a
  visualization is already based on a saved query, both queries apply.
 </para>
</section>
 <section id="sharing-dashboards">
  <title>Sharing Dashboards</title>
 <para>
  Dashboards can be saved and re-used. They can also be shared with other
  users. For this purpose, use the options to the right of the search box at
  the top border of the log management window:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To save a dashboard, use <guilabel>Save Dashboard</guilabel>. By default,
    saving a dashboard also saves the time filter that is defined at the time
    of saving. You can disable this default by clearing the <guilabel>Store
    time with dashboard</guilabel> option. Disabling the default means that the
    time filter is set to the currently selected time each time the dashboard
    is loaded.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To load a dashboard, use <guilabel>Load Saved Dashboard</guilabel>. A saved
    dashboard can be loaded and used by any OpenStack or Monitoring Service
    operator.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    To share a dashboard with other users, use <guilabel>Share
    Dashboard</guilabel>. The option displays an HTML snippet that can be used
    to embed the dashboard in a Web page. It also displays a direct link to the
    dashboard that you can forward. As a prerequisite for using an embedded
    dashboard or a direct link, a user must have <phrase>SUSE OpenStack Cloud
    Monitoring</phrase> access.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>
