<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="components">
 <title>Components</title>
 <para>
  The following illustration provides an overview of the main components of
  &productmonitoring;:
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="images-overview-structure.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="images-overview-structure.png"/>
   </imageobject>
   <textobject><phrase>structure_new.png</phrase>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <para>
  &productmonitoring; relies on OpenStack as
  technology for building cloud computing platforms for public and private
  clouds. OpenStack consists of a series of interrelated projects delivering
  various components for a cloud infrastructure solution and allowing for the
  deployment and management of Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS) platforms.
 </para>
 <para>
  For details on OpenStack, refer to the
  <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/">OpenStack documentation</link>.
 </para>

 <section xml:id="monitoring-service">
  <title>Monitoring Service</title>
 <para>
  The Monitoring Service is the central &productmonitoring;
  component. It is responsible for receiving, persisting,
  and processing metrics and log data, as well as providing the data to the
  users.
 </para>
 <para>
  The Monitoring Service relies on Monasca. It uses Monasca for high-speed
  metrics querying and integrates the streaming alarm engine and the
  notification engine of Monasca. For details, refer to the
  <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Monasca">Monasca Wiki</link>.
 </para>
</section>

 <section xml:id="horizon-plugin">
  <title>Horizon Plugin</title>
 <para>
  &productmonitoring; comes with a plugin for the
  OpenStack Horizon dashboard. The Horizon plugin extends the main dashboard in
  OpenStack with a view for monitoring. This enables &productmonitoring;
  users to access the monitoring and log management
  functions from a central Web-based graphical user interface. Metrics and log
  data are visualized on a comfortable and easy-to-use dashboard.
 </para>
 <para>
  For details, refer to the
  <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/developer/horizon/">OpenStack Horizon
  documentation</link>.
 </para>
 <para>
  Based on OpenStack Horizon, the monitoring data is visualized on a
  comfortable and easy-to-use dashboard which fully integrates with the
  following applications:
 </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Grafana (for metrics data). An open source application for visualizing
     large-scale measurement data.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Kibana (for log data). An open source analytics and visualization platform
     designed to work with Elasticsearch.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="metrics-agent">
  <title>Metrics Agent</title>
 <para>
  A Metrics Agent is required for retrieving metrics data from the host on
  which it runs and sending the metrics data to the Monitoring Service. The
  agent supports metrics from a variety of sources as well as a number of
  built-in system and service checks.
 </para>
 <para>
  A Metrics Agent can be installed on each virtual or physical server to be
  monitored.
 </para>
 <para>
  The agent functionality is fully integrated into the source code base of the
  Monasca project. For details, refer to the
  <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Monasca">Monasca Wiki</link>.
 </para>
</section>

 <section xml:id="log-agent">
  <title>Log Agent</title>
 <para>
  A Log Agent is needed for collecting log data from the host on which it runs
  and forwarding the log data to the Monitoring Service for further processing.
  It can be installed on each virtual or physical server from which log data is
  to be retrieved.
 </para>
 <para>
  The agent functionality is fully integrated into the source code base of the
  Monasca project. For details, refer to the
  <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Monasca">Monasca Wiki</link>.
 </para>
 </section>

</section>
