<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>

<!-- Copyright FUJITSU LIMITED 2017 -->
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"><title>Glossary</title><info/>
 
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Application Operator</bridgehead>
 <para>
  A person with limited access to cloud resources in &ostack;. An application
  operator provides services to end users or hosts services for his own
  development activities.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Dimension</bridgehead>
 <para>
  A key/value pair that allows for a flexible and concise description of the
  data to be monitored, for example, region, availability zone, service tier,
  or resource ID. Each dimension describes a specific characteristic of the
  metrics to be monitored.
 </para>
 <para>
  In &productmonitoring;, metrics are uniquely
  identified by a name and a set of dimensions. Dimensions can serve as a
  filter for the monitoring data.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">&elasticsearch;</bridgehead>
 <para>
  An open source application that provides a highly scalable full-text search
  and analytics engine. &productmonitoring; uses
  &elasticsearch; as the underlying technology for storing, searching, and
  analyzing large volumes of log data.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Grafana</bridgehead>
 <para>
  An open source application for visualizing large-scale measurement data.
  &productmonitoring; integrates with Grafana for
  visualizing the monitoring data.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS)</bridgehead>
 <para>
  The delivery of computer infrastructure (typically a platform virtualization
  environment) as a service.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">InfluxDB</bridgehead>
 <para>
  An open source time-series database that supports high write loads and large
  data set storage. &productmonitoring; uses
  InfluxDB as the underlying technology for storing metrics and the alarm
  history.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Kibana</bridgehead>
 <para>
  An open source analytics and visualization platform designed to work with
  &elasticsearch;. &productmonitoring; integrates
  with Kibana for visualizing the log data.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Logstash</bridgehead>
 <para>
  An open source application that provides a data collection engine with
  pipelining capabilities. &productmonitoring;
  integrates with Logstash for collecting, processing, and outputting logs.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">MariaDB</bridgehead>
 <para>
  An open source relational database that provides an SQL-compliant interface
  for accessing data. &productmonitoring; uses
  MariaDB as the underlying technology for storing configuration information,
  alarm definitions, and notification methods.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Metrics</bridgehead>
 <para>
  Self-describing data structures that allow for a flexible and concise
  description of the data to be monitored. Metrics values represent the actual
  monitoring data that is collected and presented in &productmonitoring;.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">monasca</bridgehead>
 <para>
  An open source Monitoring as a Service solution that integrates with
  &ostack;. It forms the core of &productmonitoring;.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Monitoring Service Operator</bridgehead>
 <para>
  A person responsible for maintaining and administrating &productmonitoring;.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">&ostack; Operator</bridgehead>
 <para>
  A person responsible for maintaining and administrating &ostack;, the
  underlying platform technology of &productmonitoring;.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Platform as a Service (PaaS)</bridgehead>
 <para>
  The delivery of a computing platform and solution stack as a service.
 </para>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Software as a Service (SaaS)</bridgehead>
 <para>
  A model of software deployment where a provider licenses an application to
  customers for use as a service on demand.
 </para>
</appendix>
