<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<section id="users-roles">
 <title>Users and Roles</title>
 <para>
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> users can be grouped by their role. The following user
  roles are distinguished:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    An <emphasis role="bold">application operator</emphasis> acts as a service
    provider in the OpenStack environment. He books virtual machines in
    OpenStack to provide services to end users or to host services that he
    needs for his own development activities. <phrase>CMM</phrase> helps
    application operators to ensure the quality of their services in the cloud.
   </para>
   <para>
    For details on the tasks of the application operator, refer to the
    <emphasis>Application Operator's Guide</emphasis>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The<emphasis role="bold"> OpenStack operator</emphasis> is a special
    application operator. He is responsible for administrating and maintaining
    the underlying OpenStack platform and ensures the availability and quality
    of the OpenStack services (e.g. Heat, Nova, Cinder, Swift, Glance, or
    Keystone).
   </para>
   <para>
    For details on the tasks of the OpenStack operator, refer to the
    <emphasis>OpenStack Operator's Guide</emphasis>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The <emphasis role="bold">Monitoring Service operator</emphasis> is
    responsible for administrating and maintaining <phrase>CMM</phrase>. He
    provides the cloud monitoring services to the other users and ensures the
    quality of the Monitoring Service.
   </para>
   <para>
    For details on the tasks of the Monitoring Service operator, refer to the
    <emphasis>Monitoring Service Operator's Guide</emphasis>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>

 <section id="user-management">
  <title>User Management</title>
 <para id="is_fully_integrated_with_Key_concept_conbody_section_2_p">
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> is fully integrated with Keystone, the identity service
  which serves as the common authentication and authorization system in
  OpenStack.
 </para>
 <para id="idg-overview-whatiscmm-c-userroles-xml-8">
  The <phrase>CMM</phrase> integration with Keystone requires any
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> user to be registered as an OpenStack user. All
  authentication and authorization in <phrase>CMM</phrase> is done through
  Keystone. If a user requests monitoring data, for example,
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> verifies that the user is a valid user in OpenStack and
  allowed to access the requested metrics.
 </para>
 <para id="users_are_created_and_admini_concept_conbody_section_2_p">
  <phrase>CMM</phrase> users are created and administrated in OpenStack:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist id="Each_user_assumes_a_role_in_O_concept_conbody_section_2_ul">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Each user assumes a role in OpenStack to perform a specific set of
    operations. The OpenStack role specifies a set of rights and privileges.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Each user is assigned to at least one project in OpenStack. A project is an
    organizational unit that defines a set of resources which can be accessed
    by the assigned users.
   </para>
   <para>
    Application operators in <phrase>CMM</phrase> can monitor the set of
    resources that is defined for the projects to which they are assigned.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  For details on user management, refer to the
  <ulink url="http://docs.openstack.org/">OpenStack documentation</ulink>.
 </para>
 </section>
</section>
