<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities; ]>
<section id="defining-alarms">
 <title>Defining Alarms</title>
 <para>
  You have to define alarms to monitor your cloud resources. An alarm
  definition specifies the metrics to be collected and the threshold at which
  an alarm is to be triggered for a cloud resource. If the specified threshold
  is reached or exceeded, the alarm is triggered and notifications can be sent
  to inform users. By default, an alarm definition is evaluated every minute.
 </para>
 <para>
  To handle a large variety of monitoring requirements, you can create either
  simple alarm definitions that refer to one metrics only, or compound alarm
  definitions that combine multiple metrics and allow you to track and process
  more complex events.
 </para>
 <para>
  Example for a simple alarm definition that checks whether the system-level
  load of the CPU exceeds a threshold of 90 percent:
 </para>
<screen>cpu.system_perc{hostname=monasca} &gt; 90</screen>
 <para>
  Example for a simple alarm definition that checks the average time of the
  system-level load of the CPU over a period of 480 seconds. The alarm is
  triggered only if this average is greater than 95 percent:
 </para>
<screen>avg(cpu.system_perc{hostname=monasca}, 120) &gt; 95 times 4</screen>
 <para>
  Example for a compound alarm definition that evaluates two metrics. The alarm
  is triggered if either the system-level load of the CPU exceeds a threshold
  of 90 percent, or if the disk space that is used by the specified service
  exceeds a threshold of 90 percent:
 </para>
<screen>avg(cpu.system_perc{hostname=monasca}) &gt; 90 OR
max(disk.space_used_perc{service=monitoring}) &gt; 90</screen>
 <para>
  To create, edit, and delete alarms, use <guilabel>Monitoring &gt; Alarm
  Definitions</guilabel>.
 </para>
 <para>
  The elements that define an alarm are grouped into
  <guilabel>Details</guilabel>, <guilabel>Expression</guilabel>, and
  <guilabel>Notifications</guilabel>. They are described in the following
  sections.
 </para>
 <section id="alarm-details">
  <title>Details</title>
 <para>
  For an alarm definition, you specify the following details:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <guilabel>Name</guilabel>. Mandatory identifier of the alarm. The name must
    be unique within the project for which you define the alarm.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <guilabel>Description</guilabel>. Optional. A short description that
    depicts the purpose of the alarm.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <guilabel>Severity</guilabel>. The following severities for an alarm are
    supported: <guilabel>Low</guilabel> (default), <guilabel>Medium</guilabel>,
    <guilabel>High</guilabel>, or <guilabel>Critical</guilabel>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The severity affects the status information on the
    <guilabel>Overview</guilabel> page. If an alarm that is defined as
    <guilabel>Critical</guilabel> is triggered, the corresponding resource is
    displayed in a red box. If an alarm that is defined as
    <guilabel>Low</guilabel>, <guilabel>Medium</guilabel>, or
    <guilabel>High</guilabel> is triggered, the corresponding resource is
    displayed in a yellow box only.
   </para>
   <para>
    The severity level is subjective. Choose a level that is appropriate for
    prioritizing the alarms in your environment.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <figure>
  <title>Creating an Alarm Definition</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-alarmdef-create.png" width="70%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-alarmdef-create.png" width="90%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Expression</bridgehead>
 <para>
  The expression defines how to evaluate a metrics. The expression syntax is
  based on a simple expressive grammar. For details, refer to the
  <ulink url="https://github.com/openstack/monasca-api/blob/stable/ocata/docs/monasca-api-spec.md">Monasca API documentation</ulink>.
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-alarmdef-create-expression.png" width="75%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-alarmdef-create-expression.png" width="90%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <para>
  To define an alarm expression, proceed as follows:
 </para>
 <orderedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
     Select the metrics to be evaluated.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Select a statistical function for the metrics: <literal>min</literal> to
    monitor the minimum values, <literal>max</literal> to monitor the maximum
    values, <literal>sum</literal> to monitor the sum of the values,
    <literal>count</literal> for the monitored number, or
    <literal>avg</literal> for the arithmetic average.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Enter one or multiple dimensions in the <guilabel>Add a
    dimension</guilabel> field to further qualify the metrics.
   </para>
   <para>
    Dimensions filter the data to be monitored. They narrow down the evaluation
    to specific entities. Each dimension consists of a key/value pair that
    allows for a flexible and concise description of the data to be monitored,
    for example, region, availability zone, service tier, or resource ID.
   </para>
   <para>
    The dimensions available for the selected metrics are displayed in the
    <guilabel>Matching Metrics</guilabel> section. Type the name of the key you
    want to associate with the metrics in the <guilabel>Add a
    dimension</guilabel> field. You are offered a select list for adding the
    required key/value pair.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Enter the threshold value at which an alarm is to be triggered, and combine
    it with a relational operator <literal>&lt;</literal>,
    <literal>&gt;</literal>, <literal>&lt;=</literal>, or
    <literal>&gt;=</literal>.
   </para>
   <para>
    The unit of the threshold value is related to the metrics for which you
    define the threshold, for example, the unit is percentage for
    <literal>cpu.idle_perc</literal> or MB for
    <literal>disk.total_used_space_mb</literal>.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Switch on the <guilabel>Deterministic</guilabel> option if you evaluate a
    metrics for which data is received only sporadically. The option should be
    switched on, for example, for all log metrics. This ensures that the alarm
    status is <literal>OK</literal> and displayed as a green box on the
    <guilabel>Overview</guilabel> page although metrics data has not yet been
    received.
   </para>
   <para>
    Do not switch on the option if you evaluate a metrics for which data is
    received regularly. This ensures that you instantly notice, for example,
    that a host machine is offline and that there is no metrics data for the
    agent to collect. On the <guilabel>Overview</guilabel> page, the alarm
    status therefore changes from <literal>OK</literal> to
    <literal>UNDETERMINED</literal> and is displayed as a gray box.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Enter one or multiple dimensions in the <guilabel>Match by</guilabel> field
    if you want these dimensions to be taken into account for triggering
    alarms.
   </para>
   <para>
    Example: If you enter <literal>hostname</literal> as dimension, individual
    alarms will be created for each host machine on which metrics data is
    collected. The expression you have defined is not evaluated as a whole but
    individually for each host machine in your environment.
   </para>
   <para>
    If <guilabel>Match by</guilabel> is set to a dimension, the number of
    alarms depends on the number of dimension values on which metrics data is
    received. An empty <guilabel>Match by</guilabel> field results in exactly
    one alarm.
   </para>
   <para>
    To enter a dimension, you can simply type the name of the dimension in the
    <guilabel>Match by</guilabel> field. The dimensions you enter cannot be
    changed once the alarm definition is saved.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Build a compound alarm definition to combine multiple metrics in one
    expression. Using the logical operators <literal>AND</literal> or
    <literal>OR</literal>, any number of sub-expressions can be combined.
   </para>
   <para>
    Use the <guilabel>Add</guilabel> button to create a second expression, and
    choose either <literal>AND</literal> or <literal>OR</literal> as
    <guilabel>Operator</guilabel> to connect it to the one you have already
    defined. Proceed with the second expression as described in Step 1 to Step
    6 above.
   </para>
   <para>
    The following options are provided for creating and organizing compound
    alarm definitions:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Create additional sub-expressions using the <guilabel>Add</guilabel>
      button.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Finish editing a sub-expression using the <guilabel>Submit</guilabel>
      button.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Delete a sub-expression using the <guilabel>Remove</guilabel> button.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Change the position of a sub-expression using the <guilabel>Up</guilabel>
      or <guilabel>Down</guilabel> button.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <note>
  <para>
   You can also edit the expression syntax directly. For this purpose, save
   your alarm definition and update it using the <guilabel>Edit Alarm
   Definition</guilabel> option.
  </para>
  <para>
   By default, an alarm definition is evaluated every minute. When updating the
   alarm definition, you can change this interval. For syntax details, refer to
   the Monasca API documentation on
   <ulink url="https://github.com/openstack/monasca-api/blob/stable/ocata/docs/monasca-api-spec.md#alarm-definition-expressions">Alarm Definition Expressions</ulink>.
  </para>
 </note>
</section>
 <section id="alarm-notifications">
  <title>Notifications</title>
 <para>
  You can enable notifications for an alarm definition. As soon as an alarm is
  triggered, the enabled notifications will be sent.
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-alarmdef-create-notifications.png" width="95%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="socm-alarmdef-create-notifications.png" width="90%"
     format="PNG"></imagedata>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <para>
  The <guilabel>Notifications</guilabel> tab allows you to select the
  notifications from the ones that are predefined in your environment. For a
  selected notification, you specify whether you want to send it for a status
  transition to <guilabel>Alarm</guilabel>, <guilabel>OK</guilabel>, and/or
  <guilabel>Undetermined</guilabel>.
 </para>
</section>
</section>
