<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="soc-monitoring"><title>SUSE OpenStack Cloud Monitoring</title><info/>

 <para>
  As more and more applications are deployed on cloud systems and cloud systems
  are growing in complexity, managing the cloud infrastructure is becoming
  increasingly difficult. &productmonitoring;
  helps mastering this challenge by providing a sophisticated Monitoring as a
  Service solution that is operated on top of OpenStack-based cloud computing
  platforms.
 </para>
 <para>
  The component architecture of OpenStack provides for high flexibility, yet it
  increases the burden of system operation because multiple services must be
  handled. &productmonitoring; offers an
  integrated view of all services and assembles and presents related metrics
  and log data in one convenient access point. While being flexible and
  scalable to instantly reflect changes in the OpenStack platform,
  &productmonitoring; provides the ways and means required to
  ensure multi-tenancy, high availability, and data security. The high
  availability architecture of &productmonitoring;
  ensures an optimum level of operational performance eliminating the risk of
  component failures and providing for reliable crossover.
 </para>
 <para>
  &productmonitoring; covers all aspects of a
  Monitoring as a Service solution:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Central management of monitoring and log data from medium and large-size
    OpenStack deployments.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Storage of metrics and log data in a resilient way.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Multi-tenancy architecture to ensure the secure isolation of metrics and
    log data.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Horizontal and vertical scalability to support constantly evolving cloud
    infrastructures. When physical and virtual servers are scaled up or down to
    varying loads, the monitoring and log management solution can be adapted
    accordingly.
   </para>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
   <xi:include href="soc-monitoring-operations-about-monitoring.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="soc-monitoring-operations-architecture.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="soc-monitoring-operations-basic-usage.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="soc-monitoring-operations-key-features.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="soc-monitoring-operations-components.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="soc-monitoring-operations-user-roles.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="soc-monitoring-operations-ops-maintenance.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="soc-monitoring-operations-data-visualizations.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="soc-monitoring-operations-define-alarms.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="soc-monitoring-operations-define-notifications.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="soc-monitoring-operations-statuses.xml"/>
   <xi:include href="soc-monitoring-operations-supported-metrics.xml"/>
</chapter>
