<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent"> %entities;
]>

<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="basic-usage-scenario">
 <title>Basic Usage Scenario</title>
 <para>
  The monitoring solution of &productmonitoring;
  addresses the requirements of large-scale public and private clouds where
  high numbers of physical and virtual servers need to be monitored and huge
  amounts of monitoring data need to be managed. &productmonitoring;
  consolidates metrics, alarms, and notifications, as well
  as health and status information from multiple systems, thus reducing the
  complexity and allowing for a higher level analysis of the monitoring data.
 </para>
 <para>
  &productmonitoring; covers all aspects of a
  Monitoring as a Service solution:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Storage of monitoring data in a resilient way.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Multi-tenancy architecture for submitting and streaming metrics. The
    architecture ensures the secure isolation of metrics data.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Horizontal and vertical scalability to support constantly evolving cloud
    infrastructures. When physical and virtual servers are scaled up or down to
    varying loads, the monitoring solution can be adapted accordingly.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  The basic usage scenario of setting up and using the monitoring features of
  &productmonitoring; looks as follows:
 </para>
 <informalfigure>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="images-metricslogs.png" width="75%" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="images-metricslogs.png"/>
   </imageobject>
   <textobject><phrase>MetricsLogs.png</phrase>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </informalfigure>
 <para>
  The <emphasis role="bold">Monitoring Service operator</emphasis> is
  responsible for providing the monitoring features to the application
  operators and the &ostack; operator. This enables the application operators
  and the &ostack; operator to focus on operation and ensure the quality of
  their services without having to carry out the tedious tasks implied by
  setting up and administrating their own system monitoring software. The
  Monitoring Service operator uses the features for monitoring the
  operation of &productmonitoring;.
 </para>
 <para>
  As the Monitoring Service operator, you have the following responsibilities:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Deploying the Monitoring Service, thus providing the monitoring features to
    the application operators, and the monitoring and log management features
    to the &ostack; operator.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Regular maintenance of the components and services for &productmonitoring;.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Backup of the &productmonitoring; databases,
    configuration files, and customized dashboards.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Monitoring of &productmonitoring; for quality
    assurance.</para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Application operators</emphasis> monitor the virtual
  machines on which they provide services to <emphasis role="bold">end
  users</emphasis> or services they need for their development activities. They
  ensure that the physical and virtual servers on which their services are
  provided are up and running as required.
 </para>
 <para>
  The <emphasis role="bold">&ostack; operator</emphasis> is responsible for
  administrating and maintaining the underlying &ostack; platform. The
  monitoring and log management services of &productmonitoring;
  enable you to ensure the availability and quality of your platform.
  You use &productmonitoring; for:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Monitoring physical and virtual servers, hypervisors, and &ostack;
    services.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Monitoring middleware components, for example, database services.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Retrieving and analyzing the log data of the &ostack; services and
    servers, the middleware components, and the operating system.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <section xml:id="metrics-monitoring">
  <title>Metrics</title>
  <para>
   A Metrics Agent can be installed and configured on each physical and virtual
   server where cloud resources are to be monitored. The agent is responsible
   for querying metrics and sending the data to the Monitoring Service for
   further processing.
  </para>
  <para>
   Metrics are self-describing data structures that are uniquely identified by a
   name and a set of dimensions. Each dimension consists of a key/value pair
   that allows for a flexible and concise description of the data to be
   monitored, for example, region, availability zone, service tier, or resource
   ID.
  </para>
  <para>
   The Metrics Agent supports various types of metrics including the following:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     System metrics, for example, CPU usage, consumed disk space, or network
     traffic.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Host alive checks. The agent can perform active checks on a host to
     determine whether it is alive using ping (ICMP) or SSH.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Process checks. The agent can check and monitor a process, for example, the
     number of instances, memory size, or number of threads.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     HTTP endpoint checks. The agent can perform up/down checks on HTTP
     endpoints by sending an HTTP request and reporting success or failure to
     the Monitoring Service.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Service checks. The agent can check middleware services, for example,
     MySQL, Kafka, or RabbitMQ.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &ostack; services. The agent can perform specific checks on each process
     that is part of an &ostack; service.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Log metrics. The agent can check and monitor the number of critical log
     entries in the log data retrieved from the cloud resources.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="data-visualization-analysis">
   <title>Data Visualization and Analysis</title>
   <para>
    All &productmonitoring; user groups work with a
    graphical user interface that is seamlessly integrated into their cloud
    infrastructure. <phrase>Based on &ostack; Horizon, the user interface
    enables access to all monitoring functionality and the resulting large-scale
    monitoring data.</phrase>
   </para>
   <para>
    A comfortable dashboard visualizes the health and status of the cloud
    resources. It allows &productmonitoring; users
    to experiment with many ways of analyzing the performance of their cloud
    resources in real-time. They cannot only view but also share and explore
    visualizations of their monitoring data.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="alarms-notifications">
   <title>Alarms and Notifications</title>
   <para>
    &productmonitoring; supports GUI-based alarm and
    notification management. <phrase>Template-based alarm definitions allow for
    monitoring a dynamically changing set of resources without the need for
    reconfiguration. While the number of underlying virtual machines is changing,
    for example, this ensures the efficient monitoring of scalable cloud
    services. Alarm definitions allow you to specify expressions that are
    evaluated based on the metrics data that is received. Alarm definitions can
    be combined to form compound alarms. Compound alarms allow you to track and
    process even more complex events. Notifications can be configured in order to
    inform &productmonitoring; users when an alarm
    is triggered.</phrase>
   </para>
  </section>
</section>
