<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="user-dashboard-overview">
 <title>Using the Dashboard</title>
 <para>
  Often referred to as Horizon or the Horizon dashboard, you can use this
  console to manage resources on a domain and project level in a web-based
  graphical user interface (GUI).
 </para>
 <para>
  Horizon is the OpenStack service that serves as the basis for the &kw-hos;
  dashboards.
 </para>
 <para>
  The dashboards provide a web-based user interface to &kw-hos; services
  including Compute, Volume Operations, Networking, and Identity.
 </para>
 <section xml:id="access-horizon">
  <title>Accessing Horizon</title>
  <para>
   To access the Horizon dashboard as a non cloud administrator, you should ask
   the cloud admin for the host name or public IP address of the dashboard, and
   for your user name and password. If you are a cloud admin, you can determine
   the URL and credentials by following the steps in
   <xref linkend="cloudadmin-gui"/>.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    If you are authenticating against an external source such as an LDAP
    directory or via WebSSO you cannot change your password via the change
    password option in User settings.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   Along the left side of the Horizon user interface are sections that provide
   access to Project and Settings sections. If your login credentials have been
   assigned the 'admin' role you will also see a separate Admin section that
   provides additional system-wide setting options.
  </para>
  <para>
   Across the top are menus to switch between projects and menus where you can
   access user settings.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="browser-support-horizon">
  <title>Browser support for Horizon</title>
  <para>
   According to OpenStack.org, Horizon is tested and supported on the latest
   versions of Firefox and Chrome, and IE9+. Below is a summary of browser
   support for Horizon
  </para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Very good</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Very well tested; should work as expected
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term> Good</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Moderately tested; should look nice and work fine, may have a few visual
      issues
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Poor</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Visually inferior
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Broken</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Essential functionality not working
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>No</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Not supported
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <informaltable colsep="1" rowsep="1">
   <tgroup cols="3">
    <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
    <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
    <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
    <thead>
     <row>
      <entry>Browser</entry>
      <entry>Status</entry>
      <entry>Versions </entry>
     </row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <row>
      <entry>Chrome</entry>
      <entry>HPE Tested</entry>
      <entry>43.0.2357.81</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Firefox </entry>
      <entry>HPE Tested</entry>
      <entry>31+</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Firefox ESR</entry>
      <entry>HPE Tested</entry>
      <entry>31+</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Internet Explorer 11</entry>
      <entry>HPE Tested</entry>
      <entry>11.0.9600.18314</entry>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Internet Explorer 10</entry>
      <entry>Not HPE Tested</entry>
      <entry/>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Internet Explorer 9</entry>
      <entry>Not HPE Tested</entry>
      <entry/>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Internet Explorer 8 and below</entry>
      <entry>Not supported</entry>
      <entry/>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Safari</entry>
      <entry>Not HPE Tested</entry>
      <entry/>
     </row>
     <row>
      <entry>Opera</entry>
      <entry>Not HPE Tested</entry>
      <entry/>
     </row>
    </tbody>
   </tgroup>
  </informaltable>
  <note>
   <para>
    Please refer to the
    <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Horizon">OpenStack
    Dashboard ("Horizon") wiki</link> for additional compatibility and testing
    information.
   </para>
  </note>
  <para>
   At the bottom of this page, you can see some of the services you can manage
   right from the dashboard. Remember that Horizon runs over TLS so you will
   need to use the HTTPS protocol with your Horizon IP address.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="dashboard-limitations">
  <title>Dashboard Use</title>
  <para>
   As a Cloud or Domain admin of the &kw-hos; dashboard, you should follow the
   included recommendations for continued success with your cloud.
  </para>
  <important>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Do not create projects in the <emphasis>default</emphasis> domain. If you
      would like to create projects for your users, please create a new domain
      to host the new projects.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you are a Cloud admin, you may make changes to the
      <emphasis>default</emphasis> domain, however changes should be made from
      the command-line and not through the dashboard.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you are a Domain admin, you will need to modify the domain from the
      command-line and not from the dashboard.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </important>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="DashProject">
  <title>Project dashboard</title>
  <para>
   Use the <emphasis role="bold">Project</emphasis> dashboard to implement and
   build out your cloud. This dashboard contains tools to create virtual server
   instances, create and configure your network, configure access tools (such
   as key pairs and security groups) and cloud resource templates (stacks).
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="DashAdmin">
  <title>Admin dashboard</title>
  <para>
   Use the <emphasis role="bold">Admin</emphasis> dashboard to view, allocate,
   and manage all resources within the cloud.
  </para>
  <para>
   The Admin dashboard allows you to manage instances, define flavors, create
   and configure images, manage networks, view system resources, manage
   projects, and manage users.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="DashSettings">
  <title>Settings dashboard</title>
  <para>
   Use the <emphasis role="bold">Settings</emphasis> dashboard to change your
   display language and settings, your time zone, and your password.
  </para>
  <para>
   Click <emphasis role="bold">Settings</emphasis> in the user menu to display
   the Settings dashboard.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="login-dashboard">
  <title>Accessing the Dashboard</title>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Open a web browser that has both JavaScript and cookies enabled.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     In the address bar, enter the host name or IP address for the dashboard.
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      If a certificate warning appears when you try to access the URL for the
      first time, a self-signed certificate is in use. These certificates are
      not considered trustworthy by default. Verify the certificate or add an
      exception in the browser to bypass the warning. For information about
      managing certificates, see
      <xref linkend="idg-all-security-tls-config-xml-1"/>.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <emphasis role="bold">Log In</emphasis> page, enter your user name
     and password and then click <emphasis role="bold">Connect</emphasis>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The UserID with the <literal>admin</literal> role is provided with a
     special tab called Admin. The menu options underneath this tab are similar
     to the non-admin user views but cover all projects as well as some
     additional panels not available to general users.
    </para>
    <para>
     The Overview page provides a summary by project of the current utilization
     of major OpenStack resources. The information on this screen is drawn
     directly from the Compute or Nova service API and provides the ability to
     filter the query by date range and an option to download results into a
     CSV file that is compatible with Microsoft Excel or can be imported into a
     database.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     If you are a non-admin user, you will only be able to select a project
     from the list at the top of the screen.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="horizon-dashboard-examples">
  <title>Horizon Dashboard</title>
  <para>
   There are several services you can manage in the Horizon dashboard.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Viewing System Information</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   The <literal>System Information</literal> panel provides a list of all
   currently installed &ostack; services and their operation status.
  </para>
  <para>
   Additional panels on the <literal>System Information</literal> display
   sub-service status for services like Compute, Block Storage, and Network
   services. This are tabs for Compute Services, Block Storage Services,
   Network Agents, and Orchestration Services.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Managing Quotas</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   In the left hand menu, <menuchoice><guimenu>Admin</guimenu><guimenu>Systems</guimenu><guimenu>Defaults</guimenu></menuchoice> shows a list of
   Quota Names such as VCPUs, RAM, Instances, and storage. Click
   <guimenu>Update Defaults</guimenu> to manage Default Quotas.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Managing Routers</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   In the menu,
   <menuchoice><guimenu>Project</guimenu><guimenu>Network</guimenu><guimenu>Routers</guimenu></menuchoice>
   displays a list of routers. Routers connect end user networks together as
   well as to provide external connectivity. This panel shows all currently
   deployed routers and associated metadata. From here the system administrator
   can create, edit, and delete routers.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Managing Host Aggregates</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   Selecting <menuchoice><guimenu>Admin</guimenu><guimenu>Compute</guimenu><guimenu>Host Aggregates</guimenu></menuchoice> displays a list of host aggregates along
   with Availability Zones and Hosts. You can manage Host Aggregates in the
   <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> drop-down box.
  </para>
  <para>
   <emphasis role="bold">Hypervisor Status</emphasis>
  </para>
  <para>
   Selecting
   <menuchoice><guimenu>Admin</guimenu><guimenu>Compute</guimenu><guimenu>Hypervisors</guimenu></menuchoice>
   displays a view of total consumed resources, the hypervisors currently
   running, the physical server for each hypervisor instance, the type of
   hypervisor, and the infrastructure resources consumed by the hypervisor.
  </para>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Compute Host</guimenu> tab lists the currently configured
   physical hosts, the Availability Zone of each host, status, and a button to
   <guimenu>Disable Service</guimenu>.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="other-panels">
  <title>Other Panels</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The <emphasis role="bold">Updates and Extensions </emphasis>panel provides
     a list of available files that can be downloaded and installed. This view
     is also only available to UserIDs with the <literal>admin</literal> role.
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      Administrators should be cautious to ensure that Horizon Extensions
      they install come from a trusted source and/or have undergone
      appropriate review and testing. Administrators should be aware of the
      risk of spear phishing, by which they may receive an offer to install
      an apparently useful application which also performs malicious actions.
     </para>
    </note>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">Host aggregates </emphasis>are a grouping of
     physical servers or hosts with associated metadata. A host can belong to
     multiple aggregates.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Common use cases for host aggregates include supporting the scheduling of
     instances to a subset of hosts that have a specific capability or flavor
     such as a specific type of storage, lots of RAM, and/or large numbers of
     processors.
    </para>
    <para>
     Another use case of host aggregates is to support the arrangement of hosts
     into logical groups for load balancing and instance distribution. Host
     aggregates are configured and only viewable by system admins. The end user
     view of a host aggregate is called an Availability Zone. Availability
     zones are created via the Nova API and the host aggregates function. End
     users can use availability zones for similar use cases. For example, an
     application could be deployed on hosts in multiple availability zones. A
     load balancer can then be configured and the instances running each
     deployment of the application in each availability zone can be assigned to
     the load balancer thus providing a measure of failover and high
     availability support.
    </para>
    <para>
     Additional information on host aggregates and availability zones is
     available at
     <link xlink:href="http://blog.russellbryant.net/2013/05/21/availability-zones-and-host-aggregates-in-openstack-compute-nova/"/>
     and
     <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/openstack-ops/content/scaling.html"/>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">The Instances panel</emphasis> provides a view of
     all deployed end user instances across all projects, the images applied to
     those instances, the status of each instance, flavor type, and network
     information. This information is also supplied by the Nova API.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">The Volumes panel</emphasis> is displayed if the
     OpenStack Cinder service is available. Cinder provides block storage
     infrastructure. Block storage provides the ability for end users to attach
     storage as discrete drives to a compute instance. These drives are
     persistent and can be reassigned to a different instance. The Volumes tab
     on this view shows all currently created volumes and associated metadata
     and status, which physical host the volume is hosted on, and the ability
     for the admin to manage each volume.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">Flavors</emphasis> are virtual hardware templates.
     Flavors are used to define a virtual compute host. Flavors are assigned
     during the creation of a new instance. This panel displays all of the
     current flavor types and provides the ability for the admin to create,
     edit or delete flavors. Hosting organizations often use flavors as a form
     of billing unit; flavors with more resources are charged at a higher rate
     than flavors with fewer resources.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">Images</emphasis> are discrete software builds that
     can be loaded onto an instance. An image can be a standalone operating
     system implementation or a bundle of operating system and other
     pre-configured applications. This panel displays all currently available
     images and associated metadata and enables the system administrator to
     create, edit and delete images.
    </para>
    <important>
     <para>
      If you encounter the following error:
     </para>
<screen>ERROR: Unable to create new image. URL scheme not supported.</screen>
     <para>
      The error message indicates that the Glance service has not been
      configured to support the import of Glance images via the
      <emphasis>http</emphasis> option. This option can be enabled by your
      system administrator by enabling this function in the Glance
      configuration file.
     </para>
    </important>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">Networks</emphasis> are used by end users to provide
     connectivity to and between their deployed instances. This panel provides
     a list of all currently deployed networks and associated metadata and
     enables the system administrator the ability to created, edit, and delete
     networks.
    </para>
    <!-- Commented in DITA: -->
    <!-- Commenting out multi-region support content. This should be
    uncommented once multi-region support is available.
<p><keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> provides five VNIC types to use when creating network
ports: Normal, Direct, Direct Physical, MacVTap and Bare Metal.
<image href="../../media/horizon/VNIC-Types.png" id="VNICTypes"/></p>
-->
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">Quotas</emphasis> provide the means to limit
     resource usage. Quotas are assigned per project. This panel provides a
     view of all current quotas and enables a system administrator with the
     ability to edit quota line items.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">The Identity panel</emphasis> has two major panels.
     The Projects panel provides a list of all current projects and enables a
     system administrator the ability to create, modify, and delete panels and
     panel membership.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis role="bold">The Users panel</emphasis> is available only to
     system administrators and provides the ability to create, modify, and
     delete users. These users are considered "local" to Keystone and are
     authenticated by Keystone.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</chapter>
