<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet
 href="urn:x-daps:xslt:profiling:novdoc-profile.xsl" 
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "IGNORE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.user.dash">
 <title>Using &cloud; &dash;</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>Instances are virtual machines that run inside the cloud. To start
  an instance, you must have a virtual machine image that contains the following 
  information: which operating system to use, a user name and password with which 
  to log in to the &vmguest;, file storage etc. The cloud contains
  a pool of such images that have been uploaded and made
  accessible to members of different projects.  If 
  you want to make the virtual machine accessible from outside the
	cloud, you need to configure security groups. If needed, block storage
	devices (<literal>volumes</literal>) can be attached to a running
	instance (or detached and attached to another instance at any time).</para>
 </abstract>
 <para>
  <remark>taroth 2012-08-22: DEVs, I'm in the process of restucturing the chapter
  (moving topics around for a more logical order), I will fill the skeleton sections
  below with the respective contents tomorrow - feel free to answer any 
  DEVs questions in the meantime :)</remark>
 </para>

 <sect1 id="sec.user.dash.req">
  <title>Requirements</title>
  <para></para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.user.dash.intro">
  <title>&cloud; &dash;&mdash;Overview</title>
  <para></para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="sec.user.dash.img">
  <title>Managing Images</title>
  <para>
   Images cannot be added from the &cloud; &dash;, you need to use the
   command line tool <command>glance add</command> instead. For details,
   refer to <xref linkend="sec.adm.cli.img.upload"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.user.dash.inst.launch">
  <title>Launching Instances</title>
  <para>After images have been uploaded to Glance, you can launch instances
   that are based on those images. Upon start, you need to specify the following 
   key parameters:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>The <quote>size</quote> (<literal>flavor</literal>) of the virtual 
    machine.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>A keypair for SSH access of the instance. For details, refer to 
    <xref linkend="sec.user.dash.inst.access.keys"/>. In case an image uses a 
    static &rootuser; password or a static key set (neither is recommended), you 
    do not need to provide a keypair on start of the instance.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>A security group that the instance should belong to. Security groups 
    are a kind of cloud firewall that define which incoming network traffic should
    be forwarded to instances. For details, refer to 
    <xref linkend="sec.user.dash.inst.access.security"/>.</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <procedure id="pro.user.instances.launch">
   <title>Launching an Instance</title>
   <step>
    <para>Log in to &cloud; &dash;.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>If you are a member of multiple projects, select a <guimenu>Project</guimenu>
    from the drop-down list at the top of the tab.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Click the <guimenu>Images &amp; Snapshot</guimenu> category. The &dash;
     shows the <guimenu>Images</guimenu> that have been uploaded to Glance and
     are available for this project. 
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Select an image and click <guimenu>Launch</guimenu>.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>In the window that opens, specify the following:</para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>Enter a <guimenu>Server Name</guimenu> that will be assigned to the
       virtual machine.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>From the <guimenu>Flavor</guimenu> drop-down list, select the 
       <quote>size</quote> of the virtual machine to launch.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Select a <guimenu>Keypair</guimenu>.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>In <guimenu>Instance Count</guimenu>, enter the number of virtual 
      machines to launch from this image.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Activate the <guimenu>Security Groups</guimenu> that you want to
       assign to the instance. If you did not create any specific security groups,
       you can only assign the instance to the default security group.</para>
      <informalfigure>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
         <imagedata fileref="cloud_dash_launch_instance.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
         <imagedata fileref="cloud_dash_launch_instance.png" width="70%" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Click <guimenu>Launch Instance</guimenu>. The instance will be 
       started on any of the &compnode;s in the cloud. 
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>After you have launched an instance, switch to the <guimenu>Instances &amp;
  Volumes</guimenu> catgory view the <guimenu>Instance Name</guimenu>, its 
  (private or public) <guimenu>IP address</guimenu>, its <guimenu>Size</guimenu>,
  its <guimenu>Status</guimenu>, <guimenu>Task</guimenu>, and 
  <guimenu>Power State</guimenu>.</para>

  <figure>
   <title>&cloud; &dash;&mdash;List of Launched Instances</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="cloud_dash_instances_volumes.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="cloud_dash_instances_volumes.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para>
   <remark>taroth 2012-08-23: DEVs, is the following correct?</remark>
   If you did not provide a keypair on start and did not touch security groups
   or rules so far, by default the instance can only be accessed from inside the 
   cloud via VNC at this point. Eeven pinging the instance is not possible. To 
   change this, proceed with <xref linkend="sec.user.dash.inst.access"/>.</para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.user.dash.inst.access">
  <title>Configuring Access to the Instances</title>
  <para>For SSH access to an instance, you usually need to provide a keypair at
   launch time and to adjust the security rules. The default security
   rules block access to SSH ports and prevent pinging an instance. 
   To make the instance also accessible from outside the cloud, assign
   a floating (public) IP address.</para>

  <sect2 id="sec.user.dash.inst.access.keys">
   <title>Creating or Importing Keys</title>
   <para>Keypairs are SSH credentials that are injected into images when they are
    launched. Create at least one keypair per project. If you already generated
    a keypair with an external tool, you can import it into &ostack;. The keypair
    can be used for multiple instances belong to that project.</para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>Log in to &cloud; &dash;.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If you are a member of multiple projects, select a <guimenu>Project</guimenu>
    from the drop-down list at the top of the tab.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click the <guimenu>Access &amp; Security</guimenu> category. The &dash;
      shows <guimenu>Floating IPs</guimenu>, <guimenu>Security Groups</guimenu>, and
      <guimenu>Keypairs</guimenu> for the selected project.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>To import a keypair that you have generated with an external tool:</para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>Click <guimenu>Import Keypair</guimenu>.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>In the window that opens, enter a name for the keypair and
        copy the public key into the respective input field.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>Confirm your choice.</para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>To create a new keypair:</para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>Click <guimenu>Create Keypair</guimenu>.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>In the window that opens, enter a name for the keypair and confirm 
        your choice.</para>
       <para>&ostack; generates a keypair and provides the private key for 
       download as a <filename>*.pem</filename> file.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>Save the <filename>*.pem</filename> file locally and change its 
        permissions so that only you can read and write to the file:</para>
       <screen>chmod 600 <replaceable>MY_PRIV_KEY</replaceable>.pem</screen>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>The public key of the keypair is registered at the Nova database. The 
   &dash; lists the keypair in the <guimenu>Access &amp; Security</guimenu> 
   category as shown in <xref linkend="fig.cloud.dash.keylist"/>. </para>
   <figure id="fig.cloud.dash.keylist">
    <title>&cloud; &dash;&mdash;Keypairs</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="cloud_dash_access_security.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="cloud_dash_access_security.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.user.dash.inst.access.security">
   <title>Configuring Security Groups and Rules</title>
   <para>In &productname;, security groups are used to define which incoming 
    network traffic should be forwarded to instances. Security groups hold a set 
    of firewall policies (security goup rules).</para>
   <sect3 id="sec.user.dash.inst.access.security.groups">
    <title>Security Groups</title>

    <para> When launching an instance, you need to define which security groups 
    it should belong to. A default security group is available for each project. 
    It allows all network traffic from other members of this group and discards 
    traffic from other IP addresses and groups.</para>

    <para>Multiple security groups for a project can be defined, with each group 
    holding a different set of firewall policies. This is useful if you
    have groups of instances that should differ in firewall configuration (for example,
    front-end and back-end servers). An instance can be assigned to multiple 
    security groups.</para>
    <procedure id="pro.cloud.dash.security.groups">
     <title>Creating Or Deleting Security Groups</title>
     <step>
      <para>Log in to &cloud; &dash;.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>If you are a member of multiple projects, select a <guimenu>Project</guimenu>
    from the drop-down list at the top of the tab.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Click the <guimenu>Access &amp; Security</guimenu> category. The &dash;
      shows <guimenu>Floating IPs</guimenu>, <guimenu>Security Groups</guimenu>, and
      <guimenu>Keypairs</guimenu> for the selected project.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>To create a new security group:</para>
      <substeps>
       <step>
        <para>Click <guimenu>Create Security Group</guimenu>. 
       </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>In the window that opens, enter a <guimenu>Name</guimenu> and 
        <guimenu>Description</guimenu> for the group and confirm your changes.</para>
       </step>
      </substeps>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
      To delete one or multiple security groups:
     </para>
      <substeps>
       <step>
        <para>
        Activate the check boxes in front of the groups that you want to
        delete.
       </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>
        Click <guimenu>Delete Security Groups</guimenu> and confirm your choice in the
        pop-up that appears.
       </para>
        <para>
        A message on the Web page shows if the action has been successful.
       </para>
        <note>
         <title>Deleting Security Groups</title>
         <para>The default security group for a project cannot be deleted.</para>
         <para>
         In case another group cannot be deleted, it is still assigned to a
         running instance. To change that:
        </para>
         <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
           <para>Switch to the <guimenu>Instances &amp; Volumes</guimenu> category 
           to view instances that have been launched.
          </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
           <para>Click the instances' name links to view details such as the
           security group that is assigned to the respective instance.
          </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
           <para>Terminate the instance belonging to the security group that you 
          want to delete. Relaunch the instance and assign it to another security 
          group.</para>
          </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
        </note>
       </step>
      </substeps>
     </step>
    </procedure>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 id="sec.user.dash.inst.access.security.rules">
    <title>Security Group Rules</title>
    <para>You can adjust rules of the default security group as well as rules of
    any other security group that has been created. As soon as the rules for a 
    group are modified, the new rules are automatically applied to all running 
    instances belonging to that security group.</para>
    <para>Adjust the rules in a security group to allow access to instances via 
    different ports and protocols. This is necessary to be able to access instances
    via SSH, to ping them or to allow UDP traffic (for example, for an DNS server
    running on an instance.)</para>
    <para>Rules in security groups are specified by the following parameters:</para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Source of traffic</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Decide if to allow traffic to instances only from IP addresses 
       inside the cloud (from other group members) or from <emphasis>all</emphasis>
       IP addresses. <!-- IP subnet in CIDR notation)-->
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Protocol </term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Choose between TCP (for SSH), ICMP (for pings), or UDP.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Destination Port on Virtual Machine</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Define a port range. To open a single port only, enter the same value
       twice. ICMP does not support ports. In that case, enter values which define 
       the codes and types of ICMP traffic that should be allowed.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>If no further security groups have been created, any instances are 
     automatically assigned to the default security group (if not specified
     otherwise). Unless you change the rules for the default group, this means that
     those instances are only accessible from IP addresses belonging to other members 
     of this group. They cannot be accessed from any IP addresses outside.
     </para>
    <procedure id="pro.cloud.dash.security.rules">
     <title>Configuring Security Group Rules</title>
     <step>
      <para>Log in to &cloud; &dash;.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>If you are a member of multiple projects, select a <guimenu>Project</guimenu>
    from the drop-down list at the top of the tab.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Click the <guimenu>Access &amp; Security</guimenu> category. The &dash;
      shows <guimenu>Floating IPs</guimenu>, <guimenu>Security Groups</guimenu>, and
      <guimenu>Keypairs</guimenu> for the selected project.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
      Select the group to modify and click <guimenu>Edit Rules</guimenu>. The window 
      that appears shows which rules have already been configured. 
     </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>To allow SSH access to the instances:</para>
      <substeps>
       <step>
        <para>Set <guimenu>IP Protocol</guimenu> to <literal>TCP</literal>.</para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>Enter the value <literal>22</literal> in both
        <guimenu>From Port</guimenu> and <guimenu>To Port</guimenu>. </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>To allow access from <emphasis>all</emphasis> IP addresses (specified 
        as IP subnet in CIDR notation as <literal>0.0.0.0/0</literal>), leave the
        other fields unchanged.
       </para>
        <para>Alternatively, allow only IP addresses from other security groups
        to access the specified port. In that case, select the desired 
        security group from the <guimenu>CIDR</guimenu> drop-down list. </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>Confirm your changes to add the rule.</para>
       </step>
      </substeps>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To allow pinging the instances:</para>
      <substeps>
       <step>
        <para>Set <guimenu>IP Protocol</guimenu> to <literal>ICMP</literal>.
       </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>Enter the value <literal>-1</literal> in both <guimenu>From
        Port</guimenu> and <guimenu>To Port</guimenu>. This allows access to all 
        codes and all types of ICMP traffic, respectively.</para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>To allow access from <emphasis>all</emphasis> IP addresses 
        (<literal>0.0.0.0/0</literal>), leave the other fields unchanged.
       </para>
        <para>Alternatively, allow only members of other security groups to ping
        instances. In that case, select the desired security group from the 
        <guimenu>CIDR</guimenu> drop-down list.</para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>Confirm your changes to add the rule.</para>
       </step>
      </substeps>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>To allow access via UDP port (for example, for an DNS server
      running on a VM):</para>
      <substeps>
       <step>
        <para>Set <guimenu>IP Protocol</guimenu> to <literal>UDP</literal>.</para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>Enter the value <literal>53</literal> in both
        <guimenu>From Port</guimenu> and <guimenu>To Port</guimenu>. </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>To allow access from <emphasis>all</emphasis> IP addresses 
        (<literal>0.0.0.0/0</literal>), leave the other fields 
        unchanged.
       </para>
        <para>Alternatively, allow only IP addresses from other security groups
        to access the specified port. In that case, select the desired 
        security group from the <guimenu>CIDR</guimenu> drop-down list. </para>
       </step>
       <step>
        <para>Confirm your changes to add the rule.</para>
       </step>
      </substeps>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <figure>
     <title>&cloud; &dash;&mdash;Adding Security Rules</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="cloud_dash_sec_groups_add_rule.png" width="80%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="cloud_dash_sec_groups_add_rule.png" width="60%" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   
   <!--taroth 2012-08-15: mention when non-default sec groups are useful (info
    by mvidner, for CLI chapter mention how to change security groups for running 
    instances, info by cthiel: 
    sure, this is possible, but AFAIK only through the command-line:
    
    usage: nova add-secgroup <server> <secgroup>
    Add a Security Group to a server.
    
    Positional arguments:
    <server>    Name or ID of server.
    <secgroup>  Name of Security Group.
    
    
    usage: nova remove-secgroup <server> <secgroup>
    
    Remove a Security Group from a server.
    
    Positional arguments:
    <server>    Name or ID of server.
    <secgroup>  Name of Security Group.
   -->
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.user.dash.inst.access.ips">
   <title>Managing IP Addresses</title>
   <para>Each instance can have two IP addresses: a private and a public one. 
    Private IP addresses are used for communication between instances, public
    ones for communication with the outside world. When an instance is launched,
    it is automatically assigned a private IP address which stays the same
    until the instance is explicitly terminated.<remark>taroth 2012-08-22: DEVs: 
     does an instance also lose its private IP on reboot?</remark>
   </para>
   <para>From the pool of floating IPs available in &ostack; Nova, you can 
     allocate a number of floating IP address to a project (the limit is defined
     by the quota). Then you can add a floating IP address an instance of that
     project. Floating IP addresses can be dynamically 
    disassociated and associated with other instances at any time.
    <remark>taroth 2012-08-21: DEVs, whose task
     is it to create floating IPs in the first place? admin? operator? and is
     there more than the Nova pool to allocate IPs from?</remark>
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Allocating Floating (Public) IPs to a Project</title>
    <para>Before you can assign a floating IP address to an instance, you first 
     need to allocate floating IPs to a project.</para>
    <step>
     <para>Log in to &cloud; &dash;.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If you are a member of multiple projects, select a <guimenu>Project</guimenu>
    from the drop-down list at the top of the tab.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click the <guimenu>Access &amp; Security</guimenu> category. The &dash;
      shows a list of <guimenu>Floating IPs</guimenu>, <guimenu>Security Groups</guimenu>,
      and <guimenu>Keypairs</guimenu> for the current project. 
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>To allocate a floating IP address to the current project:</para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>Click <guimenu>Allocate IP to Project</guimenu>.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>In the window that opens, select a <guimenu>Pool</guimenu> out of 
        which to take the IP address.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>Click <guimenu>Allocate IP</guimenu>.</para>
       <para>The &dash; shows the allocated IP addresses in the <guimenu>Access &amp;
         Security</guimenu> category. The first IP shown for an instance is the 
         private IP address, the second one is the floating IP address.</para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      To release one or multiple floating IP addresses from a project:
     </para>
     <substeps>
      <step>
       <para>
        Activate the check boxes in front of the IP addresses that you want to
        release.
       </para>
      </step>
      <step>
       <para>Click <guimenu>Release Floating IPs</guimenu>. The IP addresses are
        put back into the pool of IP addresses that are available for all projects. 
        If an IP address is currently assigned to a running instance, 
        it will automatically be dissociated from the instance.</para>
      </step>
     </substeps>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure>
    <title>Assigning Floating (Public) IP Addresses to Instances</title>
    <para>After floating IP addresses have been allocated to
     the current project, you can assign them to running instances. One floating 
     IP address can be assigned to an instance at a time.</para>
    <step>
     <para>Log in to &cloud; &dash;.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If you are a member of multiple projects, select a <guimenu>Project</guimenu>
    from the drop-down list at the top of the tab.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click the <guimenu>Access &amp; Security</guimenu> category. The 
      &dash; shows a list of <guimenu>Floating IPs</guimenu>, 
      <guimenu>Security Groups</guimenu>, and <guimenu>Keypairs</guimenu> 
      for the current project. 
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select an IP address and click <guimenu>Associate IP</guimenu>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>In the window that opens, select the <guimenu>Instance</guimenu>
      to associate the IP with and confirm your choice.</para>
     <para>In the <guimenu>Access &amp; Security</guimenu> category, the list of 
      <guimenu>Floating IPs</guimenu> shows the ID of the instance with which
      the IP has been associated. The instance is now publically available under
      the respective floating IPs address (provided you have also configured 
      the security groups rules for the instance accordingly). For details,
      refer to <xref linkend="sec.user.dash.inst.access.security"/>.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="sec.user.dash.inst.manage">
  <title>Managing Instances</title>
  <para>The following are typical tasks for managing instances:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>Accessing instances from remote</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Viewing logs</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Creating instance snapshots to preserve a certain disk state of an
     instance</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Using instance snaphots as base for new images</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Rebooting or terminating instances</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Passing or suspending instances</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Using volumes for persistent storage</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect2 id="sec.user.dash.inst.manage.logs">
   <title>Viewing Instance Logs</title>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>Log in to &cloud; &dash;.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If you are a member of multiple projects, select a <guimenu>Project</guimenu>
    from the drop-down list at the top of the tab.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click the <guimenu>Instances &amp; Volumes</guimenu> category.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select the instance and from the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu>
      drop-down list, select <guimenu>View Log</guimenu>.</para>
     <para>Alternatively, click the instance's name and switch to the
      <guimenu>Log</guimenu> tab that opens.</para>
     <para>The &dash; shows the output of the instance's serial console. To make
      use of this feature, the respective image must have set the serial console
      correctly in &grub;.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.user.dash.inst.manage.remote">
   <title>Accessing Instances from Remote</title>
   <para>The &dash;'s built-in VNC client allows you to access instances
    at any time.</para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Accessing an Instance via VNC</title>
    <step>
     <para>Log in to &cloud; &dash;.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If you are a member of multiple projects, select a <guimenu>Project</guimenu>
    from the drop-down list at the top of the tab.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click the <guimenu>Instances &amp; Volumes</guimenu> category.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select the instance tho access and from the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu>
      drop-down list, select <guimenu>VNC Console</guimenu>.</para>
     <para>Alternatively, click the instance's name and switch to the
      <guimenu>VNC</guimenu> tab that opens.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>To display a larger VNC screen, use the link <guimenu>Click here
     to show only VNC</guimenu>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>To leave the large VNC screen, use the back button of the browser.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>

   <para>
    <remark>DEVs, is the following correct?</remark>
    To access an instance via SSH, the following requirements need to be 
    fulfilled:</para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>The security group which the instance is assigned to, must be configured
    to allow SSH access. For details, refer to 
    <xref linkend="sec.user.dash.inst.access.security"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>To allow SSH access from outside the cloud, a floating IP 
      address must be assigned to the instance. For details, refer to 
      <xref linkend="sec.user.dash.inst.access.ips"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>You must know the private or public IP address of the instance. To look
    it up, log in to &cloud; &dash;. On the <guimenu>Project</guimenu> tab, 
      switch to the <guimenu>Instances &amp; Volumes</guimenu> category. If only
      one IP address is shown for the instance, it is the private IP address (for
      communication inside the cloud). If a second IP address is shown, the second
      one is the public (floating) IP address.</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.user.dash.inst.manage.snapshots">
   <title>Using Instance Snapshots</title>
   <para>Snapshots preserve the disk state of a running instance. 
     <remark>taroth 2012-08-21: DEVs, if I got it right, ephemeral disks are 
      generally excluded from the snapshots?</remark> You can launch a new
     instance from a snapshot or use a snapshot to create a new image based upon 
     the snapshot. 
    </para>

   <procedure>
    <title>Creating Instance Snapshots</title>
    <step>
     <para>Log in to &cloud; &dash;.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If you are a member of multiple projects, select a <guimenu>Project</guimenu>
    from the drop-down list at the top of the tab.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click the <guimenu>Instances &amp; Volumes</guimenu> category.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select the instance for which to create a snapshot. From the
        <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> drop-down list, select
        <guimenu>Snapshot</guimenu>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>In the window that opens, enter a name for the snapshot and confirm your 
        changes. The &dash; shows the new <guimenu>Instance Snapshot</guimenu> 
        in the <guimenu>Images &amp; Snapshot</guimenu> category.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>To launch a new instance from the snapshot, select the snapshot and
      click <guimenu>Launch</guimenu>. Proceed with launching an instance as 
      described in <xref linkend="pro.user.instances.launch"/>.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure>
    <title>Basing an Image on a Snapshot</title>
    <step>
     <para>Log in to &cloud; &dash;.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If you are a member of multiple projects, select a <guimenu>Project</guimenu>
    from the drop-down list at the top of the tab.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click the <guimenu>Images &amp; Snapshots</guimenu> category.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select the snapshot and from the <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> drop-down 
        list, select <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>.
       </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>In the window that opens, enter the image properties.
        For more information, refer to <xref linkend="sec.adm.dash.img"/>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click <guimenu>Update Image</guimenu>. </para>
     <para>&dash; shows the newly created image in the list of images in the 
        <guimenu>Images &amp; Snapshot</guimenu> category. If you delete the 
        snapshot, upon which the image is based, the image will be deleted as 
        well. If you delete the image, the snapshot upon which it is based, will 
        be deleted as well.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.user.dash.inst.manage.terminate">
   <title>Pausing, Suspending, Rebooting or Terminating Instances</title>
   <para> For maintenance reasons, you can pause or suspend images&mdash;provided
   they are running on &kvm; or &xen;. Pausing or suspending avoids the consequences 
   that come with terminating or rebooting an instance.</para>
   <important>
    <title>Risk of Data Loss</title>
    <para>
     <remark>taroth 2012-08-21: DEVs, is the following correct?</remark>
      Terminating or rebooting an instance has the following consequences:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>All data on the image's root disk and ephemeral disks are destroyed.
        To prevent that, use volumes and attach them to an instance for 
        persistent storage.</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>If a floating IP address was assigned to that instance,
        the IP adress is disassociated from that image. However, it is still available
        in the pool of allocated IP addresses for the current project.</para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </important>

   <para>If you pause an instance, the content of the virtual machine is stored
     to memory (RAM) and the image is kept running in a <quote>frozen</quote>
     state. When suspending an instance, the contents of the virtual 
     machine is stored to disk and memory and vCPUS are freed.
    </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>Log in to &cloud; &dash;.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>If you are a member of multiple projects, select a <guimenu>Project</guimenu>
    from the drop-down list at the top of the tab.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click the <guimenu>Instances &amp; Volumes</guimenu> category.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select the instance which to put out of the running state. From the
      <guimenu>Actions</guimenu> drop-down list, select the respective action.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="sec.user.dash.inst.manage.volumes">
   <title>Using Volumes for Persistent Storage</title>
   <para></para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.user.dash.inst.manage.usage">
   <title>Tracking Usage</title>
   <para></para>
  </sect2>

 </sect1>






 <sect1 id="sec.user.dash.vol">
  <title>Managing Volumes</title>
  <para></para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
