<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet
 href="urn:x-daps:xslt:profiling:novdoc-profile.xsl" 
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "IGNORE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="cha.user.instances">
 <title>Launching and Managing Instances</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>Instances are virtual machines that run inside the cloud. To start
  an instance, you must have a virtual machine image that contains the following 
  information: which operating system to use, a user name and password with which 
  to log in to the &vmguest;, file storage etc. The cloud contains
  a pool of such images that cloud administrators have uploaded and made
  accessible to members of different projects. Apart from the image to use,
  you also need to specify the <quote>size</quote> of the VM to start 
  (called <literal>flavor</literal> in &ostack;) and to provide an SSH key. If 
  you want to make the virtual machine accessible from outside the
	cloud, you need to configure security groups. If needed, block storage
	devices (<literal>volumes</literal>) can be attached to a running
	instance (or detached and attached to another instance at any time).</para>
 </abstract>
 <!--taroth 2012-08-13-->
 <!--basic steps and tasks:
    * create keypair
    * configure security groups
    * launch instance
   [* log in to instance (SSH/VNC)] 
    * create volume
    * attach volume to instance/remove volume from instance
    * terminate/shut down instance
    -->
 <sect1 id="sec.user.instances.keys">
  <title>Creating or Importing Keys</title>
  <para>Before you can launch instances, you need to create a key pair. Keypairs
  are SSH credentials that are injected into images when they are launched.  
 </para>
  <procedure>
   <title>Creating a Keypair with the &cloud; &dash;</title>
   <para>
    <remark>taroth 2012-08-14: DEVs, do I need one keypair per project? or
   one keypair per image to launch?
   </remark>To allow login to an instance via SSH, create a keypair. If you have
   already created a keypair with an external tool, you can import it into
   &ostack;
   </para>
   <step>
    <para>Log in to &cloud; &dash; with your user name and password.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>If you are a member of multiple projects, select a project from the 
    drop-down list at the top of the <guimenu>Projects</guimenu>
    tab.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Click the <guimenu>Access &amp; Security</guimenu> category. The &dash;
    shows <guimenu>Floating IPs</guimenu>, <guimenu>Security Groups</guimenu>, and
    <guimenu>Keypairs</guimenu> for the selected project.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>To import a keypair that you have generated with an external tool:</para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>Click <guimenu>Import Keypair</guimenu>.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>In the window that opens, enter a name for the keypair and
    copy the public key into the respective input field.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Confirm your choice to make &ostack; register the public key at
      the Nova database.</para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>To create a new keypair:</para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>Click <guimenu>Create Keypair</guimenu>.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>In the window that opens, enter a name for the keypair and confirm 
      your choice.</para>
      <para>&ostack; generates a keypair and registers the public key at the Nova
    database. It provides the private key for download as a <filename>*.pem</filename>
    file.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Save the <filename>*.pem</filename> file locally and change its 
      permissions so that only you can read and write to the file:</para>
      <screen>chmod 600 <replaceable>MY_PRIV_KEY</replaceable>.pem</screen>
     </step>
    </substeps>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sec.user.instances.launch">
   <title>Launching an Instance</title>
   <para> After you have created or imported a keypair which is required for 
   launching an instance, you are now ready to launch an instance in the cloud. </para>
  </sect1>
 </chapter>
