<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_r3k_v2c_jt">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Allocating Proxy, Account, and Container
    (PAC) Servers for Object Storage</title>
  <body><!--not tested-->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    <p>A Swift proxy, account, and container (PAC) server is a node that runs the swift-proxy,
      swift-account and swift-container services. It is used to respond to API requests and to store
      account and container data. The PAC node does not store object data.</p>
    <p>This section describes the procedure to allocate PAC servers during the <b>initial</b>
      deployment of the system. </p>
    <section>
      <title>To allocate Swift PAC servers</title>
      <p>Perform the following steps to allocate PAC servers:</p>
    </section>
    <ul>
      <li>Verify if the example input model already contains a suitable server role. The server
        roles are usually described in the <codeph>data/server_roles.yml</codeph> file. If the
        server role is not described, you must add a suitable server role and allocate drives to
        store object data. For instructions, see <xref href="../../planning/objectstorage/creating_roles_swift_nodes.xml"
          >Creating Roles for Swift Nodes</xref> and <xref href="../../planning/objectstorage/allocating_disk_drives.xml"
          >Allocating Disk Drives.</xref></li>
      <li>Verify if the example input model has assigned a cluster to Swift proxy, account,
        container servers. It is usually mentioned in the <codeph>data/control_plane.yml</codeph>
        file. If the cluster is not assigned, then add a suitable cluster. For instructions, see
          <xref href="../../planning/objectstorage/creating_pac_cluster.xml">Creating a Proxy, Account, and Container (PAC)
          Cluster.</xref></li>
      <li>Identify the physical servers and their IP address and other detailed information.<ul
          id="ul_tzf_pqb_jt">
          <li>You add these details to the servers list (usually in the
              <codeph>data/servers.yml</codeph> file).</li>
          <li>As with all servers, you must also verify and/or modify the server-groups information
            (usually in <codeph>data/server_groups.yml</codeph>)</li>
        </ul></li>
    </ul>
    <p>The only part of this process that is unique to Swift is the allocation of disk drives for
      use by the account and container rings. For instructions, see <xref
        href="../../planning/objectstorage/allocating_disk_drives.xml#allocating-disk-drives">Allocating Disk Drives.</xref></p>
  </body>
</topic>
