<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="ironic-tls">
    <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>TLS Certificates with Ironic Python Agent (IPA) Images</title>
    
    <body>
        <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
        
        <p>As part of <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/>, Ironic Python Agent, better known as IPA in the OpenStack community, 
            images are supplied and loaded into glance.  Two types of image exist.  One is a traditional 
            boot ramdisk which is used by the agent_ipmitool, pxe_ipmitool, and pxe_ilo drivers.  The other is 
            an ISO image that is supplied as virtual media to the host when using the agent_ilo driver.
            </p>
        <p>
            As these images are built in advance, they are unaware of any private certificate authorities.  
            Users attempting to utilize self-signed certificates or a private certificate authority will need 
            to inject their signing certificate(s) into the image in order for IPA to be able to boot on a 
            remote node, and ensure that the TLS endpoints being connected to in <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> can be trusted.  This 
            is not an issue with publicly signed certificates.
            </p>
        <p>
            As two different types of images exist, below are instructions for disassembling the image 
            ramdisk file or the ISO image.  Once this has been done, you will need to re-upload 
            the files to glance, and update any impacted node's driver_info, for example  
            the deploy_ramdisk and ilo_deploy_iso settings that were set when the node was first defined.  Respectively, 
            this can be done with the 
            
<codeblock>           
ironic node-update &lt;node> replace driver_info/deploy_ramdisk=&lt;glance_id>
</codeblock>
            
            or 
 <codeblock>           
 ironic node-update &lt;node> replace driver_info/ilo_deploy_iso=&lt;glance_id>
</codeblock>
            
        </p>
        
        
    </body>
    
</topic>

