<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="ironic-node-config">
    <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Node Configuration</title>
    
    <body><!--not tested-->
        <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
        
<section>

    <title>DHCP</title>
    <p>Once booted, nodes obtain network configuration via DHCP.  If multiple interfaces are to be utilized, 
        a user may wish to pre-build images with settings to execute DHCP on all interfaces.  An easy utility 
        to build custom images is the <xref href="https://github.com/openstack/diskimage-builder" scope="external" format="html">diskimage-builder</xref> 
        utility which has a <xref href="https://github.com/openstack/diskimage-builder/tree/master/elements/dhcp-all-interfaces"  scope="external" format="html">dhcp-all-interfaces</xref> element that can 
        be utilized to initiate DHCP on all interfaces.</p>
    
    <p>The diskimage-builder tool does not support building UEFI images. The following patchset can be used to build UEFI images: 
        <xref href="https://review.openstack.org/#/c/287784" format="html" scope="external"/>
</p>
    
    </section>
        
        <section id="IRONIC-311">
            <title>Configuration Drives</title>
            
            <note type="caution">Configuration Drives are stored unencrypted and should not include any sensitive data. </note>
            
    <p>Users may wish to utilize 
        <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide/cli_config_drive.html"  scope="external" format="html">Configuration Drives</xref> 
        to store metadata for initial boot setting customization.  While Configuration Drives are extremely useful for 
        initial machine configuration, as a general security practice, they should not include any sensitive data. 
        Configuration Drives should only be trusted upon the initial boot of an instance. <codeph>cloud-init</codeph> utilizes a 
        lock file for this purpose. Custom instance images should not rely upon the integrity of a Configuration 
        Drive beyond the initial boot of a host as an administrative user with-in a deployed instance can potentially
        modify a configuration drive once written to disk and released for use.</p>
    
</section>
    </body>
</topic>
