<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.xml"> %entities; ]><!--Edit status: not edited-->
<section id="serverallocation">
   <title>
      <phrase/>Server Allocation</title>
        <para/>
        


    <para>The configuration processor allocates servers to a cluster or resource group in the
        following sequence:</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>Any <guilabel>servers</guilabel> that are persisted with a state of "allocated" are
            first returned to the <guilabel>cluster</guilabel> or <guilabel>resource
                group</guilabel>. Such servers are always allocated even if this contradicts the
            cluster size, failure-zones, or list of server roles since it is assumed that these
            servers are actively deployed.</para>
      </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>If the <guilabel>cluster</guilabel> or <guilabel>resource group</guilabel> is still
            below its minimum size, then any <guilabel>servers</guilabel> that are persisted with a
            state of "deleted", but where the server is now listed in the input model (i.e. the server
            was removed but is now back), are added to the group providing they meet the
            <guilabel>failure-zone</guilabel> and <guilabel>server-role</guilabel> criteria. If
            they do not meet the criteria then a warning is given and the
            <guilabel>server</guilabel> remains in a deleted state (i.e. it is still not allocated
            to any other cluster or group). These <guilabel>servers</guilabel> are not part of the
            current deployment, and so you must resolve any conflicts before they can be
            redeployed.</para>
      </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>If the <guilabel>cluster</guilabel> or <guilabel>resource group</guilabel> is still
            below its minimum size, the configuration processor will allocate additional
            <guilabel>servers</guilabel> that meet the <guilabel>failure-zone</guilabel> and
            <guilabel>server-role</guilabel> criteria. If the allocation policy is set to "strict"
            then the failure zones of servers already in the cluster or resource group are not
            considered until an equal number of servers has been allocated from each zone.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>


    </section>
