<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited--> 
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="manage_compute_instances">
    <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Managing Compute Hosts</title>
    <shortdesc>Operations Console (Ops Console) provides a graphical interface for you to add and
        delete compute hosts.</shortdesc>
    <body>
        <p>As your deployment grows and changes, you may need to add more compute hosts to increase
            your capacity for VMs, or delete a host to reallocate hardware for a different use. To
            accomplish these tasks, in previous versions of <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> you had to
            use the command line to update configuration files and run ansible playbooks. Now
            Operations Console (Ops Console) provides a graphical interface for you to complete the
            same tasks quickly using menu items in the console.</p>

        <note type="important"> Do not refresh the Ops Console page or open Ops Console in another
            window during the following tasks. If you do, you will not see any notifications or be
            able to review the error log for more information. This would make troubleshooting
            difficult since you would not know the error that was encountered, or why it
            occurred.</note>

        <p>Use Ops Console to perform the following tasks:</p>
        <ul>
            <li><xref type="section" href="#manage_compute_instances/ops_create_hosts">Create a
                    Compute Host</xref></li>
            <li><xref type="section" href="#manage_compute_instances/ops_deactivate">Deactivate a
                    Compute Host</xref></li>
            <li><xref type="section" href="#manage_compute_instances/ops_activate">Activate a
                    Compute Host</xref></li>
            <li><xref type="section" href="#manage_compute_instances/ops_delete">Delete a Compute
                    Host</xref></li>
        </ul>

        <note type="attention">In order to use Ops Console, you need to have the correct permissions
            and know the URL or VIP connected to Ops console during installation. For steps on how
            to complete these tasks, see <xref href="../opsconsole_overview.dita">Using the
                Operations Console.</xref></note>

        <section id="ops_create_hosts">
            <title>Create a Compute Host</title>
            <p>If you need to create additional compute hosts for more virtual machine capacity, you
                can do this easily on the Compute Hosts screen.</p>
            <p>To add a compute host:</p>
            <ol>
                <li>To open Operations Console, in a browser enter either the URL or Virtual IP
                    connected to Ops Console. <p>For
                    example:</p><codeblock>https://myhelion.test:9095
https://VIP:9095</codeblock></li>
                <li>On the <b>Home</b> screen, click the menu represented by 3 horizontal lines.
                        <image href="../../../media/opsconsole/OpsConsoleBurgerMenu.png"/></li>
                <li>From the menu that slides in on the left side, click <b>Compute</b>, and then
                        <b>Compute Hosts</b>.</li>
                <li>On the <b>Compute Hosts</b> page, click <b>Create Host</b>.</li>
                <li>On the <b>Add &amp; Activate Compute Host</b> tab that slides in from the right,
                    enter the following information: <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Host ID</dt>
                            <dd>HLM model's server ID</dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Host Role</dt>
                            <dd>Defined in the HLM model and cannot be modified in Ops Console</dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Host Group</dt>
                            <dd>Defined in the HLM model and cannot be modified in Ops Console</dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Host NIC Mapping</dt>
                            <dd>Defined in the HLM model and cannot be modified in Ops Console</dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Encryption Key</dt>
                            <dd>If the configuration is encrypted, enter the encryption key
                                here</dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl></li>
                <li>Click <b>Create Host</b>, and in the confirmation screen that opens, click
                        <b>Confirm</b>.</li>
                <li>Wait for Helion to complete the pre deployment steps. This process can take up
                    to 2 minutes.</li>
                <li>If pre-deployment is successful, you will see a notification that deployment has
                    started. <note type="attention">If you receive a notice that pre-deployment did
                        not complete successfully, read the notification explaining at which step
                        the error occured. You can click on the error notification and see the
                        ansible log for the configuration processor playbook. Then you can click
                            <b>Create Host</b> in step 4 again and correct the mistake.</note></li>
                <li>Wait for Helion to complete the deployments steps. This process can take up to
                    20 minutes.</li>
                <li>If deployment is successful, you will see a notification and a new entry will
                    appear in the compute hosts table.<note type="attention">If you receive a notice
                        that deployment did not complete successfully, read the notification
                        explaining at which step the error occured. You can click on the error
                        notification for more details.</note></li>
            </ol>
        </section>

        <section id="ops_deactivate">
            <title>Deactivate a Compute Host</title>
            <p>If you have multiple compute hosts and for debugging reasons you want to disable them
                all except one, you may need to deactivate and then activate a compute host. If you
                want to delete a host, you will also have to deactivate it first. This can be done
                easily in the Operations Console.</p>
            <note type="attention">The host must be in the following state: <b>ACTIVATED</b></note>
            <p>To deactivate a compute host:</p>
            <ol>
                <li>To open Operations Console, in a browser enter either the URL or Virtual IP
                    connected to Ops Console. <p>For
                    example:</p><codeblock>https://myhelion.test:9095
https://VIP:9095</codeblock></li>
                <li>On the <b>Home</b> screen, click the menu represented by 3 horizontal lines.
                        <image href="../../../media/opsconsole/OpsConsoleBurgerMenu.png"/></li>
                <li>From the menu that slides in on the left side, click <b>Compute</b>, and then
                        <b>Compute Hosts</b>.</li>
                <li>On the <b>Compute Hosts</b> page, in the row for the host you want to
                    deactivate, click the details button. <image
                        href="../../../media/opsconsole/DetailDots.png"/></li>
                <li>Click <b>Deactivate</b>, and in the confirmation screen that opens, click
                        <b>Confirm</b>.</li>
                <li>Wait for Helion to complete the operation. This process can take up to 2
                    minutes.</li>
                <li>If deactivation is successful, you will see a notification and in the compute
                    hosts table the <b>STATE</b> will change to <b>DEACTIVATED</b>. <note
                        type="attention">If you receive a notice that the operation did not complete
                        successfully, read the notification explaining at which step the error
                        occured. You can click on the link in the error notification for more
                        details. In the compute hosts table the <b>STATE</b> will remain
                            <b>ACTIVATED</b>.</note>
                </li>
            </ol>
        </section>
        <section id="ops_activate">
            <title>Activate a Compute Host</title>
            <note type="attention">The host must be in the following state:
                <b>DEACTIVATED</b></note>
            <p>To activate a compute host:</p>
            <ol>
                <li>To open Operations Console, in a browser enter either the URL or Virtual IP
                    connected to Ops Console. <p>For
                    example:</p><codeblock>https://myhelion.test:9095
https://VIP:9095</codeblock></li>
                <li>On the <b>Home</b> screen, click the menu represented by 3 horizontal lines.
                        <image href="../../../media/opsconsole/OpsConsoleBurgerMenu.png"/></li>
                <li>From the menu that slides in on the left side, click <b>Compute</b>, and then
                        <b>Compute Hosts</b>.</li>
                <li>On the <b>Compute Hosts</b> page, in the row for the host you want to activate,
                    click the details button. <image href="../../../media/opsconsole/DetailDots.png"
                    /></li>
                <li>Click <b>Activate</b>, and in the confirmation screen that opens, click
                        <b>Confirm</b>.</li>
                <li>Wait for Helion to complete the operation. This process can take up to 2
                    minutes.</li>
                <li>If activation is successful, you will see a notification and in the compute
                    hosts table the <b>STATE</b> will change to <b>ACTIVATED</b>. <note
                        type="attention">If you receive a notice that the operation did not complete
                        successfully, read the notification explaining at which step the error
                        occured. You can click on the link in the error notification for more
                        details. In the compute hosts table the <b>STATE</b> will remain
                            <b>DEACTIVATED</b>.</note>
                </li>
            </ol>
        </section>
        <section id="ops_delete">
            <title>Delete a Compute Host</title>
            <p>If you need to scale down the size of your current deployment to use the hardware for
                other purposes, you may want to delete a compute host.</p>
            <note type="attention">Complete the following steps before deleting a host: <ul>
                    <li>host must be in the following state: <b>DEACTIVATED</b></li>
                    <li>Optionally you can migrate the instance off the host to be deleted. To do
                        this, complete the following sections in the <xref
                            href="../maintenance/compute/remove_compute_node.dita">Removing
                            Hosts</xref> topic: <ol>
                            <li>Disable provisioning on the compute host.</li>
                            <li>Use live migration to move any instances on this host to other
                                hosts.</li>
                        </ol>
                    </li>
                </ul></note>
            <p>To delete a compute host:</p>
            <ol>
                <li>To open Operations Console, in a browser enter either the URL or Virtual IP
                    connected to Ops Console. <p>For
                    example:</p><codeblock>https://myhelion.test:9095
https://VIP:9095</codeblock></li>
                <li>On the <b>Home</b> screen, click the menu represented by 3 horizontal lines.
                        <image href="../../../media/opsconsole/OpsConsoleBurgerMenu.png"/></li>
                <li>From the menu that slides in on the left side, click <b>Compute</b>, and then
                        <b>Compute Hosts</b>.</li>
                <li>On the <b>Compute Hosts</b> page, in the row for the host you want to delete,
                    click the details button. <image href="../../../media/opsconsole/DetailDots.png"
                    /></li>
                <li>Click <b>Delete</b>, and if the configuration is encrypted, enter the encryption
                    key.</li>
                <li>in the confirmation screen that opens, click <b>Confirm</b>.</li>
                <li>In the compute hosts table you will see the <b>STATE</b> change to
                        <b>Deleting</b>.</li>
                <li>Wait for Helion to complete the operation. This process can take up to 2
                    minutes.</li>
                <li>If deletion is successful, you will see a notification and in the compute hosts
                    table the host will not be listed. <note type="attention">If you receive a
                        notice that the operation did not complete successfully, read the
                        notification explaining at which step the error occured. You can click on
                        the link in the error notification for more details. In the compute hosts
                        table the <b>STATE</b> will remain <b>DEACTIVATED</b>.</note>
                </li>
            </ol>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>For More Information</title>
            <p>For more information on how to complete these tasks through the command line, see the
                following topics:</p>
            <ul>
                <li><xref href="../maintenance/compute/add_hpelinux_compute.dita">Increasing
                        Capacity by Adding Nodes</xref></li>
                <li><xref href="../maintenance/compute/remove_compute_node.dita">Removing
                        Nodes</xref></li>
            </ul>
        </section>
    </body>
</topic>
