<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="time_series_graphs">
    <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Time Series Graphs</title>
    <abstract><shortdesc outputclass="hdphidden">This page allows you to define charts that display data based on the metrics and
        parameters you choose.</shortdesc></abstract>
    <body>
        <p>Charts and graphs provide a quick way to visualize large amounts of complex data. It is
            especially useful when trying to find relationships and understand your data, which
            could include thousands or even millions of variables. You can create a new chart in
            Operations Console from <b>My Dashboard</b>.</p>
        
        <p>The charts in Operations Console are based on Monasca data. When you create a new chart
            you will be able to select the time range and the metric you want to chart. The list of
            Metrics you can choose from is equivalent to using the <b>monasca metric-name-list</b>
            on the command line. After you select a metric, you can then specify a dimension, which
            is derived from the <b>monasca metric-list –name &lt;metric_name&gt;</b> command line
            results. The dimension list changes based on the selected metric. </p>
        <section id="ops_create_charts">
            <title>Create a Chart</title>
            <p>Create a chart to visually display data for up to 6 metrics over a period of time.</p>
            <p>To create a chart:</p>
            <ol>
                <li>On the <b>My Dashboard</b> screen, select <b>Create New Chart</b>.</li>
                <li>On the <b>Add New Time Series Chart</b> screen, in <b>Chart
                    Definition</b>complete any of the optional fields: <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Name</dt>
                            <dd>Short description of chart.</dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Time Range</dt>
                            <dd>Specifies the interval between metric collection. The default is
                                <b>1 hour</b>. Can be set to hours (1,2,4,8,24) or days
                                (7,30,45).</dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Chart Update Rate</dt>
                            <dd>Collects metric data and adds it to the chart at the specified
                                interval. The default is <b>1 minute</b>. Can be set to minutes
                                (1,5,10,30) or 1 hour.</dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Chart Type</dt>
                            <dd>Determines how the data is displayed. The default type is
                                <b>Line</b>. Can be set to the following values: <ul>
                                    <li><image href="../../../media/opsconsole/LineChartIcon.png"/>
                                        Line</li>
                                    <li><image href="../../../media/opsconsole/BarChartIcon.png"/>
                                        Bar</li>
                                    <li><image href="../../../media/opsconsole/StackedBarIcon.png"
                                    />Stacked Bar</li>
                                    <li><image href="../../../media/opsconsole/AreaIcon.png"
                                    />Area</li>
                                    <li><image href="../../../media/opsconsole/AreaStackedIcon.png"
                                    />Stacked Area </li>
                                </ul></dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Chart Size</dt>
                            <dd>This controls the visual display of the chart width as it appears on
                                <b>My Dashboard</b>. The default is <b>Small</b>. This field can
                                be set to <b>Small</b> to display it at 50% or <b>Large</b> for
                                100%.</dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl><note type="note">None of these fields require that you change the
                        defaults. Only the <b>Metric</b> and <b>Function</b> fields in the <b>Chart
                            Data</b> section are required. It is recommended that you at least
                        create a name to identify the chart.</note></li>
                <li>On the <b>Add New Time Series Chart</b> screen, in <b>Added Chart
                    Data</b>complete the following fields: <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Metric</dt>
                            <dd>In Monasca, a metric is a multi-dimensional description that
                                consists of the following fields: name, dimensions, timestamp, value
                                and value_meta. The pre-populated list is equivalent to using the
                                    <b>monasca metric-name-list</b> on the command line.</dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Dimension</dt>
                            <dd> The set of unique dimensions that are defined for a specific
                                metric. Dimensions are a dictionary of key-value pairs. This
                                pre-populated list is equivalent to using the <b>monasca metric-list
                                    –name &lt;metric_name&gt;</b> on the command line.</dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Function</dt>
                            <dd>Operations Console uses Monasca to provide the results of all
                                mathematical functions. Monasca in turns uses Graphite to perform
                                the mathematical calculations and return the results. The default is
                                    <b>AVG</b>. The <b>Function</b> field can be set to <b>AVG</b>
                                (default), <b>MIN</b>, <b>MAX</b>. and <b>COUNT</b>. For more
                                information on these functions, see the <xref
                                    href="http://www.aosabook.org/en/graphite.html"  
                                    format="html">Graphite</xref> documentation.</dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl><note type="note">Only the <b>Metric</b> and <b>Function</b> fields are
                        required. You will not be able to click <b>Add Data to Chart</b> until these
                        options are selected.</note></li>
                <li>Click <b>Add Data To Chart</b>. To add another metric to the chart, repeat the previous step until all metrics are added. The maximum you can have in one chart is 6 metrics. </li>
                <li>To create the chart, click <b>Create New Chart</b>.</li>
            </ol>
            
            <p>After you click <b>Create New Chart</b>, you will be returned to My Dashboard where the new chart will be shown. From the My Dashboard screen you can use the menu beside each chart to delete or edit the chart. You can also select an option to create a comma-delimited file of the data in the chart.</p>
        </section>
    </body>  
</topic>
