<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="concept_controlplanes_regions">
    <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Control Planes and Regions</title>
    <body><!--not tested-->
        <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
        
    <section>
    <p>A region in OpenStack terms is a collection of URLs that together provide a consistent set of services
        (Nova, Neutron, Swift, etc). Regions are represented in the Keystone identity service
        catalog and clients can decide which region they want to use.</p>
    <p>For the owner of a cloud, regions provide a way of segmenting resources for scale,
        resilience, and isolation.<!-- However, each region needs some resources for its
        <uicontrol>control-plane</uicontrol>.--></p>
        
        <sectiondiv  audience="INTERNAL">  
    <p>Regions don't have to be disjointed; for example, you can have a Swift service shared
        across more than one region, in which case the Swift URL for both regions will be the same 
        and any region-specific services will use the same Swift instance.
        
        However, not all services can be shared in this way.  
        For example, a Neutron service cannot be used by more 
        than one Nova and so these will generally be deployed 
        as region specific services, provided from separate control-planes.   
        
        Equally in <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>, Mysql and RabbitMQ cannot be shared by more than one 
        instance of the same service (for example a single mysql cluster cannot 
        be used by two different instances of Nova, and so these are also 
        deployed on a per-control basis. </p>
        
        <p>In the input model, each region is defined as a set of services 
        drawn from one or more control-planes.  All of the following are valid mappings 
        of control-planes to regions:</p>
            
        <image href="../../../../media/inputmodel/multi-region.png"/>            
        
     </sectiondiv>  
     
        <p>In a simple single control-plane cloud,  there is no need for a separate region definition 
            and the control-plane itself can define the region name.</p>
    <!--<p>Thus in the cloud model we say that a <uicontrol>control-plane</uicontrol> may provide some
        or all of the endpoints for one or more Regions.</p>-->
    </section>
        
    </body>
</topic>


