<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="concept_virtual_machines_as_servers">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Virtual Machines as Servers </title>
  <body><!--not tested-->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    
    <section>
      <p>Starting in <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/>, servers can be configured as hypervisors which host 
        virtual machines that are can be defined, instantiated and configured as servers for hosting 
        <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> services.  Both the hypervisors and the VMs are treated as “servers” 
        within the input model with additional attributes to define the relationship.</p>
      
      <p>To define a hypervisor in the input model:</p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>Set the attribute <codeph>hlm-hypervisor: true</codeph> for the server.</li>
        <li>Define how network groups that are needed by the VMs will be mapped to the 
          hypervisor’s interfaces by adding <codeph>passthrough-network-groups</codeph> to the interface model of the hypervisor.</li>
        
      </ul>
      
      <p>To define a virtual machine server in the input model:</p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>Create a server object that includes the <codeph>hypervisor-id</codeph> attribute.  
          This indicates that the server is a virtual machine, and also identifies 
          the physical server that will host the VM.</li>
        <li>Specify virtual machine CPU sizing information in the server’s CPU model.</li>
        <li>Specify virtual machine memory sizing information in the server’s memory model.</li>
        <li>Specify virtual machine disk sizing information in the server’s disk model.</li>
        <li>Specify the virtual machine’s network devices in the server’s nic-mappings object.</li>
        
      </ul>
      
      <p>Given the above information, <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> will configure the hypervisors 
        and create thea virtual machines running the HPE Linux operating system.  Subsequent configuration 
        of the virtual machine’s operating system, and installation and configuration of <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> 
        services on that virtual machine server, use the same lifecycle management mechanisms as physical servers.</p>
      
      
      <p>Note that a hypervisor can still be used to run <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>  services, so for example 
        a server can be both running VMs (that in turn are running API services, MySQL, etc) and also be running services 
        that are better not virtualized such as Swift, VSA, etc.</p>
      
    </section>
    
    
  </body>
</topic>
