<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="DCN_integration">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>DCN Integration with Multisite Support for
    Neutron</title>
  <body>

    <section>
      <title>HPE Distributed Cloud Networking (DCN) capabilities in <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"
        /></title>
      <p>HPE Distributed Cloud Networking (DCN) is network overlay software that enables network 
        virtualization both within data centers and between them.
        <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> allows you to use DCN as your networking.
        This choice is an all-or-nothing option in that you cannot use traditional networking in
          <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> if you choose to use DCN.</p>
      <p product="HOS">For that reason, and others, you cannot upgrade an existing installation of
          <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> to <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> with DCN. The network
        configuration you had previously will not work. Therefore, to use DCN, you must install
          <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> as a new deployment, and follow the steps outlined in
        these documents.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Features not available when DCN is deployed</title>
      <p>Because of the foundational differences between DCN networks and traditional networking,
        when DCN is running in <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>, these features are not deployed:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Neutron openvswitch-agent </li>
        <li>Neutron DHCP agent </li>
        <li>Neutron L3 or VPN agents </li>
        <li>Neutron Metadata-agent </li>
        <li>Neutron LBAAS, LBAASv2 agents</li>
      </ul><note>DCN has a neutron-server component (DCN-ML2 or DCN-CORE-PLG), VRS and a
        medatata-agent (which are essentially replacements for neutron OVS, L3, and DHCP, and
        metadata agents).</note>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Notes about deploying DCN in <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/></title>
      <ol>
        <li>Neutron-server must be running with either the Nuage mechanism driver (DCN-ML2) or the
          core-plugin (DCN-CORE-PLG). DCN-ML2 is preferred. </li>
        <li>VRS with the Nuage metadata-agent and VRS-G. VRS runs on compute nodes, VRS-G runs on a
          standalone node. </li>
        <li>(Optional): Virtualized services controller (VSC) There are two ways to have VSC(s) 
          deployed, one via playbooks and another via bringing up the provided VSC VM disk image.
        </li>
        <li>The <xref href="DCN_ml2.xml#DCN_ml2/DCN_downloads">external components</xref> you must
          download will need to be "staged" for deployment into <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> using the
            <xref href="DCN_ml2.xml#DCN_ml2/download_instructions">third-party import
            mechanism.</xref> The third-party import playbook does the staging. </li>
        <li>After running the third-party import playbook, <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> needs to be
          configured for DCN. </li>
        <li>Run configuration processor </li>
        <li>(Optional) If VSC is to be deployed via playbooks, you will need to perform additional 
          configuration steps and run the configuration processor again.
        </li>
        <li>Run the standard <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> steps to deploy. 
        </li>
      </ol>
      <note>Additional steps are required if VSC is deployed via playbooks. See next section for details.</note>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
