<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: ready for edit (Carter)-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="UsingVPNaaS">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Using VPN as a Service (VPNaaS)</title>
  <body>
    <!--not tested-->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    <p><b><keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> VPNaaS Configuration</b></p>
    <p>This document describes the configuration process and requirements for the <keyword
        keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> Virtual Private Network (VPN) as a Service module.</p>
    <p>
      <ul id="LBaaSlist">
        <li><xref href="vpnaas.xml#UsingVPNaaS/Prerequisites">Prerequisites</xref></li>
        <li><xref href="vpnaas.xml#UsingVPNaaS/Considerations">Considerations</xref></li>
        <li><xref href="vpnaas.xml#UsingVPNaaS/Configuration">Configuration</xref></li>
        <!--<li><xref href="vpnaas.xml#UsingVPNaaS/Troubleshooting">Troubleshooting</xref></li>-->
        <li><xref href="vpnaas.xml#UsingVPNaaS/MoreInfo">More Information</xref></li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <section id="Prerequisites">
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      <ol>
        <li><keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> must be installed. </li>
        <li>Before setting up VPNaaS, you will need to have created an external network and a subnet
          with access to the internet. Information on how to create the external network and subnet
          can be found in the <xref href="vpnaas.xml#UsingVPNaaS/MoreInfo"> More Information</xref>
          section of this document.</li>
        <li>You should assume 172.16.0.0/16 as the ext-net CIDR in this document.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section id="Considerations">
      <title>Considerations</title>
      <p>Using the Neutron plugin-based VPNaaS causes additional processes to be run on the Network
        Service Nodes. One of these processes, the ipsec charon process from StrongSwan, runs as
        root and listens on an external network. A vulnerability in that process can lead to remote
        root compromise of the Network Service Nodes. If this is a concern customers should consider
        using a VPN solution other than the Neutron plugin-based VPNaaS and/or deploying additional
        protection mechanisms. </p>
    </section>

    <section id="Configuration">
      <title>Configuration</title>
      <sectiondiv>
        <b>Setup Networks</b>
        <p>You can setup VPN as a Service (VPNaaS) by first creating networks, subnets and routers
          using the <codeph>neutron</codeph> command line. The VPNaaS module enables the ability to
          extend access between private networks across two different <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>
          clouds or between a <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> cloud and a non-cloud network. VPNaaS is
          based on the open source software application called StrongSwan. StrongSwan (more
          information available at<xref href="http://www.strongswan.org/" format="html"
             >http://www.openswan.org</xref>) is an IPsec implementation and provides
          basic VPN gateway functionality.</p>
        <note>You can execute the included commands from any shell with access to the service APIs.
          In the included examples, the commands are executed from the lifecycle manager, however
          you could execute the commands from the controller node or any other shell with
          aforementioned service API access. </note>
        <note>The use of floating IP's is not possible with the current version of VPNaaS when DVR
          is enabled. Ensure that no floating IP is associated to instances that will be using
          VPNaaS when using a DVR router. Floating IP associated to instances are ok when using CVR
          router.</note>
        <ol>
          <li>From the lifecycle manager, create first private network, subnet and router assuming
            that <i>ext-net</i> is created by
            admin.<codeblock>neutron net-create privateA
neutron subnet-create --name subA privateA 10.1.0.0/24 --gateway 10.1.0.1
neutron router-create router1
neutron router-interface-add router1 subA
neutron router-gateway-set router1 ext-net</codeblock></li>
          <li>Create second private network, subnet and router.
            <codeblock>neutron net-create privateB
neutron subnet-create --name subB privateB 10.2.0.0/24 --gateway 10.2.0.1
neutron router-create router2
neutron router-interface-add router2 subB
neutron router-gateway-set router2 ext-net</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv id="StartVirtualMachines">
        <b>Start Virtual Machines</b>
        <ol>
          <li>From the lifecycle manager run the following to start the virtual machines. Begin with
            adding secgroup rules for SSH and ICMP.
            <codeblock>neutron security-group-rule-create default --protocol icmp
neutron security-group-rule-create default --protocol tcp --port-range-min 22 --port-range-max 22</codeblock></li>
          <li>Start the virtual machine in the privateA subnet. Using <i>nova images-list</i>, use
            the image id to boot image instead of the image name. After executing this step, it is
            recommended that you wait approximately 10 seconds to allow the virtual machine to
            become active.
            <codeblock>NETA=$(neutron net-list | awk '/privateA/ {print $2}')
nova boot --flavor 1 --image &lt;id&gt; --nic net-id=$NETA vm1</codeblock></li>
          <li>Start the virtual machine in the privateB subnet. <codeblock>NETB=$(neutron net-list | awk '/privateB/ {print $2}')
nova boot --flavor 1 --image &lt;id&gt; --nic net-id=$NETB vm2</codeblock>
            </li>
          <li>Verify private IP's are allocated to the respective vms. Take note of IP's for later
            use. <codeblock>nova show vm1
nova show vm2</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <b>Create VPN</b>
        <ol>
          <li>You can set up the VPN by executing the below commands from the lifecycle manager or
            any shell with access to the service APIs. Begin with creating the policies with
              <codeph>vpn-ikepolicy-create</codeph> and <codeph>vpn-ipsecpolicy-create </codeph>.
            <codeblock>neutron vpn-ikepolicy-create ikepolicy
neutron vpn-ipsecpolicy-create ipsecpolicy</codeblock></li>
          <li>Create the VPN service at router1.
            <codeblock>neutron vpn-service-create --name myvpnA --description "My vpn service" router1 subA</codeblock></li>
          <li>Wait at least 5 seconds and then run <codeph>ipsec-site-connection-create</codeph> to
            create a ipsec-site connection. Note that <codeph>--peer-address</codeph> is the assign
            ext-net IP from router2 and <codeph>--peer-cidr</codeph> is subB cidr.
            <codeblock>neutron ipsec-site-connection-create --name vpnconnection1 --vpnservice-id myvpnA \
--ikepolicy-id ikepolicy --ipsecpolicy-id ipsecpolicy --peer-address 172.16.0.3 \
--peer-id 172.16.0.3 --peer-cidr 10.2.0.0/24 --psk secret</codeblock></li>
          <li>Create the VPN service at router2.
            <codeblock>neutron vpn-service-create --name myvpnB --description "My vpn serviceB" router2 subB </codeblock></li>
          <li>Wait at least 5 seconds and then run <codeph>ipsec-site-connection-create</codeph> to
            create a ipsec-site connection. Note that <codeph>--peer-address</codeph> is the
            assigned ext-net IP from router1 and <codeph>--peer-cidr</codeph> is subA cidr.
            <codeblock>neutron ipsec-site-connection-create --name vpnconnection2 --vpnservice-id myvpnB \
--ikepolicy-id ikepolicy --ipsecpolicy-id ipsecpolicy --peer-address 172.16.0.2 \
--peer-id 172.16.0.2 --peer-cidr 10.1.0.0/24 --psk secret</codeblock></li>
          <li>On the lifecycle manager, run the <codeph>ipsec-site-connection-list</codeph> command
            to see the active connections. Be sure to check that the vpn_services are ACTIVE. You
            can check this by running <codeph>vpn-service-list</codeph> and then checking
            ipsec-site-connections status. You should expect that the time for both vpn-services and
            ipsec-site-connections to become ACTIVE could take as long as 1 to 3 minutes.
            <codeblock>neutron ipsec-site-connection-list
+--------------------------------------+----------------+--------------+---------------+------------+-----------+--------+
| id                                   | name           | peer_address | peer_cidrs    | route_mode | auth_mode | status |
+--------------------------------------+----------------+--------------+---------------+------------+-----------+--------+
| 1e8763e3-fc6a-444c-a00e-426a4e5b737c | vpnconnection2 | 172.16.0.2   | "10.1.0.0/24" | static     | psk       | ACTIVE |
| 4a97118e-6d1d-4d8c-b449-b63b41e1eb23 | vpnconnection1 | 172.16.0.3   | "10.2.0.0/24" | static     | psk       | ACTIVE |
+--------------------------------------+----------------+--------------+---------------+------------+-----------+--------+</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <b>Verify VPN</b>
        <p>In the case of non-admin users, you can verify the VPN connection by pinging the virtual
          machines.</p>
        <ol>
          <li>Check the VPN connections. <note>vm1-ip and vm2-ip denotes private IP's for vm1 and
              vm2 respectively. The private IP's are obtained from step 4 under <xref
                href="vpnaas.xml#UsingVPNaaS/StartVirtualMachines">Start Virtual Machines</xref>
              section. If you are unable to SSH to the private network due to a lack of direct
              access, the VM console can be accessed through Horizon.</note>
            <codeblock>ssh cirros@vm1-ip
password: &lt;password&gt;
            
# ping the private IP address of vm2
ping ###.###.###.###</codeblock></li>
          <li>In another terminal.
            <codeblock>ssh cirros@vm2-ip
password: &lt;password&gt;
              
# ping the private IP address of vm1
ping ###.###.###.###</codeblock></li>
          <li>You should see ping responses from both virtual machines.</li>
        </ol>
        <p>As the admin user, you should check to make sure that a route exists between the router
          gateways. Once the gateways have been checked, packet encryption can be verified by using
          traffic analyzer (tcpdump) by tapping on the respective namespace (qrouter-* in case of
          non-DVR and snat-* in case of DVR) and tapping the right interface (qg-***). </p>
        <note>When using DVR namespaces, all the occurrences of qrouter-xxxxxx in the following
          commands should be replaced with respective snat-xxxxxx.</note>
        <ol>
          <li>Check the if the route exists between two router gateways. You can get the right
            qrouter namespace id by executing <i>sudo ip netns</i>. Once you have the qrouter
            namespace id, you can get the interface by executing <i>sudo ip netns qrouter-xxxxxxxx
              ip addr</i> and from the result the interface can be
            found.<codeblock>sudo ip netns
sudo ip netns exec qrouter-&lt;router1 UUID&gt; ping &lt;router2 gateway&gt;
sudo ip netns exec qrouter-&lt;router2 UUID&gt; ping &lt;router1 gateway&gt;</codeblock></li>
          <li>Initiate a tcpdump on the interface.
            <codeblock>sudo ip netns exec qrouter-xxxxxxxx tcpdump -i qg-xxxxxx</codeblock></li>
          <li>Check the VPN connection.
            <codeblock>ssh cirros@vm1-ip
password: &lt;password&gt;
              
# ping the private IP address of vm2
ping ###.###.###.###</codeblock></li>
          <li>Repeat for other namespace and right tap interface.
            <codeblock>sudo ip netns exec qrouter-xxxxxxxx tcpdump -i qg-xxxxxx</codeblock></li>
          <li>In another terminal.
            <codeblock>ssh cirros@vm2-ip
password: &lt;password&gt;
              
# ping the private IP address of vm1
ping ###.###.###.###</codeblock></li>
          <li>You will find encrypted packets containing ‘ESP’ in the tcpdump trace.</li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>

    <!-- Preserving the section in case we need to add Troubleshooting back in. 
    <section id="Troubleshooting">
      <title>Troubleshooting</title>
      <p>You can use the following information here for assistance with troubleshooting the VPNaaS service. </p>

    </section>
    -->

    <section id="MoreInfo">
      <title>More Information</title>
      <p>VPNaaS currently only supports Pre-shared Keys (PSK) security between VPN gateways. A
        different VPN gateway solution should be considered if stronger, certificate-based security
        is required.</p>
      <p>For more information on the neutron command-line interface (CLI) and VPN as a Service
        (VPNaaS), see the OpenStack networking command-line client reference: <xref
          href="http://docs.openstack.org/cli-reference/content/neutronclient_commands.html"
            format="html"/></p>
      <p>For information on how to create an external network and subnet, see the OpenStack manual:
          <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide/dashboard_create_networks.html"
            format="html"/>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
