<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.1">
  <title>Overview</title>
  <section>
    <title>Objectives</title>
    <para>The Ceilometer project was started in 2012 with one simple goal in mind: to
                provide an infrastructure to collect any information needed regarding
                OpenStack projects. It was designed so that rating engines could use this
                single source to transform events into billable items which we
                label as “metering”.</para>
    <para>As the project started to come to life, collecting an
                <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/ceilometer/latest/contributor/measurements.html">increasing number of meters</link> across multiple projects, the OpenStack
                community started to realize that a secondary goal could be added to
                Ceilometer: become a standard way to meter, regardless of the
                purpose of the collection. This data can then be pushed to any set of targets
                using provided publishers mentioned in pipeline-publishers section.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Metering</title>
    <para>If you divide a billing process into a 3 step process, as is commonly done in
                the telco industry, the steps are:</para>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>
          <xref linkend="term-metering"/>
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          <xref linkend="term-rating"/>
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          <xref linkend="term-billing"/>
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>Ceilometer’s initial goal was, and still is, strictly limited to step
                one. This is a choice made from the beginning not to go into rating or billing,
                as the variety of possibilities seemed too large for the project to ever
                deliver a solution that would fit everyone’s needs, from private to public
                clouds. This means that if you are looking at this project to solve your
                billing needs, this is the right way to go, but certainly not the end of the
                road for you.</para>
  </section>
</section>
