<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="upgradeto50">
  <title>Upgrade to <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-50"/></title>
  <body>
    <!--<p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>-->
    <section id="about">
      <title>Performing the Upgrade from <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-40"/> to <keyword
          keyref="kw-hos-phrase-50"/></title>
      <note type="warning">The process for upgrading from <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-40"/> to
          <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-50"/> requires a reboot. It also requires that you <b>do
          not make any configuration changes before the upgrade</b>. Config changes must only be
        made after the upgrade process is complete. </note>
      <p>When upgrading from <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-40"/> to <keyword
          keyref="kw-hos-phrase-50"/> you will use the same configuration files in your
          <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud/definition</codeph> directory as you used when originally
        installing the software.</p>
      <p>The configuration you specified will remain unchanged through the upgrade process;
          <b>however</b>, if you made any configuration changes by passing parameters to any Ansible
        playbooks using the <codeph>-e</codeph> option, you should find the affected files and make
        the required changes directly in the files in <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud</codeph> and commit
        them to the git repository so that those changes are tracked and applied during the upgrade
        process. Otherwise they will not be applied after the upgrade.</p>
      <p> After the upgrade process has completed, the Cinder Volume and Backup services will by
        default run on the first node in the Cinder Volume host group. To migrate these services to
        a different node follow the instructions in <xref
          href="../operations/blockstorage/managing_cinder_volumebackup_services.xml">Managing
          Cinder Volume and Backup Services</xref>. </p>
      <p>You may also install <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-50"/> as a full install. Those
        instructions are found in the installation guide. See <xref
          href="../installation/installation_overview.xml">Installation Overview</xref> for
        details. If you choose to do a fresh install it is important that you completely wipe your
        disks prior to doing the installation, otherwise errors may occur.</p>
    </section>



    <section id="prereqs"><title>Prerequisites</title>
      <p>These steps assume you have an installed and working <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-40"/>
        cloud.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="mainSteps"><title>Upgrade Overview</title>
      <p>To perform the upgrade, the workflow will look something like this:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Run the upgrade to apply updates to all nodes in the cloud (including the node hosting
          the lifecycle manager itself), as per instructions below.</li>
        <li>Reboot all of the nodes in your cloud in order to take in the new kernel changes
          introduced in <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-50"/>. Instructions on rebooting your cloud
          nodes are provided below.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>


    <section id="upgradesteps"><title>Upgrade Instructions</title>
      <ol>
        <li>Get status of all your services, if desired <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts hlm-status.yml</codeblock>
          <p>If status comes back bad for any service, run the service reconfigure playbook, with
            naming convention <codeph>&lt;service>-reconfigure.yml</codeph>, for that service, then
            run the status playbook for that service and see if the issue is resolved.</p>
          <p>The status playbooks have this naming convention:</p>
          <codeblock>&lt;service>-status.yml</codeblock>
          <p>A full list is included at the end of this document.</p></li>

        <li>Sign in and download the <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-50"/> product and signature
          files at the links below: <ol>
            <li><xref href="http://www.hpe.com/software/entitlements" format="html"  
                >Software Entitlement Portal</xref></li>
            <!-- <li><xref
                href="https://helion.hpwsportal.com/catalog.html#/Category/%7B%22categoryId%22%3A10389%7D/Show"
                format="html"  >HPE Helion OpenStack Files</xref>
            </li>
            <li><xref
                href="https://helion.hpwsportal.com/catalog.html#/Category/%7B%22categoryId%22%3A10507%7D/Show"
                format="html"  >HPE Helion OpenStack Signature Files</xref></li>-->
          </ol></li>
        <li>You can verify the download was complete via the signature verification process outlined
            <xref
            href="https://h20392.www2.hpe.com/portal/swdepot/displayProductInfo.do?productNumber=HPLinuxCodeSigning"
              format="html">here</xref>.</li>

        <li>To begin the upgrade process, log in to the lifecycle manager as the user you created
          during the <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-40"/> deployment, and mount the install media at
            <codeph>/media/cdrom</codeph>; for example:
          <codeblock>sudo mount HelionOpenStack-5.0.iso /media/cdrom</codeblock></li>


<!-- NEED THE NAME OF THE TAR FILE USED TO INSTALL HOS 5.0 -->


        <li>Unpack the following tarball: 
          <codeblock>cd ~
tar faxv /media/cdrom/hos/hos-5.0.0-20161014T020249Z.tar</codeblock></li>

        <li>Run the included initialization script to update the deployer: <codeblock>~/hos-5.0.0/hos-init.bash</codeblock>
          <note type="important">If you encounter a code merge error, please see 
            <xref keyref="upgrade_git_merge"/>. After
            git merge conflicts have been resolved, please repeat step #6 to re-run
            hos-init.bash</note>
        </li>
        <!--
        <li>If you have made any changes to your configuration files, ensure that you commit them to
          your local git and if any merge conflicts are reported, you must resolve them before
          proceeding (See the article on how to <xref keyref="upgrade_git_merge">Resolve any Merge
            Conflicts</xref>):
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion
git add –A
git commit –m "My changes"</codeblock>
        </li>-->

        <!--<li>Note, if you want to install the Rados Gateway service, you must do so AFTER the upgrade
          completes. At that point you can follow the instructions in <xref
            href="../operations/maintenance/ceph/add_ceph_rados_node.xml#add_monitor_node"/></li>-->

        <li id="config">Run the configuration processor:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Update your deployment
            directory:<codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</codeblock><p><!--Removed step to comment out eon-upgrade.yml, per DOCS-2938--></p></li>



        <li>Run the upgrade playbook (required for all models/deployments): <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts hlm-upgrade.yml</codeblock>
        </li>
        
        <!--<li><b>ESX - additional step:</b> Once the upgrade is complete, skip to the <xref
            href="upgrade21to30.xml#upgradeto30/esx">Further ESX Model Upgrade Instructions</xref>
          section.</li>-->
      </ol>
    </section>


    <!--<section id="bnx2x" conkeyref="knownissues30/bnx2x"/>-->

    <section id="rebooting_general"><title>Rebooting Your Nodes</title>
      <p>To complete the upgrade and for Linux for HPE Helion updates to take effect, you must
        reboot all your nodes. The instructions for rebooting controller, compute, and storage nodes
        are found below. Note that you should follow the order prescribed for each type of
        deployment, for example, Swift, VSA, or Ceph.</p>
      <p>Expand the sections below for those instructions.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="expandCollapse">
      <sectiondiv outputclass="expandall">Expand All</sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="collapseall">Collapse All</sectiondiv>
    </section>
    <section id="generalOrder">
      <title outputclass="headerH">Recommended Node Reboot Order</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection"><p>To ensure that rebooted nodes reintegrate into the
          cluster, the key is having enough time between controller reboots. </p> The recommended
        way to achieve this is as follows: <ol>
          <li>Reboot controller nodes one-by-one with a suitable interval in between. If you
            alternate between controllers and compute nodes you will gain more time between the
            controller reboots. </li>
          <li>Reboot of compute nodes (if present in your cloud).</li>
          <li>Reboot of Swift nodes (if present in your cloud).</li>
          <li>Reboot of VSA nodes (if present in your cloud)</li>
          <li>Reboot of Ceph nodes (if present in your cloud).</li>
          <li>Reboot of ESX nodes (if present in your cloud).</li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv></section>
    <section id="rebootControllers"><title outputclass="headerH">Rebooting Controller Nodes</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection">
        <p><b>Migrate Singleton Services First</b></p>
        <p>The first consideration before rebooting any controller nodes is that there are a few
          services that run as singletons (non-HA), thus they will be unavailable while the
          controller they run on is down. Typically this is a very small window, but if you want to
          retain the service during the reboot of that server you should take special action to
          maintain service, such as migrating the service.</p>
        <p>For these steps, if your singleton services are running on controller1 and you move them
          to controller2, then ensure you move them back to controller1 before proceeding to reboot
          controller2.</p>
        <p><b>For the <codeph>cinder-volume</codeph> singleton service:</b></p>
        <p>Execute the following command on each controller node to determine which node is hosting
          the cinder-volume singleton. It should be running on only one node: </p>
        <codeblock>ps auxww | grep cinder-volume | grep -v grep</codeblock>
        <p>Run the <codeph>cinder-migrate-volume.yml</codeph> playbook - details about the Cinder
          volume and backup migration instructions can be found in <xref
            href="../operations/blockstorage/managing_cinder_volumebackup_services.xml#topic_l1p_vpy_jt"
            >Managing Cinder Volume and Backup Services</xref>.</p>
        <p><b>For the <codeph>nova-consoleauth</codeph> singleton service:</b></p>
        <p>The <codeph>nova-consoleauth</codeph> component runs by default on the first controller
          node, that is, the host with <codeph>consoleauth_host_index=0</codeph>. To move it to
          another controller node before rebooting controller 0, run the ansible playbook
            <codeph>nova-start.yml</codeph> and pass it the index of the next controller node. For
          example, to move it to controller 2 (index of 1), run:
          <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts nova-start.yml --extra-vars "consoleauth_host_index=1"</codeblock></p>
        <p><b>Reboot the Controllers</b></p> In order to reboot the controller nodes, you must first
        retrieve a list of nodes in your cloud running control plane services. <codeblock>for i in $(grep -w cluster-prefix ~/helion/my_cloud/definition/data/control_plane.yml | awk '{print $2}'); do grep $i ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible/hosts/verb_hosts | grep ansible_ssh_host | awk '{print $1}'; done</codeblock>
        <p>Then perform the following steps from your lifecycle manager for each of your controller
          nodes:</p>
        <ol>
          <li>If any singleton services are active on this node, they will be unavailable while the
            node is down. If you want to retain the service during the reboot, you should take
            special action to maintain the service, such as migrating the service as appropriate as
            noted above.</li>
          <li>Stop all services on the controller node that you are rebooting first:
            <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts hlm-stop.yml --limit &lt;controller node></codeblock></li>
          <li>Reboot the controller node, e.g. run the following command on the controller itself: <codeblock>sudo reboot</codeblock>
            <p>Note that the current node being rebooted could be hosting the lifecycle manager.</p>
          </li>
          <li>Wait for the controller node to become ssh-able and allow an additional minimum of
            five minutes for the controller node to settle. Start all services on the controller
            node:
            <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts hlm-start.yml --limit &lt;controller node></codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>Verify that the status of all services on that is OK on the controller node:
            <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts hlm-status.yml --limit &lt;controller node></codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>When above start operation has completed successfully, you may proceed to the next
            controller node. Ensure that you migrate your singleton services off the node
            first.</li>
        </ol>
        <note>It is important that you not begin the reboot procedure for a new controller node
          until the reboot of the previous controller node has been completed successfully (i.e. the
          hlm-status playbook has completed without error). </note>
        <note>If your system includes VSA nodes, rebooting a controller node will not re-start CMC
          as it is Java application. You will need to restart it.</note>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>

    <section id="rebootCompute"><title outputclass="headerH">Rebooting Compute Nodes</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection">
        <p>To reboot a compute node the following operations will need to be performed:</p>
        <ul>

          <li>Disable provisioning of the node to take the node offline to prevent further instances
            being scheduled to the node during the reboot. </li>
          <li>Identify instances that exist on the compute node, and then either: <ul>
              <li>Live migrate the instances off the node before actioning the reboot. OR </li>
              <li>Stop the instances</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>Reboot the node </li>
          <li>Restart the Nova services </li>
          <li>Restart any instances stopped above</li>
        </ul>
        <ol>
          <li>Disable provisioning:
            <codeblock>nova service-disable --reason "&lt;describe reason>" &lt;node name> nova-compute</codeblock>If
            the node has existing instances running on it these instances will need to be migrated
            or stopped prior to re-booting the node.</li>
          <li> Live migrate existing instances. Identify the instances on the compute node. Note:
            The following command must be run with nova admin
            credentials.<codeblock>nova list --host &lt;hostname&gt; --all-tenants</codeblock></li>
          <li>Migrate or Stop the instances on the compute node. <p>If your instance is booted from
              a volume and has any number of Cinder volume attached, use the <codeph>nova
                live-migration</codeph>
            command:</p><codeblock>nova live-migration &lt;instance uuid&gt; [&lt;target compute host&gt;]</codeblock>
            If your instance has local (ephemeral) disk(s) only, you can use the --block-migrate
            option:<codeblock>nova live-migration --block-migrate &lt;instance uuid&gt; [&lt;target compute host&gt;]</codeblock>Note:
            The [&lt;target compute host&gt;] option is optional. If you do not specify a target
            host then the nova scheduler will choose a node for you.<p>If your instances have a mix
              of ephemeral and block storage then live migration will not work and you can use the
                <codeph>nova stop</codeph> command:</p><p>Stop the instances on the node by running
              the following command for each of the
              instances:</p><codeblock>nova stop &lt;instance-uuid&gt;</codeblock><p>For more
              details about live migration, see <xref
                href="../operations/maintenance/live_migration.xml"/>.</p></li>
          <li>Stop all services on the Compute node:
            <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts hlm-stop.yml --limit &lt;compute node></codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>SSH to your Compute nodes and reboot them: <codeblock>sudo reboot</codeblock>
            <p>The operating system cleanly shuts down services and then automatically reboots. If
              you want to be very thorough, run your backup jobs just before you reboot.</p>
          </li>
          <li>Run the hlm-start.yml playbook from the lifecycle manager. If needed, use the
            bm-power-up.yml playbook to restart the node. Specify just the node(s) you want to start
            in the 'nodelist' parameter arguments, i.e.
            nodelist=&lt;node1&gt;[,&lt;node2&gt;][,&lt;node3&gt;].<codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost bm-power-up.yml -e nodelist=&lt;compute node></codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>Execute the <b>hlm-start.yml </b>playbook. Specifying the node(s) you want to start in
            the 'limit' parameter arguments. This parameter accepts wildcard arguments and also
            '@&lt;filename>' to process all hosts listed in the file.
            <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts hlm-start.yml --limit &lt;compute node></codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>Re-enable provisioning on the node:
            <codeblock>nova service-enable &lt;node-name> nova-compute</codeblock></li>
          <li> Restart any instances you
            stopped.<codeblock>nova start &lt;instance-uuid></codeblock>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>

    <section id="rebootSwift"><title outputclass="headerH">Rebooting Swift Nodes</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection"><p>If your Swift services are on controller node,
          please follow the controller node reboot instructions above.</p>
        <p id="firstp">For a dedicated Swift PAC cluster or Swift Object resource node: </p>For each
        Swift host <ol>
          <li>Stop all services on the Swift node:
            <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts hlm-stop.yml --limit &lt;swift node></codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>Reboot the Swift node by running the following command on the Swift node itself:
            <codeblock>sudo reboot</codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>Wait for the node to become ssh-able and then start all services on the Swift node:
            <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts hlm-start.yml --limit &lt;swift node> </codeblock>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>
    <section id="vsa"><title outputclass="headerH">Rebooting VSA Nodes</title><sectiondiv
        outputclass="insideSection">
        <p>If your cloud is deployed with VSA, then the reboot sequence will be as follows:</p>
        <ol>
          <li>Identify all VSA nodes of a given cluster </li>
          <li>Pick one of the VSA nodes of the cluster and reboot it manually</li>
          <li>Check VSA VM's status :
            <codeblock>ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts vsa-status.yml --limit &lt;vsa_node name></codeblock></li>
          <li>Wait for VSA to come up, Check cluster status using CMC ( status should be
            "normal")</li>
          <li>Run the following command from your first controller node which will open the HP
            StoreVirtual Centralized Management Console (CMC) GUI <codeblock>/opt/HP/StoreVirtual/UI/jre/bin/java -jar /opt/HP/StoreVirtual/UI/UI.jar </codeblock>
            <p>If you are unable to access the CMC utility, you should verify the port you access it
              with this command:</p>
            <codeblock>netstat -anp | grep vnc</codeblock>
            <p>If that does not resolve the issue, you may need to restart the VNC server with this
              command:</p>
            <codeblock>vnc4server</codeblock></li>
          <li>To view the cluster status , go to: management group -&gt; click on the respective
            cluster -&gt; check for status</li>
          <li>Repeat steps 2-4 for the other remaining nodes of the same VSA cluster. </li>
          <li>Go to step 1 and repeat all steps for the other clusters.</li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>

    <section id="reboot_ceph"><title outputclass="headerH">Rebooting Ceph</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection">
        <!--Note that Ceph has two components: <ul>
          <li>monitor nodes</li>
          <li>OSD nodes</li>
        </ul> If a monitor is deployed on controller node, then the rebooting sequence of the
        controller takes precedence over monitor nodes. You should reboot the group of nodes in
        specified order. For a given group (say controller or compute or VSA or ceph OSD etc),
        reboot should be done one-by-one, in series. For example, if there are three OSD nodes say
        OSD1, OSD2, OSD3 then you should reboot OSD1 and then OSD2 and so on.<ol>
          <li>Controller node (reboot of this will take care of the monitor as well) </li>
          <li>Compute node </li>
          <li>Standalone storage or dedicated storage, including: <ul>

              <li>VSA</li>
              <li>Ceph OSD</li>
              <li>Ceph monitor (if deployed on stand alone node). If monitor is deployed on
                controller node then rebooting sequence of controller takes precedence over monitor
                nodes.</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ol>More commonly, the monitor is deployed as a standalone; i.e., as separate set of
        resource nodes. In this case the reboot sequence will be: <ol>
          <li>Controller node </li>
          <li>Compute node </li>
          <li>Ceph monitor node </li>
          <li>Ceph OSD nodes </li>
        </ol> -->
        <p>There are two categories of ceph nodes:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>monitor nodes</li>
          <li>OSD nodes</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Ceph nodes should be rebooted in their position in the overall sequence described in the
          reboot order section above.</p>
        <p>You should reboot both categories of ceph nodes in the order: monitor nodes, then OSD
          nodes. All ceph nodes should reboot one-by-one, in series. </p> If a monitor is deployed
        on controller node, then the rebooting sequence of the controller caters for the monitor
        nodes, so you need to additionally reboot only the OSD nodes. <p>If the monitor is deployed
          as a standalone; i.e., as separate set of resource nodes, you should reboot the monitor
          nodes before rebooting the OSD nodes.</p> For example, if there are three monitor nodes
        and three OSD nodes say, MON1, MON2 and MON3, with OSD1, OSD2, OSD3, then you should reboot
        MON1, then MON2 and then MON3 followed by OSD1, then OSD2 and so on In both cases, please
        ensure that you are serializing the reboot of a given family (monitor or OSD or controller);
        that is, don't reboot them all at the same time. This will ensure that each service is up
        and running and there is no impact on the client side. To reboot Ceph nodes, follow the
        sequence below to safely reboot the entire Ceph cluster: <ol>
          <li>Reboot a Ceph monitor node in the cluster. </li>
          <li>Once the monitor node comes up, wait for a minute and then execute the following
            command:
            <codeblock>ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts ceph-status.yml --limit &lt;monitor-hostname></codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>If the above playbook executes successfully, repeat from step 1 to reboot the next
            Ceph monitor node in the cluster. </li>
          <li>Once all the monitor nodes have been rebooted, execute
            <codeblock>ceph quorum_status </codeblock>on a monitor node and ensure that all the
            monitors have joined the quorum by observing that in the output, the "quorum_names"
            section lists all the monitors in the Ceph cluster. </li>
          <li>Login to the OSD node to be rebooted and execute the following command to avoid the
            cluster rebalancing itself: <codeblock>ceph osd set noout</codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>Stop all the OSD services on the current node by executing below command:
            <codeblock>sudo systemctl stop  ceph-osd@*</codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>Now reboot the OSD node. </li>
          <li>Once the OSD node is up, log in and execute the following command and observe that a
            line similar to "osd.0 192.17.11.7:6801/3824 boot" appears for all the OSDs on the node:
            <codeblock>ceph -w</codeblock> To quit, this command press Ctrl + C </li>
          <li>Verify that all the OSDs on this node are 'up' by executing following command (and
            observing that all the OSDs under the current host are reported as 'up')
            <codeblock>ceph osd tree</codeblock> If any of the OSDs are reported as 'down', please
            check the logs for the corresponding OSD (in the
              <codeph>/var/log/ceph/&lt;cluster-name>-osd.&lt;osd_number>.log</codeph> file) for
            resolving the issue. </li>
          <li>Now execute the following command from the re-booted OSD node, to unset the cluster
            from noout : <codeblock>ceph osd unset noout</codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>Execute the following playbook from the lifecycle manager node to check the status of
            the OSDs that have just come up:
            <codeblock>ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts ceph-status.yml --limit &lt;OSD-hostname></codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>If the above playbook does not report any errors, repeat from step 5 for another Ceph
            OSD node in the cluster. </li>
          <li>Once the entire cluster is rebooted, execute this command
            <codeblock>ceph health detail</codeblock> to ensure that you see HEALTH_OK. </li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>
    <section><title outputclass="headerH">Rebooting OVSvApp</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection">
        <p>After upgrade, execute the following commands to restart the OVSvApp VM.</p>
        <ol id="ol_ibp_zh3_px">
          <li>Stop all services on the OVSvApp
            node.<codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts hlm-stop.yml --limit &lt;ovsvapp nodes></codeblock></li>
          <li>SSH to your OVSvApp nodes and reboot them.<codeblock>sudo reboot</codeblock></li>
          <li>Execute the <codeph>hlm-start.yml</codeph> playbook. Specify the node(s) you want to
            start in the 'limit' parameter arguments.
            <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts hlm-start.yml --limit &lt;ovsvapp nodes></codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv></section>

    <section id="checkVersion"><title outputclass="headerH">Checking Version Updates</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection">
        <p>To check the Linux for HPE Helion version run from the lifecycle manager node to any
          other node via its IP address:</p>
        <codeblock>ssh &lt;IP_address> uname -a</codeblock> The output should be:
        <codeblock>Linux helion-cp1-c1-m2-mgmt 4.4.7-1-amd64-hpelinux #hpelinux1 SMP Thu Apr 14 13:21:49 UTC 2016 x86_64 GNU/Linux</codeblock>
        To check to see if a node has been successfully updated on a control plane node, run from
        the lifecycle manager node to any other node via its IP address: :
        <codeblock>ssh &lt;IP_address> cat /etc/HP_Helion_version | grep Helion</codeblock> The
        output should look like this:
        <codeblock>HPE Helion OpenStack hos-3.0.0 (build 01-1017)</codeblock>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>



    <section id="esx"><title outputclass="headerH">Further ESX Model Upgrade Instructions</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection">
        <p>Once you have completed the initial upgrade instructions, you must follow these
          additional steps for ESX deployments:</p>
        <p>Check exsiting ESX Compute:</p>
        <ol>
          <li>Verify existing ESX computes can be seen by EON and are activated.
            <codeblock>eon resource-list
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+
ID	Name	Moid	Resource Manager ID	IP Address	Port	Type	State
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+
fdf19467-e7a1-496f-81e5-bcb07bc6e564	Compute-02	domain-c9949	70be00c8-691b-43af-b757-e67e4b11425c	UNSET	UNSET	esxcluster	activated
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+</codeblock>
          </li>
        </ol>
        <p>Activate New ESX Compute Cluster</p>
        <ol>
          <li>After upgrade, download the new <codeph>activationtemplate.json</codeph> file for a
            new cluster
            activation.<codeblock>eon get-activation-template [--filename &lt;ACTIVATION_JSON_NAME&gt;] --type &lt;RESOURCE_TYPE&gt;</codeblock></li>
          <li>Fill the appropriate details in the <codeph>activationtemplate.json</codeph>
            file.</li>
          <li>Activate the new cluster on an already-activated Data center (DC) or a new Data center
            can be performed with the following command:<p>
              <codeblock>eon resource-activate &lt;RESOURCE_ID> --config-json &lt;activate-template></codeblock>
            </p><p><b>Example:</b>
            </p><p>
              <codeblock>eon resource-activate 9ab2196d-37d2-4006-a2c7-08946b5194ea --config-json activate-template.json</codeblock>
            </p><p><!--Added resorce-activate step, per DOCS-2938--></p></li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>

    <section id="magnum_upgrade">
      <title outputclass="headerH">Adding Magnum After Upgrade</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection">
        <p>Adding Magnum after the upgrade of <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-40"/> to <keyword
            keyref="kw-hos-phrase-50"/> can be found in the document, <xref
            keyref="install_magnum/install_magnum_existing"/>.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>
        

    <section id="getStatus">
      <title outputclass="headerH">Get List of Status Playbooks</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection">
        <p>Running the following command will yield a list of status playbooks:</p>
        <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ls *status*</codeblock> Here is the list:
        <codeblock>stack@helion-control-plane-cluster1-m1-mgmt:~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible$ ls *status*
barbican-status.yml       heat-status.yml              monasca-status.yml
bind-status.yml           hlm-pre-upgrade-status.yml   neutron-status.yml
bm-power-status.yml       hlm-status.yml               nova-status.yml
ceilometer-status.yml     hlm-ux-services-status.yml   octavia-status.yml
_ceph_cluster_status.yml  horizon-status.yml           ops-console-status.yml
ceph-status.yml           hos-extra-status.yml         percona-status.yml
cinder-status.yml         ironic-status.yml            powerdns-status.yml
cmc-status.yml            keystone-status.yml          rabbitmq-status.yml
designate-status.yml      kronos-api-status.yml        sherpa-status.yml
eon-status.yml            logging-producer-status.yml  swift-status.yml
FND-AP2-status.yml        logging-server-status.yml    vsa-status.yml
FND-CLU-status.yml        logging-status.yml           zookeeper-status.yml
freezer-status.yml        memcached-status.yml
glance-status.yml         monasca-agent-status.yml
</codeblock>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>
    <p outputclass="hostarget"/>
  </body>
</topic>
