<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.1">
  <title>Host networking</title>
  <para>After installing the operating system on each node for the architecture
            that you choose to deploy, you must configure the network interfaces. We
            recommend that you disable any automated network management tools and
            manually edit the appropriate configuration files for your distribution.
            For more information on how to configure networking on your
            distribution, see the <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-12/book_sle_admin/data/sec_basicnet_manconf.html">SLES 12</link>
            or <link xlink:href="https://doc.opensuse.org/documentation/leap/reference/html/book.opensuse.reference/cha.basicnet.html">openSUSE</link>
            documentation.</para>
  <para>All nodes require Internet access for administrative purposes such as package
            installation, security updates, Domain Name System (DNS), and
            Network Time Protocol (NTP). In most cases, nodes should obtain
            Internet access through the management network interface.
            To highlight the importance of network separation, the example architectures
            use <link xlink:href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1918">private address space</link> for the
            management network and assume that the physical network infrastructure
            provides Internet access via Network Address Translation (NAT)
            or other methods. The example architectures use routable IP address space for
            the provider (external) network and assume that the physical network
            infrastructure provides direct Internet access.</para>
  <para>In the provider networks architecture, all instances attach directly
            to the provider network. In the self-service (private) networks architecture,
            instances can attach to a self-service or provider network. Self-service
            networks can reside entirely within OpenStack or provide some level of external
            network access using Network Address Translation (NAT) through
            the provider network.</para>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="networklayout.png"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="networklayout.png"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <para>The example architectures assume use of the following networks:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Management on 10.0.0.0/24 with gateway 10.0.0.1</para>
      <para>This network requires a gateway to provide Internet access to all
                    nodes for administrative purposes such as package installation,
                    security updates, Domain Name System (DNS), and
                    Network Time Protocol (NTP).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Provider on 203.0.113.0/24 with gateway 203.0.113.1</para>
      <para>This network requires a gateway to provide Internet access to
                    instances in your OpenStack environment.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>You can modify these ranges and gateways to work with your particular
            network infrastructure.</para>
  <para>Network interface names vary by distribution. Traditionally,
            interfaces use <literal>eth</literal> followed by a sequential number. To cover all
            variations, this guide refers to the first interface as the
            interface with the lowest number and the second interface as the
            interface with the highest number.</para>
  <para>Unless you intend to use the exact configuration provided in this
            example architecture, you must modify the networks in this procedure to
            match your environment. Each node must resolve the other nodes by
            name in addition to IP address. For example, the <literal>controller</literal> name must
            resolve to <literal>10.0.0.11</literal>, the IP address of the management interface on
            the controller node.</para>
  <warning>
    <para>Reconfiguring network interfaces will interrupt network
                connectivity. We recommend using a local terminal session for these
                procedures.</para>
  </warning>
  <note>
    <para>Your distribution enables a restrictive firewall by
                default. During the installation process, certain steps will fail
                unless you alter or disable the firewall. For more information
                about securing your environment, refer to the <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/security-guide/">OpenStack Security
                    Guide</link>.</para>
  </note>
  <xi:include href="install-install-obsenvironment-networking-obsenvironment-networking-controller-obs.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="install-install-obsenvironment-networking-obsenvironment-networking-compute-obs.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="install-install-obsenvironment-networking-obsenvironment-networking-storage-cinder.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="install-install-obsenvironment-networking-obsenvironment-networking-verify-obs.xml"/>
</section>
