<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="liveInstMigration">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Live Migration of Instances</title>
  <abstract><shortdesc outputclass="hdphidden">Live migration allows you to move active compute
      instances between compute nodes, allowing for less downtime during
    maintenance.</shortdesc></abstract>
  <body>
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    <section id="about">
      <p><keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> Nova offers a set of commands that allow you to move compute
        instances between compute hosts. Which command you use will depend on the state of the host,
        what operating system is on the host, what type of storage the instances are using, and
        whether you want to migrate a single instance or all of the instances off of the host. We
        will describe these options on this page as well as give you step-by-step instructions for
        performing them.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="options">
      <title>Migration Options</title>
      <p><b>If your compute node has failed</b></p>
      <p>A compute host failure could be caused by hardware failure, such as the data disk needing
        to be replaced, power has been lost, or any other type of failure which requires that you
        replace the baremetal host. In this scenario, the instances on the compute node are
        unrecoverable and any data on the local ephemeral storage is lost. If you are utilizing
        block storage volumes, either as a boot device or as additional storage, they should be
        unaffected.</p>
      <p>In these cases you will want to use one of the Nova evacuate commands, which will cause
        Nova to rebuild the instances on other hosts.</p>
      <p>This table describes each of the evacuate options for failed compute nodes:</p>
      <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_fnj_tq1_sw">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Command</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><p><codeph>nova evacuate &lt;instance> &lt;hostname></codeph></p></entry>
              <entry>This command is used to evacuate a single instance from a failed host. You
                specify the compute instance UUID and the target host you want to evacuate it to. If
                no host is specified then the Nova scheduler will choose one for you.<p>See
                    <codeph>nova help evacuate</codeph> for more information and syntax. Further
                  details can also be seen in the OpenStack documentation here: <xref
                    href="http://docs.openstack.org/admin-guide/cli_nova_evacuate.html"
                    format="html" scope="external">Evacuate Instances</xref>.</p></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><p><codeph>nova host-evacuate &lt;hostname> --target_host
                    &lt;target_hostname></codeph></p></entry>
              <entry>This command is used to evacuate all instances from a failed host. You specify
                the hostname of the compute host you want to evacuate. Optionally you can specify a
                target host. If no target host is specified then the Nova scheduler will choose a
                target host for each instance.<p>See <codeph>nova help host-evacuate</codeph> for
                  more information and syntax.</p></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <p><b>If your compute node is active, powered on, and the data disks are in working
        order</b></p>
      <p>If your compute host is powered on and the data disks are in working order you can utilize
        the migration commands to migrate your compute instances. There are two migration features,
        "cold" migration (also referred to simply as "migration") and live migration. Migration and
        live migration are two different functions.</p>
      <p><b>Cold migration</b> is used to copy an instances data in a <codeph>SHUTOFF</codeph>
        status from one compute host to another. It does this using passwordless SSH access which
        has security concerns associated with it. For this reason, the <codeph>nova migrate</codeph>
        function has been disabled by default but you have the ability to enable this feature if you
        would like. Details on how to do this can be found in <xref
          href="../compute/enabling_resize.xml"/>.</p>
      <p><b>Live migration</b> can be performed on instances in either an <codeph>ACTIVE</codeph> or
          <codeph>PAUSED</codeph> state and uses the QEMU hypervisor to manage the copy of the
        running processes and associated resources to the destination compute host using the
        hypervisors own protocol and thus is a more secure method and allows for less downtime.
        There may be a short network outage, usually a few milliseconds but could be up to a few
        seconds if your compute instances are busy, during a live migration. Also there may be some
        performance degredation during the process.</p>
      <p>The compute host must remain powered on during the migration process.</p>
      <p>Both the cold migration and live migration options will honor Nova group policies, which
        includes affinity settings. There is a limitation to keep in mind if you use group policies
        and that is discussed in the <xref href="live_migration.xml#liveInstMigration/limitations"
          >limitations</xref> section.</p>
      <p>This table describes each of the migration options for active compute nodes:</p>
      <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_vjs_wgf_5w">
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
          <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4" colwidth="1*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Command</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
              <entry align="center">Linux for HPE Helion</entry>
              <entry align="center">RHEL</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><p><codeph>nova migrate &lt;instance_uuid></codeph></p></entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Used to cold migrate a single instance from a compute host. The
                    <codeph>nova-scheduler</codeph> will choose the new host.</p>
                <p>This command will work against instances in an <codeph>ACTIVE</codeph> or
                    <codeph>SHUTOFF</codeph> state. The instances, if active, will be shutdown and
                  restarted. Instances in a <codeph>PAUSED</codeph> state cannot be cold
                  migrated.</p>
                <p>See the difference between cold migration and live migration at the start of this
                  section.</p>
              </entry>
              <entry align="center"/>
              <entry align="center"/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><p><codeph>nova host-servers-migrate &lt;hostname></codeph></p></entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Used to cold migrate all instances off a specified host to other available hosts,
                  chosen by the <codeph>nova-scheduler</codeph>.</p>
                <p>This command will work against instances in an <codeph>ACTIVE</codeph> or
                    <codeph>SHUTOFF</codeph> state. The instances, if active, will be shutdown and
                  restarted. Instances in a <codeph>PAUSED</codeph> state cannot be cold
                  migrated.</p><p>See the difference between cold migration and live migration at
                  the start of this section.</p>
              </entry>
              <entry align="center"/>
              <entry align="center"/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><p><codeph>nova live-migration &lt;instance_uuid> [&lt;target
                  host>]</codeph></p></entry>
              <entry>Used to migrate a single instance between two compute hosts. You can optionally
                specify a target host or you can allow the nova scheduler to choose a host for you.
                If you choose to specify a target host, ensure that the target host has enough
                resources to host the instance prior to live migration.<p>Works for instances that
                  are booted from a block storage volume or that have any number of block storage
                  volumes attached.</p><p>This command works against instances in
                    <codeph>ACTIVE</codeph> or <codeph>PAUSED</codeph> states only.</p><p>Will work
                  on both Linux for HPE Helion and RHEL compute hosts.</p></entry>
              <entry align="center">X</entry>
              <entry align="center">X</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><p><codeph>nova live-migration --block-migrate &lt;instance_uuid> [&lt;target
                    host>]</codeph></p></entry>
              <entry>Used to migrate a single instance between two compute hosts. You can optionally
                specify a target host or you can allow the nova scheduler to choose a host for you.
                If you choose to specify a target host, ensure that the target host has enough
                resources to host the instance prior to live migration.<p>Works for instances that
                  are booted from local (ephemeral) disk(s) only or if your instance has a mix of
                  ephemeral disk(s) and block storage volume(s) but are not booted from a block
                  storage volume.</p><p>This command works against instances in
                    <codeph>ACTIVE</codeph> or <codeph>PAUSED</codeph> states only.</p><p>Will work
                  on Linux for HPE Helion compute hosts only.</p></entry>
              <entry align="center">X</entry>
              <entry/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><p><codeph>nova host-evacuate-live &lt;hostname> [--target-host
                    &lt;target_hostname>]</codeph></p></entry>
              <entry>Used to live migrate all instances off of a compute host. You can optionally
                specify a target host or you can allow the nova scheduler to choose a host for you.
                If you choose to specify a target host, ensure that the target host has enough
                resources to host the instance prior to live migration.<p>Works for instances that
                  are booted from a block storage volume or that have any number of block storage
                  volumes attached.</p><p>This command works against instances in
                    <codeph>ACTIVE</codeph> or <codeph>PAUSED</codeph> states only.</p><p>Will work
                  on both Linux for HPE Helion and RHEL compute hosts.</p></entry>
              <entry align="center">X</entry>
              <entry align="center">X</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><p><codeph>nova host-evacuate-live --block-migrate &lt;hostname> [--target-host
                    &lt;target_hostname>]</codeph></p></entry>
              <entry>Used to live migrate all instances off of a compute host. You can optionally
                specify a target host or you can allow the nova scheduler to choose a host for you.
                If you choose to specify a target host, ensure that the target host has enough
                resources to host the instance prior to live migration.<p>Works for instances that
                  are booted from local (ephemeral) disk(s) only or if your instance has a mix of
                  ephemeral disk(s) and block storage volume(s) but are not booted from a block
                  storage volume.</p><p>This command works against instances in
                    <codeph>ACTIVE</codeph> or <codeph>PAUSED</codeph> states only.</p><p>Will work
                  on Linux for HPE Helion compute hosts only. </p></entry>
              <entry align="center">X</entry>
              <entry/>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section id="limitations"><title>Limitations of these Features</title>
      <p>There are limitations that may impact your use of this feature:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>To use live migration, your compute instances must be in either an
            <codeph>ACTIVE</codeph> or <codeph>PAUSED</codeph> state on the compute host. If you
          have instances in a <codeph>SHUTOFF</codeph> state then cold migration should be
          used.</li>
        <li>Instances in a <codeph>Paused</codeph> state cannot be live migrated using the Horizon
          dashboard. You will need to utilize the NovaClient CLI to perform these.</li>
        <li>Both cold migration and live migration honor an instance's group policies. If you are
          utilizing an affinity policy and are migrating multiple instances you may run into an
          error stating no hosts are available to migrate to. To work around this issue you should
          specify a target host when migrating these instances, which will bypass the
            <codeph>nova-scheduler</codeph>. You should ensure that the target host you choose has
          the resources available to host the instances.</li>
        <li>The <codeph>nova host-evacuate-live</codeph> command will produce an error if you have a
          compute host that has a mix of instances that use local ephemeral storage and instances
          that are booted from a block storage volume or have any number of block storage volumes
          attached. If you have a mix of these instance types, you may need to run the command
          twice, utilizing the <codeph>--block-migrate</codeph> option. This is described in further
          detail in the <xref href="live_migration.xml#liveInstMigration/troubleshooting"
            >troubleshooting</xref> section.</li>
        <li>If you are using both Linux for HPE Helion (KVM) and RHEL compute hosts, you cannot live
          migrate instances between them. Instances on KVM hosts can only be live migrated to other
          KVM hosts and the same for RHEL hosts. This is due to Red Hat's use of non-standard
          machine models.</li>
        <li>The migration options described in this document are not available on ESX compute
          hosts.</li>
        <li>Only instances booted from a block storage volume can be live migrated between RHEL
          compute hosts. If you are using local ephemeral storage then this feature is not
          supported. This is a limitation in RHEL 7.2.</li>
        <li>Ensure that you read and take into account any other limitations that exist in the
          release notes. See <xref href="../../releasenotes50.xml"/> for more details.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>


    <section id="liveMigrate"><title>Performing a Live Migration</title>
      <p>Cloud administrators can perform a migration on an instance using either the Horizon
        dashboard, API, or CLI. Instances in a <codeph>Paused</codeph> state cannot be live migrated
        using the Horizon GUI. You will need to utilize the CLI to perform these.</p>
      <p>We have documented different scenarios:</p>
    </section>

    <section id="failed_host">
      <title outputclass="headerH">Migrating instances off of a failed compute host</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection">
        <ol>
          <li>Log in to the lifecycle manager.</li>
          <li>If the compute node is not already powered off, do so with this playbook:
              <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost bm-power-down.yml -e nodelist=&lt;node_name></codeblock><note>The
              value for <codeph>&lt;node_name></codeph> will be the name that Cobbler has when you
              run <codeph>sudo cobbler system list</codeph> from the lifecycle manager.</note></li>
          <li>Source the admin credentials necessary to run administrative commands against the Nova
            API:<codeblock>source ~/service.osrc</codeblock></li>
          <li>Force the <codeph>nova-compute</codeph> service to go down on the compute
              node:<codeblock>nova service-force-down &lt;hostname> nova-compute</codeblock><note>The
              value for &lt;hostname> can be obtained by using <codeph>nova host-list</codeph> from
              the lifecycle manager.</note></li>
          <li>Evacuate the instances off of the failed compute node. This will cause the
            nova-scheduler to rebuild the instances on other valid hosts. Any local ephemeral data
            on the instances is lost.<p>For single instances on a failed
              host:<codeblock>nova evacuate &lt;instance_uuid> &lt;target_hostname></codeblock></p><p>For
              all instances on a failed
            host:</p><codeblock>nova host-evacuate &lt;hostname> [--target_host &lt;target_hostname>]</codeblock></li>
          <li>Once you have repaired the failed node and start it back up again, when the
              <codeph>nova-compute</codeph> process starts back up it will clean up the evacuated
            instances.</li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>

    <section id="active_host">
      <title outputclass="headerH">Migrating instances off of an active compute host</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection">
        <p><b>Migrating instances using the Horizon dashboard</b></p>
        <p>The Horizon dashboard offers a GUI method for performing live migrations. Instances in a
            <codeph>Paused</codeph> state will not provide you the live migration option in Horizon
          so you will need to use the CLI instructions in the next section to perform these.</p>
        <ol>
          <li>Log into the Horizon dashboard with admin credentials.</li>
          <li>Navigate to the <b>Admin -> System -> Instances</b> menu as seen in the screenshot
            below.</li>
          <li>Next to the instance you want to migrate, select the drop down menu and choose the
              <b>Live Migrate Instance</b> option. <p><image
                href="../../../media/hos.docs/livemigration1.png"/></p></li>
          <li>In the Live Migrate wizard you will see the compute host the instance currently
            resides on and then a drop down menu that allows you to choose the compute host you want
            to migrate the instance to. Select a destination host from that menu. You also have two
            checkboxes for additional options, which are described below: <p><b>Disk Over Commit</b>
              - If this is not checked then the value will be <codeph>False</codeph>. If you check
              this box then it will allow you to override the check that occurs to ensure the
              destination host has the available disk space to host the instance.</p><p><b>Block
                Migration</b> - If this is not checked then the value will be
              <codeph>False</codeph>. If you check this box then it will migrate the local disks by
              using block migration. Use this option if you are only using ephemeral storage on your
              instances. If you are using block storage for your instance then ensure this box is
              not checked.</p><p><image href="../../../media/hos.docs/livemigration2.png"/></p></li>
          <li>Select the <b>Live Migrate Instance</b> button to begin your live migration.</li>
        </ol>
        <p><b>Migrating instances using the NovaClient CLI</b></p>
        <p>For command-line access you can utilize the NovaClient to perform migrations. The
          lifecycle manager node in your cloud environment should have the NovaClient already
          installed. If you will be accessing your environment through a different method you will
          need to ensure that the NovaClient is installed. You can do this via python-pip and the
          instructions can be found here: <xref
            href="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide/common/cli_install_openstack_command_line_clients.html"
            format="html" scope="external">Install the OpenStack command-line clients</xref>.</p>
        <p>You will need to utilize admin credentials to perform the commands in the steps. From the
          lifecycle manager you can source the service.osrc file which is provided that has the
          necessary credentials:<codeblock>source ~/service.osrc</codeblock></p>
        <p>Here are the steps to perform:</p>
        <ol>
          <li>Log in to the lifecycle manager.</li>
          <li>Identify the instances on the compute node you wish to migrate:
              <codeblock>nova list --all-tenants --host &lt;hostname&gt;</codeblock><p>Example
              showing a host with a single compute instance on
            it:</p><codeblock>stack@helion-cp1-c1-m1-mgmt:~$ nova list --host helion-cp1-comp0001-mgmt --all-tenants
+--------------------------------------+------+----------------------------------+--------+------------+-------------+-----------------------+
| ID                                   | Name | Tenant ID                        | Status | Task State | Power State | Networks              |
+--------------------------------------+------+----------------------------------+--------+------------+-------------+-----------------------+
| 553ba508-2d75-4513-b69a-f6a2a08d04e3 | test | 193548a949c146dfa1f051088e141f0b | ACTIVE | -          | Running     | adminnetwork=10.0.0.5 |
+--------------------------------------+------+----------------------------------+--------+------------+-------------+-----------------------+</codeblock></li>
          <li>When using live migration you can either specify a target host that the instance will
            be migrated to or you can omit the target to allow the nova-scheduler to choose a node
            for you. If you want to get a list of available hosts you can use this command:
            <codeblock>nova host-list</codeblock></li>
          <li>Migrate the instance(s) on the compute node using the notes below. <p>If your instance
              is booted from a block storage volume or has any number of block storage volumes
              attached, use the <codeph>nova live-migration</codeph> command with this
              syntax:</p><codeblock>nova live-migration &lt;instance uuid&gt; [&lt;target compute host&gt;]</codeblock><p>If
              your instance has local (ephemeral) disk(s) only or if your instance has a mix of
              ephemeral disk(s) and block storage volume(s), you should use the
                <codeph>--block-migrate</codeph>
              option:</p><codeblock>nova live-migration --block-migrate &lt;instance uuid&gt; [&lt;target compute host&gt;]</codeblock><note>The
              [&lt;target compute host&gt;] option is optional. If you do not specify a target host
              then the nova scheduler will choose a node for you.</note><p><b>Multiple
              instances</b></p><p>If you want to live migrate all of the instances off a single
              compute host you can utilize the <codeph>nova host-evacuate-live</codeph>
            command.</p>Issue the host-evacuate-live command, which will begin the live migration
            process. <p>If all of the instances on the host are using at least one local (ephemeral)
              disk, you should use this
              syntax:</p><codeblock>nova host-evacuate-live --block-migrate &lt;hostname></codeblock><p>Alternatively,
              if all of the instances are only using block storage volumes then omit the
                <codeph>--block-migrate</codeph>
              option:</p><codeblock>nova host-evacuate-live &lt;hostname></codeblock><note>You can
              either let the nova-scheduler choose a suitable target host or you can specify one
              using the <codeph>--target-host &lt;hostname> </codeph> switch. See <codeph>nova help
                host-evacuate-live</codeph> for details.</note></li>
        </ol>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>


    <section id="troubleshooting">
      <title outputclass="headerH">Troubleshooting migration or host evacuate issues</title>
      <sectiondiv outputclass="insideSection">
        <p><b>Issue:</b> When attempting to use <codeph>nova host-evacuate-live</codeph> against a
          node, you receive the error below:</p>
        <codeblock>$ nova host-evacuate-live helion-cp1-comp0001-mgmt --target-host helion-cp1-comp0003-mgmt
+--------------------------------------+-------------------------+--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+
| Server UUID                          | Live Migration Accepted | Error Message                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                        |
+--------------------------------------+-------------------------+--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+
| 95a7ded8-ebfc-4848-9090-2df378c88a4c | False                   | Error while live migrating instance: helion-cp1-comp0001-mgmt is not on shared storage: Live migration can not be used without shared storage except a booted from volume VM which does not have a local disk. (HTTP 400) (Request-ID: req-9fd79670-a780-40ed-a515-c14e28e0a0a7)     |
| 13ab4ef7-0623-4d00-bb5a-5bb2f1214be4 | False                   | Error while live migrating instance: helion-cp1-comp0001-mgmt is not on shared storage: Live migration cannot be used without shared storage except a booted from volume VM which does not have a local disk. (HTTP 400) (Request-ID: req-26834267-c3ec-4f8b-83cc-5193d6a394d6)     |
+--------------------------------------+-------------------------+---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+</codeblock>
        <p><b>Fix:</b> This occurs when you are attempting to live evacuate a host that contains
          instances booted from local storage and you are not specifying
            <codeph>--block-migrate</codeph> in your command. Re-attempt the live evacuation with
          this syntax:</p>
        <codeblock>nova host-evacuate-live <b>--block-migrate</b> &lt;hostname> [--target-host &lt;target_hostname>]</codeblock>
        <p><b>Issue:</b> When attempting to use <codeph>nova host-evacuate-live</codeph> against a
          node, you receive the error below:</p>
        <codeblock>$ nova host-evacuate-live --block-migrate helion-cp1-comp0001-mgmt --target-host helion-cp1-comp0003-mgmt
+--------------------------------------+-------------------------+-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+
| Server UUID                          | Live Migration Accepted | Error Message                                                                                                                                                                                                     |
+--------------------------------------+-------------------------+-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+
| e9874122-c5dc-406f-9039-217d9258c020 | False                   | Error while live migrating instance: helion-cp1-comp0001-mgmt is not on local storage: Block migration can not be used with shared storage. (HTTP 400) (Request-ID: req-60b1196e-84a0-4b71-9e49-96d6f1358e1a)     |
| 84a02b42-9527-47ac-bed9-8fde1f98e3fe | False                   | Error while live migrating instance: helion-cp1-comp0001-mgmt is not on local storage: Block migration can not be used with shared storage. (HTTP 400) (Request-ID: req-0cdf1198-5dbd-40f4-9e0c-e94aa1065112)     |
+--------------------------------------+-------------------------+-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------+</codeblock>
        <p><b>Fix:</b> This occurs when you are attempting to live evacuate a host that contains
          instances booted from a block storage volume and you are specifying
            <codeph>--block-migrate</codeph> in your command. Re-attempt the live evacuation with
          this syntax:</p>
        <codeblock>nova host-evacuate-live &lt;hostname> [--target-host &lt;target_hostname>]</codeblock>
        <p><b>Issue:</b> When attempting to use <codeph>nova live-migration</codeph> against an
          instance, you receive the error below:</p>
        <codeblock>$ nova live-migration 2a13ffe6-e269-4d75-8e46-624fec7a5da0 helion-cp1-comp0002-mgmt
ERROR (BadRequest): helion-cp1-comp0001-mgmt is not on shared storage: Live migration can not be used without shared storage except a booted from volume VM which does not have a local disk. (HTTP 400) (Request-ID: req-158dd415-0bb7-4613-8529-6689265387e7)</codeblock>
        <p><b>Fix:</b> This occurs when you are attempting to live migrate an instance that was
          booted from local storage and you are not specifying <codeph>--block-migrate</codeph> in
          your command. Re-attempt the live migration with this syntax:</p>
        <codeblock>nova live-migration <b>--block-migrate</b> &lt;instance_uuid> &lt;target_hostname></codeblock>
        <p><b>Issue:</b> When attempting to use <codeph>nova live-migration</codeph> against an
          instance, you receive the error below:</p>
        <codeblock>$ nova live-migration --block-migrate 84a02b42-9527-47ac-bed9-8fde1f98e3fe helion-cp1-comp0001-mgmt
ERROR (BadRequest): helion-cp1-comp0002-mgmt is not on local storage: Block migration can not be used with shared storage. (HTTP 400) (Request-ID: req-51fee8d6-6561-4afc-b0c9-7afa7dc43a5b)</codeblock>
        <p><b>Fix:</b> This occurs when you are attempting to live migrate an instance that was
          booted from a block storage volume and you are specifying <codeph>--block-migrate</codeph>
          in your command. Re-attempt the live migration with this syntax:</p>
        <codeblock>nova live-migration &lt;instance_uuid> &lt;target_hostname></codeblock>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>


  </body>
</topic>
