<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.ent"> %entities;
]>
<!---->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="concept_interfacemodel"><title>Interface Model</title>
        
        

    <para><emphasis>A <guilabel>server-role</guilabel> identifies an
        <guilabel>interface-model</guilabel> that describes how its network interfaces are to
        be configured and used.</emphasis></para>

        
    <para>Network groups are mapped onto specific network interfaces via an
        <guilabel>interface-model</guilabel>, which describes the network devices that need to
        be created (bonds, ovs-bridges, etc) and their properties.</para>

        
    <para>An <guilabel>interface-model</guilabel> acts like a template; it can define how some or
        all of the <guilabel>network-groups</guilabel> are to be mapped for a particular
        combination of physical NICs. However, it is the <guilabel>service-components</guilabel>
        on each server that determine which <guilabel>network-groups</guilabel> are required and
        hence which interfaces and <guilabel>networks</guilabel> will be configured. This means
        that <guilabel>interface-models</guilabel> can be shared between different
        <guilabel>server-roles</guilabel>. For example, an API role and a database role may
        share an interface model even though they may have different disk models and they will
        require a different subset of the <guilabel>network-groups</guilabel>.</para>

    <para>Within an <guilabel>interface-model</guilabel>, physical ports are identified by a device
        name, which in turn is resolved to a physical port on a server basis  via a <guilabel>nic-mapping</guilabel>.
        To allow different physical servers to share an <guilabel>interface-model</guilabel>, the
        <guilabel>nic-mapping</guilabel> is defined as a property of each
        <guilabel>server</guilabel>.</para>

        
        <para>The <literal>interface-model</literal> can also used to describe how network devices are to be configured for use with DPDK, SR-IOV, and PCI Passthrough.</para>

    </section>
