<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="changing_swift_zone">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Changing Swift Zone Layout</title>
  <body><!--not tested-->
    <section id="about">
      <p>Before changing the number of Swift zones or the assignment of servers to specific zones,
        you must ensure that your system has sufficient storage available to perform the operation.
        Specifically, if you are adding a new zone, you may need additional storage. There are two
        reasons for this:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>You cannot simply change the Swift zone number of disk drives in the ring. Instead, you
          need to remove the server(s) from the ring and then re-add the server(s) with a new Swift
          zone number to the ring. At the point where the servers are removed from the ring, there
          must be sufficient spare capacity on the remaining servers to hold the data that was
          originally hosted on the removed servers.</li>
        <li>The total amount of storage in each Swift zone must be the same. This is because new
          data is added to each zone at the same rate. If one zone has a lower capacity than the
          other zones, once that zone becomes full, you cannot add more data to the system – even if
          there is unused space in the other zones.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>As mentioned above, you cannot simply change the Swift zone number of disk drives in an
        existing ring. Instead, you must remove and then re-add servers. This is a summary of the
        process:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Identify appropriate server groups that correspond to the desired Swift zone
          layout.</li>
        <li>Remove the servers in a server group from the rings. This process may be protracted,
          either by removing servers in small batches or by using the weight-step attribute so that
          you limit the amount of replication traffic that happens at once.</li>
        <li>Once all the targeted servers are removed, edit the <codeph>swift-zones</codeph>
          attribute in the ring specifications to add or remove a Swift zone.</li>
        <li>Re-add the servers you had temporarily removed to the rings. Again you may need to do
          this in batches or rely on the weight-step attribute.</li>
        <li>Continue removing and re-adding servers until you reach your final configuration.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section id="howto"><title>Process for Changing Swift Zones</title>
      <p>This section describes the detailed process or reorganizing Swift zones. As a concrete
        example, we assume we start with a single Swift zone and the target is three Swift zones.
        The same general process would apply if you were reducing the number of zones as well.</p>
      <p>The process is as follows:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Identify the appropriate server groups that represent the desired final state. In this
          example, we are going to change the Swift zone layout as follows: <p>
            <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_uql_rkc_cv">
              <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Original Layout</entry>
                    <entry>Target Layout</entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeblock>swift-zones:
  - 1d: 1
    server-groups:
       - AZ1
       - AZ2
       - AZ3</codeblock></entry>
                    <entry><codeblock>swift-zones:
   - 1d: 1
     server-groups:
        - AZ1
   - id: 2
        - AZ2
   - id: 3
        - AZ3</codeblock></entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table></p>
          <p>The plan is to move servers from server groups <codeph>AZ2</codeph> and
              <codeph>AZ3</codeph> to a new Swift zone number. The servers in <codeph>AZ1</codeph>
            will remain in Swift zone 1.</p></li>
        <li>If you have not already done so, consider setting the weight-step attribute as described
          in <xref href="swift_weight_attribute.xml"/>.</li>
        <li>Identify the servers in the <codeph>AZ2</codeph> server group. You may remove all
          servers at once or remove them in batches. If this is the first time you have performed a
          major ring change, we suggest you remove one or two servers only in the first batch. When
          you see how long this takes and the impact replication has on your system you can then use
          that experience to decide whether you can remove a larger batch of servers, or increase or
          decrease the weight-step attribute for the next server-removal cycle. To remove a server,
          use steps 2-9 as described in <xref
            href="../maintenance/swift/removing_swift_node.xml#remove_swift_node/passthrough"/>
          ensuring that you don't remove the remove the servers from the input model.</li>
        <li>This process may take a number of ring rebalance cycles until the disk drives are
          removed from the ring files. Once this happens, you can edit the ring specifications and
          add Swift zone 2 as shown in this example:
          <codeblock>swift-zones:
  - id: 1
    server-groups:
      - AZ1
      - AZ3
  - id: 2
       - AZ2</codeblock></li>
        <li>The server removal process in step #3 set the "remove" attribute in the
            <codeph>pass-through</codeph> attribute of the servers in server group
            <codeph>AZ2</codeph>. Edit the input model files and remove this
            <codeph>pass-through</codeph> attribute. This signals to the system that the servers
          should be used the next time we rebalance the rings (i.e. the server should be added to
          the rings).</li>
        <li>Commit your configuration to the <xref href="../../installation/using_git.xml">local
            git repo</xref>, as follows:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
git add -A
git commit -m "My config or other commit message"</codeblock></li>
        <li>Run the configuration processor:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Use the playbook to create a deployment directory:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Rebuild and deploy the Swift rings containing the re-added servers by running this
          playbook:
          <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-deploy.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Wait until replication has finished. For more details, see <xref
            href="safe_rebalance_deploy_ring.xml"/>.</li>
        <li>You may need to continue to rebalance the rings. For instructions, see the "Final
          Rebalance Stage" steps at <xref
            href="input_model_change_existing_rings.xml#change_swift_rings/final_rebalance"/>.</li>
        <li>At this stage, the servers in server group <codeph>AZ2</codeph> are responsible for
          Swift zone 2. Repeat the process in steps #3-9 to remove the servers in server group
            <codeph>AZ3</codeph> from the rings and then re-add them to Swift zone 3. The ring
          specifications for zones (step 4) should be as follows:
          <codeblock>swift-zones:
  - 1d: 1
    server-groups:
      - AZ1
  - id: 2
      - AZ2
  - id: 3
      - AZ3</codeblock></li>
        <li>Once complete, all data should be dispersed (i.e. each replica is located) in the Swift
          zones as specified in the input model.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
