<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_pcv_fy4_nt">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Gathering Swift Monitoring Metrics</title>
  <body><!--not tested-->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    <p>The <codeph>swiftlm-scan</codeph> command is the mechanism used to gather metrics for the
      Monasca system. These metrics are used to derive alarms. For a list of alarms that can be
      generated from this data, see <xref href="../alarm_resolutions.dita"/>.</p>
    <p>To view the metrics, use the <codeph>swiftlm-scan</codeph> command directly. Log on to the
      Swift node as the root user. The following example shows the command and a snippet of the
        output:<codeblock>$ sudo swiftlm-scan --pretty
. . .
  {
    "dimensions": {
      "device": "sdc", 
      "hostname": "padawan-ccp-c1-m2-mgmt", 
      "service": "object-storage"
    }, 
    "metric": "swiftlm.swift.drive_audit", 
    "timestamp": 1442248083, 
    "value": 0, 
    "value_meta": {
      "msg": "No errors found on device: sdc"
    }
  }, 
. . .</codeblock><note>To
        make the JSON file easier to read, use the <codeph>--pretty</codeph> option.</note></p>
    <p>The fields are as follows:</p>
    <p>
      <simpletable>
        <strow>
          <stentry><codeph>metric</codeph></stentry>
          <stentry>Specifies the name of the metric.</stentry>
        </strow>
        <strow>
          <stentry><codeph>dimensions</codeph></stentry>
          <stentry>Provides information about the source or location of the metric. The dimensions
            differ depending on the metric in question. The following dimensions are used by
              <codeph>swiftlm-scan</codeph>:<ul id="ul_vdp_km2_jt">
              <li><b>service</b>: This is always <b>object-storage</b>.</li>
              <li><b>component</b>: This identifies the component. For example,
                  <b>swift-object-server</b> indicates that the metric is about the
                swift-object-server process.</li>
              <li><b>hostname</b>: This is the name of the node the metric relates to. This is not
                necessarily the name of the current node.</li>
              <li><b>url</b>: If the metric is associated with a URL, this is the URL.</li>
              <li><b>port</b>: If the metric relates to connectivity to a node, this is the port
                used.</li>
              <li><b>device</b>: This is the block device a metric relates to.</li>
            </ul></stentry>
        </strow>
        <strow>
          <stentry><codeph>value</codeph></stentry>
          <stentry>The value of the metric. For many metrics, this is simply the value of the
            metric. However, if the value indicates a status. If <codeph>value_meta</codeph>
            contains a <b>msg</b> field, the value is a status. The following status values are
              used:<ul id="ul_rjy_hm2_jt">
              <li>0 - no error</li>
              <li>1 - warning</li>
              <li>2 - failure</li>
            </ul></stentry>
        </strow>
        <strow>
          <stentry><codeph>value_meta</codeph></stentry>
          <stentry>Additional information. The <b>msg</b> field is the most useful of this
            information. </stentry>
        </strow>
      </simpletable>
    </p>
    <section>
      <title>Optional Parameters</title>
      <p>You can focus on specific sets of metrics by using one of the following optional
        parameters: </p>
      <p>
        <simpletable>
          <strow>
            <stentry><codeph>--replication</codeph></stentry>
            <stentry>Checks replication and health status.</stentry>
          </strow>
          <strow>
            <stentry><codeph>--file-ownership</codeph></stentry>
            <stentry>Checks that Swift owns its relevant files and directories.</stentry>
          </strow>
          <strow>
            <stentry><codeph>--drive-audit</codeph></stentry>
            <stentry>Checks for logged events about corrupted sectors (unrecoverable read errors) on
              drives.</stentry>
          </strow>
          <strow>
            <stentry><codeph>--connectivity</codeph></stentry>
            <stentry>Checks connectivity to various servers used by the Swift system, including:<ul
                id="ul_owk_pp2_jt">
                <li>Checks this node can connect to all memcachd servers</li>
                <li>Checks that this node can connect to the Keystone service (only applicable if
                  this is a proxy server node)</li>
              </ul></stentry>
          </strow>
          <strow>
            <stentry><codeph>--swift-services</codeph></stentry>
            <stentry>Check that the relevant Swift processes are running.</stentry>
          </strow>
          <strow>
            <stentry><codeph>--network-interface</codeph></stentry>
            <stentry>Checks NIC speed and reports statistics for each interface.</stentry>
          </strow>
          <strow>
            <stentry><codeph>--check-mounts</codeph></stentry>
            <stentry>Checks that the node has correctly mounted drives used by Swift.</stentry>
          </strow>
          <strow>
            <stentry><codeph>--hpssacli</codeph></stentry>
            <stentry>If this server uses a Smart Array Controller, this checks the operation of the
              controller and disk drives.</stentry>
          </strow>
        </simpletable>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
