<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_ohx_j1t_4t">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Determining When to Rebalance and Deploy a New
    Ring</title>
  <body>
    <!--not tested-->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    <p>Before deploying a new ring, you must be sure the change that has been applied to the last
      ring is complete (i.e., all the partitions are in their correct location). There are three
      aspects to this:</p>
    <ul id="ul_dnm_m1t_4t">
      <li>
        <p>Is the replication system busy? </p>
        <p>You might want to postpone a ring change until after replication has finished. If the
          replication system is busy repairing a failed drive, a ring change will place additional
          load on the system. To check that replication has finished, use the
            <codeph>swift-recon</codeph> command with the <b>--replication</b> argument. (For more
          information, see <xref href="validating_swift_recon.xml"/>.) The oldest completion time
          can indicate that the replication process is very busy. If it is more than 15 or 20
          minutes then the object replication process are probably still very busy. The following
          example indicates that the oldest completion is 120 seconds, so that the replication
          process is probably not
          busy:<codeblock>$ sudo swift-recon --replication
===============================================================================
--> Starting reconnaissance on 3 hosts
===============================================================================
[2015-10-02 15:31:45] Checking on replication
[replication_time] low: 0, high: 0, avg: 0.0, total: 0, Failed: 0.0%, no_result: 0, reported: 3
Oldest completion was 2015-10-02 15:31:32 (120 seconds ago) by 192.168.245.4:6000.
Most recent completion was 2015-10-02 15:31:43 (10 seconds ago) by 192.168.245.3:6000.
===============================================================================</codeblock></p>
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      <ul id="ul_k2d_2dt_4t">
        <li>
          <p>Are there drive or server failures? </p>
          <p>A drive failure does not preclude deploying a new ring. In principal, there should be
            two copies elsewhere. However, another drive failure in the middle of replication might
            make data temporary unavailable. If possible, postpone ring changes until all servers
            and drives are operating normally.</p>
        </li>
        <li>Has <codeph>min-part-hours</codeph> elapsed? <p>The <codeph>swift-ring-builder</codeph>
            will refuse to build a new ring until the <codeph>min-part-hours</codeph> has elapsed
            since the last time it built rings. You must postpone changes until this time has
            elapsed. </p><p>You can determine how long you must wait by running the
              <codeph>swift-compare-model-rings.yml</codeph> playbook, which will tell you how long
            you until the <codeph>min-part-hours</codeph> has elapsed. For more details, see <xref
              href="swift_ring_mgmt.xml"/>.</p><p>You can change the value of
              <codeph>min-part-hours</codeph>. (For instructions, see <xref
              href="swift_min_part_hours.xml"/>).</p></li>
        <li>Is the Swift dispersion report clean? <p>Run the
              <codeph>swift-dispersion-report.yml</codeph> playbook (as described in <xref
              href="swift_dispersion_report.xml"/>) and examine the results. If the replication
            process has not yet replicated partitions that were moved to new drives in the last ring
            rebalance, the dispersion report will indicate that some containers or objects are
            missing a copy.</p><p>For
            example:</p><codeblock>There were 462 partitions missing one copy.</codeblock><p>Assuming
            all servers and disk drives are operational, the reason for the missing partitions is
            that the replication process has not yet managed to copy a replica into the
            partitions.</p><p>You should wait an hour and rerun the dispersion report process and
            examine the report. The number of partitions missing one copy should have reduced.
            Continue to wait until this reaches zero before making any further ring
            rebalances.</p><note>It is normal to see partitions missing one copy if disk drives or
            servers are down. If all servers and disk drives are mounted, and you did not recently
            perform a ring rebalance, you should investigate whether there are problems with the
            replication process. You can use the Operations Console to investigate replication
            issues.</note><note type="important">If there are any partitions missing two copies, you
            must reboot or repair any failed servers and disk drives as soon as possible. Do not
            shutdown any Swift nodes in this situation. Assuming a replica count of 3, if you are
            missing two copies you are in danger of losing the only remaining copy.</note></li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </body>
</topic>
