<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="swift_filesystem_ts">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Troubleshooting Swift File System Usage
    Issues</title>
  <body><!--not tested-->
    <p>If you have recycled your environment to do a re-installation and you haven't run the
        <codeph>wipe_disks.yml</codeph> playbook in the process, you may experience an issue where
      your file system usage continues to grow exponentially even though you aren't adding any files
      to your Swift system. This is likely occurring because the quarantined directory is getting
      filled up. You can find this directory at <codeph>/srv/node/disk0/quarantined</codeph>.</p>
    <p>You can resolve this issue by following these steps:</p>
    <ol>
      <li>SSH to each of your Swift nodes and stop the replication processes on each of them. The
        following commands must be executed on each of your Swift nodes. Make note of the time that
        you performed this action as you will reference it in step three.
        <codeblock>sudo systemctl stop swift-account-replicator
sudo systemctl stop swift-container-replicator
sudo systemctl stop swift-object-replicator</codeblock></li>
      <li>Example the <codeph>/var/log/swift/swift.log</codeph> file and look for events that
        indicate when the auditor processes have started and completed audit cycles. For more
        details, see <xref href="filesystem_usage_nowipe.xml#swift_filesystem_ts/swift_log"
          >Examining the Swift Log for Audit Event Cycles</xref>.</li>
      <li>Wait until you see that the auditor processes have finished two complete cycles since the
        time you stopped the replication processes (from step one). You must check every Swift node,
        which on a lightly loaded system that was recently installed this should take less than two
        hours.</li>
      <li>At this point you should notice that your quarantined directory has stopped growing. You
        may now delete the files in that directory on each of your nodes.</li>
      <li>Restart the replication processes using the Swift start playbook: <ol>
          <li>Log in to the lifecycle manager.</li>
          <li>Run the Swift start playbook:
            <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts swift-start.yml</codeblock></li>
        </ol></li>
    </ol>
    <section id="swift_log"><title>Examining the Swift Log for Audit Event Cycles</title>
      <p>Below is an example of the <codeph>object-server</codeph> start and end cycle details. They
        were taken by using the following command on a Swift node:</p>
      <codeblock>sudo grep object-auditor /var/log/swift/swift.log|grep ALL</codeblock>
      <p>Example output:</p>
      <codeblock>$ sudo grep object-auditor /var/log/swift/swift.log|grep ALL
...
Apr  1 13:31:18 padawan-ccp-c1-m1-mgmt object-auditor: Begin object audit "forever" mode (ALL)
Apr  1 13:31:18 padawan-ccp-c1-m1-mgmt object-auditor: Object audit (ALL). Since Fri Apr  1 13:31:18 2016: Locally: 0 passed, 0 quarantined, 0 errors files/sec: 0.00 , bytes/sec: 0.00, Total time: 0.00, Auditing time: 0.00, Rate: 0.00
Apr  1 13:51:32 padawan-ccp-c1-m1-mgmt object-auditor: Object audit (ALL) "forever" mode completed: 1213.78s. Total quarantined: 0, Total errors: 0, Total files/sec: 7.02, Total bytes/sec: 9999722.38, Auditing time: 1213.07, Rate: 1.00</codeblock>
      <p>In this example, the auditor started at <codeph>13:31</codeph> and ended at
          <codeph>13:51</codeph>.</p>
      <p>In this next example, the <codeph>account-auditor</codeph> and
          <codeph>container-auditor</codeph> use similar message structure, so we only show the
        container auditor. You can substitute <codeph>account</codeph> for
          <codeph>container</codeph> as well:</p>
      <codeblock>$ sudo grep container-auditor /var/log/swift/swift.log
...
Apr  1 14:07:00 padawan-ccp-c1-m1-mgmt container-auditor: Begin container audit pass.
Apr  1 14:07:00 padawan-ccp-c1-m1-mgmt container-auditor: Since Fri Apr  1 13:07:00 2016: Container audits: 42 passed audit, 0 failed audit
Apr  1 14:37:00 padawan-ccp-c1-m1-mgmt container-auditor: Container audit pass completed: 0.10s</codeblock>
      <p>In the example, the container auditor started a cycle at <codeph>14:07</codeph> and the
        cycle finished at <codeph>14:37</codeph>.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
