<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_ask_vgb_dv">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Support Resources</title>
  <abstract><shortdesc outputclass="hdphidden">Using the knowledge base and contacting the HPE TS
      Support Cloud CoE team.</shortdesc>The public knowledge base and the HPE TS Support Cloud CoE
    Team can be used as resources to solve issues in your cloud.</abstract>
  <body><!--not tested-->
    <section id="kb"><title>Using the Knowledge Base</title>
      <p>The public knowledge base for <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> can be reached at <xref
          href="http://h20566.www2.hpe.com/portal/site/hpsc/public/psi/home/?sp4ts.oid=7261055#topIssuesAndSolution"
          format="html"  >Hewlett Packard Enterprise Support Center - HPE Helion
          OpenStack</xref>.</p>
      <p>You can look through the top issues or search for the specific issue you are experiencing.
        Knowledge documents listed with the content type <codeph>Knowledge Centered Support</codeph>
        are made by HPE TS Support cloud CoE engineers. If you do not find your issue listed then we
        suggest you contact support directly. </p>
    </section>

    <section id="support"><title>Contacting the HPE TS Support Cloud CoE</title>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p><b>Call the HPE Support Number</b></p>
        <p>Once you have registered for HPE TS Support you will be mailed a Service Agreement ID
          (SAID) and a phone number to call (www.hpe.com/contact). HPE customers with a Datacenter
          Care for Cloud contract will have to use their designated contact number. You can use that
          phone number to log support requests. Please have your SAID number available when calling.
          The support agent will log a case with the information you provide and the case will be
          sent to the HPE TS Support Cloud CoE Team. The response time will depend on the service
          level agreement (SLA) in place.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p><b>Electronic Case Logging</b></p>
        <p>There is the option of visiting the <xref href="http://www.hpe.com/support/hpesc"
            format="html"  >HPE Support Center</xref> to log a support case via the
          website. You will be asked to setup and provide a PIN code for correct routing of your
          support case to the HPE TS Support Cloud CoE team. Use your HPE Passport and your Service
          Agreement ID (SAID) to electronically log your support case.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
