<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="add_vsa">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Adding a VSA Node</title>
  <abstract><shortdesc outputclass="hdphidden">Adding a VSA node allows you to add additional
      capacity.</shortdesc><p>You may have a need to add a VSA node for additional storage capacity
      or another purpose and these steps will help you achieve this.</p></abstract>
  <body>
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>

    <p>The process for adding additional VSA nodes to your cloud environment involves two major
      tasks:</p>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>Adding the VSA node(s) to your input model</li>
        <li>Updating your VSA management group and cluster to add the additional node(s)</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>Once you have completed these two tasks, you should add those new hosts to your monitoring
      checks following the directions in <xref href="#add_vsa/monitoring" format="dita">How to add
        an additional VSA node to your monitoring checks</xref>.</p>

    <section id="prereqs"><title>Prerequisites</title>
      <p>You should have one or more baremetal servers that meet the minimum hardware requirements
        for a VSA node which are detailed in the <xref href="../../../planning/hw_support_matrix.xml">Hardware
          Support Matrix</xref>.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="notes"><title>Notes</title>
      <p>When adding additional VSA nodes you should consider the high availability (HA)
        implications to this action. Your VSA nodes are made highly available via the server-group
        and cluster options. For example, if you had an existing cluster of 3 VSA nodes and you
        dispersed them across three server-groups using <codeph>RACK1</codeph>,
          <codeph>RACK2</codeph>, and <codeph>RACK3</codeph> and you wanted to additional capacity
        you may want to consider adding another cluster of 3 VSA nodes to maintain high
        availability. If you want to add an additional 1-2 VSA nodes per RACK then that is also
        possible but you would lose the HA aspect of the server-group.</p>
      <p>The recommended maximum number of VSA nodes per cluster is 16 before you need to create
        additional clusters.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="steps"><title>How to add an additional VSA node to your input model and deploy
        it</title>
      <p>Follow these steps to add additional VSA nodes to your cloud environment.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Log in to your lifecycle manager.</li>
        <li>Checkout the <codeph>site</codeph> branch of your local git so you can begin to make the
          necessary edits:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/my_cloud/definition/data
git checkout site</codeblock></li>
        <li>Edit your <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud/definition/data/servers.yml</codeph> file to include
          the details about your new VSA node(s), ensuring you take into account the notes at the top of this page concerning HA.
          <p>For example, if you already had a cluster of
            three VSA nodes and needed to add a fourth one you would add your details to the bottom
            of the file in this
            format:</p><codeblock># VSA Storage Nodes

   - id: vsa4
     ip-addr: 10.13.111.148
     role: VSA-ROLE
     server-group: RACK1
     nic-mapping: HP-DL360-4PORT
     mac-addr: f0:92:1c:05:f5:78
     ilo-ip: 192.168.9.4
     ilo-password: password
     ilo-user: admin</codeblock><p>You
            can find detailed descriptions of these fields <xref keyref="configobj_servers"
              >here</xref>.</p><note type="important">You will need to verify that the
              <codeph>ip-addr</codeph> value you choose for this node does not conflict with any
            other IP address in your cloud environment. You can confirm this by checking the
              <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud/info/address_info.yml</codeph> file on your lifecycle
            manager.</note></li>
        <li>In your <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud/definition/data/control_plane.yml</codeph> file you
          will need to check the values for <codeph>member-count</codeph>,
            <codeph>min-count</codeph>, and <codeph>max-count</codeph>, if you specified them, to
          ensure that they match up with your new total node count. <p>For example, if you had
            previously specified <codeph>member-count: 3</codeph> and are adding a fourth VSA node,
            you will need to change that value to <codeph>member-count: 4</codeph>.</p><p>See <xref
              keyref="configobj_controlplane">Input Model - Control Plane</xref> for more
            details.</p></li>
        <li>Commit your configuration to the <xref href="../../../installation/using_git.xml">local
            git repo</xref>, as follows:
          <codeblock>git commit -a -m "Adding additional VSA node"</codeblock></li>
        <li>Run the configuration processor:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Update your deployment directory:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Add the new node into Cobbler:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost cobbler-deploy.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Then you can image the node:
            <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost bm-reimage.yml -e nodelist=&#60;node name></codeblock><note>If
            you don't know the <codeph>&#60;node name></codeph> already, you can get it by using
              <codeph>sudo cobbler system list</codeph></note><p>Before proceeding, you may want to
            take a look at <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud/info/server_info.yml</codeph> to see if the
            assignment of the node you have added is what you expect. It may not be, as nodes will
            not be numbered consecutively if any have previously been removed. This is to prevent
            loss of data; the configuration processor retains data about removed nodes and keeps
            their ID numbers from being reallocated. See the Persisted Server Allocations section in
              <xref keyref="persisteddata/persistedserverallocations"><keyword
                keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> Input Model</xref> for information on how this
          works.</p></li>
        <li>Complete the deployment of your new node with this playbook, ensuring you use the
            <codeph>--limit</codeph> option. With the <codeph>--limit</codeph> switch you will need
          to specify your first controller node (which may be your lifecycle manager) if you are
          adding VSA nodes to your environment for the first time. If you added a VSA cluster during
          your initial cloud deploy then you only need to specify your new VSA nodes and can leave
          the controller node out.
            <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts site.yml --tags "generate_hosts_file"
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts site.yml --limit &#60;hostname_vsa_node,hostname_first_controller></codeblock><note>If
            you don't know the <codeph>&#60;hostname></codeph> already, you can get it by looking in
            the <codeph>~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible/host_vars</codeph> directory.</note></li>
      </ol>
    </section>



    <section id="update_cluster"><title>How to add an additional VSA node to your management group
        and cluster</title>
      <p>You can add additional VSA node(s) in an automated process using the provided Ansible
        playbooks only if you used this method initially to create the cluster. If you used the HPE
        StoreVirtual Centralized Management Console (CMC) GUI to create the cluster, you must
        continue to use the CMC utility to add new node(s) and manage your cluster.</p>
      <p><b>Using Ansible</b></p>
      <p>If you initially created your VSA cluster using Ansible (using the <xref
          href="../../../installation/configure_vsa.xml#config_vsa/create_cluster"/> instructions,
        you can add nodes to that cluster using the same playbook. Using this playbook to perform
        cluster operations is highly recommended.</p>
      <p>Perform the following steps:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Log in to the lifecycle manager.</li>
        <li>Run the following playbook, which will update both your management group and your
          cluster:
          <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible/
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts vsalm-configure-cluster.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>When prompted, enter an administrative user name and password you will use to administer
          your cluster via the CMC utility, should it be needed in the future.</li>
        <li>Confirm in the output of the playbook that your new node is added.</li>
        <li>You can view the added node to the cluster in CMC GUI as follows: <ol id="ol_r5f_ll3_wv">
            <li>Launch the CMC utility. See <xref
                href="../../../installation/configure_vsa.xml#config_vsa/cmc">Launching the
                CMC utility GUI</xref> for more details.</li>
            <li>Find the VSA system. </li>
            <li>View the added node in the cluster.</li>
          </ol></li>
      </ol>
      <p outputclass="expandcode"><b>Show | Hide</b> Using the CMC Utility</p>
      <p outputclass="hiddencode">
        <ol>
          <li>On your lifecycle manager, collect the IP addresses of the VSA virtual machines that
            you added from the
              <codeph>~/scratch/ansible/next/my_cloud/stage/info/net_info.yml</codeph> file. This
            file is generated as part of output of the configuration processor during installation.
            You will need this IP address in the next steps.</li>
          <li>Launch the CMC utility. You will likely want to use the same method you used when you
            did your initial VSA cluster configuration. See <xref
              href="../../../installation/configure_vsa.xml#config_vsa/cmc">Launching the
              CMC utility GUI</xref> for more details.</li>
          <li>In the CMC GUI, click the <b>Find</b> menu and then select the <b>Find Systems</b>
            options. <p><image href="../../../../media/vsa/addvsa_cmc1.png"/></p>
          </li>
          <li>Click the <b>Add</b> button which will open the <b>Enter IP Address</b> dialogue box
            where you can enter the IP address of the VSA node(s) that you are adding. These will be
            the same IP addresses you noted in step 1 from your
              <codeph>~/scratch/ansible/next/my_cloud/stage/info/net_info.yml</codeph> file.
                <p><image href="../../../../media/vsa/addvsa_cmc2.png"/></p></li>
          <li>Once you have all of your VSA nodes entered, click the <b>Close</b> button. <p><image
                href="../../../../media/vsa/addvsa_cmc3.png"/></p></li>
          <li>Next, click the <b>Tasks</b> menu and then navigate to the <b>System</b> submenu and
            select the <b>Add to Existing Management Group</b> option. <p><image
                href="../../../../media/vsa/addvsa_cmc4.png"/></p></li>
          <li>In the Management Group wizard, select your new VSA node and then press
              <b>Continue</b>. <p><image href="../../../../media/vsa/addvsa_cmc5.png"/></p></li>
          <li>Select your <b>Group Name</b> from the drop down box and then press <b>Add</b> to
            continue. <p><image href="../../../../media/vsa/addvsa_cmc6.png"/></p></li>
          <li>The CMC utility will then add your new VSA node to the management group. Once it has
            completed you will see the <b>Status</b> change to <codeph>Storage System
              Normal</codeph>. <p><image href="../../../../media/vsa/addvsa_cmc7.png"/></p></li>
          <li>Add the VSA node to an existing cluster. <ul>
              <li>Right click the newly added VSA node and select <b>Add to Existing Cluster</b>:
                    <p><image href="../../../../media/vsa/addvsa_cmc8.png"/></p></li>
              <li>Select your cluster from the drop down box. Select the storage system to add to
                the cluster and then click OK: <p><image
                    href="../../../../media/vsa/addvsa_cmc9.png"/></p></li>
              <li>You can then mouse over your VSA node to see the Storage System get successfully
                added to the cluster: <p><image href="../../../../media/vsa/addvsa_cmc10.png"
                /></p></li>
            </ul></li>
        </ol>
      </p>
    </section>

    <section id="monitoring"><title>How to add an additional VSA node to your monitoring
        checks</title>
      <p>If you want to add a new VSA node to the monitoring service checks, there is an additional
        playbook that must be run to ensure this happens:</p>
      <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts monasca-deploy.yml --tags active_ping_checks</codeblock>
    </section>

  </body>
</topic>
