<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd" >
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="central_log_GS">
  <title>Getting Started with Centralized Logging Service</title>
  <body>
    <p>A typical cloud consists of multiple servers which makes locating a specific log from a
      single server difficult. The Centralized Logging feature helps the administrator evaluate and
      troubleshoot the distributed cloud deployment from a single location.</p>
    <section id="new40_logging">
      <title>New in <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/></title>
      <p>The Logging API is a new component in the centralized logging
        architecture. It works between log producers and log storage. In most cases it works by
        default after installation with no additional configuration. To use Logging API with
        logging-as-a-service or with Helion Carrier Grade, you must configure an end-point. This
        component adds flexibility and supportability for features in the future. <b>Do I need to
          Configure monasca-log-api?</b> If you are only using Helion Lifecycle Manager (HLM), then
        the default configuration is ready to use. <note type="important">If you are using logging
          in any of the following deployments, then you will need to query Keystone to get an
          end-point to use. <ul>
            <li>Logging as a Service</li>
            <li>Platform as a Service</li>
            <li>Helion Carrier Grade</li>
          </ul></note> The Logging API is protected by Keystone’s role-based access control. To
        ensure that logging is allowed and Monasca alarms can be triggered, the user must have the
        monasca-user role. <b>To get an end-point from Keystone:</b><ol>
          <li>Log on to HLM (deployer node).</li>
          <li>To list the Identity service catalog, run:
            <codeblock> source ./service.osrc
 openstack catalog list</codeblock></li>
          <li>In the output, find Kronos, and its region. For Example: <table frame="all" rowsep="1"
              colsep="1" id="table_kyst_endpoint">
              <tgroup cols="3">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.17*"/>
                <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="8.52*"/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Name</entry>
                    <entry>Type</entry>
                    <entry>Endpoints</entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry>kronos</entry>
                    <entry>region2</entry>
                    <entry>public: http://myhelion.test:5607/v3.0 admin:
                      http://192.168.245.5:5607/v3.0 internal:
                      http://192.168.245.5:5607/v3.0</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table></li>
          <li>Use the same port number as found in the output. In the example, you would use port
            5607.</li>
        </ol>
      </p>
      
      <p>In <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> the logging-ansible restart
        playbook has been updated to manage the start,stop, and restart of the Centralized Logging
        Service in a specific way. This change was made to ensure the proper stop, start, and
        restart of Elasticsearch. <note type="important">It is recommended that you only use the
          logging playbooks to perform the start, stop, and restart of the Centralized Logging
          Service. Manually mixing the start, stop, and restart operations with the logging
          playbooks will result in complex failures.</note> For more information, see <xref
          href="central_log_configure_manage.dita#central_log_manage/CL_stop_start">How Do I Stop
          and Start the Service?</xref></p>
    </section>

    <section id="info">
      <title>Where Can I Find More Information?</title>
       <p> For more information about the centralized logging components,
        see the following sites: <ul>
          <li><xref href="https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/logstash/current/introduction.html"
              format="html" scope="external">Logstash</xref></li>
          <li><xref href="http://www.elasticsearch.org/guide" scope="external" format="html"
              >Elasticsearch</xref></li>
          <li><xref href="http://www.elasticsearch.org/blog/scripting-security" scope="external"
              format="html">Elasticsearch Scripting and Security</xref></li>
          <li><xref href="https://media.readthedocs.org/pdf/beaver/latest/beaver.pdf" format="pdf"
              scope="external">Beaver</xref></li>
          <li><xref href="http://www.elasticsearch.org/guide/en/kibana/current/index.html"
              scope="external" format="html">Kibana Dashboard</xref></li>
          <li><xref href="http://kafka.apache.org/" scope="external" format="html">Apache
              Kafka</xref></li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
