<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_gll_nsn_15">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Configuring the <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>
    Firewall</title>
  <body><!--not tested-->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    <section id="about">
      <p>The following instructions provide information about how to identify and modify the overall
        <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> firewall that is configured in front of the control services. This
        firewall is administered only by a cloud admin and is not available for tenant use for
        private network firewall services.</p>
      <p>During the installation process, the configuration processor will automatically generate
        "allow" firewall rules for each server based on the services deployed and block all other
        ports. These are populated in <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud/info/firewall_info.yml</codeph>,
        which includes a list of all the ports by network, including the addresses on which the
        ports will be opened. This is described in more details <xref
          href="../architecture/input_model/concepts/firewallconfiguration.dita">here</xref>.</p>
      <p>The <codeph>firewall_rules.yml</codeph> file in the input model allows you to define
        additional rules for each network group. You can read more about this <xref
          keyref="configobj_firewallrules">here</xref>.</p>
      <p>The purpose of this document is to show you how to make post-installation changes to the
        firewall rules if the need arises.</p>
      <note type="important">This process is not to be confused with the <xref
          href="../networking/fwaas.dita">Firewall as a Service</xref>, which is a separate service
        that enables the ability for <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> tenants to create north-south,
        network-level firewalls to provide stateful protection to all instances in a private, tenant
        network. This service is optional and is tenant-configured.</note>
    </section>
    <section id="howto"><title>Making Changes to the Firewall Rules</title>
      <ol>
        <li>Log in to your lifecycle manager.</li>
        <li>Edit your <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud/definition/data/firewall_rules.yml</codeph> file and
          add the lines necessary to allow the port(s) needed through the firewall. <p>In this
            example we are going to open up port range 5900-5905 to allow VNC traffic through the
            firewall:</p>
          <codeblock>
  - name: VNC
    network-groups:
  - MANAGEMENT
    rules:
     - type: allow
       remote-ip-prefix:  0.0.0.0/0
       port-range-min: 5900
       port-range-max: 5905
       protocol: tcp</codeblock>
          <note>The example above shows a <codeph>remote-ip-prefix</codeph> of
              <codeph>0.0.0.0/0</codeph> which opens the ports up to all IP ranges. To be more
            secure you can specify your local IP address CIDR you will be running the VNC connect
            from.</note></li>
        <li>Commit those changes to your local git:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
git add -A
git commit -m "firewall rule update"</codeblock></li>
        <li>Run the configuration processor:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Create the deployment directory structure:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Change to the deployment directory and run the
            <codeph>osconfig-iptables-deploy.yml</codeph> playbook to update your iptable rules to
          allow VNC:
          <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts osconfig-iptables-deploy.yml</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
      <p>You can repeat these steps as needed to add, remove, or edit any of these firewall
        rules.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
