<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="gettingstarted_ops">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Operations Overview</title>
  <abstract><shortdesc outputclass="hdphidden">A high-level overview of the processes related to
      operating a <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> cloud.</shortdesc></abstract>
  <body>
    <!--not tested-->

    <section><title>What is a cloud operator?</title>
      <p>When we talk about a cloud operator it is important to understand the scope of the tasks
        and responsibilities we are referring to. <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> defines a cloud
        operator as the person or group of people who will be administering the cloud
        infrastructure, which includes:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Monitoring the cloud infrastructure, resolving issues as they arise.</li>
        <li>Managing hardware resources, adding/removing hardware due to capacity needs.</li>
        <li>Repairing, and recovering if needed, any hardware issues.</li>
        <li>Performing domain administration tasks, which involves creating and managing projects,
          users, and groups as well as setting and managing resource quotas.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>


    <section id="tools"><title>Tools provided to operate your cloud</title>
      <p><keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> provides the following tools which are available to operate your
        cloud:</p>
      <p><b>Operations Console</b></p>
      <p>Often referred to as the Ops Console, you can use this console to view data about your
        cloud infrastructure in a web-based graphical user interface (GUI) to make sure your cloud
        is operating correctly. By logging on to the console, <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>
        administrators can manage data in the following ways:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Triage alarm notifications in the central dashboard</li>
        <li>Monitor the environment by giving priority to alarms that take precedence</li>
        <li>Manage compute nodes and easily use a form to create a new host</li>
        <li>Refine the monitoring environment by creating new alarms to specify a combination of
          metrics, services, and hosts that match the triggers unique to an environment</li>
        <li>Plan for future storage by tracking capacity over time to predict with some degree of
          reliability the amount of additional storage needed</li>
      </ul>
      <p>For more details on how to connect to and use the Ops Console, see <xref
          href="opsconsole_overview.xml"/>.</p>
      <p><b>Dashboard</b></p>
      <p>Often referred to as Horizon or the Horizon dashboard, you can use this console to manage
        resources on a domain and project level in a web-based graphical user interface (GUI). The
        following are some of the typical operational tasks that you may perform using the
        dashboard:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Creating and managing projects, users, and groups within your domain.</li>
        <li>Assigning roles to users and groups to manage access to resources.</li>
        <li>Setting and updating resource quotas for the projects.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>For more details, see the following pages:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><xref href="understanding_identity.xml"/></li>
        <li><xref href="cloudadmin_dashboard.xml"/></li>
      </ul>
      <p><b>Command-line interface (CLI)</b></p>
      <p>Each service within <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> provides a command-line client, such as the
        novaclient (sometimes referred to as the python-novaclient or nova CLI) for the Compute
        service, the keystoneclient for the Identity service, etc. There is also an effort in the
        OpenStack community to make a unified client, called the openstackclient, which will combine
        the available commands in the various service-specific clients into one tool. By default, we
        install each of the necessary clients onto the hosts in your environment for you to use.</p>
      <p>You will find processes defined in our documentation that use these command-line tools.
        There is also a list of common cloud administration tasks which we have outlined which you
        can use the command-line tools to do. For more details, see <xref href="cloudadmin_cli.xml"
        />.</p>
    </section>

    <section><title>Daily tasks</title>
      <ul id="ul_mx2_z4x_rv">
        <li><b>Ensure your cloud is running correctly</b>: <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> is deployed as
          a set of highly available services to minimize the impact of failures. That said, hardware
          and software systems can fail. Detection of failures early in the process will enable you
          to address issues before they affect the broader system. <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>
          provides a monitoring solution, based on OpenStack’s Monasca, which provides monitoring
          and metrics for all OpenStack components and much of the underlying system, including
          service status, performance metrics, compute node, and virtual machine status. Failures
          are exposed via the Operations Console and/or alarm notifications. In the case where more
          detailed diagnostics are required, you can use a centralized logging system based on the
          Elasticsearch, Logstash, and Kibana (ELK) stack. This provides the ability to search
          service logs to get detailed information on behavior and errors.</li>
        <li><b>Perform critical maintenance</b>: To ensure your OpenStack installation is running
          correctly, provides the right access and functionality, and is secure, you must should
          ongoing adjustments to the environment. Examples of some daily maintenance tasks
            include:<ul id="ul_nx2_z4x_rv">
            <li>Add/remove projects and users. The frequency of this task depends on your
              policy.</li>
            <li>Apply security patches (if released).</li>
            <li>Run daily backups.</li>
          </ul></li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section><title>Weekly or monthly tasks</title><ul id="ul_nz4_npx_rv">
        <li><b>Do regular capacity planning</b>: Your initial deployment will likely reflect the
          known near to mid-term scale requirements, but at some point your needs will outgrow your
          initial deployment’s capacity. You can expand <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> in a variety of
          ways, such as by adding compute and storage capacity. </li>
      </ul>
      <p>To manage your cloud’s capacity, begin by determining the load on the existing system.
        OpenStack is a set of relatively independent components and services, so there are multiple
        subsystems that can affect capacity. These include control plane nodes, compute nodes,
        object storage nodes, block storage nodes, and an image management system. At the most basic
        level, you should look at the CPU used, RAM used, I/O load, and the disk space used relative
        to the amounts available. For compute nodes, you can also evaluate the allocation of
        resource to hosted virtual machines. This information can be viewed in the Operations
        Console. You can pull historical information from the monitoring service (OpenStack’s
        Monasca) by using its client or API. Also, OpenStack provides you some ability to manage the
        hosted resource utilization by using quotas for projects. You can track this usage over time
        to get your growth trend so that you can project when you will need to add capacity.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Semi-annual tasks</title>
      <ul id="ul_y1v_5sx_rv">
        <li><b>Perform upgrades</b>: OpenStack releases new versions on a six-month cycle. In
          general, HPE Helion will release a new version shortly after that. Each new release
          consists of both new functionality and/or services, as well as bug fixes for existing
          functionality. </li>
      </ul>
      <note>If you are planning to upgrade, this is also an excellent time to evaluate your existing
        capabilities, especially in terms of capacity (see Capacity Planning above).</note>
    </section>

    <section><title>Troubleshooting</title>
      <p>As part of managing your cloud, you should be ready to troubleshoot issues, as needed. The
        following are some common troubleshooting scenarios and solutions:</p>
      <p><b>How do I determine if my cloud is operating correctly now?</b>: <keyword keyref="kw-hos"
        /> provides a monitoring solution based on OpenStack’s Monasca service. This service
        provides monitoring and metrics for all OpenStack components, as well as much of the
        underlying system. By default, <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> comes with a set of alarms that
        provide coverage of the primary systems. In addition, you can define alarms based on
        threshold values for any metrics defined in the system. You can view alarm information in
        the Operations Console. You can also receive or deliver this information to others by
        configuring email or other mechanisms. Alarms provide information about whether a component
        failed and is affecting the system, and also what condition triggered the alarm. </p>
      <p><b>How do I troubleshoot and resolve performance issues for my cloud?</b>: There are a
        variety of factors that can affect the performance of a cloud system, such as the
        following:</p>
      <ul id="ul_vb3_ttx_rv">
        <li>Health of the control plane</li>
        <li>Health of the hosting compute node and virtualization layer</li>
        <li>Resource allocation on the compute node</li>
      </ul>
      <p>If your cloud users are experiencing performance issues on your cloud, use the following
        approach:</p>
      <ol id="ol_wb3_ttx_rv">
        <li>View the compute summary page on the Operations Console to determine if any alarms have
          been triggered. </li>
        <li>Determine the hosting node of the virtual machine that is having issues.</li>
        <li>On the compute hosts page, view the status and resource utilization of the compute node
          to determine if it has errors or is over-allocated.</li>
        <li>On the compute instances page you can view the status of the VM along with its
          metrics.</li>
      </ol>
      <p><b>How do I troubleshoot and resolve availability issues for my cloud?</b>: If your cloud
        users are experiencing availability issues, determine what your users are experiencing that
        indicates to them the cloud is down. For example, can they not access the Dashboard service
        (Horizon) console or APIs, indicating a problem with the control plane? Or are they having
        trouble accessing resources? Console/API issues would indicate a problem with the control
        planes. Use the Operations Console to view the status of services to see if there is an
        issue. However, if it is an issue of accessing a virtual machine, then also search the
        consolidated logs that are available in the ELK stack or errors related to the virtual
        machine and supporting networking.</p>
    </section>


    <section id="support"><title>Common Questions</title>
      <p><b>To manage a cloud, how many administrators do I need?</b></p>
      <p>A 24x7 cloud needs a 24x7 cloud operations team. If you already have a NOC, manging the
        cloud can be added to their workload.</p>
      <p>A cloud with 20 nodes will need a part-time person. You can manage a cloud with 200 nodes
        with two people. As the amount of nodes increases and processes and automation are put in
        place, you will need to increase the number of administrators but the need is not linear. As
        an example, if you have 3000 nodes and 15 clouds you will probably need 6
        administrators.</p>
      <p><b>What skills do my cloud administrators need to have?</b></p>
      <p>Your administrators should be experienced Linux admins. They should have experience in
        application management, as well as experience with Ansible. It's a plus if they have
        experience with bash shell scripting and python programming skills.</p>
      <p>In addition, you will need networking engineers. A 3000 node environment will need two
        networking engineers.</p>
      <p><b>What operations should I plan on performing daily, weekly, monthly, or
          semi-annually?</b></p>
      <p>You should plan for operations by understanding what tasks you need to do daily, weekly,
        monthly, or semi-annually. The specific list of tasks that you need to perform depends on
        your cloud configuration, but should include the following high-level tasks:</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
