<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/topic.dtd" >
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="ops_dashboard_overview">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Using the Dashboard</title>
  <abstract><shortdesc outputclass="hdphidden">Often referred to as Horizon or the Horizon
      dashboard, you can use this console to manage resources on a domain and project level in a
      web-based graphical user interface (GUI).</shortdesc></abstract>
  <body>
    <!--not tested-->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    <p>Horizon is the OpenStack service that serves as the basis for the <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>
      dashboards.</p>
    <p>The dashboards provide a web-based user interface to <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> services
      including Compute, Volume Operations, Networking, and Identity.</p>
    <section><title>Accessing Horizon</title> To access the Horizon dashboard as a non cloud
      administrator, you should ask the cloud admin for the host name or public IP address of the
      dashboard, and for your user name and password. If you are a cloud admin, you can determine
      the URL and credentials by following the steps in <xref href="cloudadmin_dashboard.xml"/>.
        <note>If you are authenticating against an external source such as an LDAP directory or via
        WebSSO you cannot change your password via the change password option in User
        settings.</note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <p>Along the left side of the Horizon user interface are sections that provide access to
        Project and Settings sections. If your login credentials have been assigned the 'admin' role
        you will also see a separate Admin section that provides additional system-wide setting
        options.</p>
      <p>Across the top are menus to switch between projects and menus where you can access user
        settings.</p>
    </section>


    <section><title>Browser support for Horizon</title> According to OpenStack.org, Horizon is
      tested and supported on the latest versions of Firefox and Chrome, and IE9+. Below is a
      summary of browser support for Horizon <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Very good</dt>
          <dd>Very well tested; should work as expected</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt> Good</dt>
          <dd>Moderately tested; should look nice and work fine, may have a few visual issues</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Poor</dt>
          <dd>Visually inferior</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Broken</dt>
          <dd>Essential functionality not working</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>No</dt>
          <dd>Not supported</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl><table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_svx_qfm_vt">
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.0*"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
          <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.0*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Browser</entry>
              <entry>Status</entry>
              <entry>Versions </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Chrome</entry>
              <entry>HPE Tested</entry>
              <entry>43.0.2357.81</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Firefox </entry>
              <entry>HPE Tested</entry>
              <entry>31+</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Firefox ESR</entry>
              <entry>HPE Tested</entry>
              <entry>31+</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Internet Explorer 11</entry>
              <entry>HPE Tested</entry>
              <entry/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Internet Explorer 10</entry>
              <entry>Not HPE Tested</entry>
              <entry/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Internet Explorer 9</entry>
              <entry>Not HPE Tested</entry>
              <entry/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Internet Explorer 8 and below</entry>
              <entry>Not supported</entry>
              <entry/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Safari</entry>
              <entry>Not HPE Tested</entry>
              <entry/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Opera</entry>
              <entry>Not HPE Tested</entry>
              <entry/>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <note>Please refer to the <xref href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Horizon" format="html"
           >OpenStack Dashboard ("Horizon") wiki</xref> for additional compatibility
        and testing information.</note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <p>At the bottom of this page, you can see some of the services you can manage right from the
        dashboard. Remember that Horizon runs over TLS so you will need to use the HTTPS protocol
        with your Horizon IP address.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="DashProject">
      <title>Project dashboard</title>
      <p>Use the <b>Project</b> dashboard to implement and build out your cloud. This dashboard
        contains tools to create virtual server instances, create and configure your network,
        configure access tools (such as key pairs and security groups) and cloud resource templates
        (stacks).</p>
    </section>

    <section id="DashAdmin">
      <title>Admin dashboard</title>
      <p>Use the <b>Admin</b> dashboard to view, allocate, and manage all resources within the
        cloud.</p>
      <p>The Admin dashboard allows you to manage instances, define flavors, create and configure
        images, manage networks, view system resources, manage projects, and manage users.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="DashSettings">
      <title>Settings dashboard</title>
      <p>Use the <b>Settings</b> dashboard to change your display language and settings, your time
        zone, and your password.</p>
      <p>Click <b>Settings</b> in the user menu to display the Settings dashboard.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <ol>
        <li>Open a web browser that has both JavaScript and cookies enabled.</li>
        <li>In the address bar, enter the host name or IP address for the dashboard.<note> If a
            certificate warning appears when you try to access the URL for the first time, a
            self-signed certificate is in use. These certificates are not considered trustworthy by
            default. Verify the certificate or add an exception in the browser to bypass the
            warning. You can manage certificates by visiting the topic <xref
              href="configuring_tls.xml"/></note></li>
        <li>On the <b>Log In</b> page, enter your user name and password and then click <b>Sign
            In</b>.<p>
            <image href="../../media/horizon/HelionLogin.png">
              <alt/>
            </image>
          </p></li>
        <li>The UserID with the <codeph>admin</codeph> role is provided with a special tab called
          Admin. The menu options underneath this tab are similar to the non-admin user views but
          cover all projects as well as some additional panels not available to general users.
            <p>The Overview page provides a summary by project of the current utilization of major
            OpenStack resources. The information on this screen is drawn directly from the Compute
            or Nova service API and provides the ability to filter the query by date range and an
            option to download results into a CSV file that is compatible with Microsoft Excel or
            can be imported into a database.</p></li>
        <li>If you are a non-admin user, you will only be able to select a Project from the list at
          the top of the screen.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section id="horizon-dashboard-examples"><title>Horizon Dashboard Examples</title><p>The
        following screen shots illustrate some of the services you can manage in the Horizon
        dashboard. <!--Removed anchor point images--><!-- id="images" --></p>
      <p><b>Viewing System Info</b></p>
      <p><image href="../../media/horizon/HorizonSystemInfo.png" id="SystemInfo"/></p>
      <p>The System Info panel provides a list of all currently installed OpenStack services and
        their operation status.</p><p/><p>Additional panels on the System Info display sub service
        status for services like Compute, Block Storage, and Network services. This is a view of the
        Compute Services tab. There is also a Block Storage Services tab and a tab for Network
        Agents.</p>
      <p><b>Managing Quotas</b></p>
      <p><image href="../../media/horizon/quotas2.png" id="image_lnv_rb3_ps"/></p>
      <p>The Managing Quotas panel provides a list of system quotas that you can view and edit, such
        as VCPU's, RAM and Storage.</p>
      <p><b>Managing Routers</b></p>
      <p><image href="../../media/horizon/routers.png" id="image_kl5_5b3_ps"/></p>
      <p>Routers are created to connect end user networks together as well as to provide external
        connectivity. This panel provides a list of all currently deployed routers and associated
        metadata and enables the system administrator the ability to create, edit, and delete
        routers.</p>
      <p><b>Managing Availability Zones</b>
      </p><p><image href="../../media/horizon/AZ.png" id="image_slz_wb3_ps"/></p>
      <p><b>Getting Hypervisor Status</b></p>
      <p><image href="../../media/horizon/hypervisors.png" id="image_jt2_zb3_ps"/></p>
      <p>The first tab option on the Hypervisors panel provides a view of the different hypervisors
        currently running, which physical server each hypervisor instance is running on, the type of
        hypervisor, and the infrastructure resources consumed by the hypervisor. </p><p>The Compute
        Host tab lists all of the currently configured physical hosts, which Availability Zone each
        host is configured for, the status, and total consumed resources.</p>
      <p><b>Creating a DNS Record</b></p>
      <p><image href="../../media/horizon/create_a_record.png" id="image_zfd_cc3_ps"/></p>
      <p><b>Managing Services</b></p>
      <p><image href="../../media/horizon/services.png" id="image_d5m_2c3_ps"/></p>
      <p><b>Viewing Stacks</b></p>
      <p><image href="../../media/horizon/stacks.png" id="image_lgf_gc3_ps"/></p>
      <p><b>Creating a Domain</b></p>
      <p><image href="../../media/horizon/create_domain.png" id="image_pdf_3c3_ps"/></p>
      <p><b>Viewing Network Topology</b></p>
      <p><image href="../../media/horizon/HelionDashboardMenusnew1.png" id="image_xdh_gf3_ps"/></p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Other Panels</title>
      <ul>
        <li>The <b>Updates and Extensions </b>panel provides a list of available files that can be
          downloaded and installed. This view is also only available to UserIDs with the
            <codeph>admin</codeph> role. <note>Administrators should be cautious to ensure that
            Horizon Extensions they install come from a trusted source and/or have undergone
            appropriate review and testing. Administrators should be aware of the risk of spear
            phishing, by which they may receive an offer to install an apparently useful application
            which also performs malicious actions.</note></li>
        <li>
          <b>Host aggregates </b>are a grouping of physical servers or hosts with associated
          metadata. A host can belong to multiple aggregates.</li>
        <li>Common use cases for host aggregates include supporting the scheduling of instances to a
          subset of hosts that have a specific capability or flavor such as a specific type of
          storage, lots of RAM, and/or large numbers of processors. <p>Another use case of host
            aggregates is to support the arrangement of hosts into logical groups for load balancing
            and instance distribution. Host aggregates are configured and only viewable by system
            admins. The end user view of a host aggregate is called an Availability Zone.
            Availability zones are created via the Nova API and the host aggregates function. End
            users can use availability zones for similar use cases. For example, an application
            could be deployed on hosts in multiple availability zones. A load balancer can then be
            configured and the instances running each deployment of the application in each
            availability zone can be assigned to the load balancer thus providing a measure of
            failover and high availability support.</p>
          <p>Additional information on host aggregates and availability zones is available at <xref
              href="http://blog.russellbryant.net/2013/05/21/availability-zones-and-host-aggregates-in-openstack-compute-nova/"
              format="html"  
              >http://blog.russellbryant.net/2013/05/21/availability-zones-and-host-aggregates-in-openstack-compute-nova/</xref>
            and <xref href="http://docs.openstack.org/openstack-ops/content/scaling.html"
              format="html"  
              >http://docs.openstack.org/openstack-ops/content/scaling.html</xref>.</p></li>
        <li><b>The Instances panel</b> provides a view of all deployed end user instances across all
          projects, the images applied to those instances, the status of each instance, flavor type,
          and network information. This information is also supplied by the Nova API.</li>
        <li><b>The Volumes panel</b> is displayed if the OpenStack Cinder service is available.
          Cinder provides block storage infrastructure. Block storage provides the ability for end
          users to attach storage as discrete drives to a compute instance. These drives are
          persistent and can be reassigned to a different instance. The Volumes tab on this view
          shows all currently created volumes and associated metadata and status, which physical
          host the volume is hosted on, and the ability for the admin to manage each volume.</li>
        <li><b>Flavors</b> are virtual hardware templates. Flavors are used to define a virtual
          compute host. Flavors are assigned during the creation of a new instance. This panel
          displays all of the current flavor types and provides the ability for the admin to create,
          edit or delete flavors. Hosting organizations often use flavors as a form of billing unit;
          flavors with more resources are charged at a higher rate than flavors with fewer
          resources.</li>
        <li><b>Images</b> are discrete software builds that can be loaded onto an instance. An image
          can be a standalone operating system implementation or a bundle of operating system and
          other pre-configured applications. This panel displays all currently available images and
          associated metadata and enables the system administrator to create, edit and delete
          images. <note type="important">If you encounter the following error:
            <codeblock>ERROR: Unable to create new image. URL scheme not supported.</codeblock>The
            error message indicates that the Glance service has not been configured to support the
            import of Glance images via the <i>http</i> option. This option can be enabled by your
            system administrator by enabling this function in the Glance configuration file. </note>
        </li>
        <li><b>Networks</b> are used by end users to provide connectivity to and between their
          deployed instances. This panel provides a list of all currently deployed networks and
          associated metadata and enables the system administrator the ability to created, edit, and
          delete networks.</li>
        <li><b>Quotas</b> provide the means to limit resource usage. Quotas are assigned per
          project. This panel provides a view of all current quotas and enables a system
          administrator with the ability to edit quota line items.</li>
        <li><b>The Identity panel</b> has two major panels. The Projects panel provides a list of
          all current projects and enables a system administrator the ability to create, modify, and
          delete panels and panel membership.</li>
        <li><b>The Users panel</b> is available only to system administrators and provides the
          ability to create, modify, and delete users. These users are considered "local" to
          Keystone and are authenticated by Keystone.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>




    <!-- <xref href="#topic1564"> Return to Top </xref>-->

  </body>
</topic>
