<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd" >
<topic xml:lang="en-us" id="opsconsole">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Operations Console Overview</title>
  <abstract><shortdesc outputclass="hdphidden">Often referred to as the Ops Console, you can use
      this web-based graphical user interface (GUI) to view data about your cloud infrastructure and
      ensure your cloud is operating correctly.</shortdesc></abstract>
  <body>
    <section id="about"> You can use the Operations Console (Ops Console) for <keyword
        keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> to view data about your Helion cloud infrastructure in a web-based
      graphical user interface (GUI) and ensure your cloud is operating correctly. By logging on to
      the console, <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> administrators can manage data in the following ways:
        <b>Triage alarm notifications.</b>
      <ul>
        <li>Alarm Definitions and notifications now have their own screens and are collected under
          the <b>Alarm Explorer</b> menu item which can be accessed from the Central Dashboard.
          Central Dashboard now allows you to customize the view in the following ways: <ul>
            <li>Rename or re-configure existing alarm cards to include services different from the
              defaults</li>
            <li>Create a new alarm card with the services you want to select</li>
            <li>Reorder alarm cards using drag and drop</li>
            <li>View all alarms that have no service dimension now grouped in an <b>Uncategorized
                Alarms</b> card</li>
            <li>View all alarms that have a service dimension that does not match any of the other
              cards -now grouped in an <b>Other Alarms</b> card</li>
          </ul></li>
        <li> You can also easily access alarm data for a specific component. On the Summary page for
          the following components, a link is provided to an alarms screen specifically for that component:<ul>
            <li><xref href="opsconsole/manage_compute_instances.xml">Compute Instances</xref></li>
            <li><xref href="../operations/opsconsole/block_storage_alarm.xml">Block
              Storage</xref></li>
            <li><xref
                href="opsconsole/OpsConsole_manage_swift.xml#manage_swift_perf/Ops_Swift_AlarmSumm"
                >Object Storage</xref></li>
            <li><xref href="http://docs.hpcloud.com/#helion/operations/opsconsole/hdp_summary.html"
                  format="html">Developer Platform</xref></li>
          </ul></li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Monitor the environment by giving priority to alarms that take precedence.</title>
      <p>Alarm Explorer now allows you to manage alarms in the following ways:</p><ul>
        <li>Refine the monitoring environment by creating new alarms to specify a combination of
          metrics, services, and hosts that match the triggers unique to an environment</li>
        <li>Filter alarms in one place using an enumerated filter box instead of service badges</li>
        <li>Specify full alarm IDs as dimension key-value pairs in the form of
            <b>dimension=value</b></li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Support Changes</title>
      <p><ul>
          <li>To resolve scalability issues, plain text search through alarm sets is no longer
            supported</li>
          <li><keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> no longer supports DBaaS and MSGaaS panels in the
            Helion Development Platform (HDP). If these products were installed in HDP 2.x, they
            will be removed during upgrade.</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>The Business Logic Layer of Ops Console is a middleware component that serves as a single
        point of contact for the user interface to communicate with OpenStack services such as
        Monasca, Nova, and others.</p>
    </section>

  </body>
</topic>
