<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="thirdpartydriver">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Third-party Driver Support</title>
  <abstract><shortdesc outputclass="hdphidden"><keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> comes with a
      selection of built-in plugins and drivers that services use. Depending on your environment you
      may have a need to add additional third-party plugins or drivers. This document provides an
      overview of deployer-side additions to a <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>
    deployment.</shortdesc></abstract>
  <body>
    <!--not tested-->
    <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
    <section id="about">
      <p><keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> comes with a selection of built-in plugins and drivers
        that services use. Depending on your environment you may have a need to add additional
        third-party plugins or drivers. This document provides an overview of deployer-side
        additions to a <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> deployment.</p>
      <p>We will describe the third-party plugin process from two perspectives. The first will be
        from the perspective of an administrator who wants to add a third-party plugin to their
          <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> environment. The second will be from the perspective of a
        developer who wants to package their driver for use on <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>.</p>
      <ul>
        <li><xref href="thirdparty_driver_support.xml#thirdpartydriver/overview">Third-party Plugin
            Overview</xref>
          <ul>
            <li><xref href="thirdparty_driver_support.xml#thirdpartydriver/venv_editing">Note about
                deployer-side Virtual Environment Editing</xref></li>
            <li><xref href="thirdparty_driver_support.xml#thirdpartydriver/admin">Third-party
                Plugin as an Administrator</xref>
              <ul>
                <li><xref href="thirdparty_driver_support.xml#thirdpartydriver/patching_venv"
                    >Patching a venv after a deploy has already occurred</xref></li>
                <li><xref href="thirdparty_driver_support.xml#thirdpartydriver/multiple_drivers"
                    >Handling multiple drivers</xref></li>
                <li><xref href="thirdparty_driver_support.xml#thirdpartydriver/upgrade">Rolling
                    third-party drivers forward with new <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>
                  versions</xref></li>
              </ul></li>
            <li><xref href="thirdparty_driver_support.xml#thirdpartydriver/driver_packager"
                >Third-party Plugin Support as a Driver Packager</xref>
              <ul>
                <li><xref href="thirdparty_driver_support.xml#thirdpartydriver/binary1">Binary
                    dependencies: in-venv</xref></li>
                <li><xref href="thirdparty_driver_support.xml#thirdpartydriver/binary2">Binary
                    dependencies: at the OS layer</xref></li>
                <li><xref href="thirdparty_driver_support.xml#thirdpartydriver/packaging">Packaging
                    non-pypi-based Python</xref></li>
              </ul></li>
          </ul></li>
        <li><xref href="thirdparty_driver_support.xml#thirdpartydriver/example">Example: Adding a
            3rd Party Neutron Plugin</xref></li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="overview"> </section>
    <section id="venv_editing"><title>Note about deployer-side Virtual Environment Editing</title>
      <p>Additional driver code may be required in a venv; this Python driver code can be injected
        into a venv using the venv-edit.yml playbook.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="admin"><title>Third-party Plugin as an Administrator</title>
      <p>The third-party driver contains a directory of packaged Python content (wheels). This can
        be injected into a venv as follows. Assume that the wheelhouse is unpacked in
          <codeph>/home/hlmuser/third-party-wheelhouse</codeph> and it's to be applied to the nova
        venv.</p>
      <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost venv-edit.yml \
     -e source=/opt/hlm_packager/nova-20150101T120000Z.tgz \
     -e suffix=001 \
     -e wheelhouse=/home/hlmuser/third-party-wheelhouse \
     -e wheel='foo-driver'</codeblock>
      <p>The result of this will be to create a second venv,
          <codeph>nova-20150101T120000Z001.tgz</codeph> in the <codeph>/opt/hlm_packager</codeph>
        directory, and update the <codeph>packages</codeph> manifest in that directory to record
        it.</p>
      <p>At this point, a deployment (or an upgrade) can take place as normal because the deployer
        considers the new version number (<codeph>20150101T120000Z001</codeph>) to be in advance,
        that venv package will be selected. For the case of an upgrade, service restarts will be
        performed as necessary.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="patching_venv"><title>Patching a venv after a deploy has already occurred</title>
      <p>Typically it would be advisable for an administrator to patch their venvs prior to a deploy
        or upgrade: indeed, one would expect that in most scenarios, the need for a particular extra
        driver will be understood in advance.</p>
      <p>It is not, however, a hard-and-fast requirement to do this because the venv-edit process
        produces a new venv with an updated version number. The driver can be inserted after an
        initial deployment - and the typical upgrade process will replace the running venvs with the
        newer one.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="multiple_drivers"><title>Handling multiple drivers</title>
      <p>It is possible to apply several third-party patches at once, either one-at-a-time (with
        suffixes 001, 002, etc.) or potentially all-at-once. To do this, the contents of the input
        wheelhouses should be combined, and the target wheel names be given, space-separated, as the
          <codeph>wheel</codeph> parameter to <codeph>venv-edit.yml</codeph>.</p>
      <codeblock>mkdir ~/third-party-wheelhouse
cp ~/third-party-wheelhouse-{foo,bar,baz}/* ~/third-party-wheelhouse
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost venv-edit.yml \
     -e source=/opt/hlm_packager/nova-20150101T120000Z.tgz \
     -e suffix=001 \
     -e wheelhouse=/home/hlmuser/third-party-wheelhouse \
     -e wheel='foo-driver bar-driver baz-driver'</codeblock>
      <p>Whether or not this is advisable is a decision that depends upon context: for instance, it
        might be the case that multiple additional drivers can be configured to live side-by-side in
        the storage case; depending on the invasiveness of the driver. However, it's likely that it
        only makes sense to have one third party driver - eg, for neutron.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="upgrade"><title>Rolling third-party drivers forward with new <keyword
          keyref="kw-hos"/> versions</title>
      <p>There is no automatic support for this; driver patches much be reapplied to their target
        venvs every time a new Helion version is received.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="driver_packager"><title>Third-party Plugin Support as a Driver Packager</title>
      <p>The driver packager needs to have enough knowledge of Python tooling to ensure that the
        requirements in the following steps are met. This is meant to be used as a guide only and
        support is limited.</p>
      <p>The requirement for the packager is to construct a <codeph>wheelhouse</codeph> directory.
        Wheels are a standard Python distribution format. They can be constructed using the
          <codeph>wheel</codeph> command. Typically the process might look as follows:</p>
      <note>It is not necessary that this process be performed on the lifecycle manager itself; such
        packaging could potentially be performed in advance, merely delivering the finished
        wheelhouse to the customer.</note>
      <p>Note that binary contents (Python .so files) will need to be compatible with the version of
        Python in the target venv.</p>
      <codeblock># Assumes the source is in ~/scratch/source_dir
virtualenv ~/scratch/v
mkdir ~/third-party-wheelhouse
~/scratch/v/bin/pip install -U pip wheel
~/scratch/v/bin/pip wheel --wheel-dir ~/third-party-wheelhouse ~/scratch/source_dir</codeblock>
      <p>At the end of this process, a number of wheels will be left in
          <codeph>~/third-party-wheelhouse</codeph>. These may include additional dependencies
        specified through the usual distutils machinery.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="binary1"><title>Binary dependencies: in-venv</title>
      <p>Providing that the wheelhouse is constructed on a system that's binary-compatible with the
        target venv (and therefore the host that it'll be deployed on), native extensions can be
        packaged as wheels without any additional effort.</p>
      <p>A compiler toolchain will be required to make this work.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="binary2"><title>Binary dependencies: at the OS layer</title>
      <p>Some Python drivers utilise third-party binary extensions that are installed into the base
        operating system; Ceph's `rados.py` is an example of this. For those third-party drivers,
        the additional third-party libraries need to be installed on the appropriate target systems
        manually by the driver installer.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="packaging"><title>Packaging non-pypi-based Python</title>
      <p>In some cases it's necessary to generate a wheel out of Python code that has not been
        suitably packaged (a missing setup.py, perhaps, or no pypi versions available).</p>
      <p>Whilst the generation of a wheel from first principles is beyond the scope of this
        document, the format itself is pretty trivial: see <xref
          href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0427/" format="html" scope="external">PEP
          0427</xref> for details. A rudimentary - but sufficient - implementation of this can be
        seen in <codeph>/ansible/roles/venv/templates/wheels_parallel.bash.j2</codeph>.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="example"><title>Example: Adding a 3rd Party Neutron Plugin</title>
      <p>To show how to add a 3rd party plugin we are going to use <xref
          href="https://github.com/openstack/networking-l2gw" scope="external" format="html"
          >'networking-l2gw'</xref> as an example. You can replace the references to the
        'networking-l2gw' plugin with the plugin or driver of your choice.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>On a local Linux workstation with <codeph>python-pip</codeph> installed you will build
          or obtain a python wheel of the driver or plugin source that you want to add. These steps
          show how to create the wheel, if you already have the wheel then you can skip to step #2.<ol>
            <li>In this example, we are going to download the install package for 'networking-l2gw'
              while skipping the installation:
              <codeblock>pip install -d ./ networking-l2gw</codeblock></li>
            <li>In the same directory that the 'networking-l2gw' package is, create a
                <codeph>requirements.txt</codeph> file with the contents below which you will use as
              the input for the pip wheel command in a later step.
              <codeblock>networking-l2gw</codeblock></li>
            <li>Also in that same directory you need to create an empty directory called
              'third-party-wheelhouse'.</li>
            <li>Using <codeph>pip wheel</codeph> you will create a wheel file for the
              'networking-l2gw' package: <codeblock>pip wheel --no-deps --wheel-dir=third-party-wheelhouse -r ./requirements.txt</codeblock>
              <p>The result should be a file named
                  <codeph>networking_l2gw-2015.1.1-py2-none-any.whl</codeph> in your
                'third-party-wheelhouse' directory.</p></li>
            <li>On your lifecycle manager, create a new directory named 'wheelhouse':
              <codeblock>mkdir ~/wheelhouse</codeblock></li>
            <li>Copy the <codeph>networking_l2gw-2015.1.1-py2-none-any.whl</codeph> file from your
              local workstation into the <codeph>~/wheelhouse</codeph> directory that you
              created.</li>
          </ol></li>
        <li>On your lifecycle manager, run the <codeph>venv-edit.yml</codeph> playbook to add the
          driver or plugin package to the desired virtual environment. <ol>
            <li>Check in your <codeph>/opt/hlm_packager/</codeph> directory for the file name of
              your <codeph>neutron-*.tgz</codeph> file to use in the command in the next step.</li>
            <li>For our 'networking-l2gw' example we would use this command using the wheel file we
              created in the previous step. Replace the source file name with the one relevant to
              your environment.
              <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost venv-edit.yml -e source=/opt/hlm_packager/neutron-20151026T074248Z.tgz -e suffix=0001 -e wheelhouse=~/wheelhouse -e wheel='networking_l2gw'</codeblock></li>
            <li>The result should be a new <codeph>neutron-*.tgz</codeph> package in the
                <codeph>opt/hlm-packager</codeph> directory.</li>
          </ol></li>
        <li>You should now run the <codeph>site.yml</codeph> playbook which should create a Neutron
          virtual environment in <codeph>/opt/stack/services/neutron</codeph> on the target nodes
          running the Neutron service which included the contents of the 3rd party 'networking-l2gw'
          package:
          <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts site.yml</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </section>

  </body>
</topic>
