<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.1">
  <title>Image-Volume cache</title>
  <para>OpenStack Block Storage has an optional Image cache which can dramatically
            improve the performance of creating a volume from an image. The improvement
            depends on many factors, primarily how quickly the configured back end can
            clone a volume.</para>
  <para>When a volume is first created from an image, a new cached image-volume
            will be created that is owned by the Block Storage Internal Tenant. Subsequent
            requests to create volumes from that image will clone the cached version
            instead of downloading the image contents and copying data to the volume.</para>
  <para>The cache itself is configurable per back end and will contain the most
            recently used images.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Configure the Internal Tenant</title>
    <para>The Image-Volume cache requires that the Internal Tenant be configured for
                the Block Storage services. This project will own the cached image-volumes so
                they can be managed like normal users including tools like volume quotas. This
                protects normal users from having to see the cached image-volumes, but does
                not make them globally hidden.</para>
    <para>To enable the Block Storage services to have access to an Internal Tenant, set
                the following options in the <literal>cinder.conf</literal> file:</para>
    <screen language="ini">cinder_internal_tenant_project_id = PROJECT_ID
cinder_internal_tenant_user_id = USER_ID</screen>
    <para>An example <literal>cinder.conf</literal> configuration file:</para>
    <screen language="ini">cinder_internal_tenant_project_id = b7455b8974bb4064ad247c8f375eae6c
cinder_internal_tenant_user_id = f46924c112a14c80ab0a24a613d95eef</screen>
    <note>
      <para>The actual user and project that are configured for the Internal Tenant do
                    not require any special privileges. They can be the Block Storage service
                    project or can be any normal project and user.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Configure the Image-Volume cache</title>
    <para>To enable the Image-Volume cache, set the following configuration option in
                the <literal>cinder.conf</literal> file:</para>
    <screen language="ini">image_volume_cache_enabled = True</screen>
    <note>
      <para>If you use Ceph as a back end, set the following configuration option in
                    the <literal>cinder.conf</literal> file:</para>
      <screen language="ini">[ceph]
image_volume_cache_enabled = True</screen>
    </note>
    <para>This can be scoped per back end definition or in the default options.</para>
    <para>There are optional configuration settings that can limit the size of the cache.
                These can also be scoped per back end or in the default options in
                the <literal>cinder.conf</literal> file:</para>
    <screen language="ini">image_volume_cache_max_size_gb = SIZE_GB
image_volume_cache_max_count = MAX_COUNT</screen>
    <para>By default they will be set to 0, which means unlimited.</para>
    <para>For example, a configuration which would limit the max size to 200 GB and 50
                cache entries will be configured as:</para>
    <screen language="ini">image_volume_cache_max_size_gb = 200
image_volume_cache_max_count = 50</screen>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Notifications</title>
    <para>Cache actions will trigger Telemetry messages. There are several that will be
                sent.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><literal>image_volume_cache.miss</literal> - A volume is being created from an image which
                        was not found in the cache. Typically this will mean a new cache entry would
                        be created for it.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><literal>image_volume_cache.hit</literal> - A volume is being created from an image which
                        was found in the cache and the fast path can be taken.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><literal>image_volume_cache.evict</literal> - A cached image-volume has been deleted from
                        the cache.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Managing cached Image-Volumes</title>
    <para>In normal usage there should be no need for manual intervention with the cache.
                The entries and their backing Image-Volumes are managed automatically.</para>
    <para>If needed, you can delete these volumes manually to clear the cache.
                By using the standard volume deletion APIs, the Block Storage service will
                clean up correctly.</para>
  </section>
</section>
