<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.1">
  <title>Volume-backed image</title>
  <para>OpenStack Block Storage can quickly create a volume from an image that refers
            to a volume storing image data (Image-Volume). Compared to the other stores
            such as file and swift, creating a volume from a Volume-backed image performs
            better when the block storage driver supports efficient volume cloning.</para>
  <para>If the image is set to public in the Image service, the volume data can be
            shared among projects.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Configure the Volume-backed image</title>
    <para>Volume-backed image feature requires locations information from the cinder
                store of the Image service. To enable the Image service to use the cinder
                store, add <literal>cinder</literal> to the <literal>stores</literal> option in the <literal>glance_store</literal> section
                of the <literal>glance-api.conf</literal> file:</para>
    <screen language="ini">stores = file, http, swift, cinder</screen>
    <para>To expose locations information, set the following options in the <literal>DEFAULT</literal>
                section of the <literal>glance-api.conf</literal> file:</para>
    <screen language="ini">show_multiple_locations = True</screen>
    <para>To enable the Block Storage services to create a new volume by cloning Image-
                Volume, set the following options in the <literal>DEFAULT</literal> section of the
                <literal>cinder.conf</literal> file. For example:</para>
    <screen language="ini">glance_api_version = 2
allowed_direct_url_schemes = cinder</screen>
    <para>To enable the <command>openstack image create --volume &lt;volume&gt;</command> command to
                create an image that refers an <literal>Image-Volume</literal>, set the following options in
                each back-end section of the <literal>cinder.conf</literal> file:</para>
    <screen language="ini">image_upload_use_cinder_backend = True</screen>
    <para>By default, the <command>openstack image create --volume &lt;volume&gt;</command> command
                creates the Image-Volume in the current project. To store the Image-Volume into
                the internal project, set the following options in each back-end section of the
                <literal>cinder.conf</literal> file:</para>
    <screen language="ini">image_upload_use_internal_tenant = True</screen>
    <para>To make the Image-Volume in the internal project accessible from the Image
                service, set the following options in the <literal>glance_store</literal> section of
                the <literal>glance-api.conf</literal> file:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>cinder_store_auth_address</literal>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>cinder_store_user_name</literal>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>cinder_store_password</literal>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <literal>cinder_store_project_name</literal>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Creating a Volume-backed image</title>
    <para>To register an existing volume as a new Volume-backed image, use the following
                commands:</para>
    <screen language="console">$ openstack image create --disk-format raw --container-format bare IMAGE_NAME

$ glance location-add &lt;image-uuid&gt; --url cinder://&lt;volume-uuid&gt;</screen>
    <para>If the <literal>image_upload_use_cinder_backend</literal> option is enabled, the following
                command creates a new Image-Volume by cloning the specified volume and then
                registers its location to a new image. The disk format and the container format
                must be raw and bare (default). Otherwise, the image is uploaded to the default
                store of the Image service.</para>
    <screen language="console">$ openstack image create --volume SOURCE_VOLUME IMAGE_NAME</screen>
  </section>
</section>
