<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.1">
  <title>Cinder Scheduler Weights</title>
  <section>
    <title>AllocatedCapacityWeigher</title>
    <para>Allocated Capacity Weigher weighs hosts by their allocated capacity.</para>
    <para>The default behavior is to place new volume to the host allocated the least
                space. This weigher is intended to simulate the behavior of
                SimpleScheduler. If you prefer to place volumes to host allocated the most
                space, you can set the <literal>allocated_capacity_weight_multiplier</literal> option to a
                positive number and the weighing has the opposite effect of the default.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>CapacityWeigher</title>
    <para>Capacity Weigher weighs hosts by their virtual or actual free capacity.</para>
    <para>For thin provisioning, weigh hosts by their virtual free capacity
                calculated by the total capacity multiplied by the max over subscription
                ratio and subtracting the provisioned capacity; Otherwise, weigh hosts by
                their actual free capacity, taking into account the reserved space.</para>
    <para>The default is to spread volumes across all hosts evenly. If you prefer
                stacking, you can set the <literal>capacity_weight_multiplier</literal> option to a
                negative number and the weighing has the opposite effect of the default.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>ChanceWeigher</title>
    <para>Chance Weigher assigns random weights to hosts.</para>
    <para>Used to spread volumes randomly across a list of equally suitable hosts.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>GoodnessWeigher</title>
    <para>Goodness Weigher.  Assign weights based on a host’s goodness function.</para>
    <para>Goodness rating is the following:</para>
    <screen language="none">  0 -- host is a poor choice
  .
  .
 50 -- host is a good choice
  .
  .
100 -- host is a perfect choice</screen>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>VolumeNumberWeigher</title>
    <para>Weigher that weighs hosts by volume number in backends.</para>
    <para>The default is to spread volumes across all hosts evenly. If you prefer
                stacking, you can set the <literal>volume_number_multiplier</literal> option to a positive
                number and the weighing has the opposite effect of the default.</para>
  </section>
</section>
