<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="configobj_bonddataoptionslinux">
    <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/><!-- Configuration Object -  -->Bond configuration options for the "linux" provider</title>
    <body><!--not tested-->
        <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
        
        <section id="bonddataoptionslinux">
    <p>The Linux bonding driver supports a large number of parameters that control the operation
        of the bond, as described in the <xref
            href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/Documentation/networking/bonding.txt" scope="external"
            format="html">Linux Ethernet Bonding Driver HOWTO</xref> document. The parameter names and
        values may be specified as key-value pairs in the <codeph>options</codeph> section of
        <codeph>bond-data</codeph>.</p>
    <p>Options used in the <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> examples are:</p>
    
    <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_bonddataoptionslinux">
        <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
            <thead>
                <row>
                    <entry>Key</entry>
                    <entry>Value Descriptions</entry>
                </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>mode</entry>
                    <entry>Specifies the bonding policy. Possible values are: <ul>
                        <li>balance-rr - Transmit packets in sequential order from the first available
                            slave through the last.</li>
                        <li>active-backup - Only one slave in the bond is active. A different slave
                            becomes active if, and only if, the active slave fails.</li>
                        <li>balance-xor - Transmit based on the selected transmit hash policy.</li>
                        <li>broadcast - Transmits everything on all slave interfaces.</li>
                        <li>802.3ad - IEEE 802.3ad Dynamic link aggregation.</li>
                        <li>balance-tlb - Adaptive transmit load balancing: channel bonding that does not
                            require any special switch support.</li>
                        <li>balance-alb - Adaptive load balancing: includes balance-tlb plus receive load
                            balancing (rlb) for IPV4 traffic and does not require any special switch
                            support.</li>
                    </ul>
                    </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>miimon</entry>
                    <entry>Specifies the MII link monitoring frequency in milliseconds. This determines
                        how often the link state of each slave is inspected for link failures. Accepts
                        values in milliseconds.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>primary</entry>
                    <entry>The device to use as the primary when the mode is one of the possible values
                        below: <ul>
                            <li>active-backup</li>
                            <li>balance-tlb</li>
                            <li>balance-alb</li>
                        </ul></entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </table>

</section>
    </body>
</topic>


