<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="configobj_networkgroups">
    <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Network Groups</title>
    <body><!--not tested-->
        <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
        


    <p>Network-groups define the overall network topology, including where service-components
        connect, what load balancers are to be deployed, which connections use TLS, and network
        routing. They also provide the data needed to map Neutron's network configuration to the
        physical networking.</p>
        <codeblock>---
  product:
     version: 2
        
  network-groups:
        
     - name: EXTERNAL-API
       hostname-suffix: extapi
        
       load-balancers:
         - provider: ip-cluster
           name: extlb
           external-name:
        
           tls-components:
             - default
           roles:
            - public
           cert-file: my-public-helion-cert
        
      - name: EXTERNAL-VM
        tags:
          - neutron.l3_agent.external_network_bridge
        
      - name: GUEST
        hostname-suffix: guest
        tags:
          - neutron.networks.vxlan
        
      - name: MANAGEMENT
        hostname-suffix: mgmt
        hostname: true
        
        component-endpoints:
          - default
        
        routes:
          - default
        
        load-balancers:
          - provider: ip-cluster
            name: lb
            components:
              - default
            roles:
              - internal
              - admin
        
        tags:
          - neutron.networks.vlan:
              provider-physical-network: physnet1</codeblock>
    <p>
        <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="network_groups">
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Key</entry>
                        <entry>Value Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>name</entry>
                        <entry>An administrator-defined name for the network group. The name is used to make
                            references from other parts of the input model.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>component-endpoints (optional)</entry>
                        <entry>The list of <uicontrol>service-components</uicontrol> that will bind to or
                            need direct access to networks in this network-group.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>hostname (optional)</entry>
                        <entry>If set to true, the name of the address associated with a network in this
                            group will be used to set the hostname of the server. <note
                                type="important">
                                <codeph>hostname</codeph> <b>must</b> be set to <codeph>true</codeph> for one, and only one, of your
                                network groups.
                            </note></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>hostname-suffix (optional)</entry>
                        <entry>If supplied, this string will be used in the name generation (see <xref
                            keyref="namegeneration">Name Generation</xref>). If not specified,
                            the name of the network-group will be used.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>load-balancers (optional)</entry>
                        <entry>A list of load balancers to be configured on networks in this network-group.
                            Because load balances need a virtual IP address, any network group that contains a
                            load balancer can only have one network associated with it.
                        
                        <p>For clouds consisting of a single control plane, a load balancer may be fully defined 
                            within a <codeph>network-group</codeph> object.  See Load balancer definitions in network groups.</p>
                         
                        <p>Starting in <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/>, a load balancer may be defined within a 
                            <codeph>control-plane</codeph> object and referenced by name from a <codeph>network-group</codeph> object.  
                            See <xref keyref="configobj_lb_defs_networkgroups">Load balancer definitions</xref> in control planes.</p>
                            
                            
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry id="routes">routes (optional)</entry>
                        <entry><p>A list of <uicontrol>network-groups</uicontrol> that networks in this
                            group provide access to via their gateway. This can include the value “default”
                            to define the default route.</p> 
                            <p>A network group with no services attached to it
                            can be used to define routes to external networks.</p>
                            <p>The name of a Neutron provide network defined via configuration-data 
                                (see <xref keyref="configobj_neutron_provider_networks/neutron_name">here</xref>)
                                can also be included in this list.</p>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>tags (optional)</entry>
                        <entry>A list of network tags. Tags provide the linkage between the physical network
                            configuration and the Neutron network configuration.
                        <p>Starting in <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/>, network tags may be defined as part of a Neutron <codeph>configuration-data</codeph> 
                            object rather than as part of a <codeph>network-group</codeph> object (see section 
                            <xref keyref="configobj_configurationdata_neutron">Configuration Data</xref>).</p>
                        
                        
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry id="mtu">mtu (optional)</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <p>Specifies the MTU value required for networks in this network group 
                            If not specified a default value of 1500 is used.
                            </p>
                            <p>See notes <xref keyref="configobj_mtu">here</xref> on how MTU settings are applied to interfaces when 
                                there are multiple tagged networks on the same interface.</p>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </p>
    <p>A load balancer definition has the following attributes:</p>
    <p>
        <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_load_balancer">
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Key</entry>
                        <entry>Value Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>name</entry>
                        <entry>An administrator-defined name for the load balancer.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>provider</entry>
                        <entry>The service component that implements the load balancer. Currently only
                            "ip-cluster" (ha-proxy) is supported. Future releases will provide support for
                            external load balancers.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>roles</entry>
                        <entry>The list of endpoint roles that this load balancer provides (see below).
                            Valid roles are "public", "internal", and "admin'. To ensure separation of
                            concerns, the role "public" cannot be combined with any other role. See <xref
                                keyref="concept_loadbalancers">Load Balancers</xref> for an example of how
                            the role provides endpoint separation.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>components (optional)</entry>
                        <entry>The list of <uicontrol>service-components</uicontrol> for which the load
                            balancer provides a non-encrypted virtual IP address for.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry id="tls_components">tls-components (optional)</entry>
                        <entry>The list of <uicontrol>service-components</uicontrol> for which the load
                            balancer provides TLS-terminated virtual IP addresses for. In <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-30"/>,
                         TLS is now supported for internal as well as public endpoints.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>external-name (optional)</entry>
                        <entry>The name to be registered in Keystone for the publicURL. If not specified,
                            the virtual IP address will be registered. Note that this value cannot be changed
                            after the initial deployment.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>cert-file (optional)</entry>
                        <entry>The name of the certificate file to be used for TLS endpoints.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </p>


    </body>
</topic>

