<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: not edited-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="standalone_deployer">
    <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Using a Dedicated Lifecycle Manager
        Node</title>
    <body>
        <!-- Tested 5/22 by Joel -->
        <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>

        <section id="about">
            <p>All of the example configurations included host the lifecycle manager on the first
                controller nodes. It is also possible to deploy this service on a dedicated node. A
                typical use case for wanting to run the dedicated lifecycle manager is to be able to
                test the deployment of different configurations without having to re-install the
                first server. Some administrators might also prefer the additional security of
                keeping all of the configuration data on a separate server from those that users of
                the cloud connect to (although all of the data can be encrypted and SSH keys can be
                password protected).</p>
            <p>Here is a graphical representation of what this setup would look like:</p>
            <p><image href="../../../media/examples/entry_scale_kvm_vsa_shared.png"/></p>
            <p><xref href="../../../media/examples/entry_scale_kvm_vsa_shared_lg.png"
                      format="html">Download a high-resolution version</xref></p>
        </section>

        <section id="steps">
            <title>Specifying a dedicated lifecycle manager in your input model</title>
            <p>In order to specify a dedicated lifecycle manager in your input model, make the
                following edits to your configuration files.</p>
            <note type="important">The indentation of each of the input files is important and will
                cause errors if not done correctly. Use the existing content in each of these files
                as a reference when adding additional content for your lifecycle manager.</note>
            <ul>
                <li>Update <uicontrol>control_plane.yml</uicontrol> to add the lifecycle
                    manager.</li>
                <li>Update <uicontrol>server_roles.yml</uicontrol> to add the lifecycle manager
                    role.</li>
                <li>Update <uicontrol>net_interfaces.yml</uicontrol> to add the interface definition
                    for the lifecycle manager.</li>
                <li>Create a <uicontrol>disks_lifecycle_manager.yml</uicontrol> file to define the
                    disk layout for the lifecycle manager.</li>
                <li>Update <uicontrol>servers.yml</uicontrol> to add the dedicated lifecycle manager
                    node.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>

        <section id="control_plane_yml"><title>Control_plane.yml</title>
            <p>The snippet below shows the addition of a single node cluster into the control plane
                to host the lifecycle manager service. Note that, in addition to adding the new
                cluster, you also have to remove the lifecycle manager component from the
                    <codeph>cluster1</codeph> in the examples:</p>
            <codeblock>  clusters:
<b>     - name: cluster0
       cluster-prefix: c0
       server-role: LIFECYCLE-MANAGER-ROLE
       member-count: 1	
       allocation-policy: strict
       service-components:
         - lifecycle-manager</b>
         - ntp-client
     - name: cluster1
       cluster-prefix: c1
       server-role: CONTROLLER-ROLE
       member-count: 3
       allocation-policy: strict
       service-components:
         - ntp-server</codeblock>
            <p>This specifies a single node of role <codeph>LIFECYCLE-MANAGER-ROLE</codeph> hosting
                the lifecycle manager.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="server_roles_yml"><title>Server_roles.yml</title>
            <p>The snippet below shows the insertion of the new server roles definition:</p>
            <codeblock>   server-roles:
      
<b>      - name: LIFECYCLE-MANAGER-ROLE
        interface-model: LIFECYCLE-MANAGER-INTERFACES
        disk-model: LIFECYCLE-MANAGER-DISKS</b>	
      
      - name: CONTROLLER-ROLE</codeblock>
            <p>This defines a new server role which references a new interface-model and disk-model
                to be used when configuring the server.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="net_interfaces_yml"><title>Net-interfaces.yml</title>
            <p>The snippet below shows the insertion of the network-interface info:</p>
            <codeblock><b>    - name: LIFECYCLE-MANAGER-INTERFACES
      network-interfaces:
        - name: BOND0
          device:
             name: bond0
          bond-data:
             options:
                 mode: active-backup
                 miimon: 200
                 primary: hed3
             provider: linux
             devices:
                 - name: hed3
                 - name: hed4
          network-groups:
             - MANAGEMENT</b></codeblock>
            <p>This assumes that the server uses the same physical networking layout as the other
                servers in the example. For details on how to modify this to match your
                configuration, see <xref keyref="localizing_inputmodel/netinterfaces"
                    >net_interfaces.yml</xref>.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="disks_lifecycle_manager_yml"><title>Disks_lifecycle_manager.yml</title>
            <p>In the examples, disk-models are provided as separate files (this is just a
                convention, not a limitation) so the following should be added as a new file named
                    <codeph>disks_lifecycle_manager.yml</codeph>:</p>
            <codeblock>---
   product:
      version: 2
        
   disk-models:
<b>   - name: LIFECYCLE-MANAGER-DISKS
     # Disk model to be used for Lifecycle Managers nodes
     # /dev/sda_root is used as a volume group for /, /var/log and /var/crash
     # sda_root is a templated value to align with whatever partition is really used
     # This value is checked in os config and replaced by the partition actually used
     # on sda e.g. sda1 or sda5
        
     volume-groups:
       - name: hlm-vg
         physical-volumes:
           - /dev/sda_root
        
       logical-volumes:
       # The policy is not to consume 100% of the space of each volume group.
       # 5% should be left free for snapshots and to allow for some flexibility.
          - name: root
            size: 80%
            fstype: ext4
            mount: /
          - name: crash
            size: 15%
            mount: /var/crash
            fstype: ext4
            mkfs-opts: -O large_file
        consumer:
              name: os</b></codeblock>
        </section>
        <section id="servers_yml"><title>Servers.yml</title>
            <p>The snippet below shows the insertion of an additional server used for hosting the
                lifecycle manager. Provide the address information here for the server you are
                running on, i.e., the node where you have installed the <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>
                ISO.</p>
            <codeblock>  servers:
     # NOTE: Addresses of servers need to be changed to match your environment.
     #
     #       Add additional servers as required
        
<b>     #Lifecycle-manager
     - id: lifecycle-manager
       ip-addr: &#60;your IP address here>
       role: LIFECYCLE-MANAGER-ROLE
       server-group: RACK1
       nic-mapping: HP-SL230-4PORT
       mac-addr: 8c:dc:d4:b5:c9:e0
       # ipmi information is not needed </b>
          
     # Controllers
     - id: controller1
       ip-addr: 192.168.10.3
       role: CONTROLLER-ROLE</codeblock>
        </section>
    </body>
</topic>
