<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.xml"> %entities; ]><!--Edit status: ready for edit (Carter)-->
<section id="UsingVPNaaS">
   <title>
      <phrase/>Using VPN as a Service (VPNaaS)</title>
    
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">
         <phrase/> VPNaaS Configuration</emphasis></para>

    <para>This document describes the configuration process and requirements for the <phrase/> Virtual Private Network (VPN) as a Service module.</para>

    <itemizedlist id="idg-userguide----networking-vpnaas-dita-2">
        <listitem/>
        <listitem/>
        <listitem/>
        <!--<li><xref href="vpnaas.xml#UsingVPNaaS/Troubleshooting">Troubleshooting</xref></li>-->
        <listitem/>
      </itemizedlist>

    
      <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Prerequisites</bridgehead>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><phrase/> must be installed. </para>

         </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Before setting up VPNaaS, you will need to have created an external network and a subnet
          with access to the internet. Information on how to create the external network and subnet
          can be found in the <xref linkend="UsingVPNaaS"/>
          section of this document.</para>

         </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>You should assume 172.16.0.0/16 as the ext-net CIDR in this document.</para>

         </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
   

    
      <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Considerations</bridgehead>
      <para>Using the Neutron plugin-based VPNaaS causes additional processes to be run on the Network
        Service Nodes. One of these processes, the ipsec charon process from StrongSwan, runs as
        root and listens on an external network. A vulnerability in that process can lead to remote
        root compromise of the Network Service Nodes. If this is a concern customers should consider
        using a VPN solution other than the Neutron plugin-based VPNaaS and/or deploying additional
        protection mechanisms. </para>

   

    <formalpara id="idg-userguide----networking-vpnaas-dita-5">
      <title>Configuration</title>
      
   </formalpara>

    

    
      <bridgehead renderas="sect4">More Information</bridgehead>
      <para>VPNaaS currently only supports Pre-shared Keys (PSK) security between VPN gateways. A
        different VPN gateway solution should be considered if stronger, certificate-based security
        is required.</para>

      <para>For more information on the neutron command-line interface (CLI) and VPN as a Service
        (VPNaaS), see the OpenStack networking command-line client reference: <ulink url="http://docs.openstack.org/cli-reference/content/neutronclient_commands.html"/></para>

      <para>For information on how to create an external network and subnet, see the OpenStack manual:
          <ulink url="http://docs.openstack.org/user-guide/dashboard_create_networks.html"/></para>

   
  </section>
