<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entities.xml"> %entities; ]><section id="newsecurity">
   <title>
      <phrase/>Security Features Overview</title>
    <para/>

    
      <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Security features in <phrase/>
      </bridgehead>
      <para>Enterprises need protection against security breaches, insider threats, and operational
        issues that increases the risk of losing sensitive data. By combining technologies from both
        OpenStack services and HPE Security – Data Security products, <phrase/> provides capabilities that help you to protect your data at rest
        and in transit, enable centralized key management, and achieve compliance with
        PCI-DSS.</para>
      <para>In <phrase/>, a number of security enhancements are
        available to strengthen and harden your cloud deployment. Below is an overview of some of
        the features and a brief description. Follow the links to the relevant topics for
        instructions on setup, configuration, and use of these security features.</para>
   
    <formalpara id="rbac">
      <title>Role-based access control (RBAC) support for Neutron networks </title>
      <para/>
   </formalpara>
    
    <formalpara id="adminRoles">
      <title>Separate service administrator role</title>
      <para/>
   </formalpara>
    <formalpara id="interservicePasswords">
      <title>Inter-service password enhancements</title>
      <para>
         <phrase/>
      </para>
   </formalpara>
    <formalpara id="red_hat">
      <title>SELinux for Red Hat KVM </title>
      <para/>
   </formalpara>
    
      <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Data in transit protection via configurable TLS for internal API
        endpoints</bridgehead>
      <para id="tls_internal">With <phrase/>, data transmission between
        internal API endpoints is encrypted using TLS v 1.2 to protect sensitive data against
        unauthorized disclosure and modification (spoofing and tampering attacks). Additionally, you
        can configure TLS using your own certificates, from a Certificate Authority of your choice,
        providing deployment flexibility.
        <!--See <xref href="tls.xml#configure_tls"/> for more
      information.--></para>
   
    
      <bridgehead renderas="sect4">Data at rest protection using project-based encryption</bridgehead>
      <para>You can encrypt sensitive data-at-rest on per tenant or project basis, while storing
        and managing keys externally and centrally using HPE ESKM. This capability requires the
        OpenStack Barbican API and OASIS KMIP (Key Management Interoperability Protocol) plug-ins
        for integration and supports encryption of Cinder block storage with <phrase/>.
        <!--For more
        information see <xref href="dar.xml#topic_rqy_dfm_gv"/>.--></para>
   
    <formalpara id="cadf">
      <title>CADF-compliant security audit logs</title>
      <para/>
   </formalpara>
    <formalpara id="pciReady">
      <title>PCI readiness</title>
      <para>
         <phrase/>
         <phrase/>
         <phrase/>
      </para>
   </formalpara>

  </section>
