<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
  <title>OpenStack Compute (nova)</title>
  <info/>
  <chapter>
    <title>What is nova?</title>
    <info/>
    <para>Nova is the OpenStack project that provides a way to provision compute
                instances (aka virtual servers). Nova supports creating virtual machines,
                baremetal servers (through the use of ironic), and has limited support for
                system containers. Nova runs as a set of daemons on top of existing Linux
                servers to provide that service.</para>
    <para>It requires the following additional OpenStack services for basic function:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/keystone/latest/">Keystone</link>: This provides
                        identity and authentication for all OpenStack services.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/glance/latest/">Glance</link>: This provides the
                        compute image repository. All compute instances launch from glance images.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/neutron/latest/">Neutron</link>: This is
                        responsible for provisioning the virtual or physical networks that compute
                        instances connect to on boot.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>It can also integrate with other services to include: persistent block
                storage, encrypted disks, and baremetal compute instances.</para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>For End Users</title>
    <info/>
    <para>As an end user of nova, you'll use nova to create and manage servers with
                either tools or the API directly.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Tools for using Nova</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/horizon/latest/user/launch-instances.html">Horizon</link>: The
                            official web ui for the OpenStack Project.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/python-openstackclient/latest/">OpenStack Client</link>: The official
                            CLI for OpenStack Projects. You should use this as your CLI for most things,
                            it includes not just nova commands but also commands for most of the projects
                            in OpenStack.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/python-novaclient/latest/user/shell.html">Nova Client</link>: For
                            some very advanced features (or administrative commands) of nova you may need
                            to use nova client. It is still supported, but the <literal>openstack</literal> cli is
                            recommended.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Writing to the API</title>
      <para>All end user (and some administrative) features of nova are exposed via a REST
                    API, which can be used to build more complicated logic or automation with
                    nova. This can be consumed directly, or via various SDKs. The following
                    resources will help you get started with consuming the API directly.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><link xlink:href="https://developer.openstack.org/api-guide/compute/">Compute API Guide:</link>: The
                            concept guide for the API. This helps lay out the concepts behind the API to
                            make consuming the API reference easier.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><link xlink:href="http://developer.openstack.org/api-ref/compute/">Compute API Reference</link>:
                            The complete reference for the API, including all methods and request /
                            response parameters and their meaning.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>: The
                            compute API evolves over time through <link xlink:href="https://developer.openstack.org/api-guide/compute/microversions.html">Microversions</link>. This
                            provides the history of all those changes. Consider it a "what's new" in the
                            compute API.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>: One of the trickier
                            parts to understand is the Block Device Mapping parameters used to connect
                            specific block devices to computes. This deserves its own deep dive.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>: Provide information to the
                            guest instance when it is created.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>For Operators</title>
    <info/>
    <section>
      <title>Architecture Overview</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>: An overview of how all the parts in
                            nova fit together.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Installation</title>
      <para>The detailed install guide for nova. A functioning nova will also require
                    having installed <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/keystone/latest/install/">keystone</link>, <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/glance/latest/install/">glance</link>, and <link xlink:href="https://docs.openstack.org/neutron/latest/install/">neutron</link>. Please ensure that you
                    follow their install guides first.</para>
      <xi:include href="install.xml"/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Deployment Considerations</title>
      <para>There is information you might want to consider before doing your deployment,
                    especially if it is going to be a larger deployment. For smaller deployments
                    the defaults from the  will be sufficient.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Compute Driver Features Supported</emphasis>: While the majority of nova deployments use
                            libvirt/kvm, you can use nova with other compute drivers. Nova attempts to
                            provide a unified feature set across these, however, not all features are
                            implemented on all backends, and not all features are equally well tested.</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>: A view of
                                    what features each driver supports based on what's important to some large
                                    use cases (General Purpose Cloud, NFV Cloud, HPC Cloud).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>: A detailed dive through
                                    features in each compute driver backend.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>: For large deployments, Cells v2
                            allows sharding of your compute environment. Upfront planning is key to a
                            successful Cells v2 layout.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>: Overview of the placement
                            service, including how it fits in with the rest of nova.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>: Considerations for using a real
                            WSGI container instead of the baked-in eventlet web server.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Maintenance</title>
      <para>Once you are running nova, the following information is extremely useful.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>: A collection of guides for administrating
                            nova.</para>
          <warning>
            <para>This guide was imported during the Pike cycle and is a bit out of
                                date. It will be updated during Queens to be more accurate.</para>
          </warning>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>: How nova is designed to be upgraded for minimal
                            service impact, and the order you should do them in.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>: Managing project quotas in nova.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>: Aggregates are a useful way of grouping
                            hosts together for scheduling purposes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>: How the filter scheduler is
                            configured, and how that will impact where compute instances land in your
                            environment. If you are seeing unexpected distribution of compute instances
                            in your hosts, you'll want to dive into this configuration.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>: How and
                            when you might want to extend the basic metadata exposed to compute instances
                            (either via metadata server or config drive) for your specific purposes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Reference Material</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>: the complete command reference
                            for all the daemons and admin tools that come with nova.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Configuration</emphasis>:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>: detailed
                                    configuration guides for various parts of you Nova system. Helpful
                                    reference for setting up specific hypervisor backends.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>: a complete reference of all
                                    configuration options available in the nova.conf file.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>: a sample config file
                                    with inline documentation.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Policy</emphasis>: nova, like most OpenStack projects, uses a policy language to
                            restrict permissions on REST API actions.</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>: a complete reference of all
                                    policy points in nova and what they impact.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>: a sample policy file
                                    with inline documentation.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>For Contributors</title>
    <info/>
    <para>If you are new to Nova, this should help you start to understand what Nova
                actually does, and why.</para>
    <xi:include href="contributor.xml"/>
    <para>There are also a number of technical references on both current and future
                looking parts of our architecture. These are collected below.</para>
    <xi:include href="reference.xml"/>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Indices and tables</title>
    <info/>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para/>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </chapter>
</book>
