<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: ready for edit (Nancy)-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="arcsight">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Threat Monitoring and Integration with HPE
    ArcSight</title>
  <body>
    <!--not tested-->
    <bodydiv outputclass="testbodydiv">
      <section>
        <p conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/applies-to"/>
        <p><keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>, through its centralized logging infrastructure (Logstash),
          can be configured to send events and logs to an HPE ArcSight endpoint (connector or ESM or
          Logger). Integration with HPE ArcSight provides the ability to monitor, analyze, and
          correlate <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> logs through HPE ArcSight Logger and ESM and supports
          continuous security monitoring of the entire <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> infrastructure.
          The HPE ArcSight connector in turn, can be configured to receive logs and events in real
          time from this Logstash configuration inside an <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> environment,
          further converting it to a Common Event Format (CEF) and forwarding it to your designated
          HPE ArcSight endpoint using an encrypted transport protocol. </p>
        <p>Integration with HPE ArcSight gives you the ability to monitor, analyze, and correlate
            <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> logs through HPE ArcSight Logger and ESM. It supports
          security monitoring for continuous compliance across an <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>
          deployment including: <ul id="ul_byd_4dp_yt">
            <li><keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> infrastructure </li>
            <li><keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> services </li>
            <li>Guest operating system </li>
          </ul> This integration enables you to preserve your investment in HPE ArcSight security
          infrastructure by monitoring their entire <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> cloud in addition to
          your existing IT environment, reducing the time taken to respond to security breaches, and
          providing faster analysis of security logs and events.</p>
        <!--
      <p>Technical details of this integration along with a step-by-step tutorial are available in the
      whitepaper entitled <xref
        href="http://www8.hp.com/h20195/V2/GetDocument.aspx?docname=4AA5-8025ENW&amp;cc=us&amp;lc=en"
        format="html" scope="external">Monitoring <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> with HPE ArcSight</xref>.</p>
        -->
      </section>
    </bodydiv>
  </body>
</topic>
