<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: ready for edit (Nancy)-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="barbican">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Key Management with the Barbican Service</title>
  <body>
    <!--not tested-->



    <ul>
      <li><xref href="#barbican/overview" format="dita">Barbican service overview</xref></li>
      <li><xref href="#barbican/installation" format="dita">Installation information</xref>
        <ul>
          <li><xref href="#barbican/kmip" format="dita">KMIP plug-in support</xref></li></ul></li>
          <li><xref href="#barbican/auditing" format="dita">Auditing</xref></li>
        
      <!-- TODO UPGRADE Is this only applicable to V3 docs -->  
      <!--<li><xref href="../upgrade/enable_barbican_for_upgrade.xml#barbicanUpgrade">Enabling Barbican
          when upgrading</xref> from previous versions of <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> (separate
        document)</li>-->
      <li><xref href="dar.xml#dar">KMIP configuration</xref> (separate document)</li>
    </ul>

    <section id="overview">
      <title>Barbican service overview</title>
      <p>Barbican is an OpenStack key management service offering secure storage, provisioning, and
        management of key data. The Barbican service provides management of secrets, keys and
        certificates via multiple storage back ends. The support for various back ends is provided
        via a plug-in mechanism, a Key Management Interoperability Protocol (KMIP) plug-in for a
        KMIP-compliant HSM device. Barbican supports symmetric and asymmetric key generation using
        various algorithms. Cinder, neutron-lbaas v2 and Nova will integrate with Barbican for their
        encryption key generation and storage. </p>
      <p>Barbican has two types of core feature sets: </p>
      <ul>
        <li>The <i>Barbican component,</i> a WSGI application that exposes a REST API for
          secrets/containers/orders.</li>
        <li><i>Barbican workers</i> for asynchronous processing (used for various
          messaging-event-driven tasks related to certificate generation). </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    
    <section id="features">
      <title>Key features </title> 
      <p>Following are the major features of the 
      Barbican key management service: <ul>
        <li>The ability to encrypt volumes/disks. In an OpenStack context, this means support for
          encrypting Cinder volumes (volume encryption). Cinder has its own key manager interface
          (KeyMgr) and can use BarbicanClient as one of its implementations. By default in <keyword
            keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/>, Cinder uses Barbican as its key manager when Barbican is
          enabled. KeyMgr encrypts data in the virtualization host before writing data to the remote
          disk. There are three options available in <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>
          <ul>
            <li>Tenant-based encryption for block volume storage using Barbican for KMS </li>
            <li>Barbican with KMIP and PKCS11 and external KMS (certified with HPE Atalla ESKM) </li>
            <li>3PAR StoreServ Data-At-Rest Encryption </li>
          </ul></li>
        <li>Storage and retrieval of secrets (passwords) </li>
        <li>Certificate management for Load Balancer as a Service V2 (previously known as
          Neutron-LBaaS) </li>
        <li>Ability to define and manage access policies for key material</li>
        <li>Administrative functionality, and the ability to control the lifecycle of key material </li>
        <li>Well-defined auditing ability in OpenStack services around key access and lifecycle
          events </li>
        <li>Key management as a service for PaaS application(s) deployed on an OpenStack cloud</li>
        <li>Ability to effectively scale up key management and make it highly available (handle
          failover)</li>
      </ul>
      <note type="warning" outputclass="noteInline">Do not delete the certificate container associated with your load
        balancer listeners before deleting the load balancers themselves. If you delete the
        certificate first, future operations on your load balancers and failover will cease to
        function.</note>
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section id="installation"><title>Installation information</title>
      <!-- TODO UPGRADE -->
      <!--The initial preparation for
      Barbican use looks like this:<p>Upgrade: if you are upgrading to <keyword
          keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> from 2.x versions, you need follow these steps after upgrading
        from 2.x to 3.0:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Enable Barbican via the control-plane.yml definition file. </li>
        <li>Add Barbican to services that are behind TLS (add TLS support for the Barbican load
          balancer endpoint).</li>
        <li> Add Barbican TLS to continue TLS beyond the internal load balancer (add TLS support for
          Barbican back end).</li>
        <li>The above TLS changes to the input-model definition and control-plane.yml definition
          have to be done together. These changes are explained in <xref
            href="../upgrade/enable_barbican_for_upgrade.xml#barbicanUpgrade"/>. </li>
        <li>Generate a master key. <note type="danger">Do not change your master key after deploying
            it to Barbican.</note></li>
      </ol>-->
      <p>New installations of <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/>:</p><ol>
        <li>No changes are needed for Barbican to be enabled. When installing your cloud, you should
          use the input-model definitions which already define the necessary Barbican components.
          When using the pre-defined input model files that come with <keyword
            keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/>, nothing else needs to be done in those files.</li>
        <li>Generate a master key. <note type="danger">Do not change your master key after deploying
            it to Barbican.</note></li>
        <li>If you do decide to make configuration changes to your clean install of <keyword
            keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/>, you will need to redeploy the service. Please refer to <xref
            href="barbican_admin.xml#barbicanAdmin/updating">Updating Barbican</xref> for more
          details on the available customization options. </li>
      </ol>
      <p/>
      <b>Generating a master key for secret store back ends</b><p>Barbican currently supports
        databases and KMIP as its secret store back ends. In OpenStack upstream, there are
        additional back ends available, such as the PKCS11 plug-in and dogtag plug-in, but they are
        currently not tested or supported by <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>. </p><p>In <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/>,
        by default Barbican is configured to use a database as secret (keys) storage back end. This
        back end encrypts Barbican-managed keys with a project level key (kek (key encryption key))
        before storing it in the database. Project-level keys are encrypted using a master key. As
        part of the initial Barbican configuration, you must generate and configure this master
        key.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Generate the master key using the provided python *generate_kek* script on the lifecycle
          manager node:
          <codeblock>python  ~/helion/hos/ansible/roles/KEYMGR-API/templates/generate_kek</codeblock>The
          master key is generated at stdout from the command above.</li>
        <li>Set above master key in file:
          <codeblock>~helion/my_cloud/config/barbican/barbican_deploy_config.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Replace existing *barbican_customer_master_key* value with above generated master key if
          present.</li>
        <li>Commit the change to the git repository: <!--cp -r ~/hp-ci/padawan/* ~/helion/my_cloud/definition/-->
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion
git add -A
git commit -m "My config"</codeblock></li>
        <li>Next, run ready-deployment:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible/
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Once the master key is set, continue with your cloud deployment.</li>
      </ol>
      <note>For a Barbican deployment with a database back end, the master key needs to be generated
        and configured before Barbican is deployed for the first time. Once the master key is set,
        it must not be modified.</note>
      <note>Changing the master key can result in read errors for existing secrets as those secrets
        are stored in the database and are encrypted using the previous master key. Once a new
        master key is used, Barbican will not be able to read those secrets. Also it will not be
        able to create new secrets within that project as the project key is encrypted using
        previous master key.</note>
      <p id="kmip"><b>KMIP plug-in support</b></p><p>Barbican has a KMIP plug-in to store encryption
        keys (called secrets in Barbican service terminology) in an HSM device using the KMIP
        protocol. This plug-in has been tested against Atalla ESKM with KMIP server. To enable its
        support, Barbican needs to be configured with the corresponding plug-in connection details
        and client certificate information needs to be defined in its configuration. The ESKM KMIP
        server uses a client certificate to validate a KMIP client connection established by the
        Barbican server. As part of that KMIP configuration, playbooks provide a mechanism to upload
        your client certs to nodes hosting the Barbican API server. </p><p>KMIP deployment
        instructions can be found in <xref href="dar.xml#dar"/></p>
      <note>The Installation and deployment of the Atalla ESKM or any other HSM devices and
        dependent components is beyond the scope of this document. Please refer the relevant
        documentation for your choice of product. For example, you can get more information on
        Atalla ESKM and related Data Security and Encryption Products at <xref
          href="http://www8.hp.com/us/en/software-solutions/data-security-encryption" format="html"
          scope="external"
          >http://www8.hp.com/us/en/software-solutions/data-security-encryption</xref>. </note>
      <p id="auditing"><b>Auditing of Barbican events</b></p><p>The Barbican service supports
        auditing and uses OpenStack <xref href="middleware_auditing.xml#auditing">Audit
          Middleware</xref> to generate auditing data in Cloud Auditing Data Federation (CADF)
        format. The <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> input model has a mechanism to enable / disable auditing on
        a per-service basis. When Barbican auditing is enabled, it writes audit messages to an audit
        log file that different from Barbican's own internal logging. The base location of audit log
        file is driven by common auditing configuration.</p><b>Enabling and disabling
        auditing</b><p>The auditing of Barbican events can be enabled and disabled thorough the
        Barbican reconfigure playbook. As part of Barbican's configuration, its audit messages can
        be directed to a log or to a messaging queue. By default, messages are written to the
        Barbican log file. Once an architecture-level decision is made with regards to the default
        consumer of audit events (that is, either the log or messaging), the Barbican service can be
        configured to use it as the default option when auditing is enabled. </p> Auditing can be
      disabled or enabled by following these steps on the lifecycle manager node. <ol>
        <li>Edit the file <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud/definition/cloudConfig.yml.</codeph> Note that
          all audit-related configuration is defined under the audit-settings section. Please note
          that you must use valid yaml syntax when specifying values.</li>
        <li>Any service (including Barbican) that is listed under enabled-services or
          disabled-services will override the default setting (i.e. default: enabled or default:
          disabled) To enable auditing, make sure that the Barbican service name is within the
          enabled-services list of the <codeph>audit-settings</codeph> section or is not present in
          disabled-services list when default: is set to enabled. <p>Below is the relevant section
            of <codeph>cloudConfig.yml</codeph>. Note that enabled-services are commented
          out.</p>The <codeph>default: enabled</codeph> setting applies to all services. If you want
          to disable (or enable) a few, whichever is the opposite of the default global setting you
          used) you can do so in a disabled-services (or enabled-services) section below it. Here
          enabled-services is commented out. You should only have either a default of enabled (or
          disabled) or a section of disabled (or enabled). In other words, there is no need to
          repeat the
          setting.<codeblock>audit-settings:
    default: enabled
    #enabled-services:
    #  - keystone
    #  - barbican
    disabled-services:
       - nova
       - barbican
       - keystone
       - cinder
       - ceilometer
       - neutron</codeblock>
        </li>
        <li>Once you are satisfied with your settings, copy the files to
            <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud/definition/</codeph>, and commit the changes in the git
          repository. For example, if you are using the Entry Scale KVM model, you would copy from
          ~/helion/examples/entry-scale-kvm-vsa and
          commit.<codeblock>cp -r ~/helion/examples/entry-scale-kvm-vsa/* ~/helion/my_cloud/definition/
cd ~/helion
git add -A
git commit -m "My config"</codeblock></li>
        <li>Next you would run the configuration processor and ready-deployment:
          <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible/
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</codeblock></li>
        <li>Finally, run barbican-reconfigure:
          <codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts barbican-reconfigure.yml</codeblock>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>


    <section>
      <title>Barbican key management service bootstrap data</title>
      <p>When the key management service is installed, some of the Keystone-related initial data is
        bootstrapped as part of its initial deployment. The data added is primarily around Barbican
        user, roles, service and endpoint definitions and Barbican role assignments. </p>
      <p><b>User, Roles and Service/ Endpoint Definitions</b></p>
      <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="barb">
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
          <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Type</entry>
              <entry>Name or key-value pair</entry>
              <entry>Purpose</entry>
              <entry>Comments</entry>
            </row>

          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <p>Keystone User Account</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>barbican</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Barbican user account associated with administrative privileges.</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Password is randomly generated and made available in barbican client environment
                  setup script, <i>barbican.osrc,</i> on the lifecycle manager node.</p>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <p>Keystone User Account</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>barbican_service</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Service account used for keystone token validation by barbican service.</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Password is randomly generated and stored in barbican paste configuration i.e.
                    <i>barbican-api-paste.ini</i>.</p>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <p>Keystone Role</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>key-manager:creator</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Barbican specific role which has privilege to create/modify/list keys,
                  certificates. </p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>This role has the exact same privileges as defined for '<i>creator</i>' role in
                  upstream barbican. Referenced in the service policy config file,
                    <i>policy.json</i>.</p>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <p>Keystone Role</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>key-manager:admin</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Barbican specific role that has administrative privileges.</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>This role has the exact same privileges as defined for '<i>admin</i>' role in
                  upstream barbican. Referenced in the service policy config file,
                    <i>policy.json</i>.</p>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <p>Keystone Role</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>key-manager:observer</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Barbican specific role which has privileges limited to read/list of keys,
                  certificates.</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>This role has the exact same privileges as defined for '<i>observer</i>' role in
                  upstream barbican. Referenced in the service policy config file,
                    <i>policy.json</i>.</p>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <p>Keystone Role</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>key-manager:auditor</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Barbican specific role which has privileges limited to reading metadata of keys,
                  certificates. This role does not allow reading and listing of actual keys and
                  certificates.</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>This role has the exact same privileges as defined for '<i>auditor</i>' role in
                  upstream barbican. Referenced in the service policy config file,
                    <i>policy.json</i>.</p>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <p>Keystone Role</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>key-manager:service-admin</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Barbican specific role which has privilege to modify global preferred CA and
                  modify default project quotas.</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>This role has the exact same privileges as defined for
                    '<i>key-manager:service-admin</i>' role in upstream barbican. Referenced in
                  service policy config file, <i>policy.json</i>.</p>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <p>Keystone Service</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>name: barbican type: key-manager</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Barbican service definition. Service type is <i>key-manager</i>.</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p> </p>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <p>Keystone Endpoint</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>interface: internal region: region1</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Barbican internal endpoint. This is the load-balanced endpoint exposed for
                  internal service usage.</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p> </p>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <p>Keystone Endpoint</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>interface: public region: region1</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p>Barbican public endpoint. This is the load-balanced endpoint exposed for
                  external/public service usage.</p>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <p> </p>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section>
      <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="barb2">
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
          <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>User name</entry>
              <entry>Project name</entry>
              <entry>Role name</entry>
              <entry>Purpose</entry>
            </row>

          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>barbican</entry>
              <entry>admin</entry>
              <entry>key-manager:admin</entry>
              <entry>User is assigned barbican administration privileges on keystone defined
                  <i>admin</i> project. This allows the user to manage barbican resources associated
                with that project using barbican CLI setup.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>barbican</entry>
              <entry>admin</entry>
              <entry>key-manager:service-admin </entry>
              <entry>User is assigned barbican service administration privileges on keystone defined
                  <i>admin</i> project. This role and above role allows the user to have full
                barbican related administration capabilities</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>barbican</entry>
              <entry>admin</entry>
              <entry>admin</entry>
              <entry>User assigned keystone defined administrative role on its <i>admin</i> project.
                This way customer can continue to use barbican CLI and openstack CLI without need to
                switch when testing or verifying data.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>admin</entry>
              <entry>admin</entry>
              <entry>key-manager:admin</entry>
              <entry> Keystone defined <i>admin</i> user is given barbican related administrative
                privileges on keystone defined <i>admin</i> project.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>admin</entry>
              <entry>admin</entry>
              <entry>key-manager:service-admin</entry>
              <entry>In lines of above role assignment, barbican specific service admin role is
                assigned to allow global preferred CA and quotas modifications.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>barbican_service</entry>
              <entry>services</entry>
              <entry>service</entry>
              <entry>Barbican service account is given <i>service</i> role on <i>services</i>
                project for token validation. API server uses this for creating scoped service token
                and then includes it as<i> X-Service-Token</i> when requesting customer/client token
                validation from keystone.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
   

    <section id="troubleshooting"><title>Known issues and workarounds</title>
      <ol id="ol_l5z_3x4_tv">
        <li>Make sure that in your Certificate Signing Request (CSR) 'Common Name' matches the
            <codeph>barbican_kmip_username</codeph> value defined in
            <codeph>roles/barbican-common/vars/barbican_deploy_config.yml</codeph>. Otherwise you
          may see an internal server error message in Barbican for create secret request which does
          not translate well into this issue.</li>
        <li>Currently Barbican does not return clear related error with regards to client
          certificate setup and its connectivity with KMIP server. During secret create request,
          general "Internal Server Error" is returned when the certificate is invalid or missing any
          of necessary client certificate data (client certificate, key and CA root
          certificate).</li>
        <!--<li>After reconfiguring VIP from TLS to non-TLS , false measurements appear in monitoring.
          Monasca measurements for http_status checks alternate between '0' and '1' as shown
          below.</li>-->
      </ol>
      
      <!--<codeblock>stack@padawan-ccp-c1-m1-mgmt:~$ monasca
        - -os-username monasca measurement-list - -dimensions
        component=barbican-api,monitored_host_type=vip,api_endpoint=internal - -merge_metrics</codeblock>
     <codeblock> http_status 2016-02-17T20:17:00
+................+....................+................................+............….+.….….….…...+
| name        | dimensions | timestamp                | value        | value_meta |
+................+.….…....+....................................+................-+..................+
| http_status |            | 2016-02-17T20:17:28.000Z |        1.000 |            |
|             |            | 2016-02-17T20:17:29.000Z |        0.000 |            |
|             |            | 2016-02-17T20:17:29.000Z |        1.000 |            |
|             |            | 2016-02-17T20:17:31.000Z |        0.000 |            |
|             |            | 2016-02-17T20:17:31.000Z |        1.000 |            |
|             |            | 2016-02-17T20:17:57.000Z |        0.000 |            |
|             |            | 2016-02-17T20:17:57.000Z |        1.000 |            |
+......................................................................................................+</codeblock>Both
      URLs (http and https) are being monitored after the non-TLS switch. To remedy this, edit the
      control plane definition file,
      <codeph>control_plane.yml</codeph>:<codeblock>~/helion/my_cloud/definition/data/control_plane.yml</codeblock>Make
      changes to add Barbican service components if not already there, as explained next:-->
    </section>
    <!--<section conref="../upgrade/enable_barbican_for_upgrade.xml#barbicanUpgrade/config"/>-->
    <!--<section>Commit the change in git repository.
      <codeblock>cd ~/helion
git add -A
git commit -m "My config"</codeblock>
      Then run the
      config-processor-run and ready-deployment playbooks:
      <codeblock>cd ~/helion/hos/ansible/ 
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost config-processor-run.yml 
ansible-playbook -i hosts/localhost ready-deployment.yml</codeblock>
      Then run the site.yml
      playbook:<codeblock>cd ~/scratch/ansible/next/hos/ansible 
ansible-playbook -i hosts/verb_hosts site.yml</codeblock>
    </section>-->
  </body>
</topic>
