<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: ready for edit (Nancy)-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="tlsConfig">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Transport Layer Security Configuration</title>
  <body>
    <!--not tested-->


    <section><title/>In <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-30"/>, you can provide your own certificate
      authority and certificates for internal and public virtual IP addresses (VIPs), and you should
      do so for any production cloud. The certificates automatically generated by HPE Helion
      OpenStack are useful for testing and setup, but you should always install your own for
      production use. Certificate installation is discussed below.</section>
    <section>
      <p>Before you begin, the following list of terms will be helpful when generating and
        installing certificates.</p>
      <dl>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Fully qualified domain name (FQDN) of the public VIP</dt>
          <dd>The registered domain name. A FQDN is not mandatory. It is perfectly valid to have no
            FQDN and use IP addresses instead. Note that you can use FQDNs on public endpoints, and
            you may change them whenever the need arises.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Certificate authority (CA) certificate</dt>
          <dd>Your certificates must be signed by a CA, such as your internal IT department or a
            public certificate authority. For this example we will use a self-signed
            certificate.</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Server certificate</dt>
          <dd>It is easy to confuse server certificates and CA certificates. Server certificates
            reside on the server and CA certificates reside on the client. A server certificate
            affirms that the server that sent it serves a set of IP addresses, domain names, and set
            of services. A CA certificate is used by the client to authenticate this claim. </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>SAN (subject-alt-name)</dt>
          <dd>The set of IP addresses and domain names in a server certificate request: A template
            for a server certificate. </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Certificate signing request (CSR)</dt>
          <dd>A blob of data generated from a certificate request and sent to a CA, which would then
            sign it, produce a server certificate, and send it back. </dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>External VIP</dt>
          <dd>External virtual IP address</dd>
        </dlentry>
        <dlentry>
          <dt>Internal VIP</dt>
          <dd>Internal virtual IP address</dd>
        </dlentry>
      </dl>
      <p>The major difference between an external VIP certificate and an internal VIP certificate is
        that the internal VIP has approximately 40 domain names in the SAN. This is because each
        service has a different domain name in <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase-30"/>. So it is
        unlikely that you can create an internal server certificate before running the configuration
        processor. But after a configuration processor run, a certificate request would be created
        for each of your cert-names.</p>
      <p>All of the <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> example cloud models ship with TLS enabled on
        the service API endpoints. Because TLS is enabled by default, a test certificate named
        <codeph>my-public-cert</codeph> is bundled with the release. Having this default
        certificate allows you to bring up a cloud without having to worry about certificates. It
        will not match the IP address of your environment's API endpoints, but you can ignore the
        warnings. Later, in production when you require a trusted certificate, you can add your own
        certificate and redeploy using the instructions below. This is the recommended path.</p>
    </section>


    <section>

    </section>
    

  </body>
</topic>
