<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Edit status: ready for edit (Nancy)-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="tls30overview">
  <title><ph conkeyref="HOS-conrefs/product-title"/>Transport Layer Security (TLS)  Overview</title>
  <body>
    <!--not tested-->





    <section>
      <p outputclass="aTest">The Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol, successor to SSL, provides
        the mechanisms to ensure authentication, non-repudiation, confidentiality, and integrity of
        user communications to and between the <keyword keyref="kw-hos"/> services from internal and
        public endpoints.</p>
      <p>OpenStack endpoints are HTTP (REST) services providing APIs to other OpenStack services on
        the management network. All traffic to OpenStack services coming in on the public endpoints
        and some traffic between services can be secured using TLS connections. </p>
      <p>In  <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/>, the following are enabled for TLS</p>
      <ul id="ul_tvz_tnv_4v">
        <li>API endpoints in the internal and admin VIPs can now be secured by TLS.</li>
        <li>API endpoints can be provided with their own certificates (this is shown in the model
          examples) or they can simply use the default certificate.</li>
        <li>The Barbican key management service API can be secured by TLS from the load balancer to
          the service endpoint.</li>
        <li>You can add multiple trust chains (certificate authority (CA) certificates).</li>
        <li>Fully qualified domain names (FQDNs) can be used for public endpoints and now they can
          be changed. The ability to change the domain names was new in <keyword
            keyref="kw-hos-phrase-30"/>. The external name in the input model files (in
            <codeph>~/helion/my_cloud/definition/data/network_groups.yml</codeph>) is where the
          domain name is indicated and changed. </li>
        <li>There are two monitoring alarms specific to certificates, 14-days to certificate
          expiration and 1-day to expiration.</li>

        <li>TLS can be turned off/on for individual endpoints.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section><title> <keyword keyref="kw-hos-phrase"/> clean install vs. upgrade</title> <p>Clean install: all
        TLS- encrypted services are already listed under tls-components in
          <codeph>network_groups.yml</codeph></p>
      <p>You just have to:</p>
      <ul id="ul_i3y_k4t_vv">
        <li>Add your self-signed CA cert and server cert (for testing)</li>
        <li>Or add your public (or company) CA-signed server cert and the public (or company) CA
          cert (for production)</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Upgrade: you don’t have TLS enabled already on the internal endpoints so you need to</p>
      <ul id="ul_j3y_k4t_vv">
        <li>Add your self-signed CA cert and server cert (for testing)</li>
        <li>Or add your public (or company) CA-signed server cert and the public (or company) CA
          cert (for production)</li>
        <li>Add all the services to tls-components in <codeph>network_groups.yml</codeph></li>
        <!-- TODO UPGRADE -->
        <!--<li>Add Barbican (instructions found in <xref
            href="../upgrade/enable_barbican_for_upgrade.xml#barbicanUpgrade"/>)</li>-->
      </ul>For information on enabling and disabling TLS, see <xref href="tls_config.xml#tlsConfig"/>
      <p>For instructions on installing certificates, see <xref href="tls_config.xml#tlsConfig"
        />.</p>
    </section>
    

  </body>
</topic>
